<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diabetes Care</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Diabetes Care</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">583</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">diacare</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">diabetes care</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Diabetes Care</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0149-5992</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1935-5548</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Diabetes Association</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10234749</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10234749.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10234749</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10234749</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37043827</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc22-2394</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">222394</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evaluating Ethnic Variations in the Risk of Infections in People With Prediabetes and Type 2 Diabetes: A Matched Cohort Study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1099-8460</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname><given-names initials="IM">Iain M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5248-4188</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Critchley</surname><given-names initials="JA">Julia A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhry</surname><given-names initials="UAR">Umar A.R.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeWilde</surname><given-names initials="S">Stephen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Limb</surname><given-names initials="ES">Elizabeth S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names initials="DG">Derek G.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whincup</surname><given-names initials="PH">Peter H.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names initials="T">Tess</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Population Health Research Institute, St George&#8217;s, University of London, London, U.K.</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author: Iain M. Carey, <email>i.carey@sgul.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub" iso-8601-date="2023-06-01"><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-04-12"><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>46</volume><issue>6</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">437146</issue-id><fpage>1209</fpage><lpage>1217</lpage><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2022-12-09"><day>09</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2023-03-13"><day>13</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>12</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>02</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-09-18 14:25:43.260"><day>18</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2023 by the American Diabetes Association</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref start_date="2023-04-12">https://www.diabetesjournals.org/journals/pages/license</ali:license_ref><license-p>Readers may use this article as long as the work is properly cited, the use is educational and not for profit, and the work is not altered. More information is available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.diabetesjournals.org/journals/pages/license">https://www.diabetesjournals.org/journals/pages/license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="dc222394.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="dc222394.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="s1"><title>OBJECTIVE</title><p>People living with type 2 diabetes (T2D) are at higher infection risk, but it is unknown how this risk varies by ethnicity or whether the risk is similarly observed in people with nondiabetic hyperglycemia (&#8220;prediabetes&#8221;).</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS</title><p>We included 527,151 patients in England with T2D and 273,216 with prediabetes, aged 18&#8211;90, and alive on 1 January 2015 on the Clinical Practice Research Datalink. Each was matched to two patients without diabetes or prediabetes on age, sex, and ethnic group. Infections during 2015&#8211;2019 were collated from primary care and linked hospitalization records. Infection incidence rate ratios (IRRs) for those with prediabetes or T2D were estimated, unadjusted and adjusted for confounders.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>RESULTS</title><p>People with T2D had increased risk for infections presenting in primary care (IRR 1.51, 95% CI 1.51&#8211;1.52) and hospitalizations (IRR 1.91, 1.90&#8211;1.93). This was broadly consistent overall within each ethnic group, although younger White T2D patients (age &lt;50) experienced a greater relative risk. Adjustment for socioeconomic deprivation, smoking, and comorbidity attenuated associations, but IRRs remained similar by ethnicity. For prediabetes, a significant but smaller risk was observed (primary care IRR 1.35, 95% CI 1.34&#8211;1.36; hospitalization IRR 1.33, 1.31&#8211;1.35). These were similar within each ethnicity for primary care infections, but less consistent for infection-related hospitalizations.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>The elevated infection risk for people with T2D appears similar for different ethnic groups and is also seen in people with prediabetes. Infections are a substantial cause of ill-health and health service use for people with prediabetes and T2D. This has public health implications with rising prediabetes and diabetes prevalence.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical"><title>Graphical Abstract</title><p>
<fig position="float" id="FGA" orientation="portrait"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="dc222394F0GA.jpg"/></fig>
</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group id="sp1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>National Institute for Health and Care Research</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100000272</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NIHR202213</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s6"><title>Introduction</title><p>The proportion of adults in England estimated to have type 2 diabetes (T2D) has been increasing over recent decades (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>) due to a combination of improvements in life expectancy, rising obesity levels (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), and declines in case-fatality (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Additionally, a growing proportion of U.K. adults are thought to have nondiabetic hyperglycemia or &#8220;prediabetes&#8221; (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Due to improved cardiovascular disease risk factor management, cardiovascular disease mortality among people with T2D has declined substantially in recent decades, resulting in a larger proportional increase in the burden of other conditions among people with diabetes (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). One of these is infectious diseases, which are common in people with diabetes (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), resulting in significant health service use, especially in primary care (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), and which have substantial negative impacts on quality of life (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>).</p><p>We previously showed that 15% of people with T2D had a serious infection requiring hospitalization over a 5.5-year follow-up period, a doubling of risk compared with age- and sex-matched patients without diabetes (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). However, we and other studies were unable to assess whether this risk of infection varied by ethnic group. This might arise due to differences in age structure, obesity levels, comorbidities, other risk factors (such as smoking), or potentially, socioeconomic status (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Although few studies have estimated risk by ethnicity among people with diabetes, a higher risk has been reported in the U.S. Black population (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Assessing the risk among non-White ethnic groups is important since their prevalence of T2D is markedly higher and the onset is at younger ages (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Furthermore, little is known about infection risk in the large population of people with prediabetes, where the proportion at younger ages may be higher among non-White ethnic groups (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>).</p><p>This study, therefore, aims to extend our earlier work using data from the Clinical Practice Research Datalink (CPRD) in two important ways. Firstly, we take advantage of improved ethnicity recording in the data to compare within different ethnic groups how similar the risk of infection is between people with and without T2D. Secondly, we investigate for the first time whether an association with infection is also found in people with prediabetes compared with those without diabetes or prediabetes. Finally, for both of these aims, we additionally provide a picture of the attributable risks of infection in primary care and for hospitalizations, due to prediabetes and T2D, both among those with these conditions and across the wider adult population. In doing so, we have chosen to evaluate risks in a period ending just before the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, before severe disruptions to health service use occurred.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Research Design and Methods</title><sec id="s8"><title>Data Resource</title><p>CPRD is a primary care database in the U.K. jointly sponsored by the Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency and the National Institute for Health and Care Research (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). It provides a pseudoanonymized longitudinal medical record for all registered patients (&gt;99% of the U.K. population are registered with a general practitioner), with diagnoses and other clinical information recorded using Read codes. The database recently expanded (CPRD Aurum) to include 16 million currently registered patients (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), with &gt;80% having their ethnicity recorded (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). More than 90% of contributing CPRD practices in England have consented to their data being linked to external sources; researchers have no access to geographical identifiers such as residential postcode (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). These data sources include Hospital Episodes Statistics (HES), which records every National Health Service hospital admission in England (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), and the Index of Multiple Deprivation (IMD), a composite small-area (&#8764;1,500 people) measure used in England for allocation of resources (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Within CPRD, the distribution of IMD is comparable to the national distribution and provides researchers with a good proxy for individual socioeconomic deprivation (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Study Design and Participants</title><p>This retrospective matched cohort study design included all patients aged 18&#8211;90 alive on 1 January 2015 and actively registered for at least 1 year from practices where HES linkage was available. A total of 8,722,348 patients from 1,447 practices in England were eligible (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2337/figshare.22266118" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Fig. 1</ext-link>). Ethical approval for the study was granted by CPRD&#8217;s Research Data Governance (protocol no. 21_000592).</p><p>We classified patients with prediabetes or T2D based on information recorded up to 1 January 2015. Diabetes was first identified from Read codes indicating the patient had been previously diagnosed with diabetes (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2337/figshare.22266118" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link>) and then classified into type 1 or 2 using a strategy developed previously (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2337/figshare.22266118" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Fig. 2</ext-link>) (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). A total of 527,151 T2D patients were selected (6.0% prevalence). Patients with type 1 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 33,851) were not included in this analysis, as we did not anticipate identifying differences in infection risk by ethnicity in this group. Patients with prediabetes were identified from the remaining population if they fulfilled any of <italic toggle="yes">1</italic>) Read code for &#8220;prediabetes&#8221; before 2015; <italic toggle="yes">2</italic>) HbA<sub>1c</sub> &#8805;42 mmol/mol (or &#8805;6%) during 2013&#8211;2014; or <italic toggle="yes">3</italic>) Read code suggesting impaired glucose tolerance during 2013&#8211;2014. We excluded any patients with prediabetes (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 738) if they had received any antidiabetes medication (except biguanides) before 2015. A total of 273,216 patients with prediabetes were selected (3.1% prevalence).</p><p>Patients were grouped into five broad ethnicity categories (White, South Asian, Black, mixed/other, and missing) based on recorded Read codes (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2337/figshare.22266118" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link>) (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). In the U.K., ethnicity is predominantly self-reported in primary care records. In our data, we were able to classify ethnicity for &#8764;90% of patients with prediabetes or T2D.</p><p>For each patient with prediabetes or T2D we created two distinct sets of patients without prediabetes or diabetes matched on <italic toggle="yes">1</italic>) age, sex, and practice, and <italic toggle="yes">2</italic>) age, sex, and ethnicity. For each of the four sets produced, patients were randomly selected without replacement from the set of all suitable matches. Thus, it was possible for a patient without prediabetes or diabetes to be selected in each of the four matched sets. More than 99% of prediabetes/T2D patients were matched (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2337/figshare.22266118" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Fig. 1</ext-link>), and, overall, at least one match was found for &gt;98% of patients within each ethnic group. All patients were followed up to the earliest date of patient death or deregistration, practice leaving CPRD, or 31 December 2019. We also conducted a sensitivity analyses for patients with prediabetes who received a diagnosis of diabetes during the study by censoring their follow-up time on the day of the first diabetes diagnosis.</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Infection Outcomes and Covariates</title><p>We classified and grouped infections broadly along the same lines as our previous study (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). First, we updated an extensive list of Read codes (primary care) and ICD-10 codes (hospital data) for all infection diagnoses (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2337/figshare.22266118" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link>). Second, we searched electronically in the data over a 5-year period (2015&#8211;2019) for the following: <italic toggle="yes">1</italic>) any infection with a prescription in primary care for an antibiotic, antifungal, or antiviral within &#177;14 days of the diagnosis; <italic toggle="yes">2</italic>) any new hospital episode where an infection was the primary diagnosis. In the U.K., hospital data are organized into finished consultant episodes and assigned a primary diagnosis (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Subsequent episodes can be assigned to the same admission, with a different primary diagnosis (e.g., a hospital-acquired infection). For each summary group, only one event was counted within a 90-day period, with multiple codes assumed to be the same event. Additionally, we conducted an analysis with each of the individual infection groups, again restricting to one event per group within a 90-day period.</p><p>We also extracted patient information on smoking history, BMI, and comorbidities as of 1 January 2015. We selected 12 chronic conditions routinely collected as part of the Quality and Outcomes Framework (QOF), a U.K.-wide system for performance management and payment of general practitioners in primary care (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). These were atrial fibrillation, cancer, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, coronary heart disease, chronic kidney disease, dementia, epilepsy, heart failure, hypertension, peripheral vascular disease, serious mental illness, and stroke.</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Statistical Methods</title><p>Conditional Poisson regression compared infection rates during follow-up between patients with prediabetes or T2D to those without prediabetes/diabetes, with an offset fitted for total days of follow-up time in the study (Stata 15 software). These were conditioned on the match sets, which implicitly controls for the matching factors (age, sex, and practice/ethnicity). These were initially fitted without any further adjustment, but we also fitted models that adjusted for socioeconomic status (IMD quintile, with quintile 1 representing the most deprived 20% small areas in England), smoking, and a count of comorbidities. To assess the impact of ethnicity as a confounder, we compared results from the ethnicity-matched with the non-ethnicity&#8211;matched analysis. To explore the impact of age and ethnicity as effect modifiers, we fitted stratified models by age-group (18&#8211;50, 51&#8211;70, 71&#8211;90) and by ethnicity separately as well as together. For these analyses, we present and compare unadjusted models in the main analysis because between&#8211;ethnic group differences in key confounders, such as socioeconomic deprivation, will be indirectly controlled as each model only compares within ethnic group. However, we also provide adjusted estimates (by ethnicity) in the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2337/figshare.22266118" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Material</ext-link>. Sensitivity analyses explored the impact of additionally adjusting for obesity and censoring follow-up time for patients with prediabetes who received a diagnosis of diabetes during the study period. Finally, attributable risks for infection in people with prediabetes and T2D and population-attributable risks were estimated for each ethnic group, assuming prediabetes or T2D is the direct cause of any observed infection risk. These were estimated using models stratified by 10-year age-group (18&#8211;29, 30&#8211;39, and so on to 80&#8211;89) and summed using a weighted average (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). We provide calculations derived from the unadjusted and adjusted models described above.</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Role of the Funding Source</title><p>The study funder had no role in study design, collection, analysis, and interpretation of data; writing of the report or decision to submit the paper for publication. The corresponding author had full access to all the data in the study and final responsibility for the decision to submit for publication.</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Data and Resource Availability</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from CPRD obtained under license from the U.K. Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency, but restrictions apply to the availability of these data, which were used under license for the current study and therefore are not publicly available. CPRD data governance and the license to use CPRD data do not allow distribution of patient data directly to other parties. Researchers must apply directly to CPRD for data access (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cprd.com" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cprd.com</ext-link>). However, code lists generated during the current study are available in the St George&#8217;s Research Data Repository (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.24376/rd.sgul.21565557" ext-link-type="uri">https://10.24376/rd.sgul.21565557</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s14"><title>Results</title><sec id="s15"><title>Study Population</title><p><xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> summarizes the baseline characteristics of patients with prediabetes and T2D by ethnicity. Approximately 70% of patients were classified as White ethnicity, followed by &#8764;10% as South Asian ethnicity. In the wider population, crude prevalence was highest for South Asian ethnicity (5.5% prediabetes, 11.1% T2D), with this difference more striking at younger ages (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2337/figshare.22266118" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Fig. 3</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2337/figshare.22266118" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 2</ext-link>). Patients with prediabetes were more likely to be women for all ethnicities, whereas people with T2D were more likely to be men (except for Black ethnicity). The White ethnicity group had a mean age of 67 years for both prediabetes and T2D. Non-White ethnicities were on average 10&#8211;13 years younger for prediabetes and 5&#8211;7 years younger for T2D, and consequently, had fewer comorbidities. For both prediabetes and T2D, non-White ethnicities were more likely to live in deprived areas, with 4 in 10 in the Black ethnicity group residing in the most deprived quintile. Among those with prediabetes, Black patients had the highest average recorded BMI, with 48.3% being &gt;30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>, while for those with T2D, White people had the highest BMI levels (54.3% &gt;30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of all patients with prediabetes and T2D by ethnicity</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Prediabetes (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 273,216)</th><th align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">T2D (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 527,151)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Asian</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed/other</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity unknown</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Asian</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed/other</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity unknown</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (% overall)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,368 (10.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,366 (4.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,331 (5.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189,195 (69.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,956 (10.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54,913 (10.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,533 (4.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30,289 (5.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">368,253 (69.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51,163 (9.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimated prevalence in the population (%)<xref rid="tblfn2" ref-type="table-fn">&#8224;</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matching<xref rid="tblfn3" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Age-sex-practice</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,246 (99.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,338 (99.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,300 (99.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">188,920 (99.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,922 (99.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53,776 (97.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,248 (98.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30,076 (99.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">367,264 (99.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50,935 (99.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Age-sex-ethnicity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,366 (100.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,364 (100.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,329 (100.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189,170 (100.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,949 (100.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53,763 (97.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,465 (99.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30,237 (99.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">368,206 (100.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51,141 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,267 (52.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,351 (55.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,298 (54.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97,068 (51.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,900 (49.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25,214 (45.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,389 (50.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,298 (47.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">159,901 (43.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,319 (43.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,101 (47.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,015 (45.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,033 (45.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92,127 (48.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,056 (50.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29,699 (54.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,144 (49.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,991 (52.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208,352 (56.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28,844 (56.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years), mean (SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.6 (14.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.3 (13.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.1 (13.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.3 (12.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.4 (14.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.0 (13.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.1 (13.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.5 (13.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.6 (12.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.5 (13.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quintile of socioeconomic deprivation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1&#8211;Least deprived</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,354 (8.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">291 (2.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,311 (8.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38,950 (20.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,573 (23.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,902 (8.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">591 (2.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,909 (9.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68,139 (18.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,927 (21.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;5&#8211;Most deprived</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,478 (31.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,457 (40.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,330 (28.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33,350 (17.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,997 (14.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,744 (30.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,519 (42.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,976 (29.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78,777 (21.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,814 (17.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>) mean (SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2 (5.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.7 (6.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5 (6.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.8 (6.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.2 (6.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5 (5.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.6 (6.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.8 (6.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.5 (6.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.7 (6.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI &gt;30 kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,256 (30.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,460 (48.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,046 (39.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79,821 (42.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,046 (35.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,721 (32.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,793 (47.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,633 (41.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200,101 (54.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24,436 (47.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,899 (72.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,547 (64.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,572 (55.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66,756 (35.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,013 (39.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36,620 (66.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,511 (60.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,555 (51.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114,601 (31.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,395 (34.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Former</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,647 (17.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,201 (24.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,391 (28.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91,151 (48.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,481 (44.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,999 (23.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,764 (30.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,584 (34.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197,724 (53.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25,371 (49.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Current</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,795 (10.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,604 (12.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,358 (15.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31,173 (16.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,323 (15.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,278 (9.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,246 (10.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,138 (13.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55,823 (15.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,982 (15.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbidities<xref rid="tblfn4" ref-type="table-fn">&#8225;</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,183 (59.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,128 (45.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,722 (50.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56,268 (29.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,292 (29.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,756 (36.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,367 (28.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,602 (31.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78,098 (21.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,395 (24.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1&#8211;2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,163 (37.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,650 (49.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,857 (44.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105,479 (55.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,169 (54.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29,970 (54.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,772 (61.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,443 (57.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219,638 (59.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28,075 (54.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&gt;2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,022 (3.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">588 (4.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">752 (4.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,448 (14.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,495 (16.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,187 (9.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,394 (10.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,244 (10.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70,517 (19.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,693 (20.9)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><p>Data are presented as <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%) unless indicated otherwise. The IMD was not available for 174 people (0.1%) with prediabetes and 377 (0.1%) with T2Ds. BMI was not available for 6,221 patients (2.3%) with prediabetes and 3,034 (0.6%) with T2D. Smoking was not available for 305 people (0.1%) with prediabetes and 560 (0.1%) of those with T2D.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn2"><label>&#8224;</label><p>Crude prevalence among all CPRD patients aged 18&#8211;90 actively registered on 1 January 2015 for at least 1 year.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn3"><label>*</label><p>Percentage of patients with prediabetes or T2D who were matched to at least one patient without diabetes.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn4"><label>&#8225;</label><p>Count of the following: atrial fibrillation, cancer, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, coronary heart disease, chronic kidney disease, dementia, epilepsy, heart failure, hypertension, peripheral vascular disease, serious mental illness (e.g., psychosis, schizophrenia, or bipolar affective disorder), or stroke/transient ischemic attack.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>We also compared baseline characteristic differences between patients with prediabetes or T2D and age-, sex-, and ethnicity-matched patients without prediabetes/diabetes (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2337/figshare.22266118" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 3</ext-link>). Patients with prediabetes and T2D were both more likely to live in deprived areas, be more obese, have a history of smoking, and have comorbidities than patients without prediabetes or diabetes. The relationship with socioeconomic deprivation was further explored within ethnic groups (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2337/figshare.22266118" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Fig. 4</ext-link>) and showed that the association of greater deprivation with prediabetes or T2D, compared with patients without prediabetes/diabetes, is maintained despite differences in overall deprivation between ethnic groups.</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Overall Findings for Infections</title><p>There were significant increases in infection risk for both patients with T2D and prediabetes compared with patients without prediabetes/diabetes (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Comparisons using the age-, sex-, and ethnicity-matched versus the age-, sex-, and practice-matched comparison group yielded similar results, and all analyses from this point use the age-, sex-, and ethnicity-matched group. For T2D, the (unadjusted) relative risks of infection were higher for hospitalizations (incidence rate ratio [IRR] 1.91, 95% CI 1.90&#8211;1.93) than primary care infections (IRR 1.51, 95% CI 1.51&#8211;1.52). The relative association with primary care infections was similar by sex, but slightly higher in women for hospitalizations (IRR 2.02, 95% CI 1.99&#8211;2.05 vs. IRR 1.83, 95% CI 1.80&#8211;1.85). Larger relative associations were found at younger ages for both outcomes (e.g., IRR 2.96 95% CI 2.85&#8211;3.08 for hospitalizations and T2D for ages 18&#8211;50), where the infection rates among patients without diabetes were comparatively lower. Even after accounting for the greater number of comorbidities in people with T2D (as well as differences in smoking and socioeconomic deprivation), associations with both infection outcomes were still observed among people with T2D. Adjusting for obesity only explained a small proportion of the observed association and was less influential than comorbidity in the models (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2337/figshare.22266118" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 4</ext-link>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Infection rates and IRRs in patients with prediabetes, T2D, and matched patients without prediabetes or diabetes, overall and stratified by age and sex</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Infection outcome</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Non-D matched comparison<xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prediabetes</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-D<xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Pre-T2D vs. non-D<xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2D</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-D<xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">T2D vs. non-D<xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rate<xref rid="tblfn6" ref-type="table-fn">&#8224;</xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rate<xref rid="tblfn6" ref-type="table-fn">&#8224;</xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRR1<xref rid="tblfn7" ref-type="table-fn">&#8225;</xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRR2<xref rid="tblfn7" ref-type="table-fn">&#8225;</xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rate<xref rid="tblfn6" ref-type="table-fn">&#8224;</xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rate<xref rid="tblfn6" ref-type="table-fn">&#8224;</xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRR1<xref rid="tblfn7" ref-type="table-fn">&#8225;</xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRR2<xref rid="tblfn7" ref-type="table-fn">&#8225;</xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary care</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195; All</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age-sex-practice</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">194.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33&#8211;1.35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24&#8211;1.26</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49&#8211;1.51</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32&#8211;1.34</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195; All</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age-sex-ethnicity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">194.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34&#8211;1.36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24&#8211;1.26</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">143.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51&#8211;1.52</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32&#8211;1.33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195; Females</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age-sex-ethnicity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33&#8211;1.35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24&#8211;1.26</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">257.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51&#8211;1.53</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32&#8211;1.34</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195; Males</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age-sex-ethnicity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">161.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35&#8211;1.38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23&#8211;1.26</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">181.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49&#8211;1.52</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30&#8211;1.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;18&#8211;50 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age-sex-ethnicity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68&#8211;1.74</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57&#8211;1.64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.98&#8211;2.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77&#8211;1.83</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;51&#8211;70 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age-sex-ethnicity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39&#8211;1.43</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27.1.30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61&#8211;1.63</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38&#8211;1.40</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;71&#8211;90 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age-sex-ethnicity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19&#8211;1.21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11&#8211;1.13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">235.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">181.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30&#8211;1.32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16&#8211;1.18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitalizations</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;All</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age-sex-practice</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29&#8211;1.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09&#8211;1.13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79&#8211;1.82</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40&#8211;1.43</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;All</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age-sex-ethnicity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31&#8211;1.35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09&#8211;1.13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90&#8211;1.93</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43&#8211;1.46</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Females</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age-sex-ethnicity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32&#8211;1.38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11&#8211;1.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.99&#8211;2.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48&#8211;1.52</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Males</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age-sex-ethnicity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27&#8211;1.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06&#8211;1.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80&#8211;1.85</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38&#8211;1.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;18&#8211;50 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age-sex-ethnicity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91&#8211;2.14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.72</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62&#8211;1.83</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.96</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.85&#8211;3.08</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15&#8211;2.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;51&#8211;70 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age-sex-ethnicity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43&#8211;1.50</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13&#8211;1.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25&#8211;2.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55&#8211;1.61</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;71&#8211;90 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age-sex-ethnicity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19&#8211;1.23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02&#8211;1.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66&#8211;1.70</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31&#8211;1.35</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn5"><label>*</label><p>Non-D are patients without diabetes or prediabetes matched on age-sex-practice or age-sex-ethnicity.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn6"><label>&#8224;</label><p>Crude infection rate per 1,000 per year.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn7"><label>&#8225;</label><p>IRR compared with nondiabetes. IRR1 is not adjusted (besides matching factors). IRR2 additionally adjusts for index of multiple deprivation, smoking, and number of comorbidities. Prediabetes or T2D patients are only included in the analysis if they have a matched nondiabetes patient: prediabetes with age-sex-practice match, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 274,917; prediabetes with age-sex-ethnicity match, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 275,408; T2D with age-sex-practice match, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 529,678; T2D with age-sex-ethnicity match, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 531,596.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>For people with prediabetes, (unadjusted) infection risks were smaller overall and similar for primary care (IRR 1.35, 95% CI 1.34&#8211;1.36) and hospitalizations (IRR 1.33, 95% CI 1.31&#8211;1.35) and showed similar gradation with age. After adjustment for confounders, the association with hospitalization was reduced further, especially among older ages. Censoring patients with prediabetes diagnosed with diabetes during follow-up had minimal impact on these associations (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2337/figshare.22266118" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 4</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Infection Findings by Ethnic Group</title><p><xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> plots crude infection rates (primary care, hospitalizations) in patients with prediabetes and T2D patients by ethnicity. These are compared with matched patients without diabetes/prediabetes. Among patients with T2D, infections in primary care were highest for South Asian people (235.1 per 1,000 per year), while hospitalization infections were highest for the White group (68.0 per 1,000 per year). However, compared with patients without prediabetes/diabetes in the same ethnic group, the relative increase in risk for both infection outcomes was broadly similar across ethnic groups (e.g., IRRs for hospitalization were South Asian 1.98, 95% CI 1.91&#8211;2.06; Black 1.87, 95% CI 1.76&#8211;2.00; mixed/other 1.98, 95% CI 1.88&#8211;2.08; and White 1.88, 95% CI 1.86&#8211;1.98). For prediabetes, the pattern of a similar increase in infection risk by ethnic group was observed for infections in primary care but was less consistent for hospitalizations, where Black people with prediabetes had no statistically significant increase in risk compared with Black people without prediabetes/diabetes (IRR 1.07, 95% CI 0.96&#8211;1.18).</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Infection rates and IRRs in patients with prediabetes, T2D, and without diabetes by ethnicity. Unadjusted IRRs (with 95% CIs). Nondiabetes indicates patients without diabetes or prediabetes matched on age, sex, and ethnicity.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="dc222394f1.jpg"/></fig><p>As people of non-White ethnicities with prediabetes or T2D were on average younger (and healthier) in our data than White people with the same conditions, we stratified the (unadjusted) ethnic specific IRRs by age (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>) and also adjusted the IRRs for potential confounders (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2337/figshare.22266118" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Tables 5 and 6</ext-link>). These reveal that for T2D, there tends to be a higher relative risk among the youngest ages (18&#8211;50) in the White ethnic group (IRR 2.12, 95% CI 2.07&#8211;2.16 for primary care infections; IRR 3.23, 95% CI 3.08&#8211;3.40 for hospitalizations) compared with the risks found in non-White ethnicities. Above age 50, the IRRs are generally similar between ethnicities for both prediabetes and T2D, although the Black ethnicity group with prediabetes showed no increased risk with hospitalizations. Adjusting for confounders within each ethnic group attenuated all associations, but not did alter findings made on comparisons between ethnic groups.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>IRRs for infections in patients with prediabetes and T2D vs. patients without diabetes, stratified by ethnicity and age. Orange symbols, prediabetes; blue symbols, T2D; circles, primary care; triangles, hospitalizations. Unadjusted IRRs (with 95% CIs). Nondiabetes indicates patients without diabetes or prediabetes matched on age, sex, and ethnicity.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="dc222394f2.jpg"/></fig><p>Finally, we investigated associations with specific infection types by ethnicity in prediabetes and T2D (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2337/figshare.22266118" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Tables 7 and 8</ext-link>). Within each ethnic group, associations were consistently observed for every infection group apart from extremely rare ones where power was low. Upper respiratory tract infections were almost twice as common in South Asian T2D patients compared with other ethnic groups with T2D. However, when compared with South Asian patients without diabetes/prediabetes, the relative increase in risk was more similar (IRR 1.43, 95% CI 1.40&#8211;1.46), albeit still higher than the corresponding relative risk within the White ethnic group (IRR 1.21, 95% CI 1.20&#8211;1.22).</p></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Attributable Risk Estimates</title><p>Attributable risk fractions by ethnic group due to prediabetes and T2D were estimated for primary care and hospital infections (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2337/figshare.22266118" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 9</ext-link>) and then weighted accordingly to create population-wide estimates. The attributable fractions by ethnic group among patients with prediabetes or T2D derived from the IRRs in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> were 32&#8211;36% for primary care infections and 49&#8211;56% for hospitalization infections for T2D, while for prediabetes they were similar for primary care infections (24&#8211;32%) but lower for hospitalization infections, especially among Black people with prediabetes (7%). The percentage of infections among all adults in the population attributable to prediabetes or T2D was 5.8% for primary care and 10.0% for hospitalizations. When estimated by ethnic group, these were highest among South Asian people (11.6% and 17.4%, respectively).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s19"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our study has two key findings. Firstly, we have shown that the relative risks for infection associated with T2D appear to be broadly similar within each ethnic group, and this remains true at different ages and after adjustment for potential confounders. As in our previous work (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), compared with people without prediabetes/diabetes of the same age, sex, and now additionally ethnicity, the risk of hospitalization for infection was roughly doubled among people with T2D, and &#8764;50% higher for infections requiring primary care contact and an associated prescription. Secondly, we have shown that increased risks for infection are also present in people with prediabetes, albeit lower, at approximately a 30% increase for both infection outcomes when compared with people without diabetes/prediabetes.</p><sec id="s20"><title>Strengths and Limitations</title><p>Overall, a major strength of our study is the extremely large sample size (8 million total adults, 750,000 with prediabetes and T2D). The large number of patients with prediabetes is a likely result of the increased emphasis on both vascular health checks and specifically, diabetes prevention and screening in primary care (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>), although it still may be underestimating the true scale of prediabetes in the general population, as this continues to rise globally (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). However, our sample is still likely highly representative of people living with prediabetes or T2D in England before the COVID-19 pandemic (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Previous CPRD analyses (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) have been based on an earlier data set (CPRD GOLD), which underrepresented major urban areas with ethnic diversity. By using the newer Aurum database, with higher overall recording of patient ethnicity, we were able to successfully match patients by broad ethnic group unlike previous studies (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>), resulting in a stronger design for assessing the pattern of between ethnic differences in risk. In our study, matching was highly successful overall and in each ethnic group: &gt;98% of people living with prediabetes or T2D had at least one patient without diabetes matched on age and sex. Additionally, we selected patients without diabetes or prediabetes matched on practice rather than ethnicity to establish the impact of ethnicity as a confounder in our earlier findings. Although &#8764;10% of patients with T2D or prediabetes could not be assigned an ethnicity, we retained these patients in the analysis to assess any potential bias. These patients tended to be older and more affluent, largely resembling the characteristics of the White ethnicity group, suggesting that we captured a high proportion of non-White ethnicities with T2D or prediabetes.</p><p>Importantly, our analysis was able to consider the impact of age as an effect modifier and show that relative risks were higher in the youngest age-group, where the baseline risks of infection in the population without prediabetes or diabetes tends to be much lower. For example, people &lt;50 with T2D were three times more likely to be hospitalized with an infection than people without prediabetes or diabetes. However, the increase in infection risk with age in the population reference group is such that the absolute risk differences are still greater at older ages despite the lower relative risk. Since non-White ethnic groups in the U.K. are younger on average, we were able to investigate how age was modifying the relationships with the overall ethnic-specific associations. This revealed that younger people with T2D of White ethnicity were at greater risk (both relative and absolute differences), while people with prediabetes from Black and Afro-Caribbean ethnic minorities had little or no excess risk of hospitalization for infection. We further considered the impact of factors more common in people with prediabetes or T2D (socioeconomic deprivation, smoking, comorbidity), even though some of their comorbidity, such as heart disease, may be a result of their diabetes. Although this may represent an overadjustment, our conclusions regarding ethnicity and infection risk were not altered.</p><p>Clearly, primary care recording of infection outcomes is pragmatic and imperfect, based on clinical diagnoses. However, the magnitude of infection risk was stronger for infections resulting in a hospitalization, where infection recording is more often supported by laboratory findings. Identification of both diabetes and prediabetes is dependent on general practice consultations; prediabetes, in particular, may be significantly underdiagnosed in primary care (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), resulting in misclassification of exposure and potentially underestimating the association with infection risk. However, the pattern of infection risk identified for this patient group appears similar, albeit lower, than that for people with T2D. Our study is based on retrospective cohort data from a period ending just before the COVID-19 pandemic. Incidence and recording of infections, especially in primary care, has likely been profoundly affected by the disruption to normal health service delivery during the pandemic, so we believe it is more informative to assess non&#8211;COVID-19 infection risk prior to this date. Future studies could focus on how this has been affected since 2020.</p></sec><sec id="s21"><title>Comparisons With Other Studies</title><p>Ethnic differences in infection risk have been a topic of considerable recent interest since persistent mortality differences by ethnicity were noted from the early stages of the COVID-19 pandemic (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Subsequently, a higher risk of testing positive for severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 among non-White ethnic groups was also confirmed (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). To the best of our knowledge, few studies have considered whether infections in general might differ by ethnicity in people with diabetes. The higher prevalence of tuberculosis infection reported among Hispanic and Asian people in the U.S. has been hypothesized to explain the association between diabetes and tuberculosis (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). While this might reflect poor health care access, socioeconomic deprivation, or potentially, publication bias (since most studies only report on individual infections), a recent U.S. cohort study reported higher risks of infection-related hospitalization associated with diabetes in younger people and in people of Black ethnicity (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). However, the study size (&#8764;1,500 people with diabetes) meant it could not stratify by ethnicity or consider whether differences in age among the Black population might explain ethnic variation in infection risk.</p><p>In our study, we were able to report on differences in infection rates by ethnic group at different ages, which suggested that non-White ethnicities were less likely to be hospitalized for an infection. In the U.K., overall hospitalization rates have been shown to vary by ethnicity across different conditions (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), likely due to pervasive inequalities and differences in health-seeking behaviors (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). For example, people from Black African and Caribbean ethnicities have higher reported hospitalizations for diabetes and endocrine disorders relative to the White population, but their overall hospitalization rates are significantly lower, possibly reflecting barriers to access within the health care system (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). By contrast, some specific infection groups we reported on were more common in non-White ethnicities, such as upper respiratory infections in South Asian people. These may reflect generally higher household size found for Bangladeshi and Pakistani people in the U.K. (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>), representing a greater risk of transmission among household members. However, the higher or lower infection rates by ethnicity were true irrespective of diabetes, so estimated relative risks of infection for prediabetes or T2D versus people without diabetes tended to be similar within each ethnic group (with the possible exception of a greater infection risk among younger White people with T2D). We did not assess whether diabetes clinical management or severity differed by ethnicity, although a previous study found improved risk factor recording and faster time to starting antidiabetes medications among ethnic minority groups (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s22"><title>Implications of Study Findings</title><p>Management of infections in people living with diabetes is clearly a common problem for patients and doctors but had not always received much attention before the pandemic. While National Institute for Health and Care Excellence guidelines for people with T2D provide little mention of infections (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>), we have shown that attributable risks in those living with T2D are substantial (34% for primary care, 50% for hospitalizations) and consistent by ethnic group. Although some of this attributable risk may be explained by their poorer overall health, it does not change the fact that these patients experience a large burden of infections by having T2D. Our analyses also demonstrated that higher risks were also present, although somewhat reduced, in people with prediabetes in both health care settings. This suggests that any infection risk does not begin with a diagnosis of diabetes but is instead on a continuum and already present in this large group of patients. Given the high and rising prevalence of prediabetes and T2D (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>), this is of considerable importance and results in a substantial population burden affecting people with diabetes and prediabetes and health services. We estimate that &#8764;6% of all adult infections treated in primary care and 10% of hospitalizations due to infection are statistically attributable to prediabetes or T2D and that these will continue to increase with rising prevalence (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). The South Asian population experiences the greatest estimated burden (12% and 17%, respectively) as a result of the higher prevalence of prediabetes and T2D at all ages.</p><p>There has been little previous development of interventions to reduce infection risks in people with diabetes; infection outcomes have not been included in most major diabetes management trials (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Therefore, robust observational data may instead provide an initial path to developing interventions, potentially based on increased self-management of risk factors and awareness by promptly identifying infections and knowing when to seek professional help, which could lead to reduced hospital admissions for some infections. Enhanced glucose monitoring and offering better diabetes control among the highest-risk individuals might improve infection outcomes, but this has not been clearly demonstrated and thus remains a gap in our knowledge. As we have previously shown that poor glycemic control is associated with the risk of serious infections (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>), future work could establish whether any association with HbA<sub>1c</sub> level is also present in people with prediabetes.</p><p>In conclusion, we have used large routine health databases in England to reveal that the increased infection risk associated with T2D is generally consistent across different ethnic groups and also observed in people with prediabetes. The burden of infections attributable to T2D and prediabetes is significant and will continue to have public health implications with their rising prevalence. Efforts to reduce infection risk in people with diabetes remains an important challenge in all ethnic groups.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Article Information</title><p><bold>Acknowledgments.</bold> The authors thank their helpful Patient Study Advisory Group for their input, particularly to discussion and interpretation of the results.</p><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This study is funded by the National Institute for Health and Care Research (NIHR) Research for Patient Benefit Programme (NIHR202213) and supported by the NIHR Applied Research Collaboration South London at King&#8217;s College Hospital NHS Foundation Trust.</p><p>The views expressed are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the NIHR or the Department of Health and Social Care.</p><p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Duality of Interest.</bold> No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article were reported.</p><p><bold>Author Contributions.</bold> I.M.C. led the data curation and statistical analysis. I.M.C. and J.A.C. wrote the first draft of the manuscript with input from all coauthors. I.M.C., J.A.C., U.A.R.C., S.W., D.G.C., and T.H. were involved in the conception and design of the study. J.A.C. led on funding acquisition. I.M.C, J.A.C., U.A.R.C., S.W., E.S.L., D.G.C., P.H.W., and T.H. were involved in the interpretation of data for the work. I.M.C, J.A.C., U.A.R.C., S.W., E.S.L., D.G.C., P.H.W., and T.H. approved the final version for publication. I.M.C. is the guarantor of this work and, as such, had full access to all the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="supplementary-material"><p>This article contains supplementary material online at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2337/figshare.22266118" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.2337/figshare.22266118</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Whicher</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Neill</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>RIG</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Diabetes in the UK: 2019</article-title>. <source>Diabet Med</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>242</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31901175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/dme.14225</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Forouhi</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goyder</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wild</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The Association of Public Health Observatories (APHO) Diabetes Prevalence Model: estimates of total diabetes prevalence for England, 2010-2030</article-title>. <source>Diabet Med</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>575</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>582</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21480968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1464-5491.2010.03216.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins-Jones</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schernthaner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence, glucose control and relative survival of people with Type 2 diabetes in the UK from 1991 to 2013</article-title>. <source>Diabet Med</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>770</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>780</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28173634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/dme.13332</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mainous</surname><given-names>AG</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tanner</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zayas</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harle</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of prediabetes in England from 2003 to 2011: population-based, cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e005002</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4054625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24913327</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ravindrarajah</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Howarth</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology and determinants of non-diabetic hyperglycaemia and its conversion to type 2 diabetes mellitus, 2000-2015: cohort population study using UK electronic health records</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e040201</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2020-040201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7484863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32893192</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson-Stuttard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Trends in predominant causes of death in individuals with and without diabetes in England from 2001 to 2018: an epidemiological analysis of linked primary care records</article-title>. <source>Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33549162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2213-8587(20)30431-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7886654</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tomic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Magliano</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The burden and risks of emerging complications of diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Endocrinol</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>525</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35668219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41574-022-00690-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9169030</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gregg</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in diabetes-related complications in the United States, 1990-2010</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>370</volume>:<fpage>1514</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24738668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMoa1310799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hux</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Quantifying the risk of infectious diseases for people with diabetes</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>510</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12547890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/diacare.26.2.510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Millett</surname><given-names>ERC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nitsch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>CKD and the risk of acute, community-acquired infections among older people with diabetes mellitus: a retrospective cohort study using electronic health records</article-title>. <source>Am J Kidney Dis</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>60</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25641062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.ajkd.2014.11.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4510204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson-Stuttard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Blundell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Critchley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Diabetes and infection: assessing the association with glycaemic control in population-based studies</article-title>. <source>Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>148</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26656292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2213-8587(15)00379-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Critchley</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>DeWilde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hosking</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of infection in type 1 and type 2 diabetes compared with the general population: a matched cohort study</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>513</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>521</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29330152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/dc17-2131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Niedzwiedz</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Donnell</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jani</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Ethnic and socioeconomic differences in SARS-CoV-2 infection: prospective cohort study using UK Biobank</article-title>. <source>BMC Med</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>160</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32466757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12916-020-01640-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7255908</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ishigami</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Echouffo-Tcheugui</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lutsey</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pankow</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Selvin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Diabetes and the risk of hospitalisation for infection: the Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) study</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>2458</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34345973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00125-021-05522-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8331324</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Ethnicity and Type 2 diabetes in the UK</article-title>. <source>Diabet Med</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>927</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>938</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30614072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/dme.13895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sidell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Arterburn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Racial/ethnic disparities in the prevalence of diabetes and prediabetes by BMI: Patient Outcomes Research To Advance Learning (PORTAL) multisite cohort of adults in the U.S</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>2211</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31537541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/dc19-0532</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6868463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dedman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Data resource profile: Clinical Practice Research Datalink (CPRD) Aurum</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>1740</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1740g</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30859197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ije/dyz034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6929522</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>DeWilde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhry</surname><given-names>UAR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Strachan</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for excess all-cause mortality during the first wave of the COVID-19 pandemic in England: a retrospective cohort study of primary care data</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>e0260381</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34882700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0260381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8659693</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Padmanabhan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carty</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Strongman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Approach to record linkage of primary care data from Clinical Practice Research Datalink to other health-related patient data: overview and implications</article-title>. <source>Eur J Epidemiol</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>91</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30219957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10654-018-0442-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6325980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Herbert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wijlaars</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zylbersztejn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cromwell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hardelid</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Data resource profile: Hospital Episode Statistics Admitted Patient Care (HES APC)</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>1093</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1093i</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28338941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ije/dyx015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5837677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>GOV.UK</collab></person-group>. <article-title>English indices of deprivation</article-title>. <year>2020</year>. <comment>Accessed 6 January 2023. Available from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.gov.uk/government/collections/english-indices-of-deprivation" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.gov.uk/government/collections/english-indices-of-deprivation</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mahadevan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fordyce</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Completeness and representativeness of small area socioeconomic data linked with the UK Clinical Practice Research Datalink (CPRD)</article-title>. <source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>880</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>886</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35902219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/jech-2022-219200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9484378</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>NHS Digital</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Quality and Outcomes Framework (QOF), enhanced services and core contract extraction specifications</article-title>. <year>2022</year>. <comment>Accessed 13 April 2022. Available from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://digital.nhs.uk/data-and-information/data-collections-and-data-sets/data-collections/quality-and-outcomes-framework-qof" ext-link-type="uri">https://digital.nhs.uk/data-and-information/data-collections-and-data-sets/data-collections/quality-and-outcomes-framework-qof</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hanley</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A heuristic approach to the formulas for population attributable fraction</article-title>. <source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>508</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>514</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11413183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/jech.55.7.508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1731931</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Palladino</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tabak</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khunti</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between pre-diabetes and microvascular and macrovascular disease in newly diagnosed type 2 diabetes</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open Diabetes Res Care</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e001061</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjdrc-2019-001061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7202749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32332069</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>International Diabetes Federation</collab></person-group>. <article-title>IDF Diabetes Atlas, 10th edition, 2021</article-title>. <comment>Accessed 20 January 2023. Available from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://diabetesatlas.org/atlas/tenth-edition/" ext-link-type="uri">https://diabetesatlas.org/atlas/tenth-edition/</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>JMR</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Age-, sex- and ethnicity-related differences in body weight, blood pressure, HbA<sub>1c</sub> and lipid levels at the diagnosis of type 2 diabetes relative to people without diabetes</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>1542</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1553</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32435821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00125-020-05169-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7351865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nitsch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Millett</surname><given-names>ERC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>New estimates of the burden of acute community-acquired infections among older people with diabetes mellitus: a retrospective cohort study using linked electronic health records</article-title>. <source>Diabet Med</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>606</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>614</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24341529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/dme.12384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4264938</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aldridge</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lewer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Katikireddi</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Black, Asian and Minority Ethnic groups in England are at increased risk of death from COVID-19: indirect standardisation of NHS mortality data</article-title>. <source>Wellcome Open Res</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>88</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32613083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.12688/wellcomeopenres.15922.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7317462</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mathur</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rentsch</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>.; <collab>OpenSAFELY Collaborative</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Ethnic differences in SARS-CoV-2 infection and COVID-19-related hospitalisation, intensive care unit admission, and death in 17 million adults in England: an observational cohort study using the OpenSAFELY platform</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>397</volume>:<fpage>1711</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33939953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)00634-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8087292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Tuberculosis infection among people with diabetes: United States population differences by race/ethnicity</article-title>. <source>Am J Prev Med</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>858</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>863</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32061457</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amepre.2019.12.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7246160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kandt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Longley</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Ethnic inequalities in hospital admissions in England: an observational study</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>862</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33947358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12889-021-10923-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8097885</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marmot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boyce</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goldblatt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Health Equity in England: The Marmot Review 10 Years On</article-title>. <comment>The Health Foundation, 2020. Accessed 20 January 2023. Available from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.health.org.uk/publications/reports/the-marmot-review-10-years-on" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.health.org.uk/publications/reports/the-marmot-review-10-years-on</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>GOV.UK</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Ethnicity facts and figures</article-title>. <comment>Overcrowded households. 2020. Accessed 28 November 2022. Available from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ethnicity-facts-figures.service.gov.uk/housing/housing-conditions/overcrowded-households/latest" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ethnicity-facts-figures.service.gov.uk/housing/housing-conditions/overcrowded-households/latest</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mathur</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Palla</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chaturvedi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smeeth</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Ethnic differences in the severity and clinical management of type 2 diabetes at time of diagnosis: a cohort study in the UK Clinical Practice Research Datalink</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Res Clin Pract</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>160</volume>:<fpage>108006</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31923438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.diabres.2020.108006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7042884</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Institute for Health and Care Excellence</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Type 2 diabetes in adults: management</article-title>. <comment>NICE guideline [NG28].2017. Accessed 30 June 2017. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/NG28" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/NG28</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Critchley</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>DeWilde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hosking</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Glycemic control and risk of infections among people with type 1 or type 2 diabetes in a large primary care cohort study</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>2127</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30104296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/dc18-0287</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>