<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Res Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Res Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1479</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jresmedsci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JRMS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Research in Medical Sciences : The Official Journal of Isfahan University of Medical Sciences</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1735-1995</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1735-7136</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer -- Medknow Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10366979</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10366979.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10366979</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10366979</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37496638</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jrms.jrms_602_22</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JRMS-28-49</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The value of machine learning for prognosis prediction of diphenhydramine exposure: National analysis of 50,000 patients in the United States</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrpour</surname><given-names initials="O">Omid</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saeedi</surname><given-names initials="F">Farhad</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdollahi</surname><given-names initials="J">Jafar</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amirabadizadeh</surname><given-names initials="A">Alireza</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goss</surname><given-names initials="F">Foster</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">7</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Michigan Poison &amp; Drug Information Center, Wayne State University School of Medicine, Detroit, Michigan, United States</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Rocky Mountain Poison and Drug Safety, Denver Health and Hospital Authority, Denver, CO, United States</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Medical Toxicology and Drug Abuse Research Center, Birjand University of Medical Sciences, Birjand, Iran</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Student Research Committee, Birjand University of Medical Sciences, Birjand, Iran</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Computer Engineering, Ardabil Branch, Islamic Azad University, Ardabil, Iran</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>Endocrine Research Center, Research Institute for Endocrine Sciences, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label>Department of Emergency Medicine, University of Colorado School of Medicine, Aurora, CO, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Omid Mehrpour, Data Science Institute, Southern Methodist University, Dallas, TX, USA. E-mail: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="omid.mehrpour@yahoo.com.au">omid.mehrpour@yahoo.com.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>28</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">432030</issue-id><elocation-id>49</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>8</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>12</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>26</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-07-14 05:25:24.130"><day>14</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#169; 2023 Journal of Research in Medical Sciences</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncsalicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access journal, and articles are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as appropriate credit is given and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="JRMS-28-49.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Background:</title><p>Diphenhydramine (DPH) is an antihistamine medication that in overdose can result in anticholinergic symptoms and serious complications, including arrhythmia and coma. We aimed to compare the value of various machine learning (ML) models, including light gradient boosting machine (LGBM), logistic regression (LR), and random forest (RF), in the outcome prediction of DPH poisoning.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Materials and Methods:</title><p>We used the National Poison Data System database and included all of the human exposures of DPH from January 01, 2017 to December 31, 2017, and excluded those cases with missing information, duplicated cases, and those who reported co-ingestion. Data were split into training and test datasets, and three ML models were compared. We developed confusion matrices for each, and standard performance metrics were calculated.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Results:</title><p>Our study population included 53,761 patients with DPH exposure. The most common reasons for exposure, outcome, chronicity of exposure, and formulation were captured. Our results showed that the average precision-recall area under the curve (AUC) of 0.84. LGBM and RF had the highest performance (average AUC of 0.91), followed by LR (average AUC of 0.90). The specificity of the models was 87.0% in the testing groups. The precision of models was 75.0%. Recall (sensitivity) of models ranged between 73% and 75% with an F1 score of 75.0%. The overall accuracy of LGBM, LR, and RF models in the test dataset was 74.8%, 74.0%, and 75.1%, respectively. In total, just 1.1% of patients (mostly those with major outcomes) received physostigmine.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Our study demonstrates the application of ML in the prediction of DPH poisoning.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Diphenhydramine</kwd><kwd>overdose</kwd><kwd>poisoning</kwd><kwd>prognosis</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Diphenhydramine (DPH) is a first-generation antihistamine, ie.e., available over the counter (OTC) and is used to treat allergy symptoms and as a sleeping aid.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] Even though the therapeutic window of DPH is wide, it is one of the most prevalent causes of antihistamine overdose, often presenting with anticholinergic symptoms.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] DPH exposure has been rising in the United States in recent years. The current estimates show approximately 158,000 DPH exposures between 2005 and 2016, with increased rates of attempting suicide among children, growing abuse among adults, and a tendency toward higher overdose severity.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] The American Association of Poison Control Centers (AAPCC) reported a total number of 41,132 cases of DPH exposure in 2020, compared to 65,690 cases of other antihistamines exposure.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] DPH poisoning can also result in cardiovascular and neurological complications.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] Physostigmine is a general antidote for DPH toxicity to alleviate its symptoms, but sometimes it is unavailable or not used.</p><p>Medical toxicologists at poison centers review patient records, medical history, and identify the substance or product code involved during exposure calls. Once the information in this file becomes accessible, it is sent to the National Poison Data System (NPDS). Cases are recorded contemporaneously by poison center personnel in one of five electronic medical record systems. Clinical outcomes, specific organ effects, the relationship between these effects and the agent, the duration of these effects, chronicity, demographic data, exposure time, administration sites, toxicological data, and clinical findings are documented. Depending on the case's specifics, most cases are &#8220;closed&#8221; within a few hours of initial exposure. This method was the same for DPH exposures and our analysis.</p><p>The application of machine learning (ML) and classification models for prognosis prediction has been a focus of attention in recent years.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] Logistic regression (LR) and classification models (random forest [RF] and light gradient boosting machine [LGBM]) are well-known predictive models. The growing implementation of the LR model in medicine is due to its simplicity of interpretation and low error rate.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] It is also effective in predicting a binary dependent variable based on the values of a collection of predictor variables.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] RF is an ML model developed based on a decision tree that randomly selects training sets from the original dataset, leaving the remaining dataset as the test set.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] Finally, gradient boosting is an ML strategy that enhances the precision of classification methods, such as decision trees, by correcting the model's errors at each level.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</p><p>Medical toxicology has taken advantage of these promising methods in both diagnosis/treatment and outcomes using gradient-boosting models.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] For example, LR was applied to predict seizures among patients with acute tramadol poisoning.[<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] In the emergency department, ML was used to detect individuals prone to adverse drug reactions.[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] Another study demonstrated the accuracy and reliability of the gradient-boosting model in predicting the 1-year survival of patients with cancer and the 30-day mortality of patients with sepsis.[<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref><xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] Recently, a study on patients with COVID-19 showed that the gradient-boosting model predicted death with a sensitivity of 1 and intensive care unit admission with a specificity of 0.93.[<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] A study on patients with myocardial infarction also revealed that the gradient-boosting model predicted the risk of 1-year mortality with high accuracy of 0.89 and precision of 0.84.[<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] As gradient-boosting models enhance decision tree performance, they have demonstrated promising effects on prediction models in medicine. However, despite the growing use of ML in medicine, there has been limited application of ML in predicting outcomes of DPH poisoning. In this study, we sought to investigate the effectiveness of LR, RF, and LGBM in the outcome prediction of DPH poisoning using large-scale data derived from the National Poison Data System (NPDS).</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Study design and setting</title><p>This study is a retrospective cohort study, for which data were derived from the NPDS database. NPDS is the most comprehensive database of poisoning in the United States, operated by the AAPCC that includes human substance exposures reported to all of the accredited poison control centers (PCCs) all around the country. The data were gathered by anonymous phone calls to PCCs and included follow-up and symptoms associated with exposures obtained by healthcare professionals trained in poisoning treatment and prevention. The structure of the proposed method is shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Structure of the proposed method. NPDS = National Poison Data System</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JRMS-28-49-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Selection of participants</title><p>The data for this study were gathered and reviewed by expert medical toxicologists. We included all of the human exposures to DPH from January 01, 2017, to December 31, 2017. Those cases with missing information, duplicated cases, and reported co-ingestion were excluded. According to the NPDS coding users&#8217; manual, exposure is defined as any exposure to a substance that has been ingested, inhaled, absorbed, applied to, or injected into the body, regardless of its toxicity or clinical manifestations.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] Exposure to DPH included intentional and unintentional overdose of DPH and was confirmed based on clinical symptoms and history.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Terms definition</title><p>The predictors of the prognosis include all of the clinical and laboratory findings related to DPH poisoning, which were reviewed and defined by expert medical toxicologists. Medical outcomes are classified as minor, moderate, and major effects. This assessment requires follow-up unless the initial call to the regional poison center occurs sufficiently long after the exposure that there is reasonable certainty that the clinical effect(s) will not worsen. Patients with symptoms must be monitored until they have resolved or are almost resolved unless the residual symptoms are expected to be long-lasting and of limited clinical relevance.</p><sec id="sec3-1"><title>Minor effect</title><p>The patient displayed a few symptoms due to the exposure, which are self-limiting. The patient's health has been restored to its pre-exposure level, and there are no lasting disabilities or disfigurements.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>Moderate effect</title><p>The patient displayed longer-lasting, more systemic, or severe symptoms. Typically, treatment is indicated or would have been indicated. However, the patient's symptoms were not life-threatening, and he or she has fully recovered with no permanent disability or disfigurement.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-3"><title>Major effect</title><p>The patient manifested symptoms that are life-threatening, resulting in a major lasting disability or disfigurement. Major outcomes might result in death or severe complications regardless of treatment.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-4"><title>Chronicity</title><p>Exposures were defined per NPDS guidelines and acute, acute on chronic and chronic.[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] Acute exposures are those lasting less than 8 hours, acute on chronic up to 8 hours and chronic exposures greater than 8 hours. Exposures could be continuous, repetitive or intermittent.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Data preprocessing</title><p>When developing an ML model, data preprocessing is the initial step that initiates the process. Real-world data are typically insufficient, inconsistent, imprecise (including mistakes or outliers), and lacking in specific attribute values/trends. Data preparation is important in helping clean, prepare, and organize/format raw data, preparing it for the ML models. Some models require data in a particular format, for instance, the RF technique does not accept null values; hence, null values must be removed from the original raw data set to execute the algorithm. The data also need to be arranged in such a way that it can run and compare many algorithms in parallel. In this study, preprocessing involved removing NULL or NAN values and normalizing the data so that the mean is 0 and the standard deviation is 1.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Data development and evaluation</title><p>First, we categorized our data into two datasets, including training and test sets, which contained 70% and 30% of the random sample. Then, we applied three classifier prediction models, including LR, RF, and LGBM using the sklearn and TensorFlow library in Python.[<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Statistical analysis and metrics</title><p>The study was implemented using a Jupyter notebook, and the Python programming language was employed for coding. In addition, standard evaluation metrics, including accuracy, precision, specificity, and sensitivity were used to evaluate the models&#8217; performance.</p><p>As shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, FN and FP represent the number of false-negative and false-negative samples. TN and TP reflect the number of true negative and true positive samples. Sensitivity (recall) estimates the proportion of stated positives that are accurate.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Structure of confusion matrix</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Predicted class</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Actual class</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TP</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FP</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FN</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TN</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>TP=True positive, FP=False positive, TN=True negative, FN=False-negative</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Due to a large number of datasets analyzed, the range of methodologies employed, and the peculiarities of the data set, which includes both balanced and unbalanced data, it is not easy to evaluate the accuracy of multiclass algorithms. Therefore, criteria, such as accuracy, sensitivity, and precision, are used to evaluate the performance of these algorithms. Understanding these indicators enables users to assess the accuracy of a classification model's analysis of textual data. Conventionally, in multiclass problems, accuracy, recall, specificity, area under the curve (AUC), and precision might be reported.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Baseline characteristics</title><p>The baseline characteristics of our study are shown in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Our study population included 53761 patients with DPH exposure. The mean age of the patients was 22.74 &#177; 0.07. The majority of the DPH exposure was OTC use. Intentional exposure was the most common reason for exposure (66.0). The majority of the patients had minor outcomes. Most of the DPH exposures were acute ingestion (93.7%). Physostigmine was administrated in 1.1% of patients (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 610) [<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>].</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of the participants</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, mean&#177;SD</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.74&#177;0.07 (1&#8211;89 years)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DPH alone (OTC)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31,239 (58.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DPH alone (prescription)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1988 (3.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DPH alone (unknown if OTC or prescription)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,534 (38.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reason of exposure</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Adverse reaction</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1142 (2.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Intentional</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35,473 (66)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Unintentional</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,445 (30.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Other (contamination/tampering, malicious, withdrawal)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (0.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Unknown</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">646 (1.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Total</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53,761 (100)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Major</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2288 (4.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Moderate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,108 (37.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Minor</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28,382 (52.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Unable to follow</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2983 (5.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Total</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53,761 (100)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronicity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Acute</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50,367 (93.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Acute on chronic</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1628 (3.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Chronic</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">832 (1.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Unknown</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">934 (1.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Total</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53,761 (100)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Formulation</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Aerosol/mist/spray/gas</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142 (0.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Cream/lotion/gel</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">466 (0.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Liquid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,610 (19.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Patch</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Powder/granules</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125 (0.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Solid (tablets/capsules/caplets)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41,190 (76.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Other</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103 (0.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Unknown</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1117 (2.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Total</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53,761 (100)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>DPH=Diphenhydramine, OTC=Over the counter, SD=Standard deviation</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Status of physostigmine administration in patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Out come</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Physostigmine administration, count (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Total, count (%)</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major effects</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2172 (94.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116 (5.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2288 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minor effects</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31,320 (99.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (0.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31,365 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate effects</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,659 (97.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">449 (2.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,108 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53,151 (98.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">610 (1.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53,761 (100.0)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title>Test and training datasets analysis</title><p>The specificity of each model was 87.0% in the test groups. The precision of each model was 75.0%. The recall (sensitivity) of models was between 73% and 75%. The F1 score was 75.0%. The total accuracy of LGBM, LR, and RF models in the test dataset were 74.7%, 74.0%, and 75.0%, respectively. In our study, moderate effects had the highest value of specificity (91%&#8211;92%). However, the greatest value of recall and F-1 score belonged to minor effects. The characteristics of training and test sets of the models are shown in <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. Confusion matrices for our models are shown in <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Characteristics of training and test sets of the machine learning models</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Labels</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Datasets</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Models</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major effect</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minor effect</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate effect</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specificity</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Training</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LGBM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.952470 (0.89&#8211;0.984)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.945017 (0.902&#8211;0.963)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.988782 (0.935&#8211;0.995)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.962090 (0.897&#8211;0.990)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.942155 (0.886&#8211;0.981)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.883671 (0.815&#8211;0.938)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.971873 (0.916&#8211;0.994)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.932566 (0.874&#8211;0.978)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.902513 (0.842&#8211;0.954)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.829750 (0.775&#8211;0.882)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.942907 (0.893&#8211;0.976)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.891723 (0.814&#8211;0.956)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LGBM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.901235 (0.832&#8211;0.952)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.810320 (0.765&#8211;0.874)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.910022 (0.865&#8211;0.973)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.873859 (0.809&#8211;0.951)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.902256 (0.835&#8211;0.97)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.799248 (0.734&#8211;0.858)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.924031 (0.891&#8211;0.972)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.875178 (0.805&#8211;0.943)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.885311 (0.816&#8211;0.937)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.800696 (0.764&#8211;0.853)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.924315 (0.892&#8211;0.971)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.870107 (0.799&#8211;0.926)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Precision</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Training</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LGBM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.909631 (0.852&#8211;0.956)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.891492 (0.846&#8211;0.935)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.976000 (0.943&#8211;0.995)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.925708 (0.874&#8211;0.963)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.880060 (0.836&#8211;0.924)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.780654 (0.745&#8211;0.824)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.942249 (0.891&#8211;0.983)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.867654 (0.819&#8211;0.906)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.811558 (0.774&#8211;0.863)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.686844 (0.641&#8211;0.739)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.869870 (0.827&#8211;0.905)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.789424 (0.754&#8211;0.82)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LGBM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.808720 (0.771&#8211;0.853)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.635983 (0.597&#8211;0.681)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.805380 (0.758&#8211;0.851)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.750028 (0.723&#8211;0.789)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.811366 (0.778&#8211;0.856)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.638670 (0.589&#8211;0.675)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.822077 (0.775&#8211;0.874)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.757371 (0.702&#8211;0.792)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.788790 (0.742&#8211;0.831)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.625817 (0.582&#8211;0.673)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.821904 (0.791&#8211;0.875)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.745503 (0.702&#8211;0.779)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recall</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Training</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LGBM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.952677 (0.915&#8211;0.987)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.902059 (0.871&#8211;0.943)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.917868 (0.867&#8211;0.965)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.924201 (0.891&#8211;0.976)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.868343 (0.834&#8211;0.908)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.848889 (0.803&#8211;0.888)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.875706 (0.816&#8211;0.915)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.864313 (0.821&#8211;0.907)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.862100 (0.824&#8211;0.903)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.738075 (0.701&#8211;0.773)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.752381 (0.714&#8211;0.798)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.784185 (0.765&#8211;0.821)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LGBM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.841874 (0.805&#8211;0.888)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.666667 (0.614&#8211;0.709)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.734488 (0.687&#8211;0.781)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.747676 (0.697&#8211;0.791)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.831990 (0.788&#8211;0.882)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.702854 (0.664&#8211;0.751)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.716456 (0.684&#8211;0.752)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.750433 (0.714&#8211;0.798)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.833476 (0.802&#8211;0.873)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.675485 (0.641&#8211;0.709)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.708738 (0.667&#8211;0.746)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.739233 (0.701&#8211;0.776)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F1_score</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Training</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LGBM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.930657 (0.908&#8211;0.956)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.896744 (0.854&#8211;0.926)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.896744 (0.854&#8211;0.936)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.924481 (0.897&#8211;0.974)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.874162 (0.847&#8211;0.913)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.813343 (0.785&#8211;0.864)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.907760 (0.854&#8211;0.947)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.865088 (0.823&#8211;0.906)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.836066 (0.795&#8211;0.896)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.711538 (0.687&#8211;0.768)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.806871 (0.774&#8211;0.845)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.784825 (0.754&#8211;0.831)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LGBM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.824964 (0.778&#8211;0.865)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.650964 (0.614&#8211;0.692)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.768302 (0.725&#8211;0.805)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.748077 (0.704&#8211;0.793)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.821549 (0.778&#8211;0.863)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.669226 (0.627&#8211;0.701)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.765641 (0.723&#8211;0.809)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.752139 (0.717&#8211;0.792)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.810518 (0.769&#8211;0.864)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.649703 (0.607&#8211;0.683)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.761137 (0.731&#8211;0.806)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.740453 (0.716&#8211;0.792)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accuracy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Training</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LGBM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.934230 (0.897&#8211;0.971)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.894230 (0.856&#8211;0.926)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.884230 (0.834&#8211;0.921)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.924230 (0.888&#8211;0.967)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.874497 (0.821&#8211;0.914)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.814497 (0.774&#8211;0.854)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.834497 (0.794&#8211;0.871)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.864497 (0.824&#8211;0.912)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.773508 (0.735&#8211;0.814)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.693508 (0.652&#8211;0.739)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.753508 (0.712&#8211;0.793)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.783508 (0.746&#8211;0.82)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LGBM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.817573 (0.774&#8211;0.859)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.737573 (0.704&#8211;0.774)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.737573 (0.698&#8211;0.769)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.747573 (0.712&#8211;0.783)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.770676 (0.716&#8211;0.816)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.760676 (0.723&#8211;802)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.690676 (0.642&#8211;0.735)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.750676 (0.713&#8211;0.801)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.690093 (0.645&#8211;0.734)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.750093 (0.712&#8211;0.783)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.730093 (0.699&#8211;0.772)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.740093 (0.708&#8211;0.79.1)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>LGBM=Light gradient boosting machine, LR=Logistic regression, RF=Random forest</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Confusion matrix for different models in training and test sets</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prediction</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dataset</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major effect</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minor effect</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate effect</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major effect</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Training</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LGBM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1530</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">587</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">969</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LGBM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">575</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1342</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minor effect</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Training</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LGBM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1446</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">573</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">851</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LGBM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">456</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">240</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1133</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">239</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">766</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">166</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate effect</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Training</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LGBM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1464</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">620</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">238</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">869</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LGBM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">509</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">376</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1132</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">272</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">803</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>LGBM=Light gradient boosting machine, LR=Logistic regression, RF=Random forest</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-9"><title>Negative predictive value, precision-recall, and receiver operating characteristic curves</title><p>The evaluation of our models showed a high accuracy level in precision-recall and receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves. We found that the RF model was best with an average precision-recall AUC of 0.85, followed by LGBM (average precision-recall AUC of 0.84). The LR model had the lowest performance, with an average precision-recall AUC of 0.82.</p><p>In terms of the AUC of the ROC curve, LGBM and RF both had the highest performance (average ROC curve AUC of 0.91), followed by LR (average ROC curve AUC of 0.90). <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> shows the precision-recall and ROC curves for the models in detail.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Precision-recall and ROC curves for the models. (a) Precision-recall curve for LGBM, (b) ROC curve model for LGBM, (c) Precision-recall curve for RF, (d) ROC curve for RF, (e) Precision-recall curve for LR, (f) ROC curve for LR. The diagonal black dotted line represents a baseline model (that predicts at random), hence the same values of TPR and FPR. The blue solid curve represents a ideal model. ROC = Receiver operating characteristic, TPR = True positive rate, FPR = False positive rate, LGBM = Light gradient boosting machine</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JRMS-28-49-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>The negative predictive value (NPV) of the LGBM model was 97.1 (93.45&#8211;99.42), 87.9 (84.67&#8211;91.75), 85.8 (82.31&#8211;89.47), and 90.3 in major effect, minor effect, moderate effect, and average, respectively. The NPV of the RF model was 96.5 (93.85&#8211;98.78), 87.7 (84.26&#8211;91.16), 86.0 (81.52&#8211;88.30), and 90.1 (87.62&#8211;94.07) in major effect, minor effect, moderate effect, and average, respectively. The NPV of the LR model was 97.2 (94.35&#8211;99.87), 89.9 (85.64&#8211;93.46), 85.7 (81.75&#8211;90.02), and 90.9 (87.35&#8211;94.66) in major effect, minor effect, moderate effect, and average, respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The primary goal of the current study was to compare three different ML approaches in predicting the DPH poisoning prognosis. Our findings demonstrated the efficacy and accuracy of the LR, RF, and LGBM models in DPH prognosis prediction. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study that utilized ML approaches with the aim of prognosis prediction in DPH poisonings.</p><p>Prior studies in ML in medical toxicology have found challenges in differentiating the causal agent of poisoning based on clinical symptoms, primarily due to small sample numbers. For example, a study by Nogee <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. used clinical characteristics and multiclass classification algorithms (Naive Bayes, Support Vector Machines, Decision Trees, RF, and Gradient Boosted (XGBoost), to identify the poisoning agent. They reported an overall accuracy rate of 61.9%, with carbon monoxide, opioids, and benzodiazepines exhibiting superior performance.[<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] Dong <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. utilized a RF model to predict opioid overdose and achieved a high recall (85.7%), accuracy (98.7%), and precision (99.2%). They then applied a deep learning model using the SPARCS dataset, demonstrating a high precision (99.2%), accuracy (96.8%), and fair recall (71.6%).[<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] ML has also been utilized to predict paraquat poisoning prognosis, seizures from tramadol poisoning, adverse drug events in elderly patients, smoking cessation treatment outcomes, lead poisoning in children, pesticide ototoxicity, in emergency departments.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref><xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] Using NPDS data, Mehrpour <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. applied a decision tree approach to acetaminophen and metformin,[<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref><xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref><xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] and ML classification techniques to predict the causal agent.[<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</p><p>Our models demonstrated a high NPV and specificity. The greater a test's sensitivity, the less likely it is that a person with a negative test has the disease, and hence the greater its NPV. The higher the positive predictive value of a test, the less probable it is that an individual with a positive test is free of disease.</p><p>Interestingly, we found that just 1.1% of patients (mostly in those with major outcomes) received physostigmine, a specific antidote for DPH. In a retrospective cohort trial, treatment of physostigmine to reverse anticholinergic delirium exhibited a favorable safety profile and frequently improved or cleared anticholinergic delirium when given in dosages &lt;2 mg.[<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</p><p>The strengths of our study include the following: first, since NPDS is the largest data repository of poisoning and exposures to different substances in the United States, our results may be more generalizable. Second, the findings of our study are based on the symptoms and laboratory data of cases reported to PCCs, allowing our results to be more practical and potentially useful to clinicians during their medical decision-making process. The limitations of our study are that we included patients who had exposure only to DPH, so we could not identify the prognosis of patients with co-ingestions. Moreover, these patients may not necessarily have toxicity or overdose. However, even though the results of ML models may help physicians diagnose, treat, and predict prognosis, there are few trials investigating the efficacy of ML models compared to decisions made by physicians. Finally, this study is a retrospective data analysis, so the results of this study should be interpreted cautiously.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec1-5"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>Our study demonstrates the applicability of ML methods to predict the outcome of DPH exposure is feasible with reasonable accuracy.</p><sec id="sec2-10"><title>Disclaimers</title><p>The NPDS is organized by the AAPCC, and it consists of anonymous and self-reporting cases acquired through phone calls to the country's PCCs. Because further PCC exposure may be under-reported, NPDS data do not represent the complete exposure to a particular substance. As a result, NPDS data should not imply poisoning or overdose, and the AAPCC cannot authenticate the accuracy of each report. Consequently, findings based on NPDS data only sometimes accurately reflect the AAPCC's perspective.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-11"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The authors of this study obtained the approval of NPDS. This study was reviewed by the Colorado Multiple Institutional Review Board (COMIRB#: 22-1088) and determined to be not human subject research because all of the data collected and analyzed is publicly available and fully de-identified.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-12"><title>Financial support and sponsorship</title><p>None.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec2-13"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>Dr. Goss receives consulting fees from Credo Health. Dr. Goss's financial interests have been reviewed by University of Colorado Hospital and University of Colorado School of Medicine in accordance with their institutional policies.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>The authors would like to thank the NPDS for supplying the poisoning data.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eckes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsokos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herre</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gapert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartwig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxicological identification of diphenhydramine (DPH) in suicide</article-title><source>Forensic Sci Med Pathol</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23065653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12024-012-9383-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clemons</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jandu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chary</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early intravenous lipid emulsion therapy for diphenhydramine overdose: A case report</article-title><source>Toxicol Commun</source><year>2021</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemanich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liebelt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabbatini</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased rates of diphenhydramine overdose, abuse, and misuse in the United States, 2005-2016</article-title><source>Clin Toxicol (Phila)</source><year>2021</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>1002</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33688782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/15563650.2021.1892716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gummin</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mowry</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beuhler</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spyker</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bronstein</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivers</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>2020 annual report of the American Association of Poison Control Centers&#8217; National Poison Data System (NPDS): 38<sup>th</sup> annual report</article-title><source>Clin Toxicol (Phila)</source><year>2021</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>1282</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34890263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/15563650.2021.1989785</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kauffman</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adverse events associated with diphenhydramine in children, 2008-2015</article-title><source>Clin Toxicol (Phila)</source><year>2020</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31062642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/15563650.2019.1609683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kourou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Exarchos</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Exarchos</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karamouzis</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fotiadis</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Machine learning applications in cancer prognosis and prediction</article-title><source>Comput Struct Biotechnol J</source><year>2015</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25750696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.csbj.2014.11.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4348437</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreiseitl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohno-Machado</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Logistic regression and artificial neural network classification models: A methodology review</article-title><source>J Biomed Inform</source><year>2002</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12968784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1532-0464(03)00034-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurt</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ture</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurum</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparing performances of logistic regression, classification and regression tree, and neural networks for predicting coronary artery disease</article-title><source>Expert Syst Appl</source><year>2008</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>366</fpage><lpage>74</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Study of cardiovascular disease prediction model based on random forest in eastern China</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>5245</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32251324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-020-62133-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7090086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klug</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barash</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bechler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Resheff</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tron</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ironi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A gradient boosting machine learning model for predicting early mortality in the emergency department triage: Devising a nine-point triage score</article-title><source>J Gen Intern Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31677104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-019-05512-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6957629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Igata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikegaya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Machine learning-based prediction of adverse drug effects: An example of seizure-inducing compounds</article-title><source>J Pharmacol Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28215473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jphs.2017.01.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Behnoush</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bazmi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nazari</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khodakarim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Looha</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Machine learning algorithms to predict seizure due to acute tramadol poisoning</article-title><source>Hum Exp Toxicol</source><year>2021</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1225</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33538187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0960327121991910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ouchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindvall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Machine learning to predict, detect, and intervene older adults vulnerable for adverse drug events in the emergency department</article-title><source>J Med Toxicol</source><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29858745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s13181-018-0667-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6097964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An artificial intelligence model for predicting 1-year survival of bone metastases in non-small-cell lung cancer patients based on XGBoost algorithm</article-title><source>Biomed Res Int</source><year>2020</year><volume>2020</volume><fpage>3462363</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32685470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2020/3462363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7338972</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predicting 30-days mortality for MIMIC-III patients with sepsis-3: A machine learning approach using XGboost</article-title><source>J Transl Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>462</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33287854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12967-020-02620-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7720497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Batista</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalla Costa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiavegatto Filho</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A multipurpose machine learning approach to predict COVID-19 negative prognosis in S&#227;o Paulo, Brazil</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>3343</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33558602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-021-82885-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7870665</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical feature-based machine learning model for 1-year mortality risk prediction of ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction in patients with hyperuricemia: A retrospective study</article-title><source>Comput Math Methods Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>2021</volume><fpage>7252280</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34285708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2021/7252280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8275420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gummin</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mowry</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beuhler</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spyker</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dibert</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>2019 Annual Report of the American Association of Poison Control Centers' National Poison Data System (NPDS): 37<sup>th</sup> Annual Report</article-title><source>Clinical toxicology (Philadelphia, Pa)</source><year>2020</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1360</fpage><lpage>541</lpage><comment>Epub 2020/12/12. doi: 10.1080/15563650.2020.1834219. PubMed PMID: 33305966</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33305966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/15563650.2020.1834219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><comment><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://scikit-learn.org/stable">https://scikit-learn.org/stable</uri></comment><comment>Available from: 04/11/2023</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nogee</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomassoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiclass classification machine learning identification of common poisonings. North American Congress of Clinical Toxicology (NACCT) abstracts 2020</article-title><source>Clin Toxicol (Phila)</source><year>2020</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1083</fpage><lpage>4</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rashidian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajagos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Machine learning based opioid overdose prediction using electronic health records</article-title><source>AMIA Annu Symp Proc</source><year>2019</year><volume>2019</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32308832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7153049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Metabolomics analysis in acute paraquat poisoning patients based on UPLC-Q-TOF-MS and machine learning approach</article-title><source>Chem Res Toxicol</source><year>2019</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30807114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/acs.chemrestox.8b00328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An effective machine learning approach for prognosis of paraquat poisoning patients using blood routine indexes</article-title><source>Basic Clin Pharmacol Toxicol</source><year>2017</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27390221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/bcpt.12638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of machine learning models for prediction of smoking cessation outcome</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>2584</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33807561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph18052584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7967540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Potash</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lohff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prachand</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Validation of a machine learning model to predict childhood lead poisoning</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2020</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e2012734</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32936296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.12734</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7495240</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomiazzi</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Judai</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antunes</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Favareto</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Performance of machine-learning algorithms to pattern recognition and classification of hearing impairment in Brazilian farmers exposed to pesticide and/or cigarette smoke</article-title><source>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</source><year>2019</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>6481</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30623325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11356-018-04106-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrpour</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saeedi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoyte</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decision tree outcome prediction of acute acetaminophen exposure in the United States: A study of 30,000 cases from the National Poison Data System</article-title><source>Basic Clin Pharmacol Toxicol</source><year>2022</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34649297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/bcpt.13674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amirabadizadeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakhaee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrpour</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk assessment of elevated blood lead concentrations in the adult population using a decision tree approach</article-title><source>Drug Chem Toxicol</source><year>2022</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>878</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32588664</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/01480545.2020.1783286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrpour</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saeedi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoyte</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goss</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shirazi</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correction: Utility of support vector machine and decision tree to identify the prognosis of metformin poisoning in the United States: Analysis of National Poisoning Data System</article-title><source>BMC Pharmacol Toxicol</source><year>2022</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>68</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36085086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s40360-022-00608-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9463837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrpour</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saeedi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoyte</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goss</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shirazi</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Utility of support vector machine and decision tree to identify the prognosis of metformin poisoning in the United States: Analysis of National Poisoning Data System</article-title><source>BMC Pharmacol Toxicol</source><year>2022</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>49</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35831909</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s40360-022-00588-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9281002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrpour</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoyte</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delva-Clark</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Masud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schimmel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Classification of acute poisoning exposures with machine learning models derived from the National Poison Data System</article-title><source>Basic Clin Pharmacol Toxicol</source><year>2022</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36181236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/bcpt.13800</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arens</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Abri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Safety and effectiveness of physostigmine: A 10-year retrospective review</article-title><source>Clin Toxicol (Phila)</source><year>2018</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28703024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/15563650.2017.1342828</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>