<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Pediatr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Pediatr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2282</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">frontpediatrics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Pediatr.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Pediatrics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2296-2360</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10248236</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10248236.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10248236</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10248236</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37303758</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fped.2023.1149401</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Pediatrics</subject><subj-group><subject>Systematic Review</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A systematic review of <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and risk for structural birth defects</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sujan</surname><given-names initials="AC">Ayesha C.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2015369/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pal</surname><given-names initials="A">Anish</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2313746/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Avalos</surname><given-names initials="LA">Lyndsay A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an1" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/999957/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young-Wolff</surname><given-names initials="KC">Kelly C.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an1" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1800345/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label><sup>1</sup></label><addr-line>Department of Anesthesiology, Perioperative and Pain Medicine</addr-line>, <institution>Stanford University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Stanford, CA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label><sup>2</sup></label><addr-line>Division of Research</addr-line>, <institution>Kaiser Permanente Northern California</institution>, <addr-line>Oakland, CA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label><sup>3</sup></label><addr-line>Herbert Wertheim College of Medicine</addr-line>, <institution>Florida International University</institution>, <addr-line>Miami, FL</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label><sup>4</sup></label><addr-line>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences</addr-line>, <institution>University of California</institution>, <addr-line>San Francisco, CA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><bold>Edited by:</bold> Gabrielle Lynn McLemore, Morgan State University, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><bold>Reviewed by:</bold> Camille Fung, The University of Utah, United States Jessie Maxwell, University of New Mexico, United States</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Ayesha C. Sujan <email>asujan@stanford.edu</email></corresp><fn id="an1"><label>
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work and share senior authorship.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">427660</issue-id><elocation-id>1149401</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>25</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>09</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-06-12 11:25:10.010"><day>12</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2023 Sujan, Pal, Avalos and Young-Wolff.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sujan, Pal, Avalos and Young-wolff</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY)</ext-link>. The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fped-11-1149401.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Cannabis use among pregnant women has increased over time. Therefore, there is a great public health need to understand the consequences of <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure. While several meta-analyses and reviews have summarized the evidence of <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure on adverse obstetric outcomes (e.g., low birth weight and preterm birth) and long-term offspring development, there has not been a focus on <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and risk for structural birth defects.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We conducted a systematic review using PRISMA guidelines to evaluate the association between <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and structural birth defects.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We identified 20 articles to include in our review and focused on interpreting findings from the 12 that adjusted for potential confounders. We report findings by seven organ systems. Within the 12 articles, four reported on cardiac malformations, three reported on central nervous system malformations, one reported on eye malformations, three reported on gastrointestinal malformations, one reported on genitourinary malformations, one reported on musculoskeletal malformations, and two reported on orofacial malformations.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Findings on associations between <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and birth defects reported in more than two articles were mixed (i.e., findings for cardiac, gastrointestinal, central nervous system malformations). Findings for associations between <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and birth defects reported in two articles (i.e., orofacial malformations) or in a single article (eye, genitourinary, and musculoskeletal) suggested that cannabis exposure was not associated with these types of malformations, but strong conclusions cannot be drawn from such sparce research. We review the limitations and gaps in the existing literature and call for more research to rigorously evaluate associations between <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and structural birth defects.</p></sec><sec><title>Systematic Review Registration</title><p>identifier CRD42022308130.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>pregnancy</kwd><kwd>prenatal exposure</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> exposure</kwd><kwd>cannabis</kwd><kwd>marijuana</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">National Institute on Drug Abuse</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002">NIH</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by grants R01DA047405 funded by National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA) and R01DA48033 funded by NIDA and Office of the Director, NIH (OD). The funding organizations had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; or decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="64"/><page-count count="0"/><word-count count="0"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Neonatology</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><label>1.</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Research has documented an increase in rates of cannabis use among pregnant people over time. Among a nationally representative sample of pregnant individuals in the United States, the prevalence of self-reported prenatal cannabis use in the past month increased from 3.4% in 2002&#8211;2003, to 7.0% in 2016&#8211;2017 (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Prenatal cannabis use may increase even more rapidly as more US states legalize cannabis for recreational use (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Moreover, cannabis use in pregnancy could impact fetal development because cannabis is lipid soluble and is able to cross the placenta and blood-brain barrier (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), and some previous studies have suggested a potential link between in-utero cannabis exposure and adverse offspring outcomes [e.g., (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>)]. Therefore, there is a great public health need to understand the consequences of <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure on offspring development. Several meta-analyses and reviews have summarized the evidence of <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure on adverse obstetric outcomes (e.g., low birth weight and preterm birth) and long-term offspring development (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). However, reviews to date have not focused on research regarding <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and risk for structural birth defects. The causes and risk factors for many structural birth defects remains unknown, and understanding preventable causes and risk factors for structural birth defects is particularly important given the strong association between birth defects and morbidity/mortality (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Given this need, we conducted a systematic review using Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) guidelines to evaluate whether <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure is associated with structural birth defects compared to pregnancies with no cannabis exposure (Prospective Register of Systematic Reviews [PROSPERO] registration number: CRD42022308130; (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>)].</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><label>2.</label><title>Methods</title><p>Web of Science and PubMed databases were searched for English language articles published before February 1, 2022 utilizing the following key words: &#8220;(Pregnancy OR Prenatal OR <italic toggle="yes">In utero</italic> OR Perinatal) AND (Cannabis OR Marijuana) AND (Birth defects OR Congenital malformations OR Congenital anomalies OR Central nervous system defect OR Neural tube defects OR Holoprosencephaly OR Microcephaly OR Ear defect OR Eye defect OR Gastrointestinal defect OR Biliary atresia OR Esophageal atresia OR Tracheoesophageal fistula OR Intestinal atresia OR Intestinal stenosis OR Pyloric stenosis OR Hypospadias OR Renal agenesis OR Renal hypoplasia OR Renal dysplasia OR Cardiac defect OR Musculoskeletal defect OR Congenital diaphragmatic hernia OR Gastroschisis OR Limb deficiency OR Omphalocele OR Orofacial defect OR Respiratory defect OR Choanal atresia OR Cleft lip OR Cleft palate).&#8221; The inclusion criteria were English-language articles and epidemiological studies. Animal studies and review articles were excluded as the focus of our review was strictly on human outcomes.</p><p>The search revealed 299 potentially relevant articles of which 48 were duplicates. We created an EndNote library of 251 non-duplicate articles. Two authors then independently reviewed the titles and abstracts of the articles in the EndNote library to exclude articles that did not meet the inclusion criteria. After their independent reviews, the two authors discussed disagreements and together decided to include 37 articles for a full text review. During the full text review, 17 additional articles were excluded for the following reasons: study design was a case study (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), a comparable study was conducted by the same authors using the same dataset (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>), and the study did not specifically evaluate associations between cannabis exposure in pregnancy and birth defects [e.g., cannabis was included in a general substance use exposure variable or the outcome studied was not a birth defect; (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>)]. Therefore, the final review included 20 articles (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). See <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#160;1</xref> for a PRISMA flow diagram illustrating our identification process of articles for our final review.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>PRISMA flow diagram.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fped-11-1149401-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><label>3.</label><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><label>3.1.</label><title>Study characteristics</title><p>Of the 20 included articles, 8 were from prospective studies using recruited samples (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>), and 12 were from retrospective cohort or case-control studies using health care records (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Samples sizes varied from 50 to 3,067,069. Earliest birth years for cohorts varied from 1968 to 1980. Only 3 of the articles reported on studies using urine toxicology tests (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>); the rest reported on studies that relied on self-report to measure prenatal cannabis use. Of the 17 articles that reported on studies using self-reports to measure cannabis use, 16 had measures of self-reported cannabis use, and 1 had a measure of self-reported cannabis-related diagnoses (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). The outcome definitions varied across studies with some investigating associations with specific malformations and other studies investigating associations with any malformation. While 8 studies did not adjust for any potential confounders (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>), the rest adjusted for confounding, though the specific factors adjusted for varied across studies. <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table&#160;1</xref> provides information about the characteristics of each individual study.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Description of 20 articles (listed in alphabetical order) included in the final review.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citation</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Design and sample</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample size</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Birth years</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cannabis exposure definition</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organ System</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Birth defect</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confounding adjustment</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. Astley et al. (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective study of patients in their sixth month of pregnancy recruited from a health maintenance organization in Seattle, Washington, USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (40 exposed matched to 40 unexposed)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1982&#8211;1984</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported use during the first trimester of pregnancy ascertained at an interview 6 weeks after delivery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orofacial</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fetal alcohol like facial characteristics</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2. Bandoli et al. (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective, population-based cohort of births in California, USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,067,069</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011&#8211;2017</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported cannabis-related diagnoses made during pregnancy or delivery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiac, Central nervous system, Eye, Gastrointestinal, Orofacial</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any cardiac malformation, Any central nervous malformation, Neural tube defect<break/>Anencephaly, Spina Bifida, Eye malformation Gastrointestinal malformation</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics: race and ethnicity, payer source, maternal age and education<break/>Substance use: alcohol abuse, and nicotine and substance-related diagnoses<break/>Mental health: anxiety, depression, bipolar disorder<break/>Physical health: pre-pregnancy body mass index (BMI), preexisting hypertension, preexisting diabetes</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3. Bourque et al. (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective, population-based cohort study of births in Ontario, Canada</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,001,080</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012&#8211;2018</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported use during pregnancy ascertained at the first prenatal visit or admission for birth</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastrointestinal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastroschisis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4. Coleman-Cowger et al. (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective study of patients recruited from two obstetric clinics in Maryland, USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">338</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported use in the last month ascertained at prenatal visits</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unspecified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Birth defects</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics: marital status<break/>Pregnancy-specific: trimester of self-reported use</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5. Cornelius et al. (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective study of patients 18 years or younger recruited from an outpatient prenatal clinic in Pittsburgh, USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">310</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1990&#8211;1993</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported first-trimester use</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unspecified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major and minor physical anomalies</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics: race, infant sex, maternal age, household structure, mother's parent's education, full-time or part-time school status,<break/>Substance use: alcohol use, marijuana, cocaine/crack, and other illicit drug use<break/>Mental health: social support, depression<break/>Physical health: pre-pregnancy weight, gestational weight gain, maternal height, maternal nutrition<break/>Pregnancy-specific: gestational age at birth, gravidity, adequacy of prenatal care</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6. Day et al. (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective study of patients recruited from an outpatient prenatal clinic in Pittsburgh, USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">763</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1982&#8211;1985</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported use at the fourth prenatal month visit, seventh prenatal month visit, and postpartum hospital stay about use in each trimester</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unspecified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minor and major physical abnormalities</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics: maternal age, education, marital status, work status, income, race,<break/>Substance use: use of tobacco, alcohol, and other illicit drugs<break/>Mental health: social support, depression and anxiety<break/>Physical health: gestational weight gain, maternal height<break/>Pregnancy-specific: gravidity<break/>Other: life events</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7. Downing et al. (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective, population-based, case-control study of records from 10 Centers for Birth Defects Research and Prevention across the USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,964 (135 cases, 11,829 controls)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1997&#8211;2011</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-report of use during the first trimester of pregnancy ascertained between 6 and 24 months after delivery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiac</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ebstein anomaly</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics: maternal age at delivery, paternal age at delivery, birth year, maternal race/ethnicity<break/>Substance use: none<break/>Mental health: none<break/>Physical health: maternal pre-pregnancy body mass index<break/>Pregnancy-specific: season of conception<break/>Other: family history of congenital heart defects</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8. Forrester et al. (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective, population-based, case-control study of births in Hawaii, USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">316,508</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1986&#8211;2002</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine toxicology during or shortly after delivery OR report of use on medical record</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastrointestinal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastroschisis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9. Forrester et al. (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective, population-based, case-control study of births in Hawaii, USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">316,508</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1986&#8211;2002</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine toxicology during or shortly after delivery OR report of use on medical record</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiac, Central nervous system, Eye, Gastrointestinal, Genitourinary, Musculoskeletal, Orofacial</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 selected birth defects (see paper)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10. Gibson et al. (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective study of patients recruited from a hospital in London, England</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,301</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1975&#8211;1981</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-report use up to once a week and more than once a week at antenatal interview</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unspecified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Congenital anomalies</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics: maternal age<break/>Substance use: alcohol use, tobacco use<break/>Mental health: none<break/>Physical health: none<break/>Pregnancy-specific: parity<break/>Other: none</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11. Hingson et al. (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective study of patients recruited from a hospital in Boston, USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,690</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1977&#8211;1979</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-report use during pregnancy ascertained post delivery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orofacial</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Features compatible with fetal alcohol syndrome</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12. Kharbanda et al. (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective, cohort study of births in Minnesota, USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,435</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015&#8211;2017</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine toxicology screens at the first prenatal visit (generally between 6 and 14 weeks)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unspecified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major structural birth defect</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics: maternal race/ethnicity, age,<break/>Substance use: smoking during pregnancy<break/>Mental health:<break/>Physical health: pre-pregnancy body mass index<break/>Pregnancy-specific: none<break/>Other: none</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13. Lam et al. (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective, case-control of births in California, USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149 (55 cases, 94 control)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1988&#8211;1990</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported when infant 3&#8211;6 months old</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastrointestinal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastroschisis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14. Linn et al. (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective study of patients recruited from a hospital in Boston, USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,424</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1977&#8211;1980</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported use during pregnancy ascertained during delivery admission</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unspecified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major or minor malformations</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics: race, maternal age 35 or older, on welfare<break/>Substance use: alcohol use in pregnancy, smoking 3 or more cigarettes per day at delivery<break/>Mental health: none<break/>Physical health: previous miscarriages, previous stillbirths, previous induced abortions<break/>Pregnancy-specific: parity greater than 1<break/>Other: none</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15. O&#8217;Connell et al. (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective study of patients recruited from a hospital in Ottawa, Canada</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exact dates unknown (recruitment in 1978)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported use during pregnancy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orofacial</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any minor physical anomalies, Anomalies of face and head</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16. Shaw et al. (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective, population-based, case-control study of births in California, USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,077 (538 cases, 539 controls)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1989&#8211;1991</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported use 3 months before pregnancy through pregnancy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central Nervous System</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neural tube defect</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics: race/ethnicity, education, income, age<break/>Substance use: use of other substances in the periconception period<break/>Mental health: none<break/>Physical health: maternal vitamin use<break/>Pregnancy-specific: none<break/>Other: none</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17. Torfs et al. (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective, population-based case-control study of births in California, USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">330 (110 cases, 220 controls)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1988&#8211;1990</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported first-trimester use</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastrointestinal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastroschisis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics: maternal age<break/>Substance use: none<break/>Mental health: none<break/>Physical health: none<break/>Pregnancy-specific: none<break/>Other: none</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18. Van Gelder et al. (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective, case-control study of births in 10 states that were part of the National Birth Defects Study<xref rid="table-fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,415 (13,859 cases, 6,556 controls)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1997&#8211;2005</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported use in the month before pregnancy or during the first 3 months of pregnancy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiac, Gastrointestinal, Genitourinary, Musculoskeletal, Orofacial</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atrial septal defect not otherwise specified, Atrial septal defect secundum, Coarctation of Aorta, Dextrotransposition of the great arteries, Hypoplastic left heart syndrome, Peri membranous ventricular septal defect, Pulmonary valve stenosis, Tetralogy of Fallot, Anorectal atresia, Diaphragmatic hernia, Esophageal atresia with/without tracheoesophageal fistula, Gastroschisis, Hypospadias, Craniosynostosis, Transverse limb deficiency, Anotia/microtia,<break/>Cleft lip with or without cleft palate,<break/>Cleft palate</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics: maternal age at delivery, race or ethnicity, level of education<break/>Substance use: smoking in the periconceptional period, binge drinking in the periconceptional period<break/>Mental health: none<break/>Physical health: pre-pregnancy body mass index, any periconceptional folic acid use<break/>Pregnancy-specific: none<break/>Other: none</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19. Williams et al. (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective, case-control study of births in Atlanta, Georgia, USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,151 (122 cases, 3,029 controls)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1968&#8211;1980</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maternal and paternal self-reported frequency of use 3 months prior to pregnancy through the first trimester</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiac</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral septal defect</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics: maternal age, maternal race, infant race, birth period, and hospital of birth<break/>Substance use: none<break/>Mental health:<break/>Physical health: maternal diabetes, multivitamin use<break/>Pregnancy-specific: none<break/>Other: none</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20. Witter et al. (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective study of patients in Baltimore, Maryland, USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,350</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1983&#8211;1985</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported use in pregnancy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unspecified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anomalies</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>The 10 states included in the study conducted by Van Gelder et al. (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>) were Arkansas, California, Georgia, Iowa, Massachusetts, New Jersey, New York, North Carolina, Texas, and Utah.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b"><label>3.2.</label><title>Adjusted associations with specific birth defects</title><p><xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table&#160;2</xref> includes information on adjusted associations between <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and specific birth defects. When examining associations, we only considered the 12 studies that adjusted for confounding, given the importance in doing so in assessing epidemiologic relationships (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). We included information about associations with specific malformations whenever available. However, given the rarity of specific malformations, most studies evaluated associations with organ specific malformations grouped together.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Adjusted associations for specific birth defect, organized by organ system from 12 articles that adjust for confounding.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organ system</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citation</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cannabis exposure definition</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Birth defect</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Association</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="16" colspan="1">Cardiac</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Bandoli et al. (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cannabis-related diagnosis made during pregnancy or delivery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Any cardiac malformation</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR: 1.0, 95% CI: 0.8&#8211;1.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cannabis-related diagnosis without another substance use disorder diagnoses made during pregnancy or delivery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR: 1.0, 95% CI: 0.8&#8211;1.3.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Downing et al. (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported first-trimester use</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ebstein anomaly</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 1.8, 95% CI: 0.9&#8211;3.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="8" colspan="1">Van Gelder et al. (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="8" colspan="1">Self-reported use in the month before pregnancy or during the first trimester</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atrial septal defect not otherwise specified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 1.1, 95% CI: 0.7&#8211;1.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atrial septal defect secundum</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 0.8, 95% CI: 0.6&#8211;1.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coarctation of Aorta</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 1.2, 95% CI: 0.7&#8211;1.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dextrotransposition of the great arteries</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 0.8, 95% CI: 0.5&#8211;1.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypoplastic left heart syndrome</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 0.8, 95% CI: 0.4&#8211;1.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peri membranous ventricular septal defect</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 1.0, 95% CI: 0.8&#8211;1.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulmonary valve stenosis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 1.0, 95% CI: 0.7&#8211;1.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetralogy of Fallot</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 1.1, 95% CI: 0.7&#8211;1.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Williams et al. (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any self-reported use 3 months before pregnancy through the first trimester</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Ventral septal defect</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 1.9, 95% CI: 1.3&#8211;2.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported use &lt;2 days/week 3 months before pregnancy through the first trimester</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 2.20, 95% CI: 1.2&#8211;3.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported use &gt;3 days/week 3 months before pregnancy through the first trimester</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 3.7, 95% CI: 1.6&#8211;9.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paternal-reported use &lt;2 days/week 3 months before pregnancy through the first trimester</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 1.5, 95% CI: 0.6&#8211;3.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paternal-reported use &gt;3 days/week 3 months before pregnancy through the first trimester</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 3.2, 95% CI: 0.61&#8211;10.71</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Central nervous system</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Bandoli et al. (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cannabis-related diagnosis made during pregnancy or delivery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Any central nervous system malformation</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR: 1.2, 95% CI: 1.0&#8211;1.5.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cannabis-related diagnosis without another substance use disorder diagnosis made during pregnancy or delivery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR: 1.2, 95% CI: 0.9&#8211;1.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shaw et al. (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported use 3 months before pregnancy through pregnancy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neural tube defect</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 0.7, 95% CI: 0.5&#8211;1.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Van Gelder et al. (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Self-reported use in the month before pregnancy or during the first trimester</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anencephaly</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 2.2, 95% CI: 1.3&#8211;3.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spina Bifida</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 0.9, 95% CI: 0.6&#8211;1.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Eye</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Bandoli et al. (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cannabis-related diagnosis made during pregnancy or delivery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Eye malformation</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR: 1.1, 95% CI: 0.7&#8211;1.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cannabis-related diagnosis without another substance use disorder diagnoses made during pregnancy or delivery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR: 1.2, 95% CI: 0.7&#8211;2.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="7" colspan="1">Gastrointestinal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Bandoli et al. (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cannabis-related diagnosis made during pregnancy or delivery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Any gastrointestinal malformation</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR: 1.3, 95% CI: 1.1&#8211;1.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cannabis-related diagnosis without another substance use disorder diagnoses made during pregnancy or delivery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR: 1.3, 95% CI: 1.0&#8211;1.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Torfs et al. (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-report of first-trimester use</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastroschisis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 4.5, 95% CI 2.1&#8211;9.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Van Gelder et al. (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Self-reported use in the month before pregnancy or during the first trimester</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anorectal atresia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 0.8, 95% CI: 0.5&#8211;1.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diaphragmatic hernia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 1.4, 95% CI: 0.9&#8211;2.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Esophageal atresia with/without tracheoesophageal fistula</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 1.4, 95% CI: 0.8&#8211;2.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastroschisis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 1.2, 95% CI: 0.9&#8211;1.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Genitourinary</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Van Gelder et al. (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Self-reported use in the month before pregnancy or during the first trimester</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Hypospadias</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 0.8, 95% CI: 0.5&#8211;1.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 0.8, 95% CI: 0.5&#8211;1.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Musculoskeletal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Van Gelder et al. (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Self-reported use in the month before pregnancy or during the first trimester</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Craniosynostosis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 0.8, 95% CI: 0.5&#8211;1.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transverse limb deficiency</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 1.0, 95% CI: 0.6&#8211;1.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Orofacial</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Van Gelder et al. (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Self-reported use in the month before pregnancy or during the first trimester</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anotia/microtia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 0.9, 95% CI: 0.5&#8211;1.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cleft lip with or without cleft palate</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 1.0, 95% CI: 0.8&#8211;1.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cleft palate</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 1.0, 95% CI: 0.7&#8211;1.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Bandoli et al. (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cannabis-related diagnosis made during pregnancy or delivery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Oral cleft</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR: 1.1, 95% CI: 0.9&#8211;1.5.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cannabis-related diagnosis without another substance use disorder diagnoses made during pregnancy or delivery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR: 1.1, 95% CI: 0.8&#8211;1.5.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">Unspecified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coleman-Cowger et al. (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported use during pregnancy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any birth defects</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 1.2, 95% CI: 0.5&#8211;0.9.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cornelius et al. (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported first-trimester use</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minor physical anomalies</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 3.2, 95% CI: 1.0&#8211;10.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day et al. (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported use by trimester</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minor and major physical abnormalities</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No significant association (point estimate not reported)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gibson et al. 1983 (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported use by trimester</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Congenital defects</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No significant association (point estimate not reported)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kharbanda et al. (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine toxicology screens during first prenatal visit</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major structural birth defects</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR: 0.6 95% CI: 0.2&#8211;2.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linn et al. (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported use during pregnancy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major or minor malformations</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 1.4, 95% CI: 1.0&#8211;1.9</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn2"><p>RR, relative risk; OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec id="s3b1"><label>3.2.1.</label><title>Cardiac</title><p>Results were inconsistent across the four articles reporting findings from studies assessing associations between <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and cardiac malformations (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). One article (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) indicated a dose-response relationship between self-reported cannabis use three months before pregnancy through the first trimester and ventral septal defect [any use OR: 1.9, 95% CI: 1.3, 2.8; use &lt;2 days/week OR: 2.20, 95% CI: 1.2, 3.9; use &gt;3 days/week OR: 3.7, 95% CI: 1.6, 9.0; (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>)]. Another study found increased odds of Ebstein anomaly associated with maternal self-reported first-trimester cannabis use, though the confidence interval around the estimate was wide and included the null [OR: 1.8, 95% CI: 0.9, 3.8; (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>)]. Additionally, two other articles (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>) reported no elevated risk of any cardiac malformation among infants born to individuals with a cannabis-related diagnosis made during pregnancy or delivery [RR: 1.0, 95% CI: 0.8, 1.2; (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>)] and no associations between maternal self-reported cannabis use in the month before pregnancy or during the first trimester of pregnancy and eight specific cardiac malformations [<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table&#160;2</xref>; (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)].</p></sec><sec id="s3b2"><label>3.2.2.</label><title>Central nervous system</title><p>Three articles reported findings from studies assessing <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and central nervous system (CNS) malformations, and results were conflicting (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). Two studies focused on neural tube defects [NTD; (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)]&#8212;Van Gelder et al. reported on two subtypes of NTD [anencephaly and spina bifida; (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)], while Shaw et al. focused on any NTD (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). Van Gelder et al. reported increased odds of anencephaly [odds ratio [OR]: 2.2, 95% CI: 1.3&#8211;3.7; (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)] but not spina bifida [OR: 0.9, 95% CI: 0.6&#8211;1.4; (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)] among infants born to individuals who self-reported cannabis use in the month before pregnancy or during the first trimester of pregnancy (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>); and, Shaw et al. failed to find an association between self-reported cannabis use three months before pregnancy through pregnancy and any NTD [OR: 0.7, 95% CI: 0.5&#8211;1.2; (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>)]. The third study (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>) found an increased risk of any CNS malformations among infants born to individuals with a self-reported cannabis-related diagnosis [relative risk [RR]: 1.2, 95% CI: 1.0, 1.5; (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>)].</p></sec><sec id="s3b3"><label>3.2.3.</label><title>Eye</title><p>One article reported on the association between <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and eye malformation (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). The study failed to find an association between a cannabis-related diagnosis made during pregnancy or delivery and eye malformation [RR: 1.1, 95% CI: 0.7, 1.7; (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>)].</p></sec><sec id="s3b4"><label>3.2.4.</label><title>Gastrointestinal</title><p>Three articles reported findings from studies assessing associations between <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and gastrointestinal malformations (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). The findings from these three studies were mixed. Two articles suggested <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure was associated with increased risk of gastrointestinal malformations. Specifically, one article (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>) reported an association between cannabis-related diagnoses made during pregnancy or delivery and any gastrointestinal malformation [RR: 1.3, 95% CI: 1.1, 1.5; (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>)]; and, one article (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>) reported an association between self-reported cannabis use in the first trimester and gastroschisis [OR: 4.5, 95% CI 2.1&#8211;9.8; (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>)]. However, another article (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>) did not find any significant associations between self-reported cannabis use in the month before pregnancy or during the first trimester and several specific gastrointestinal birth defects [<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table&#160;2</xref>; (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>)], including gastroschisis [OR: 1.2, 95% CI: 0.9, 1.7 (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)].</p></sec><sec id="s3b5"><label>3.2.5.</label><title>Genitourinary</title><p>One article reported on associations between <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and genitourinary malformations (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). This study failed to find an association between self-reported cannabis use in the month before pregnancy or during the first trimester and hypospadias [OR: 0.8, 95% CI: 0.5&#8211;1.2; (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)].</p></sec><sec id="s3b6"><label>3.2.6.</label><title>Musculoskeletal</title><p>One article reported on association between <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and musculoskeletal malformations (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). The study failed to find associations between self-reported cannabis use in the month before pregnancy or during the first trimester and (a) craniosynostosis (OR: 0.8, 95% CI: 0.5&#8211;1.3) or (b) transverse limb deficiency [OR: 1.0, 95% CI: 0.6&#8211;1.7; (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)].</p></sec><sec id="s3b7"><label>3.2.7.</label><title>Orofacial</title><p>Associations between <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and specific orofacial malformations were reported on in two articles (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). Both articles reported associations close to the null for each malformation [<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table&#160;2</xref>; (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)]. Specifically, Van Gelder et al. reported associations close to the null for anotia/microtia (OR: 0.9, 95% CI: 0.5&#8211;1.7), cleft lip with or without cleft palate (OR: 1.0, 95% CI: 0.8&#8211;1.3), and cleft palate [OR: 1.0, 95% CI: 0.7&#8211;1.5; (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)]; and Bandoli et al. reported an association close to the null for oral cleft [RR: 1.1, 95% CI: 0.9, 1.5; (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>)].</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><label>4.</label><title>Discussion</title><p>This systematic review found mixed and inconclusive associations between <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and risk for structural birth defects. Results were mixed among (a) the four articles reporting on adjusted associations with cardiac malformations (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>), (b) the three articles reporting on adjusted associations with central nervous system malformations (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>), and (c) the three articles reporting on adjusted associations with gastrointestinal malformations (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). Some studies suggested <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure was not associated with these types of birth defects; and, other articles suggesting that <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure was associated with increased risk of these types of birth defects. Only two articles reported on adjusted associations with orofacial malformations (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>); and, only single articles reported on adjusted associations with eye malformation (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>), genitourinary malformations (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>), and musculoskeletal malformations (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). Though the articles reporting on associations with orofacial, eye, genitourinary, and musculoskeletal malformations all suggested that <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure was not associated with these types of malformations (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>), strong conclusions cannot be drawn from these few studies that all had limitations.</p><p>There were several limitations of the included studies that may have contributed to the mixed findings on <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and birth defects. These limitations are similar to those of studies on <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and other outcomes, such as long-term neurodevelopmental and psychiatric problems (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). First, many of the studies had samples that were relatively small (e.g., 6 of the 20 studies had samples under 500) and reported findings with wide confidence intervals. Therefore, these studies had poor precision and likely were underpowered to detect associations that truly exist. Second, several studies (i.e., 16 of 20) utilized birth cohorts with births occurring more than 20 years ago, which could be problematic given increasing cannabis potency in recent years (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>) and the proliferation of newer modes of administration (e.g., vaping, edibles) with potentially different risk profiles (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). Third, most studies utilized self-report data, which may underestimate cannabis exposure (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). Therefore, these studies may have mistakenly classified exposed offspring as unexposed, reducing the likelihood of detecting a true association. Fourth, many studies did not address timing of exposure, which is particularly problematic when studying birth defects given that exposures early in pregnancy may be particularly risky for the development of major structural birth defects (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>). Fifth, most studies did not assess associations with dose of cannabis exposure. This is a major limitation given that some research has supported a dose-response relationship between <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and birth defects (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), and research has shown dose-dependent associations between <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and other outcomes (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Sixth, most studies did not adequately account for potential confounders, such as co-exposure to other substances. Despite the high co-occurrence of cannabis use and use of other substances, particularly tobacco and alcohol, in pregnancy 12 of the 20 studies did not take this into consideration. Therefore, observed associations between <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and birth defects could be attributable to exposure to a substance other than cannabis or could be explained by an interactive effect of cannabis use plus use of another substance (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). We note that one study did find similar associations with and without limiting the sample to pregnancies with substance use disorder diagnoses other than cannabis-related diagnoses (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). Nonetheless, more research is needed to parse apart the effects of <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure from exposure to other substances.</p><p>It is important to recognize that the mixed and inconclusive results on associations between <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and structural birth defects should not be interpreted as evidence suggesting cannabis use in pregnancy is safe. Rather these results indicate that the relationship between <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and structural birth defects is unknown and point to a critical need for future research. This need is particularly pressing given the documented increasing rates in prenatal cannabis use (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>).</p><p>There are several important avenues for future research. First, samples should be sufficiently large to have adequate statistical power to identify associations if they truly exist. Second, studies with large sample sizes should evaluate associations with specific malformations within organ-specific malformation groups. Third, studies would benefit from including samples comprised of recent birth cohorts given changes in cannabis potency and modes of administration that have occurred in recent years. Fourth, utilizing biological measures (e.g., urine toxicology tests) in addition to self-reported cannabis use would reduce measurement error related to <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure. Fifth, assessing the influence of timing of exposure and particularly focusing on first-trimester exposure is important. Sixth, it is also important for future studies to quantify the amount of prenatal cannabis exposure by considering the dose, frequency, potency, mode of administration and duration of use during pregnancy. Seventh, studies should utilize methods that rigorously evaluate the potential influence of confounding factors. Using conceptual models based on previous literature, researchers can identify potential factors that may confound associations between <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure and birth defects. Researchers could also consider using advanced epidemiological methods that have been utilized to study other <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> exposures to help adjust for confounding factors, such as propensity scores, cannabis use before but not during pregnancy as a comparator, and comparisons of differentially exposed siblings [see Sujan et al. for a review of methods that have been used to study antidepressant medications during pregnancy (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>)].</p><p>Importantly, no single study can implement all of these recommendations, particularly given common obstacles faced by researchers, such as funding limitations restricting the scope of studies, challenges enrolling participants, difficulty obtaining biological samples, and loss to follow-up. However, future research should try to incorporate as many of these recommendations as possible to reduce biases and maximize the overall quality of the studies. Rigorous, high-quality information on the potential consequences of <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic> cannabis exposure is vital for individuals to make informed choices about cannabis use in pregnancy, as well as for families and providers caring for infants exposed to cannabis <italic toggle="yes">in utero</italic>.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s5"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article. Further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Author contributions</title><p>All authors conceptualized the study. AS and AP conducted the literature review and extracted information from the reviewed studies. All authors interpreted the findings. AS drafted the manuscript, and all authors provided critical revisions of the manuscript. KY and LA supervised AS. AS and KY supervised AP. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s8"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s9"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Volkow</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Compton</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCance-Katz</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Self-reported medical and nonmedical Cannabis use among pregnant women in the United States</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>322</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>167</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2019.7982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31211824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6582258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <comment>Support for marijuana legalization continues to rise</comment>. (<year>2016</year>). <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2016/10/12/support-for-marijuana-legalization-continues-to-rise/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2016/10/12/support-for-marijuana-legalization-continues-to-rise/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>State Medical Marijuana Laws</collab>. (<year>2017</year>). <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.ncsl.org/research/health/state-medical-marijuana-laws.aspx" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.ncsl.org/research/health/state-medical-marijuana-laws.aspx</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gnofam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allshouse</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stickrath</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metz</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of marijuana legalization on prevalence of maternal marijuana use and perinatal outcomes</article-title>. <source>Am J Perinatol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>59</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0039-1696719</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31491805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6957332</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skelton</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hecht</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamin-Neelon</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Recreational Cannabis legalization in the US and maternal use during the preconception, prenatal, and postpartum periods</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):909. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17030909</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7037220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32024173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skelton</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hecht</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamin-Neelon</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Association of recreational Cannabis legalization with maternal Cannabis use in the preconception, prenatal, and postpartum periods</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):e210138. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.0138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33630088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7907954</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young-Wolff</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Padon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexeeff</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Den Eeden</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of cannabis retailer proximity and density with cannabis use among pregnant women in northern California after legalization of cannabis for recreational use</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e210694</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.0694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33662131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7933995</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharapova</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sirocco</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaminski</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leeb</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rolle</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of prenatal marijuana exposure on neuropsychological outcomes in children aged 1&#8211;11 years: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Paediatr Perinat Epidemiol</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>32</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>512</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ppe.12505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30335203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6261687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Correa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Maternal lifestyle factors and risk for ventricular septal defects</article-title>. <source>Birth Defects Res A Clin Mol Teratol</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>70</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>59</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bdra.10145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14991912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nashed</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laviolette</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prenatal cannabinoid exposure: emerging evidence of physiological and neuropsychiatric abnormalities</article-title>. <source>Front Psychiatry</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.624275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7841012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33519564</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roncero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valriberas-Herrero</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mezzatesta-Gava</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villegas</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grau-Lopez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cannabis use during pregnancy and its relationship with fetal developmental outcomes and psychiatric disorders. A systematic review</article-title>. <source>Reprod Health</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>9</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12978-020-0880-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32066469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7027300</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conner</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedell</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipsey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macones</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cahill</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuuli</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Maternal marijuana use and adverse neonatal outcomes: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Obstet Gynecol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>128</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>713</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/AOG.0000000000001649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27607879</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunn</surname><given-names>JKL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosales</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Center</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christ</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prenatal exposure to cannabis and maternal and child health outcomes: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):e009986. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4823436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27048634</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Filion</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abenhaim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and outcomes of prenatal recreational cannabis use in high-income countries: a scoping review</article-title>. <source>BJOG</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>127</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>8</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1471-0528.15946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31529594</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sujan</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Young-Wolff</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avalos</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>In-utero cannabis exposure and long-term psychiatric and neurodevelopmental outcomes: the limitations of existing literature and recommendations for future research</article-title>. <source>Birth Defects Res</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>114</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>689</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>713</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bdr2.2060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35708102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9357094</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Myrianthopoulos</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Congenital anomalies: mortality and morbidity, burden and classification</article-title>. <source>Am J Med Genet</source>. (<year>1987</year>) <volume>27</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>505</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajmg.1320270304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3631126</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sujan</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avalos</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Young-Wolff</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group>. <comment>Systematic review and meta-analyses of cannabis exposure during pregnancy and risk for birth defects in infants. PROSPERO CRD42022308130. (2022). Available at</comment>: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.crd.york.ac.uk/prospero/display_record.php?ID=CRD42022308130" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.crd.york.ac.uk/prospero/display_record.php?ID=CRD42022308130</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qazi</surname><given-names>QH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mariano</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milman</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beller</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crombleholme</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Abnormalities in offspring associated with prenatal marihuana exposure</article-title>. <source>Dev Pharmacol Ther</source>. (<year>1985</year>) <volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>141</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000457031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3873327</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fried</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Postnatal consequences of maternal marijuana use in humans</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>. (<year>1989</year>) <volume>562</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.1989.tb21011.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2742270</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conner</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Marijuana and alcohol use in pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Drug Intell Clin Pharm</source>. (<year>1984</year>) <volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>233</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6365495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/106002808401800308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelsberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical inquiry: what effects&#8211;if any&#8211;does marijuana use during pregnancy have on the fetus or child?</article-title><source>J Fam Pract</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>66</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>462</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28700762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sambamoorthi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robles</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jhon</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prenatal marijuana use and neonatal outcome</article-title>. <source>Neurotoxicol Teratol</source>. (<year>1991</year>) <volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>329</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0892-0362(91)90079-C</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1886543</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Gelder</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reefhuis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caton</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Werler</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Druschel</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roeleveld</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Maternal periconceptional illicit drug use and the risk of congenital malformations</article-title>. <source>Epidemiology</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>60</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/EDE.0b013e31818e5930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19057385</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kennare</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Substance use during pregnancy: risk factors and obstetric and perinatal outcomes in South Australia</article-title>. <source>Aust N Z J Obstet Gynaecol</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>220</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1479-828X.2005.00379.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15904448</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ventura</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ventura</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cronemberger</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>MJM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Teratogen exposure and congenital ocular abnormalities in Brazilian patients with mobius sequence</article-title>. <source>Arq Bras Oftalmol</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>77</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>300</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5935/0004-2749.20140076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25494376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loffredo</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Correa-Villase&#241;or</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferencz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Attributable fraction for cardiac malformations</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. (<year>1998</year>) <volume>148</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>414</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.aje.a009666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9737553</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinsheimer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yanchar</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of maternal substance abuse and smoking on children with gastroschisis</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Surg</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>43</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>879</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>83</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpedsurg.2007.12.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18485958</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Auger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rheaume</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Low</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayoub</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luu</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of prenatal exposure to opioids, cocaine, and Cannabis on eye disorders in children</article-title>. <source>J Addict Med</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>459</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ADM.0000000000000621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31917733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geva</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robles</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Alcohol, marijuana, and tobacco: effects of prenatal exposure on offspring growth and morphology at age six</article-title>. <source>Alcohol Clin Exp Res</source>. (<year>1994</year>) <volume>18</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>786</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1530-0277.1994.tb00041.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7526725</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reece</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hulse</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cannabis teratology explains current patterns of coloradan congenital defects: the contribution of increased cannabinoid exposure to rising teratological trends</article-title>. <source>Clin Pediatr (Phila)</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>58</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1085</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>123</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0009922819861281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31288542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6691650</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reece</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hulse</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Contemporary epidemiology of rising atrial septal defect trends across USA 1991&#8211;2016: a combined ecological geospatiotemporal and causal inferential study</article-title>. <source>BMC Pediatr</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>539</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12887-020-02431-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33250054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7702707</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reece</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hulse</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Canadian Cannabis consumption and patterns of congenital anomalies: an ecological geospatial analysis</article-title>. <source>J Addict Med</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>14</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>E195</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>210</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ADM.0000000000000638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32187114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7547880</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reece</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hulse</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Geotemporospatial and causal inference epidemiological analysis of US survey and overview of cannabis, cannabidiol and cannabinoid genotoxicity in relation to congenital anomalies 2001&#8211;2015</article-title>. <source>BMC Pediatr</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>47</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12887-021-02996-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35042455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8767720</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dingman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toth</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sawardekar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Associations of maternal prenatal drug abuse with measures of newborn brain structure, tissue organization, and metabolite concentrations</article-title>. <source>JAMA Pediatr</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>174</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>831</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2020.1622</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32539126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7296459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman-Cowger</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oga</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and associated birth outcomes of co-use of Cannabis and tobacco cigarettes during pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Neurotoxicol Teratol</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>84</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ntt.2018.06.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29883744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6054553</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelius</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geva</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prenatal tobacco and marijuana use among adolescents: effects on offspring gestational age, growth, and morphology</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. (<year>1995</year>) <volume>95</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>738</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.95.5.738</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7724314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelius</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldschmidt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robles</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effects of prenatal tobacco and marijuana use on offspring growth from birth through 3 years of age</article-title>. <source>Neurotoxicol Teratol</source>. (<year>1992</year>) <volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>407</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0892-0362(92)90051-B</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1488035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hingson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alpert</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dooling</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kayne</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morelock</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of maternal drinking and marijuana use on fetal growth and development</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. (<year>1982</year>) <volume>70</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>539</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.70.4.539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6981792</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Linn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenbaum</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monson</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stubblefield</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The association of marijuana use with outcome of pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source>. (<year>1983</year>) <volume>73</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1161</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.73.10.1161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6604464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1651077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Connell</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fried</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An investigation of prenatal cannabis exposure and minor physical anomalies in a low risk population</article-title>. <source>Neurobehav Toxicol Teratol</source>. (<year>1984</year>) <volume>6</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>345</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6514096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Astley</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarren</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Little</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sampson</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daling</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of facial shape in children gestationally exposed to marijuana, alcohol, and/or cocaine</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. (<year>1992</year>) <volume>89</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>67</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>77</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.89.1.67</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1728025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baghurst</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colley</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Maternal alcohol, tobacco and cannabis consumption and the outcome of pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Aust N Z J Obstet Gynaecol</source>. (<year>1983</year>) <volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>15</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1479-828X.1983.tb00151.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6575752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bandoli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jelliffe-Pawlowski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Felder</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cannabis-related diagnosis in pregnancy and adverse maternal and infant outcomes</article-title>. <source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>225</volume>:108757. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2021.108757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34049105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8282693</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourque</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dougan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Momoli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riddell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gastroschisis in Ontario, Canada: 2012&#8211;2018</article-title>. <source>Birth Defects Res</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>113</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1044</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bdr2.1896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33871183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Downing</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riehle-Colarusso</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilboa</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oster</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tinker</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Potential risk factors for ebstein anomaly, national birth defects prevention study, 1997&#8211;2011</article-title>. <source>Cardiol Young</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>29</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>819</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1047951119000970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31159903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6711372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forrester</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merz</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of trends in gastroschisis and prenatal illicit drug use rates</article-title>. <source>J Toxicol Environ Health A</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>69</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>1253</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15287390500361750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16754539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forrester</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merz</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of selected birth defects with prenatal illicit drug use, Hawaii, 1986&#8211;2002</article-title>. <source>J Toxicol Environ Health A</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>70</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>7</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15287390600748799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17162495</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kharbanda</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vazquez-Benitez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunin-Batson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romitti</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Birth and early developmental screening outcomes associated with cannabis exposure during pregnancy</article-title>. <source>J Perinatol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>40</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>473</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41372-019-0576-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31911642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7047636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torfs</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Interaction between maternal smoking and malnutrition in infant risk of gastroschisis</article-title>. <source>Birth Defects Res A Clin Mol Teratol</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>76</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>182</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bdra.20238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16498669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Velie</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morland</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Parental recreational drug use and risk for neural tube defects</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. (<year>1996</year>) <volume>144</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1155</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.aje.a008894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8956628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torfs</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Velie</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oechsli</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bateson</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curry</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A population-based study of gastroschisis: demographic, pregnancy, and lifestyle risk factors</article-title>. <source>Teratology</source>. (<year>1994</year>) <volume>50</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>44</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/tera.1420500107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7974254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Gelder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donders</surname><given-names>ART</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Devine</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roeleveld</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reefhuis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Natl birth defects prevention S. Using Bayesian models to assess the effects of under-reporting of Cannabis use on the association with birth defects, national birth defects prevention study, 1997&#8211;2005</article-title>. <source>Paediatr Perinat Epidemiol</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>28</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>424</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ppe.12140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25155701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4532339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Witter</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niebyl</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Marijuana use in pregnancy and pregnancy outcome</article-title>. <source>Am J Perinatol</source>. (<year>1990</year>) <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>36</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2007-999442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2294909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#8217;Onofrio</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Class</surname><given-names>QA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rickert</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sujan</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuja-Halkola</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Translational epidemiologic approaches to understanding the consequences of early-life exposures</article-title>. <source>Behav Genet</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>46</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>315</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10519-015-9769-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26590988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4860044</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention &amp; Office of Noncommunicable Diseases Injury and Environmental Health</collab>. <source>What you need to know about marijuana and pregnancy</source>. Atlanta, GA (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>ElSohly</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehmedic</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Church</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in Cannabis potency over the last 2 decades (1995&#8211;2014): analysis of current data in the United States</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>79</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>613</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2016.01.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26903403</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4987131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologist</collab>. <article-title>Marijuana use during pregnancy and lactation: committee opinion No. 722</article-title>. <source>Obstet Gynecol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>130</volume>:<fpage>e205</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/AOG.0000000000002354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28937574</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young-Wolff</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weisner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Routes of cannabis administration among females in the year before and during pregnancy: results from a pilot project</article-title>. <source>Addict Behav</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>106125</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.addbeh.2019.106125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31600645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7945962</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young-Wolff</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>L-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexeeff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weisner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Trends in self-reported and biochemically tested marijuana use among pregnant females in California from 2009 to 2016</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>318</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>2490</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2017.17225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29279917</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5769923</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young-Wolff</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarovar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goler</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weisner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Validity of self-reported Cannabis use among pregnant females in northern California</article-title>. <source>J Addict Med</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>287</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ADM.0000000000000581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31688149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7931632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bleyl</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenwolf</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>What is the timeline of important events during pregnancy that may be disrupted by a teratogenic exposure? Teratology primer</source>. <edition>3rd ed.</edition> Reston, VA: The Society for Birth Defects Research and Prevention (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goler</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Young-Wolff</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Data are needed on the potential adverse effects of marijuana use in pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>169</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>492</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M18-1141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30140934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6419734</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farr</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>VT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Creanga</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callaghan</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and patterns of marijuana use among pregnant and nonpregnant women of reproductive age</article-title>. <source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>213</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>201.e1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>e10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajog.2015.03.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25772211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7469257</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sujan</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oberg</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#8217;Onofrio</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Annual research review: maternal antidepressant use during pregnancy and offspring neurodevelopmental problems&#8212;a critical review and recommendations for future research</article-title>. <source>J Child Psychol Psychiatry</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>60</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>356</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpp.13004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30515808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6438736</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>