<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nordisk Alkohol Nark</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nordisk Alkohol Nark</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3921</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">nad</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NAD</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nordisk Alkohol- &amp; Narkotikatidskrift : NAT</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1455-0725</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1458-6126</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nordic Welfare Centre</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11572557</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11572557.2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11572557</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12046144</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39563976</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/14550725241276306</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_14550725241276306</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">2</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Reports</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Wishing for a more sober society: A scoping review on addiction problems and treatment in Greenland preceding the 2016 national treatment strategy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0009-0008-1120-8591</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Flyger Holflod</surname><given-names initials="J">Julie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1-14550725241276306" ref-type="aff"/><aff id="aff1-14550725241276306">
<label/>University of Southern Denmark Faculty of Health Sciences, Odense, Denmark <break/>Institute of Health &amp; Nature, University of Greenland, Ilisimatusarfik, Nuuk. Greenland</aff><xref rid="corresp1-14550725241276306" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lytken Larsen</surname><given-names initials="CV">Christina Viskum</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2-14550725241276306" ref-type="aff"/><aff id="aff2-14550725241276306">Institute of Health &amp; Nature, University of Greenland, Ilisimatusarfik, Nuuk. Greenland<break/>National Institute of Public Health, University of Southern Denmark, Copenhagen, Denmark</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niclasen</surname><given-names initials="B">Birgit</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3-14550725241276306" ref-type="aff"/><aff id="aff3-14550725241276306">Institute of Health &amp; Nature, University of Greenland, Ilisimatusarfik, Nuuk. Greenland</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#248;gaard Nielsen</surname><given-names initials="A">Anette</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4-14550725241276306" ref-type="aff"/><aff id="aff4-14550725241276306">Unit for Clinical Alcohol Research, Research Unit of Psychiatry, Department of Clinical Research, University of Southern Denmark, Odense, Denmark<break/>Department of Psychiatry Odense, Mental Health Services Region of Southern Denmark, Odense, Denmark</aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-14550725241276306">Julie Flyger Holflod, Unite of Clinical Alcohol Research, Clinical Institute, University of Southern Denmark Faculty of Health Sciences, J. B. Winsl&#248;vsvej 18, indg. 220B, Odense, Denmark. 
Email: <email>jholflod@health.sdu.dk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>42</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">487785</issue-id><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>06</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-05-03 00:25:37.317"><day>03</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-version" specific-use="live"><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11572557</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/14550725241276306</article-id><article-version>1</article-version><pub-date><day>06</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date></event><event event-type="pmc-version" specific-use="live"><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12046144</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/14550725241276306</article-id><article-version>2</article-version><pub-date><day>06</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications Ltd, or Nordic Centre for Welfare and Social Issues, unless otherwise noted. Manuscript content on this site is licensed under Creative Commons Licenses</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access page (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10.1177_14550725241276306.pdf"/><abstract><p><bold>Introduction:</bold> The per capita intake of alcohol in Greenland has risen rapidly since it became commercially available, leading to a corresponding increase in addiction problems and demands for treatment services. Despite efforts to establish addiction treatment services, none were deemed adequate. In response, the Greenlandic parliament initiated a new treatment service strategy in 2015. The aim of this study was to explore the pre-implementation process of this national service by examining literature on addiction problems and treatment services. <bold>Methods:</bold> Using a scoping review and document analysis methodology, we focused on documents related to alcohol, cannabis, gambling, addiction and treatment within the context of Greenland. Data were sourced from parliamentary records, governmental publications and academic literature in the period 2010&#8211;2016, leading up to the decision on the new treatment service. A total of 54 documents were identified and organised into three main themes: the national discourse on addiction problems; strategies and action plans addressing addiction; and demographic mapping of addiction issues within the population. Notably, addiction problems emerged as a significant public concern across all themes. <bold>Results:</bold> Three key documents emerged as pivotal in the implementation of the new treatment service: a government report from 2012; a parliamentary inquiry in spring 2013; and an agenda item in fall 2013. These documents played a crucial role in shaping discussions and decisions. <bold>Conclusion:</bold> The findings underscore the widespread recognition of addiction problems as a pressing issue in Greenland, as evidenced by the prominence of relevant documents in shaping policy discussions and the implementation of new treatment initiatives.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd>addiction treatment services</kwd><kwd>alcohol consumption</kwd><kwd>public health policy</kwd><kwd>Greenland</kwd><kwd>scoping review</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>typesetter</meta-name><meta-value>ts19</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Addiction treatment services have been available in Greenland for many years, but a significant change occurred in 2016 with the introduction of Allorfik, a dedicated addiction treatment service. The implementation of Allorfik reflected an ongoing commitment to addressing addiction and alcohol-related issues in Greenland. The balance between the necessity of restrictions of the availability of alcohol &#8211; as was seen during the colonial time &#8211; versus the protection of individuals vulnerable to addiction problems and to the social consequences of the alcohol use was constantly on the political agenda the 60s, 70s, 80s and 90s (<xref rid="bibr45-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Poulsen, 2012</xref>). Heavy drinking has been an issue since the commercial release of sales of alcohol in the early 1950s, with a peak in intake levels at around 22 L of pure alcohol a year per adult person (aged 15+&#8201;years) in the late 1980s (<xref rid="bibr1-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Aage, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bibr14-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Bjerregaard et al., 2020</xref>). In 2013, addiction problems were still considered the largest problem for health and social well-being in Greenland (<xref rid="bibr21-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Departement for Sundhed, 2012</xref>). Estimates of problematic use of alcohol have been high, with National Population Health Surveys reporting that approximately 50% of the adult population engaged in binge drinking at least once a month and approximately 30% were considered to have potentially harmful alcohol consumption in the years 2003, 2008, 2010, 2011 and 2016 (<xref rid="bibr8-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Bjerregaard &amp; Aidt, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bibr11-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Bjerregaard &amp; Dahl-Petersen, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bibr9-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Bjerregaard et al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bibr10-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; <xref rid="bibr18-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Dahl-Petersen et al., 2016</xref>). The high per capita intake of alcohol in recent decades has also resulted in a significant proportion of people reporting that they grew up in homes with alcohol-related problems (<xref rid="bibr34-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Larsen et al., 2018</xref>). Furthermore, the use of cannabis has become a growing issue, with approximately 10% of the adult population reported as regular users in 2016 (<xref rid="bibr34-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Larsen et al., 2018</xref>). Since cannabis is an illegal drug, it has been confiscated frequently in Greenland (<xref rid="bibr29-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Gr&#248;nlands Politi, 2023</xref>). However, the drinking and addiction pattern is not unique to Greenland as similar trends have been observed in other indigenous and Arctic populations (<xref rid="bibr2-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Allen et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bibr17-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Brett et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bibr28-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Gray et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bibr36-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>Social inequality in Greenland is high, particularly among those who drink the most (<xref rid="bibr24-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Departementet for Sundhed og Infrastruktur, 2014</xref>). In 2014, it was estimated that approximately 13 deaths each year were directly caused by alcohol, and hospital stays caused by alcohol were estimated to cost 8.7 million DKK each year (ibid). The extent of addiction problems within certain parts of society and across generations was revealed that, among individuals attending addiction treatment, 97.5% had grown up in homes with addiction issues and 89% had siblings who also had addiction problems (ibid). The cost of addiction problems in Greenlandic society in 2013 was estimated to be in the range of 271&#8211;338 million DKK per year, accounting for not only healthcare costs but also the added expense of social services, productivity and crimes (<xref rid="bibr22-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Departement for Sundhed, 2015</xref>). Addiction problems have consequently drained resources from various regions of Greenland and its population for decades.</p><p>Over time, addiction treatment services in Greenland have evolved in various forms and been a subject of political debate (<xref rid="bibr48-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Rosenqvist, 2001</xref>). Initially, public healthcare facilities across the country only offered detoxification for alcohol withdrawal symptoms and pharmacological treatment (e.g., Disulfiram) to promote abstinence (<xref rid="bibr43-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Niclasen &amp; Poulsen, 2020</xref>). In 1985, the AA movement was initiated by private individuals in south Greenland, which eventually led to the establishment of a certain level of partnership between the government, municipalities and private treatment organisations in Denmark and Iceland to secure access to treatment services based on the 12-step model for treatment (<xref rid="bibr30-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Humphreys, 2002</xref>). In 1995, the Greenlandic government opened the first treatment facilities in Qaqiffik, in the towns of Nuuk (the capital) and, for a short period, in Ilulissat. The treatment in these facilities was also based on the 12-step model of addiction treatment and treatment services were offered in collaboration with a private treatment institution from Denmark. However, in 2011, based on a call for tenders, the public healthcare system on behalf of the government terminated the collaboration (<xref rid="bibr43-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Niclasen &amp; Poulsen, 2020</xref>). From 2012, the responsibility of addiction treatment was appointed to another private facility in Nuuk offering treatment for addictions, albeit still treatment based on the 12-step model of addiction. The municipalities became responsible for referrals and payment of the treatment, while the healthcare system paid for travel (from other places) to and accommodation in Nuuk. This setup left the availability and direct access to treatment unchanged, as only the residents of Nuuk (30% of total population) had direct access to treatment. The treatment gap remained large, since the number of patients referred to treatment in Nuuk was only approximately 2000&#8211;300 a year (<xref rid="bibr22-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Departement for Sundhed, 2015</xref>; Departementet for Sundhed og Infrastruktur, 2014), while the estimates from the population health surveys indicate that 36% of all participants wished to change their alcohol intake (<xref rid="bibr34-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Larsen et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>In 2016, the government thus introduced a new addiction treatment service, Allorfik. Allorfik had the goal of providing easily accessible treatment for problems with addiction to alcohol, cannabis and gambling, and to be situated locally, closer to the population. This resulted in an introduction of a new treatment methodology and five new treatment centres over the course of 2.5 years and as such was a radical change to the previous ways of organising addiction treatment services with only one treatment facility available in Nuuk in addition to sporadic treatment courses by traveling counsellors outside Nuuk. The introduction of Allorfik and the improved accessibility of treatment had a notable impact on the demographics of treatment seekers. Compared to those attending the central treatment facility in Nuuk, individuals seeking treatment at local Allorfik centres were predominantly women who were employed and had families. In contrast, the central facility in Nuuk primarily treated unemployed men without families (<xref rid="bibr27-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Flyger et al., 2019</xref>).</p><sec disp-level="2" id="section1A-14550725241276306"><title>Aim of the present study</title><p>The present study poses the research question: what happened in Greenland at a political and civil servant level that led to a new strategy for addiction treatment in 2016? The aim of the study was thus to explore the publicly available documents on addiction problems (with alcohol, cannabis and gambling) that described the needs of and wishes to change how treatment is offered (i.e., government and academia) leading up to the government decision to implement the current national strategy for treatment of addiction in Greenland.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="section1B-14550725241276306"><title>Context</title><p>Greenland has a population of approximately 56,600 people with roughly 60% living in one of the five main cities in each of the five municipalities; 25% live in smaller cities and approximately 15% live in remote villages. The infrastructure in Greenland is difficult, with no roads connecting cities or villages. Transportation between inhabited areas is thus organised by airplane, helicopter or boat. This difficult infrastructure also makes access to, for example, healthcare services, difficult and very dependent on the residential area, with the only major hospital located in the capital, Nuuk, and larger healthcare facilities located in each of the five biggest cities and small facilities with only a nurse or healthcare assistant present in smaller inhabited areas (<xref rid="bibr42-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Niclasen &amp; Mulvad, 2010</xref>). Greenland's culture is rooted in Inuit heritage, with hunting and fishing remaining integral to daily life for the majority, and many Greenlanders are employed in the fishing industry today (<xref rid="bibr4-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Andersen, 2008</xref>). This is also reflected in the way health and well-being are perceived more holistically with, for example, mind, body and spirit, and local Greenlandic food as important determinants for health (<xref rid="bibr23-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Departement for Sundhed, 2020</xref>).</p><p>Greenland, a self-ruling part of the Danish Realm (i.e., the Kingdom of Denmark) since 2009, previously held the status of a Danish colony. In the transition from colony to first home rule in 1979 and later to self-rule in 2009, different government departments have transferred from Danish authority to Greenlandic authority, e.g., the healthcare system in 1992 (<xref rid="bibr52-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Statsministeriet, 2023</xref>). At the time of the handover of the national healthcare system, addiction treatment services were not initially implemented in Greenland and it remained the responsibility of the Greenlandic Government to introduce these services (<xref rid="bibr43-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Niclasen &amp; Poulsen, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bibr45-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Poulsen, 2012</xref>)</p><p>Today, Greenland operates as a representative democracy with three levels of government: municipal; national; and the Danish parliament. In national elections for the Danish parliament, Greenland elects two representatives from a single constituency. Municipally, elections occur every 4 years, with constituencies corresponding to the five municipalities. At the national level, members of the Greenlandic parliament, Inatsisartut, are elected for 4-year terms from a single constituency. Shortly after parliamentary elections, a constituent assembly convenes to elect the Inatsisartut chairman, government (Naalakkersuisut), and schedule the two annual parliamentary sessions (spring and fall assembly) (<xref rid="bibr31-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Inatsisartut, 1994</xref>). Over the years, Greenland has seen the presence of various political parties. One of the most dominant parties historically and presently is Siumut, a social democratic party. In the election leading to self-rule in 2009, the Inuit Ataqatigiit (IA) party, a democratic socialist party, secured the majority vote and took leadership of Naalakkersuisut (<xref rid="bibr19-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Dahl, 2010</xref>). Today they again hold the majority of vote and the chairmanship of Nalakkersuisut (<xref rid="bibr46-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Press, 2021</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="section2-14550725241276306"><title>Methods</title><p>The present study was inspired by the stages of a scoping review framework (<xref rid="bibr5-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Arksey &amp; O&#8217;Malley, 2005</xref>) and performed the following steps: identified the research question; identified relevant documents and selected these; and charted the documents in tables and reported these in the results section as prescribed in the framework (ibid). It was very clear from the beginning that the study had to rely on many different types of literature e.g., journal articles, reports, government and political documents, and thus could not follow the original thoughts of a scoping review as prescribed by Arksey and O&#8217;Malley as it could not compare peer-reviewed journal articles of different studies. Thus, the scoping review framework was used as inspiration for a step-by-step guide on how to progress and scope across different types of literature and sources.</p><sec id="section2A-14550725241276306"><title>Data</title><p>We performed a systematic search of the following databases and digital platforms: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.ina.gl" ext-link-type="uri">www.ina.gl</ext-link>; <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.naalakkersuisut.gl" ext-link-type="uri">www.naalakkersuisut.gl</ext-link>; <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.bibliotek.dk" ext-link-type="uri">www.bibliotek.dk</ext-link>; <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.peqqik.dl" ext-link-type="uri">www.peqqik.dl</ext-link>; PubMed; Web of Science; and Embase. We retrieved data from academic papers and reports, political documents and minutes from meetings in the parliamentary Family and Health Committee when debating addiction treatment. The political documents were retrieved from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.ina.gl" ext-link-type="uri">www.ina.gl</ext-link>, while governments documents were retrieved from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.naalakkersuisut.gl" ext-link-type="uri">www.naalakkersuisut.gl</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.peqqik.gl" ext-link-type="uri">www.peqqik.gl</ext-link>. For scientific documents, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.pubmed.com" ext-link-type="uri">www.pubmed.com</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.WebofScience.com" ext-link-type="uri">www.WebofScience.com</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.embase.com" ext-link-type="uri">www.embase.com</ext-link> were searched. We searched <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.bibliotek.dk" ext-link-type="uri">www.bibliotek.dk</ext-link> for documents in Danish and Greenlandic. The search continued using a snowball method for additional literature, i.e., all references were examined for additional relevant documents; if any were found, the references of those documents were also searched. With recurring authors, their works were also examined. The study did not include newspaper documents as there is no media-monitoring organisation in Greenland yet. As Danish and Icelandic databases do not include recent Greenlandic media, a search was not feasible. The search was limited to the years 2010&#8211;2016, when the present national strategy was decided upon and initiated.</p><p>We searched for peer-reviewed documents in the Pubmed, Web of Science, and Embase databases with the following search: (greenland) AND (((gambling OR betting OR wagering) OR (cannabis OR marijuana OR (medical marijuana) OR hemp OR cannabinoids)) OR (alcohol OR (binge drinking) OR intoxication OR (alcohol use disorder) OR (drinking pattern))). The search was limited to studies in Greenland only. We used the same search terms in Danish when searching for other documents; again, this search was limited to documents only from Greenland.</p><p>As a first step, documents were screened from the title and, if applicable, the abstract. Content relating to the treatment of other diseases was excluded, e.g., alcohol use included only as part of a dietary intake. We had several results regarding other types of healthcare treatments in Greenland but only a few were related to addiction treatment, as demonstrated in the results section. In the next step of screening, the full document was read through. We searched for documents describing the intentions and perspectives on the extent of addiction problems, future directions for addiction treatment and expectations as to what the treatment services should entail. We included documents that describe or analyse issues related to alcohol, cannabis or gambling addiction as well as addiction treatment services. We also included documents that contained perspectives on the extent of addiction problems and suggestions for addressing these issues that were not related to addiction treatment services.</p></sec><sec id="section2B-14550725241276306"><title>Analysis</title><p>We performed a document analysis (<xref rid="bibr16-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Bowen, 2009</xref>) of the available literature detailing the addiction treatment service in Greenland for historical context. We read through each document and searched for descriptions of treatment needs, perspectives on the severity of addiction problems in society and objectives for future treatment services. We extracted data in categories and thereafter assembled the documents in three major themes and reported the different perspectives. The analysis also identified significant events and the connection between different events and important documents for the process leading to the new addiction treatment strategy.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="section3-14550725241276306"><title>Results</title><p>The search for documents provided the following results: WebofScience&#8201;=&#8201;67; Pubmed&#8201;=&#8201;54; Embase&#8201;=&#8201;322; Ina.gl&#8201;=&#8201;263; Naalakkeruisut&#8201;=&#8201;13; and Bibliotek.dk&#8201;=&#8201;137. The snowball method provided five scientific documents that were included. The screening process is illustrated in <xref rid="fig1-14550725241276306" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. In total, 54 relevant documents were identified: 26 political documents; 13 government documents; and 15 scientific documents. Most of the literature was published in Danish and Greenlandic only; of the scientific publications, only nine were in English and published in peer-reviewed literature.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1-14550725241276306" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Stages of document screening and inclusion.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_14550725241276306-fig1.jpg"/></fig><p>We identified three main themes within the available literature on addictive behaviours and the development of addiction treatment services in Greenland: the national debate on addiction problems; the strategies and action plans of addiction problems; and the mapping of addiction problems. The results are presented in this order.</p><sec id="section3A-14550725241276306"><title>The national debate on addiction problems</title><p>This theme reflects the political discussion. <xref rid="table1-14550725241276306" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows each of the included items from the political agendas with the year, the proposer and political party, and the decision. <xref rid="table1-14550725241276306" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> presents that over the years, many individuals and political parties were engaged in the discussion about addiction problems. <xref rid="table2-14550725241276306" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents the so-called Paragraph 37 questions,<sup>
<xref rid="fn1-14550725241276306" ref-type="fn">1</xref>
</sup> where questions on alcohol, cannabis, gambling and abuse problems were inquired from a member of parliament to the government. in the period between 2010 and 2016, there was a parliamentary election in April 2013 and again in November 2014.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table1-14550725241276306" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Items on parliament agenda.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_14550725241276306-table1.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Year</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Title</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Proposer and</bold> p<bold>olitical party</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Parliament</bold> d<bold>ecision</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009 and 2010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposal for a resolution that Naalakkersuisut be required to establish a training programme for addiction treatment counsellors in Greenland.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atassut &#8211; the whole parliament group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rejected</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposal for debate on the current legislation regarding sales and serving of alcoholic beverages.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jane Petersen, IA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposal for debate on what alcohol policy initiatives we envisage in the future &#8211; here we are thinking both about proposals that will maintain the falling trend in the sale of alcohol and proposals that can contribute to an increased liberalisation of alcohol legislation, e.g., around closing times.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Storm Ludvigsen, IA and Andreas Uldum, Demokraatit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposal for Inatsisartut decision that Naalakkersuisut be instructed to make an early intervention to give future and new parents the opportunity to treat their abuse of hashish and alcohol during pregnancy and during breastfeeding, so that the child's health during pregnancy and early childhood can be ensured and that follow-up must take place after completion of treatment with a view to building up knowledge.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aleqa Hammond &amp; Ruth Heilmann, Siumut</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adopted</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposal for Inatsisartut decision that Naalakkersuisut be required to submit a proposal to amend Landsting Act No. 11 of 11 November 2000 on the sale and serving of alcoholic beverages, so that the opening hours for the sale of strong and weak drinks, cf. &#167;&#167; 11 and 12, are extended to at 21:00 every day of the week.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malik Bertelsen, Siumut</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postponed</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposal for inquiry debate on how we, as a society, can have a more appropriate relationship with alcohol.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siverth K. Heilmann &amp; Knud Kristiansen, Atassut</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposal for inquiry debate on adaptation of the rules for serving and selling alcoholic beverages.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gerhardt Petersem &amp; Siverth K. Heilmann, Atassut</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Withdrawn</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposal for Inatsisartut decision that Naalakkersuisut is required to draw up a targeted action plan, which must explain how society, as a whole, must deal with the growing group of citizens who have experienced brain damage due to excessive alcohol consumption. The action plan must be submitted to Inatsisartut no later than FM 2014.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agathe Fontain, IA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Items 8 and 9 discussed collectively.<break/>Adopted with amendments from the committee.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I hereby propose a resolution that Naalakkersuisut, no later than the spring meeting 2014, presents a strategy and action plan so that citizens with alcohol abuse problems and who do so on purpose can receive treatment free of charge.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mimi Karlsen, IA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Items 8 and 9 discussed collectively.<break/>Adopted with amendments from the committee.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014 (postponed and processed in 2015)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposal for Inatsisartut decision that Naalakkersuisut for FM 2015 is required to present a national action plan against hashish.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mimi Karlsen, IA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adopted with amendments from the committee.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inquiry debate on how we can best prevent and combat cannabis and alcohol abuse among children and young people.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Naaja H. Nathanielsen, vagrant &amp; Agathe Fontain, IA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1-14550725241276306"><p><italic toggle="yes">Note.</italic> IA = Inuit Ataqatigiit; NA = not available.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="table2-14550725241276306" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Paragraph 37 questions.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_14550725241276306-table2.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Date received</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Paragraph 37 question</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sender</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8 February 2010</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Does Naalakkersuisut have figures on how many children here in Greenland are born with either fetal alcohol syndrome or fetal alcohol effect due to the mother's alcohol intake during pregnancy?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Astrid Fleisher Rex, Demokraatit</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>24 January 2011</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. Does Naalakkersuisut have plans to lift the ban on liquor sales in the following places: Qaanaaq, Ittoqqortoormiit, Tasiilaq and the surrounding villages? 2. If not, what plans does Naalakkersuisut have regarding the preventive work with alcohol abuse in these places?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Justus Hansen, Demokraatit</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4 February 2011</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Has Naalakkersuisut considered doing a study on whether our alcohol consumption is different compared to other peoples and what is different if this is the case and what is the reason for this?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malik Berthelsen, Siumut</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>14 April 2011</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Question: 1. Are people now sentenced in Greenland to indefinite sentences in institutions in Greenland? 2. If so, are they offered addiction treatment while in custody? 3. Who is responsible for the costs of the treatments for addiction?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aleqa Hammond, Siumut</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>15 April 2011</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The retail chains Pisiffik, Brugsen and Pilersuisoq sent a letter to Naalakkersuisut on 13 January 2011 regarding drinks with a low alcohol content. How does Naalakkersuisut rate the letter?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malik Berthelsen, Siumut</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>15 August 2011</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">What opportunities &#8211; and what possible obstacles &#8211; does Naalakkersuisut see to strengthen the Greenlandic tax authorities&#8217; cooperation with the police regarding control of the basis of calculation for persons and companies that the police suspect of being involved in the hashish trade?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Andreas Uldum, Demokraatit</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10 February 2012</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Does the member of Naalakkersuisut intend to intervene to lift the alcohol ban in GU in Aasiaat?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kristian Jeremiassen, Siumut</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>14 Mar</bold>ch <bold>2012</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">What will Naalakkersuisut do about the growing problem of drug addiction? It has emerged that when registering births over the course of 4 months, it has been recorded that 15% of women giving birth have been users of hashish and that the newborns have had to be observed in the intensive care unit.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siverth K. Heilmann &amp; Knud Kristiansen, Atassut</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>14 June 2012</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Questions to Naalakkersuisut regarding Section 3 of the Self-Government&#8217;s order no. 4 of 4 March 2011 on the sale and serving of alcoholic beverages in Kommuneqarfik Sermersooq, which prohibits the sale and serving of beer in certain towns and villageson 1 June.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Justus Hansen, Demokraatit</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>12 April 2013</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">What ideas does Naalakkersuisut have in relation to the future efforts regarding treatment for alcohol and drug addiction?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agathe Fontain, IA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>28</bold> A<bold>ugust 2013</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Questions for Naalakkersuisut regarding the child and family area and alcohol policy in Tasiilaq</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Justus Hansen, Demokraatit</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>26 June 2015</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Question to Naalakkersuisut about money laundering</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tillie Martinussen, Demokraatit</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>25 February 2016</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Are there figures on the number of people born with fetal alcohol syndrome in Greenland?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Laura T&#224;un&#226;jik, Siumut</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>12 April 2016</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">How many &#8220;dropped out&#8221; of educational institutions because of drug abuse?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suka K Frederiksen, Siumut</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8 May 2016</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Does Naalakkersuisut have plans to establish an addiction centre on the East Coast?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Laura T&#224;un&#226;jik, Siumut</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>As can be seen from <xref rid="table1-14550725241276306" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref> and <xref rid="table2-14550725241276306" ref-type="table">2</xref>, between 2010 and 2016 there were 11 items on the parliament agenda proposing debate, resolutions, decisions and/or mandating initiatives, and 15 Paragraph 37 questions for the Minister/government related to the misuse of alcohol, cannabis, abuse and/or treatment. Few of the items and questions were directly related to addiction treatment services, but all addressed the state of problematic use in part of the population and suggested or discussed different ways of offering prevention, regulation or treatment. Item 1 from 2009 and 2010 suggested mandating the government to establish a training programme for staff in, or relevant to, the field of addiction treatment in Greenland instead of using training programmes available in Denmark. At first, this suggestion was postponed, awaiting the conclusions of a government working group, and then rejected based on the argument that Greenlandic (social) education was to have extended the syllabus to cover more on addiction problems instead.</p><p>Several items and questions raised in the political debate concerned the legislation of sales and serving of alcohol. The legislation in Greenland had been quite strict since the 1980s to handle the high levels of alcohol intake back then. All political parties seemed to be concerned about the problematic use of alcohol and cannabis in a part of the population, but did, however, disagree on what effects to expect from changes to legislation and how legislation could be altered to improve the situation. Some parties were proponents of a more liberal legislation, arguing that strict policies would not alter the underlying problems of alcohol addiction while others wished for even stricter policies and arguing that addiction problems worsened all other problems in society.</p><p>Item 4 on the agenda in 2012 suggested an establishment of a treatment service or intervention aimed at vulnerable individuals (and families experiencing addiction problems in particular); this proposal was decided and left to the government to put into affect. The Paragraph 37 question from 12 April 2013 asked by Agathe Fontain focused on how to develop public addiction treatment services. The question addressed the current services and plans for adjustments but lacked background or justification, following the normal procedure. In the reply, the government briefly described a need for a more flexible treatment service for addiction but proposed no specific plans for changing the current treatment service. Agathe Fontain and her colleague, Mimi Karlsen, followed up on the question in the fall of 2013 with item 8 (from Agathe Fontain) and item 9 (from Mimi Karlsen); they suggested new initiatives on treatment for alcohol addiction. These items were discussed simultaneously as one item in both parliament and the parliamentary health committee. After being discussed twice by all members of parliament and considered by the parliamentary health committee, the proposal was adopted with amendments suggested by the health committee. The amendments to items 8 and 9 determined a process with a preceding analysis of the following: (1) the needs of the future treatment service; and (2) an analysis of the cost of not having a treatment service compared with the cost of establishing a treatment service, as well as a process including addictions other than just alcohol addiction. The government was supposed to develop a plan for a free national alcohol addiction treatment service. Thus, in the years after the adopted proposition in 2013, there were very few items on the agenda and even fewer Paragraph 37 questions for the government, indicating a kind of political peace or awaiting the outcome of the ongoing analysis preceding a proposal for an addiction treatment service model.</p><p>Item 10 from the agendas in 2014 and 2015 was treated twice, both by parliament and by the parliamentary health committee and finally adopted with amendments. The item required the government to present a national action plan against hashish, which was presented in 2016. This content is elaborated in the next section. Item 11 on the agenda in 2016 involved a debate on preventing problematic alcohol and cannabis use among adolescents. In addition, the three Paragraph 37 questions from 2016 addressed the impact of addictive behaviours on children and adolescents and the availability of treatment for the population living on the east coast of Greenland, highlighting uncertainties and unmet needs during the initial establishment period of the new treatment service. As can be seen in <xref rid="table1-14550725241276306" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref> and <xref rid="table2-14550725241276306" ref-type="table">2</xref>, questions and items on the agenda began to emerge again in 2016 while the establishment process was presented and initiated.</p></sec><sec id="section3B-14550725241276306"><title>Strategies and action plans for addiction problems</title><p>In <xref rid="table3-14550725241276306" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, the 11 government documents identified regarding addiction problems are presented and all reflect work within action plans, strategies and prevention work about addiction problems in society.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table3-14550725241276306" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Government.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_14550725241276306-table3.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Year</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Title</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2010</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Violence and alcohol-related injuries treated in the Greenlandic healthcare system</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2011</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time for a change of attitude &#8211; Status report after three seminar days on alcohol in Nuuk 2011</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2011</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mid-term evaluation of the public health programme Inuuneritta</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2012</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Statement report: future alcohol treatment services</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2012</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inuuneritta II: Naalakkersuisut&#8217;s strategies and goals for public health 2013</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2013</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Action plan for the alcohol sector in Greenland 2013&#8211;2019</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2013</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Report: Theme day on cannabis</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2015</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Addiction treatment, needs and societal benefits</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2015</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Costs of abuse problems in Greenland</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2015</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposal for a national plan for future substance abuse treatment</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2016</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">National action plan against cannabis</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>In 2010, the government published a report on violence and alcohol-related injuries treated in the Greenlandic healthcare system. The findings, analysis and conclusions from the report were also presented in a scientific peer-reviewed article (<xref rid="bibr40-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Nex&#248;e et al., 2013</xref>), describing how violence and alcohol-related injuries put a considerable strain on the healthcare system as at least 10% of emergency visits were due to alcohol intoxication. In 2011, the government invited an interdisciplinary group of professionals to participate in a thematic meeting on alcohol. The presentations, discussions and recommendations from this meeting were presented in a report with the title &#8216;Time for attitude change&#8217; (<xref rid="bibr20-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Departement for Sundhed, 2011</xref>). The 2012 statement report on future alcohol treatment services described how the structural reform (concerning the number of municipalities and their responsibilities) in 2009 was also intended to include a redistribution of the responsibility of addiction treatment from government to the five new municipalities, as the prior municipalities had wished for local treatment options. However, this work was postponed until 2010 when it was decided that members of the government and the municipalities should develop a proposal for the future services of addiction treatment; the 2012 statement report was the result of this work. The suggestions in the statement report did not alter the structure of the service but recommended a development of the treatment of addiction service based on evidence-based treatment methods, better and more uniform referral practice, establishment of an outreach team of counsellors to provide local treatment in the small living areas and the establishment of local, specialty services aimed at people with addiction problems, mental illness and social problems.</p><p>In 2013, the government presented an action plan for addressing alcohol-related issues. The action plan was presented together with the national public health strategy, Inuuneritta II (<xref rid="bibr21-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Departement for Sundhed, 2012</xref>), by the Ministry for Health and had 11 sub-goals closely connected to the goals of Inuuneritta II, with the overall aim of increasing the quality of life for the population. The action plan and Inuuneritta II both focused on primary prevention, healthy lives and well-being for the population; in particular, it focused on children and families. Inuuneritta II was built on the recommendations from the 2011 publication, mid-term evaluation of Inuuneritta, which was also the only document identified that evaluated previous work or initiatives. As part of the Inunneritta II strategy, four pamphlets were published and distributed to schools, providing information for teachers and parents on how to protect children and adolescents from the misuse of alcohol, drugs, and tobacco.</p><p>The mandated analysis after the adoption of items 8 and 9 on the parliamentary agenda in 2013 resulted in three reports: (1) Addiction treatment: needs and societal winnings (Departementet for Sundhed og Infrastruktur, 2014); (2) Costs of addiction in Greenland (<xref rid="bibr22-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Departement for Sundhed, 2015</xref>); and (3) Proposal for the future national addiction treatment services (<xref rid="bibr25-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Departement for Sundhed og Infrastruktur, 2015</xref>), all presented in 2015. In the report on needs and societal winnings, the background information was very much reliant on the national population health surveys, surveys on health behaviours in schoolchildren, the available literature and a statistical summary of the patients treated for addiction treatment with government support for the year 2013. The report estimated that approximately half the population might have a harmful use of alcohol and that far more men than women were at risk (Departementet for Sundhed og Infrastruktur, 2014). The report also identified a significant negative social impact of addictive behaviours, noting that individuals with fewer resources tended to have a higher proportion of addiction problems. Among those receiving addiction treatment, only 2.5% had not experienced addiction problems in their childhood home (ibid). Very importantly, the report concluded that there still seemed to be a mismatch between the allocated resources to addiction treatment and the need for treatment, resulting in the majority of individuals being unable to access necessary interventions for their addiction problems. The report on the cost of addiction and harmful use of alcohol estimated that between 271 and 338 million DKK each year were attributable to addiction (<xref rid="bibr22-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Departement for Sundhed, 2015</xref>). This estimate included direct costs from healthcare, social services, wage loss and crime; however, it was not possible to include indirect costs, e.g., missed opportunities in education. The cost of extra services in schools, such as special teaching and guidance related to addiction, were not included but were estimated to be 4&#8211;8 million DKK a year. At the time of the report, the gross domestic product (GDP) of Greenland was 13.8 billion DKK; thus, the costs of addiction were assessed at being a minimum of 2% of the GDP (ibid).</p><p>The proposal for the future national addiction treatment service (<xref rid="bibr25-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Departement for Sundhed og Infrastruktur, 2015</xref>) was distributed to all members of parliament in the fall of 2015. It was subsequently included (without further political discussion) in the Finance Act negotiations, where it received the necessary funding and went into effect from 2016 onwards. The plan described an addiction treatment service directed at different age and target groups and was based on available evidence and best practice. The service was meant to include a central knowledge and management centre, local treatment centres in each municipality and outreach counsellors to provide treatment to smaller cities and villages. It was suggested that the service involve a stepped care model, which involves an evidence-based approach offering the least invasive yet effective treatment options as soon as possible. The steps in a stepped care model should increase the efforts as the severity of the problem rises (<xref rid="bibr41-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">NICE, 2011</xref>). The proposed stepped care model in this case involved the following steps:
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>Step 1: Information about the service</p></list-item><list-item><p>Step 2: Self-help materials, e.g., self-screening tests</p></list-item><list-item><p>Step 3: Motivational interviewing (for all with addiction problems and some as the only service)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Step 4: Outpatient treatment service or short treatment courses of 1 week with a traveling counsellor in smaller cities or with well-functioning people in bigger cities</p></list-item><list-item><p>Step 5: Day treatment locally and regionally for people with more support and complex needs</p></list-item><list-item><p>Step 6: Day treatment in combination with social/educational service for, e.g., pregnant families with addiction problems</p></list-item><list-item><p>Step 7: Specialised treatment services for children, adolescents and adults with mental disorders</p></list-item></list>In 2015, when the report was presented, only step 5 in the proposal existed. Step 5 was at that time delivered by a private provider, hired by the government, and consequently, everything else in the stepped care model had to be developed and implemented. The plan also described how all people seeking treatment should be offered motivational interviewing (<xref rid="bibr39-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Miller, 1983</xref>) as well as a being assessed by means of the Addiction Severity Index (<xref rid="bibr37-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">McLellan et al., 1992</xref>). The proposed service also contained several key elements to ensure successful outcomes for the people in treatment: the first element was a close collaboration between the healthcare system and social services. Additional elements were dissemination of information aimed at the general population and target groups, multidimensional assessment of all people in treatment, a carefully planned and structured follow-up procedure, action plans resolving the problems of individuals identified through the initial assessment, multidimensional treatment services and aftercare, self-help groups, a national addiction database collecting the information on the service allowing for quality assurance and development, and finally a training programme for the counsellors who delivered the new treatment services.</p><p>In 2016, a national action plan for the prevention of cannabis use was presented by the government. This plan was a result of the adoption of another political point from the agenda: item 10 in 2014. It also presented a broad range of prevention initiatives, including those involving the new treatment service, thereby supplementing the plan for providing addiction treatment.</p></sec><sec id="section3C-14550725241276306"><title>Mapping of addiction problems in the population</title><p>As can be seen in <xref rid="table4-14550725241276306" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, 13 scientific documents were identified in the period 2010&#8211;2016; these were mostly related to mapping (general health and) the extent of addiction problems in Greenland.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table4-14550725241276306" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Academia.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_14550725241276306-table4.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Author</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Year</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Title</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Type</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Published by:</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niclasen &amp; Bjerregaard</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public health among school children &#8211; results from the HBSC Greenland survey 2010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Report</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">National Institute of Public Health, SDU</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bjerregaard et al<bold>.</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inuit Health in Transition &#8211; Greenland survey 2005&#8211;2009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Report</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">National Institute of Public Health, SDU</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bjerregaard et al<bold>.</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The health survey in Avanersuaq 2010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Report</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">National Institute of Public Health, SDU</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aage et al<bold>.</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol in Greenland 1951&#8211;2010: consumption, mortality, prices</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Journal article</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Circumpolar Health</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lavik et al<bold>.</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinking patterns and biochemical signs of alcoholic liver disease in Danish and Greenlandic patients with alcohol addiction</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Journal article</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Circumpolar Health</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pedersen et al<bold>.</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wellbeing among youth in Greenland 2011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Report</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">National Institute of Public Health, SDU</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poulsen, B K.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol in Greenland &#8211; a history of obligations, prohibitions, and discrimination</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Journal article</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Greenlandic cultural and social research</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Becker &amp; Bjerregaard</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Validation of survey information on smoking and alcohol consumption against import statistics, Greenland 1993&#8211;2010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Journal article</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Circumpolar Health</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Larsen et al.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gambling behavior and problem gambling reflecting social transition and traumatic childhood events among Greenland Inuit: a cross-sectional study in a large indigenous population undergoing rapid change</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Journal article</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">J Gambl Stud</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Larsen et al.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Harmful alcohol use and frequent use of marijuana among lifetime problem gamblers and the prevalence of cross-addictive behavior among Greenland Inuit: evidence from the cross-sectional Inuit Health in Transition Greenland survey 2006&#8211;2010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Journal article</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Circumpolar Health</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nex&#248;e et al<bold>.</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Violence- and alcohol-related acute healthcare visits in Greenland</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Journal article</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Scandinavian Journal of Public Health</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bjerregaard et al<bold>.</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genetic variation in alcohol metabolising enzymes among Inuit and its relation to drinking patterns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Journal article</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Drug Alcohol Depend</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B. Niclasen</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Well-being and health among primary school students in Greenland &#8211; results from the HBSC Greenland survey 2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Report</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">National Institute of Public Health, SDU</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bjerregaard &amp; Larsen</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health Aspects of Colonisation and the Post-Colonial Period in Greenland 1721 to 2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Journal article</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Journal of Northen Studies</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dahl-Petersen et al<bold>.</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population survey in Greenland 2014: living conditions, lifestyle, and health&#8201;=&#8201;Kalaallit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Report</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">National Institute of Public Health, SDU</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rex et al<bold>.</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver biochemistry and associations with alcohol intake, hepatitis B virus infection and Inuit ethnicity: a population-based comparative epidemiological survey in Greenland and Denmark</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Journal article</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Circumpolar Health</italic>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The scientific documents identified were almost all written by or in collaboration with the Center for Public Health in Greenland, National Institute of Public Health, University of Southern Denmark and relied mostly on data gathered in the National Population Health Surveys or the Health Behavior in School Children (HBSC). All documents displayed the significant proportion of addictive behaviours in the society. In the population health surveys (<xref rid="bibr6-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Becker &amp; Ulrik, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bibr8-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Bjerregaard &amp; Aidt, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bibr11-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Bjerregaard &amp; Dahl-Petersen, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bibr9-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Bjerregaard et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bibr44-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Pedersen &amp; Bjerregaard, 2012</xref>), many aspects of health were investigated, and alcohol intake levels were reported in each of them. In the latest survey, 8.8% of participants exceeded the recommended level of alcohol intake in a week (seven for women and 14 for men) and approximately 10% had a harmful use or depended use of alcohol (<xref rid="bibr34-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Larsen et al., 2018</xref>); however, the biggest concern was binge-drinking, as 34% reported to binge-drink in 2018 (ibid) and approximately 40%&#8211;50% of participants reported to binge-drink at least once a month in previous surveys (<xref rid="bibr18-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Dahl-Petersen et al., 2016</xref>). Aage investigated the alcohol intake levels from the 1950s and the related mortality and found an increasing trend of alcohol intake from the 1950s until the peak level in around 1987, whereafter the intake decreased. Aage also found that the mortality rate followed the intake pattern and the levels of alcohol-related liver disease mortality were lower than expected (<xref rid="bibr1-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Aage, 2012</xref>). Lavik and colleagues and Rex and colleagues also investigated liver disease in individuals with alcohol addiction problems in Greenland and Denmark; both found low levels of liver disease in Inuit (<xref rid="bibr35-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Lavik et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bibr47-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Rex et al., 2016</xref>). The study by Lavik et al. was the only one related to addiction treatment services as the investigated population were patients in treatment. Becker and Bjerregaard found a significant underreporting of alcohol intake in surveys compared to import statistics (<xref rid="bibr6-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Becker &amp; Ulrik, 2013</xref>). Larsen and colleagues investigated gambling behaviour and found gambling behaviour to be associated with adverse childhood experiences, and harmful use of alcohol and cannabis (<xref rid="bibr32-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Larsen et al., 2013a</xref>, <xref rid="bibr33-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">2013b</xref>). Nex&#248;e and colleagues (<xref rid="bibr40-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Nex&#248;e et al., 2013</xref>) described how alcohol-related injuries caused a high need for other types of healthcare treatment in the emergency wards. Bjerregaard and colleagues (<xref rid="bibr15-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Bjerregaard et al., 2014</xref>) investigated genetic variation in alcohol metabolising enzymes and found a genotype that is protective against heavy drinking among the Inuit. Finally, Bjerregaard and Larsen also investigated health aspects of Greenland's colonial history and found that mental health, addiction and suicide problems were related to the colonial history of Greenland (<xref rid="bibr12-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Bjerregaard &amp; Larsen, 2016</xref>). The HBSC surveys have been carried out regularly in Greenland since 1994 and have investigated the health, behaviour and well-being in children from the 5th grade to the 10th grade in randomised samples of all schools in Greenland. The 2016 report found a decrease in alcohol intake and a later onset of alcohol intake; however, cannabis was used by 27% of the group aged 15&#8211;17 years (<italic toggle="yes">Trivsel og sundhed blandt folkeskoleelever i Gr&#248;nland : resultater fra skoleb&#248;rnsunders&#248;gelsen</italic>
<xref rid="bibr53-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr"><italic toggle="yes">HBSC reenland i 2014</italic>, 2015</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section4-14550725241276306"><title>Discussion</title><p>The reviewed documents in the present study highlight significant attention from researchers, government and politicians towards the problematic use of alcohol, other substances and addictive behaviours in Greenlandic society. The political documents demonstrated a strong and continued interest in addiction problems over the years; however, despite numerous discussions, only a few solutions were proposed. Although there was overall high interest and concern about addiction problems, an analysis of the political documents identified two more dominant opposing sides of the debate. Siumut, the largest political party in parliament, was concerned with addiction problems but did not take a firm standpoint. Rather, the party&#8217;s position was inconclusive, as their proposals and questions veered in many directions, addressing both the prohibition and expansion of sales hours for alcohol as well as early intervention for vulnerable groups. One side &#8211; led by the parties Atassut and Demokratiit &#8211; was concerned with addiction problems but believed that strict legislation had not resolved the underlying problems causing addiction. They argued for a more liberal approach to the legislation of alcohol sales and service. The opposing side &#8211; mainly led by the party IA &#8211; argued for stricter policies and the acknowledgement of addiction problems as diseases that should be dealt with through treatment service, positioning it as a government responsibility. Agatha Fontain and Mimi Karlsen, both from IA, were central figures in the debate. Before the election in April 2013, they were both members of government and hosted conferences and meetings about addiction problems; however, as shown in the analysis, they were not otherwise active in presenting new initiatives for the prevention or treatment of addiction problems. After the election in 2014 when they were no longer in government, it seemed that they seized the opportunity to propose a radical change to the treatment system.</p><p>The present review and analysis demonstrated that the government's efforts in the field were significantly determined by the adoption of items from the parliamentary agenda. For a long time, the government focus was on primary prevention initiatives and information campaigns rather than on structural changes or treatment of addiction problems. Thus, the governments seemed more engaged in the promotion of healthy lives to prevent people from developing addictive behaviours than on initiating or restructuring (more expensive) treatment of addiction problems. This could be the result of changing government and their shifting agendas; however, the responsibility for primary prevention work was largely centred in the Department of Health while the scope of prevention seemed to depend on progress in other areas, such as education, employment and housing (<xref rid="bibr14-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Bjerregaard et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bibr12-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Bjerregaard &amp; Larsen, 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bibr13-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; <xref rid="bibr33-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Larsen et al., 2013b</xref>; <xref rid="bibr51-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Seidler et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p>Among the identified documents, only one tried to assess the effects or impact of an initiative: the mid-term evaluation on the public health programme Inuuneritta in 2011. This evaluation stands out as a rare instance of assessing the outcomes of an initiative within the collected literature. The scarcity of impact assessments is notable when considering the extensive number of meetings, discussions and monitoring studies conducted over the span of 6 years. This discrepancy underscores the need for more comprehensive evaluations to gauge the effectiveness and real-world impact of initiatives aimed at addressing societal issues, such as addiction and public health, within Greenlandic context. In Denmark, the obligation to offer treatment for alcohol addiction to citizens has shifted across different administrations over time; however, this responsibility was not included in the 1992 handover of the Greenlandic healthcare system from Denmark to Greenland. As a result, the initiation and management of alcohol addiction treatment were left to the Greenlandic authorities. Previous addiction treatment in Greenland was heavily linked to private treatment initiatives in Denmark, with both collaborations and education of treatment counsellors in Denmark. This treatment largely followed the 12-step model of addiction treatment (<xref rid="bibr43-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Niclasen &amp; Poulsen, 2020</xref>). Although studies from northern Norway with Sami people (<xref rid="bibr38-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Mehus et al., 2019</xref>) and studies of Greenlanders in Denmark (<xref rid="bibr26-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Edwards et al., 2019</xref>) provide evidence that cultural safe practice have a positive impact on health, the documents in the present review revealed no significant interest in developing culturally adjusted addiction treatment in Greenland but seemed more concerned with monitoring and regulating the situation. In Alaska, a focus on addiction problems and suicide resulted in a collaboration between academia and native communities on the development of solutions to the health disparities (<xref rid="bibr3-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Allen et al., 2014</xref>). The Greenlandic process was quite different and could be related to the fact that while Greenlanders in Denmark, Sami in Norway and Alaska Natives in Alaska were all minority parts of the population, the Greenlanders were by far the majority of the population in Greenland itself. It could also be related to the transition process from colony to home rule, where decades were spent creating equal welfare opportunities in Greenland to those in Denmark (<xref rid="bibr7-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Beukel et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bibr49-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">Rud, 2014</xref>, <xref rid="bibr50-14550725241276306" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) and thus the foundation of the Greenlandic government and welfare system were based on Danish practices.</p><p>The present study describes the processes that led to the establishment of the current national addiction treatment service in Greenland. The inclusion of parliamentary debates and governmental reports and documents provide a broad perspective of the incentives behind establishing a new service, an insight that a search limited to scientific literature would not have provided. The scientific literature and much of the background material for the governmental documents (such as reports) relied on the national population health surveys conducted by the National Institute for Health, providing a rather limited perspective being the only source of information and performed by primarily Danish researchers. On the other hand, the population health surveys have been conducted regularly and over many years; they are thorough and methodologically sound; thus, data from the surveys can be considered reliable.</p><p>The extent to which the current strategy for addiction treatment delivery has succeeded and been implemented, and whether it has led to the expected improvements and results, needs to be investigated further. This will be the next step in the present study.</p></sec><sec id="section5-14550725241276306"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Across the three identified themes &#8211; the national debate, the strategies and action plans, and the mapping of addiction problems &#8211; it became evident that addiction issues held significant societal importance in Greenland. While numerous documents related to monitoring, debates, strategies and regulatory measures were found, very few focused specifically on addiction treatment. The academic documents have only focused on monitoring and the government documents were mainly mandated work from parliament.</p><p>Our analysis highlighted three key documents central to understanding the path towards a new national addiction treatment service. First, a 2012 statement report outlined the transfer of addiction treatment service responsibility to the municipalities in 2010, underscoring the subsequent ineffectiveness in addressing addiction problems. In 2013, Agathe Fontain (IA) raised a Paragraph 37 question highlighting a lack of progress. Later that same year, Agathe Fontain and her colleague Mimi Karlsen (IA) proposed two parliamentary agenda items mandating the government to develop a plan for a new addiction treatment service, provided free of charge and accessible to a larger segment of the population.</p><p>These parliamentary actions ultimately led to the implementation of the new service. The identified documents collectively highlight the challenges faced in addiction treatment, the acknowledgment of addiction problems as persistent issues within the Greenlandic society, and the essential steps taken to address these concerns through policy and legislative actions. This study thus informs future studies on addiction treatment in Greenland by situating the historical context of the changes that occurred with the introduction of Allorfik.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to thank the reviewers for a very helpful review process.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The author declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Julie Flyger Holflod <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0009-0008-1120-8591" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0009-0008-1120-8591</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><notes><fn-group><fn id="fn1-14550725241276306"><label>1.</label><p>A question about a public matter put forward by a Member of parliament to a minister/government, where there is a time limit of 10 workdays for the minister/government to answer the question. Normal procedure proscribes that the members of parliament provide a background for their concern when asking this type of question to government.</p></fn></fn-group></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aage</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Alcohol in Greenland 1951&#8211;2010: consumption, mortality, prices</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Circumpolar Health</source>, <volume>71</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/ijch.v71i0.18444</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3525923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23256091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levintova</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohatt</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Suicide and alcohol-related disorders in the U.S. Arctic: Boosting research to address a primary determinant of health disparities</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Circumpolar Health</source>, <volume>70</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>473</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>487</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/ijch.v70i5.17847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22067096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3249490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohatt</surname><given-names>G. V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beehler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>People awakening: Collaborative research to develop cultural strategies for prevention in community intervention</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Community Psychology</source>, <volume>54</volume>(<issue>1&#8211;2</issue>), <fpage>100</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>111</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10464-014-9647-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24903819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4119558</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <comment>Gr&#248;nland : m&#230;gtig og afm&#230;gtig. Retrieved from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://nota.dk/bibliotek/bogid/708237" ext-link-type="uri">https://nota.dk/bibliotek/bogid/708237</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arksey</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Malley</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Scoping studies: Towards a methodological framework</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Social Research Methodology</source>, <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>19</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1364557032000119616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>P. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulrik</surname></name></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <comment>Validation of survey information on smoking and alcohol consumption against import statistics, Greenland 1993&#8211;2010. </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/ijch.v72i0.20314</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beukel</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>F. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rytter</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Afvikling af Gr&#248;nlands kolonistatus 1945-54 &#8211; En historisk udredning.[Settlement of Greenland's colonial status 1945-54 &#8211; A historical investigation.]</source>. <publisher-name>Dansk Institut for Internationale Studier [Danish Institute of International Studies]</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjerregaard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aidt</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Levevilk&#229;r, livsstil og helbred : befolkningsunders&#248;gelsen i Gr&#248;nland 2005-2009 = Atugassarititat, inooriaaseq peqqinnerlu [Living conditions, lifestyle and health in Greenland &#8211; the Population Health Survey in Greenland 2005-2009]</source>. <publisher-name>Statens Institut for Folkesundhed, Naalakkersuisut</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjerregaard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borch-Johnsen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mulvad</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Backer</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Inuit health in Greenland: A population survey of life style and disease in Greenland and among Inuit living in Denmark</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Circumpolar Health</source>, <volume>62</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>), <fpage>3</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>79</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/ijch.v62i0.18212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14527126</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjerregaard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dahl-Petersen</surname><given-names>I. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, &amp; <collab>Statens Institut for, F.</collab> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Befolkningsunders&#248;gelsen i Gr&#248;nland 2005-2007 : levevilk&#229;r, livsstil og helbred [The Population Health Survey 2014]</source>. <publisher-name>Statens Institut for Folkesundhed</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjerregaard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dahl-Petersen</surname><given-names>I. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <source>Sundhedsunders&#248;gelsen i Avanersuaq 2010 = Avanersuarmiut peqqissusaannik misissuineq [The health survey in Avanersuaq 2010]</source>. <publisher-name>Statens Institut for Folkesundhed</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjerregaard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>C. V. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Health aspects of colonization and the post-colonial period in Greenland 1721 to 2014</article-title>. <source>Journal of Northen Studies</source>, <volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), 285&#8211;106. <comment>https://doi.org/10.36368/jns.v10i2.848</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjerregaard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>C. V. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Three lifestyle-related issues of major significance for public health among the Inuit in contemporary Greenland: A review of adverse childhood conditions, obesity, and smoking in a period of social transition</article-title>. <source>Public Health Reviews</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40985-018-0085-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29692943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5901873</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjerregaard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#248;rensen</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolstrup</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Alcohol in Greenland 1950-2018: Consumption, drinking patterns, and consequences</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Circumpolar Health</source>, <volume>79</volume>, <fpage>1814550</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/22423982.2020.1814550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32866078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7480488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjerregaard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikkelsen</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolstrup</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Genetic variation in alcohol metabolizing enzymes among Inuit and its relation to drinking patterns</article-title>. <source>Drug and Alcohol Dependence</source>, <volume>144</volume>, <fpage>239</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>244</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2014.09.774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25311581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Document analysis as a qualitative research method</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Research Journal</source>, <volume>9</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>27</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3316/QRJ0902027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeburn</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conigrave</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Mind the gap: What is the difference between alcohol treatment need and access for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Australians?</article-title><source>Drug and Alcohol Review</source>, <volume>35</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>456</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>460</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/dar.12313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26331675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dahl-Petersen</surname><given-names>I. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>C. V. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>N. O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>J&#248;rgensen</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjerregaard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <comment><italic toggle="yes">Befolkningsunders&#248;gelsen i Gr&#248;nland 2014/Kalaallit Nunaanni Innuttaasut Peqqissusaannik Misissuisitsineq 2014: Levevilk&#229;r, livsstil og helbred/Inuunermi atugassarititaasut, inooriaaseq peqqissuserlu</italic> [The Population Health Survey 2014] (87-7899-312-1, 978-87-7899-312-0). Retrieved from</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Identity, urbanization and political demography in Greenland</article-title>. <source>Acta Borealia</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>125</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>140</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08003831.2010.527528</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Departement for Sundhed</collab>. (<year>2011</year>). <comment><italic toggle="yes">Tid til holdnings&#230;ndring - statusrapport efter tre seminardage om alkohol i Nuuk</italic> 2011 [Time for a Change of Attitude - Status Report After Three Seminar Days on Alcohol in Nuuk 2011]. Retrieved from Nuuk</comment>:</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Departement for Sundhed</collab>. (<year>2012</year>). <comment><italic toggle="yes">Inuuneritta 2 - Naalakkersuisuts strategier og m&#229;ls&#230;tning for folkesundheden 2013-</italic>2019 [Inuuneritta 2 - The Government of Greenlands Strategy and Aims for the Public Health 2013-2019]. Nuuk, Greenland</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Departement for Sundhed</collab> (<year>2015</year>). <comment><italic toggle="yes">Omkostninger til misbrug i Gr&#248;nland</italic> [Costs Attributable to Addictions in Greenland]. Retrieved from Nuuk, Greenland</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Departement for Sundhed</collab> (<year>2020</year>). <comment><italic toggle="yes">Inuuneritta 3. Naalakkersuisuts strategi for samarbejdet om det gode b&#248;rneliv 2020-</italic>2030 [Inuuneritta 3 - The Government of Greenlands Strategy for Cooperation on the Good Life of Children 2020-2030]. Retrieved from Nuuk, Greenland</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Departement for Sundhed og Infrastruktur</collab>. (<year>2014</year>). <comment><italic toggle="yes">Misbrugsbehandlig, behov og samfundsm&#230;ssige gevinster</italic> [Addiction Treatment - Needs and the Societal Impact]. Retrieved from Greenland</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Departement for Sundhed og Infrastruktur</collab>. (<year>2015</year>). <comment><italic toggle="yes">Forslag til national plan for fremtidens misbrugsbehandling</italic> [Proposal For a National Plan for Future Substance Abuse Treatment]. Retrieved from Nuuk</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Val&#233;ria Montes D&#8217;Oco</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melaku Tefera</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krogh Kj&#230;r-RasmussenEdwards</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Towards indigenous social work practice: Addressing professional challenges in working with homeless Greenlanders in Aalborg, Denmark</article-title>. <source>Journal of Indigenous Social Development</source>, <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>19</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flyger</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niclasen</surname><given-names>B. V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Does establishing local treatment institutions lead to different populations seeking treatment among Greenlandic Inuit?</article-title><source>Nordic Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08039488.2019.1696887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31829764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cartwright</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stearne</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saggers</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkes</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <comment>Review of the harmful use of alcohol among Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander people - Publications - Alcohol and Other Drugs Knowledge Centre. Retrieved from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://aodknowledgecentre.ecu.edu.au/key-resources/publications/34063/?title=Review%20of%20the%20harmful%20use%20of%20alcohol%20among%20Aboriginal%20and%20Torres%20Strait%20Islander%20people" ext-link-type="uri">https://aodknowledgecentre.ecu.edu.au/key-resources/publications/34063/?title=Review%20of%20the%20harmful%20use%20of%20alcohol%20among%20Aboriginal%20and%20Torres%20Strait%20Islander%20people</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Gr&#248;nlands Politi</collab>. (<year>2023</year>). <comment><italic toggle="yes">&#197;rsstatistik</italic> 2022 [2022 Statistics]. Retrieved from Nuuk</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Alcoholics Anonymous and 12-Step Alcoholism Treatment Programs</article-title>. In: M. Galanter &amp; L. A. Kaskutas (Eds.), <source>Recent developments in alcoholism</source><comment>(vol 16). Springer. </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/0-306-47939-7_12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12638636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Inatsisartut</collab>. (<year>1994</year>). <comment><italic toggle="yes">Bet&#230;nkning afgivet af socialudvalget</italic>. [Report Submitted by the Social Committee]. Nuuk Retrieved from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ina.gl/glsamlinger/samlinger/EM-1994/dagsordenens%20punkt%2061-1-1.htm" ext-link-type="uri">https://ina.gl/glsamlinger/samlinger/EM-1994/dagsordenens%20punkt%2061-1-1.htm</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>C. V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjerregaard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<comment>2013a</comment>). <article-title>Gambling behavior and problem gambling reflecting social transition and traumatic childhood events among Greenland Inuit: A cross-sectional study in a large indigenous population undergoing rapid change</article-title>. <source>Journal of Gambling Studies</source>, <volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>733</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>748</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10899-012-9337-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23065180</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>C. V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjerregaard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<comment>2013b</comment>). <article-title>Harmful alcohol use and frequent use of marijuana among lifetime problem gamblers and the prevalence of cross-addictive behaviour among Greenland Inuit: Evidence from the cross-sectional Inuit health in transition Greenland survey 2006-2010</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Circumpolar Health</source>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>19551</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/ijch.v72i0.19551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23515920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3600424</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>C. V. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingemann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>J&#248;rgensen</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olesen</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#248;rensen</surname><given-names>I. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Backer</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjerregaard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <comment><italic toggle="yes">Befolkningsunders&#248;gelsen i Gr&#248;nland 2018. Levevilk&#229;r, livsstil og helbred - oversigt over indikatorer for folkesundheden [Population survey in Greenland 2018. Living conditions, lifestyle and health - overview of indicators for public health]</italic> [The Population Health Survey in Greenland 2018]. Retrieved from</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr35-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavik</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holmegaard</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Drinking patterns and biochemical signs of alcoholic liver disease in Danish and Greenlandic patients with alcohol addiction</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Circumpolar Health</source>, <volume>65</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>219</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>227</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/ijch.v65i3.18103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16871828</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr36-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K. S. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conigrave</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayman</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Ansari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Room</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callinan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chikritzhs</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slade</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conigrave</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Patterns of drinking in Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander peoples as self-reported on the grog survey app: A stratified sample</article-title>. <source>BMC medical Informatics and Decision Making</source>, <volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>180</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>180</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12911-019-0879-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31488135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6729068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr37-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McLellan</surname><given-names>A. T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kushner</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metzger</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grissom</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pettinati</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Argeriou</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>The fifth edition of the addiction severity Index</article-title>. <source>Journal of Substance Abuse Treatment</source>, <volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>199</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>213</lpage>. <comment>Retrieved from </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0740-5472(92)90062-S</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1334156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr38-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehus</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bongo</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engnes</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moffitt</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Exploring why and how encounters with the Norwegian health-care system can be considered culturally unsafe by North Sami-speaking patients and relatives: A qualitative study based on 11 interviews</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Circumpolar Health</source>, <volume>78</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1612703</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/22423982.2019.1612703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31072273</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6522960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr39-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Motivational interviewing with problem drinkers</article-title>. <source>Behavioural Psychotherapy</source>, <volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>147</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>172</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0141347300006583</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr40-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nex&#248;e</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilche</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niclasen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjeldsen</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>F&#230;rgemann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munck</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lauritsen</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Violence- and alcohol-related acute healthcare visits in Greenland</article-title>. <source>Scandinavian Journal of Public Health</source>, <volume>41</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>113</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>118</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1403494812469852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23242207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr41-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>NICE</collab>. (<year>2011</year>). <comment><italic toggle="yes">Common mental health problems: identification and pathways to care</italic>. Retrieved from National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr42-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niclasen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mulvad</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Health care and health care delivery in Greenland</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Circumpolar Health</source>, <volume>69</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>437</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>447</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/ijch.v69i5.17691</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21118636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr43-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niclasen</surname><given-names>B. V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poulsen</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <part-title>Rusmidler i en gr&#248;nlandsk sammenh&#230;ng - historie, forebyggelse og behandling[drugs in a greenlandic context - history, prevention and treatment]</part-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aagard</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hounsgaard</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (Eds.), <source>Menneske: Sundhed, samfund og kultur</source> (pp. <fpage>235</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>262</lpage>). <publisher-name>Klim</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr44-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjerregaard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <source>Det sv&#230;re ungdomsliv : unges trivsel i Gr&#248;nland 2011 : en unders&#248;gelse om de &#230;ldste folkeskoleelever = Inuusuttuuneq nalorninartulik : Kalaallit Nunaanni inuusuttut akornanni atugarissaarneq pillugu meeqqat atuarfianni atuartut angajulliit akornanni 2011-mi misissuisitsineq[The Difficult Youth Life: Young People's Well-Being in Greenland 2011: a Study on the Oldest Primary School Pupilsa Study on the Oldest Primary School Pupils]</source>. <publisher-name>Statens Institut for Folkesundhed. Naalakkersuisut</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr45-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poulsen</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <part-title>Alkoholens historie - en historie om p&#229;bud, forbud og forskelsbehandling[the history of alcohol - a story about obligations, prohibitions and discrimination]</part-title>. In <source>Gr&#248;nlandsk kultur- og samfundsforskning</source> (pp. <fpage>173</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>195</lpage>). <publisher-name>Ilisimatusarfik/Forlaget Atuagkat</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr46-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Press</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <comment>Greenland&#8217;s leftwing anti-mine party wins snap election. <italic toggle="yes">The Guardian</italic>. Retrieved from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2021/apr/07/greenlands-left-wing-anti-mine-party-wins-snap-election" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.theguardian.com/world/2021/apr/07/greenlands-left-wing-anti-mine-party-wins-snap-election</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr47-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rex</surname><given-names>K. F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krarup</surname><given-names>H. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laurberg</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Liver biochemistry and associations with alcohol intake, hepatitis B virus infection and Inuit ethnicity: A population-based comparative epidemiological survey in Greenland and Denmark</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Circumpolar Health</source>, <volume>75</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>29528</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/ijch.v75.29528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26928535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4772703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr48-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenqvist</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Sk&#229;l f&#246;r friheten. Alkoholbruk och-politik i sj&#228;lvstyrande gr&#246;nland. [A toast to freedom. Alcohol use and politics in the self-governing Greenland]</article-title>. <source>Nordisk Alkohol- &amp; Narkotikatidskrift : NAT</source>, <volume>18</volume>(<issue>5-6</issue>), <fpage>475</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>488</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1455072501018005-616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr49-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Governance and tradition in nineteenth-century Greenland</article-title>. <source>Interventions</source>, <volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>551</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>571</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1369801X.2013.851827</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr50-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <source>Colonialism in Greenland: Tradition, governance and legacy</source> (<comment>1;1st 2017; ed.</comment>). <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr51-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seidler</surname><given-names>I. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thygesen</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjerregaard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>C. V. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Exploring sex-specific time trends in drinking patterns in the Greenlandic population from 1993 to 2014 &#8211; a large Arctic indigenous population</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Circumpolar Health</source>, <volume>81</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>2089379</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/22423982.2022.2089379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35698457</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9225729</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr52-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Statsministeriet</collab>. (<year>2023</year>). <comment>Gr&#248;nland. [Greenland] Retrieved from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.stm.dk/statsministeriet/rigsfaellesskabet/groenland/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.stm.dk/statsministeriet/rigsfaellesskabet/groenland/</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr53-14550725241276306"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Trivsel og sundhed blandt folkeskoleelever i Gr&#248;nland : resultater fra skoleb&#248;rnsunders&#248;gelsen HBSC reenland i</collab><year>2014</year> (2015). <source>[Health Behavior in School Children (HBSC) Greenland 2014] (B. Niclasen Ed.)</source>. <publisher-name>Statens Institut for Folkesundhed &amp; Naalakkersuisut</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>