<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Public Health Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Public Health Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2534</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jphr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PHJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Public Health Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2279-9028</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2279-9036</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10074623</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10074623.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10074623</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10074623</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37035449</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/22799036231166313</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_22799036231166313</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Fentanyl, etizolam, and beyond: A feasibility study of a community
partnership using handheld Raman spectrometry to identify substances in the
local illicit drug supply</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2930-9867</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Grover</surname><given-names initials="C">Casey</given-names></name><xref rid="corresp1-22799036231166313" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>How</surname><given-names initials="J">Justine</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Close</surname><given-names initials="R">Reb</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="aff1-22799036231166313">Community Hospital of the Monterey Peninsula,
Monterey, CA, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-22799036231166313">Casey Grover, Community Hospital of the
Monterey Peninsula, 23625 Holman Highway, Monterey, CA 93940, USA. Email:
<email>casey.grover@chomp.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">432825</issue-id><elocation-id>22799036231166313</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>02</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>06</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-04-11 04:10:11.273"><day>11</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications Ltd unless otherwise noted.
Manuscript content on this site is licensed under Creative Commons
Licenses.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which
permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work
without further permission provided the original work is attributed as
specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10.1177_22799036231166313.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="section1-22799036231166313"><title>Background:</title><p>The United States is currently experiencing an unprecedented rise in fatal
drug overdoses, which is in part due to the arrival of fentanyl, fentanyl
analogs, and other synthetic drugs into the illicit drug supply. Traditional
urine drug testing is often unable to detect fentanyl analogs and other
novel synthetic drugs, which places physicians and first responders in the
difficult position of treating patients who are intoxicated with or
overdosing on unknown substances.</p></sec><sec id="section2-22799036231166313"><title>Design and methods:</title><p>We report, as a feasibility study, the development of a novel program to use
a handheld Raman spectrometry device in our hospital&#8217;s Emergency Department
to surveil our local illicit drug supply in terms of what substances are
being sold and used.</p></sec><sec id="section3-22799036231166313"><title>Results:</title><p>Using our novel program, we were able to detect 27 substances in our illicit
drug supply over a 10 month period, including fentanyl analogues. We shared,
through our local opioid safety coalition, real-time information to first
responders, substance use treatment programs, and physicians about the novel
substances we detected using the handheld Raman spectrometer.</p></sec><sec id="section4-22799036231166313"><title>Conclusions:</title><p>A community partnership of using handheld Raman spectrometry in our
hospital&#8217;s Emergency Department was successful in providing information to
health care providers about novel substances in our illicit drug market.
Additionally, the implementation of this program improved collaboration
between local health care providers and local law enforcement.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Overdose</kwd><kwd>illicit drug supply</kwd><kwd>community partnership</kwd><kwd>Raman spectrometry</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group specific-use="FundRef"><award-group id="award1-22799036231166313"><funding-source id="funding1-22799036231166313"><institution-wrap><institution>Montage Health Foundation</institution><institution-id/></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>April-June 2023</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>typesetter</meta-name><meta-value>ts1</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="section5-22799036231166313"><title>Introduction</title><p>The United States is currently struggling with substance use and deaths from drug
overdoses at extremely high levels not seen previously in history, initially fueled
by the overprescribing of opiates by medical providers.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="bibr2-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr3-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr4-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr"/>&#8211;<xref rid="bibr5-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> 2020, a year turned upside down
by the COVID-19 pandemic, proved to be the most lethal of any year in US history
from drug overdose deaths, with 92,000 Americans dying from a drug overdose.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr6-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
</sup> While total overdose deaths are increasing, deaths from cocaine and
prescription opioids remain constant. This points toward illicit opioids being the
cause for the increased rate of deaths from drug overdose.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr7-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
</sup> Unfortunately, illicit drugs are cut with multiple substances depending on
the local illicit drug market and the availability of cutting agents. Known common
adulterants of street drugs include acetaminophen, caffeine, diphenhydramine,
methorphan, alprazolam, quetiapine, chloroquine, diltiazem, cocaine, procaine,
lidocaine, quinine, quinidine, phenacetin, thiamine, and other substances.<sup><xref rid="bibr8-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="bibr9-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr"/>&#8211;<xref rid="bibr10-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup></p><p>Digging further into the overdose deaths, 2018 data noted that 75% of opioid deaths
involved a non-methadone synthetic opioid, the most common of which was fentanyl.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr7-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
</sup> Fentanyl, due to its high potency, has proven to be easy to produce and
smuggle into the United States, saturating the illicit drug supply, and resulting in
increased overdose deaths.<sup><xref rid="bibr7-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="bibr11-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="bibr12-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Beyond fentanyl, other chemical agents are rapidly arriving in
the US illicit drug supply, such as etizolam&#8212;a benzodiazepine not legal for use in
the United States, most of which are not able to be picked up by traditional urine
drug screens.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr13-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
</sup> In summary, illicit drugs across the planet are constantly changing in terms
of what is being used and what is cut or mixed into them, and our usual methods of
drug testing are unable to detect them.<sup><xref rid="bibr7-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="bibr9-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="bibr10-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> As medical providers, it is
important to know what is in our local illicit drug supply so as to be able to know
what might be causing drug dependence or overdoses in our local patient population
as well as the appropriate treatment.</p></sec><sec id="section6-22799036231166313"><title>Design and methods</title><p>Working closely with community organizations and local law enforcement agencies, our
hospital identified a community need to be able to rapidly and safely identify which
substances are in our local illicit drug supply. Handheld Raman spectrometry has
been shown to be an accurate, rapid, and useful tool in the detection of illicit drugs.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr14-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
</sup> We identified a handheld Raman spectrometry device that could inform police,
first responders, and healthcare providers about the illicit drugs and drug
combinations being sold and used in our community and thereby help our medical
providers determine what patients have been exposed to so as to provide appropriate
treatment and prevent overdose deaths.</p><p>We hypothesized that we could develop a program to use a handheld Raman spectrometer
based in our hospital&#8217;s Emergency Department that would allow a partnership between
our hospital, our local opioid safety coalition, and the law enforcement agencies in
our County to be able to surveil what substances are in our local illicit drug
supply. We then performed a feasibility study of this hypothesis, describing how we
designed the program and its efficacy over the first 10 months of the program, and
report the results of our feasibility study in this manuscript. To the best of our
knowledge, this is the first report of using handheld Raman spectrometry in a
community partnership between healthcare providers and law enforcement as a part of
an opioid safety coalition to be able to identify new substances and adulterants in
our local illicit drug supply.</p><p>Our hospital purchased a handheld Raman spectrometer (TruNarc, Thermo Scientific,
Waltham, MA, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.thermofisher.com/order/catalog/product/TRUNARC" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.thermofisher.com/order/catalog/product/TRUNARC</ext-link>) to allow
for analysis and surveillance of the illicit street drugs and drug combinations
being sold in our community. The device can identify close to 500 chemicals in the
illicit drug supply, from opiates (including fentanyl and even more potent fentanyl
derivatives), to stimulants (including methamphetamine), to depressants (including
the new highly potent illicit benzodiazepines), to hallucinogens, as well as
precursors and fillers/cutting agents. These chemicals are all quickly able to be
identified without coming into direct contact with the substance, as the user can
scan directly through plastic bags or non-opaque glass containers to minimize
exposure. The manufacturer maintains a library of substances that can be detected by
the device, and this is updated on a regular basis by the manufacturer as new
substances are identified as potential chemicals in the illicit drug supply. The
device can analyze powders, liquids, pills, and crystals&#8212;but not organic material
such as plant matter. The manufacturer maintains the database of chemicals that can
be detected, and when an analysis is performed, if a drug of abuse is detected, the
result is shown on a screen with red background (see <xref rid="fig1-22799036231166313" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). If a common filler or cutting
agent is detected, the result is shown on a screen with an orange background to
suggest that a drug of abuse might be detected and that a repeat scan should be done
in a different area of the specimen. If the chemical or substance is not recognized,
an &#8220;inconclusive&#8221; result is given. To ensure the device is functioning correctly and
accurately, the device has a quality check function and this quality check is done
as a part of our protocol before any substance is analyzed. A photo of the device
showing the result of an analysis is shown in <xref rid="fig1-22799036231166313" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. In one preliminary study, this
device was able to detect the target drug in nearly 80% of samples with reproducible
results in approximately 85% of cases, outperforming another similar type of device.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr15-22799036231166313" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
</sup> If more than one substance is in a specimen, the device can detect multiple
substances at the same time and will display all substances detected on the screen.
However, with some specimens, such as counterfeit pills, substances are not evenly
distributed through the specimen, so performing multiple scans on a specimen in
different areas ensures that all substances in the specimen are detected.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1-22799036231166313" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Handheld mass spectrometer showing the result of an analysis.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_22799036231166313-fig1.jpg"/></fig><p>The effort to design, develop, and implement this initiative was led by a local
Emergency Physician who is the lead clinical physician in our local opioid safety
coalition. Our county has had a local opioid safety coalition since 2014 involving
local hospitals, law enforcement, substance use treatment programs, first
responders, and other community organizations. Once the device was purchased by the
hospital, multiple stakeholder meetings were held to determine how the device would
be used, monitored, and safely secured on our hospital campus. The coalition lead
physician is on the medical staff of our hospital and conducted educational
trainings on how to use the device. This physician was also responsible for
reviewing all analyses done by the device on a scheduled basis to collect and review
all available information about illicit drugs detected in our community.</p><p>We identified that there would be two ways for us to use the device to be able to
identify the substances in our local illicit drug market. First, we developed a
protocol for local law enforcement to come to the hospital campus and analyze any
drug product they had seized, with hospital security assisting officers to and from
the device. Hospital security did not use the device; they were only responsible for
supervising who used the device and had access to the device. Furthermore, the
hospital did not participate in any investigations or prosecutions. Officers simply
brought any product that they wanted to analyze to the hospital and performed an
analysis using the device. The device records information from all scans performed
in a de-identified fashion, which allowed the physician supervising the program to
review the scans on the device on a scheduled basis to review what substances had
been detected. Second, we developed a hospital protocol for how to analyze any
illicit substances (or substances suspected to be illicit) that were found to be in
a patient&#8217;s possession. The hospital, prior to this initiative, had a policy in
place that when an illicit substance (or substance suspected to be illicit) was
found on a patient&#8217;s person, the substance was confiscated and sent to the pharmacy
for destruction. Consistent with privacy laws, information that an illicit (or
suspected illicit) substance was found to be in a patient&#8217;s possession was not
shared with law enforcement or any disciplinary body. We modified this protocol so
that any illicit substance (or substance suspected to be illicit) detected on a
patient was analyzed using the handheld Raman spectrometer before being sent to the
hospital pharmacy for destruction. As with the scans performed by law enforcement,
the physician supervising the program reviewed the scans on the device on a
scheduled basis to review what substances had been detected. Clinicians taking care
of the patient could document in the medical record that the patient had a substance
found on their person, as well as a physical description of the substance and what
the patient reported that the substance contained. Clinicians could document that
the substance was to be destroyed per hospital protocol, and that a handheld Raman
spectrometry analysis was done or was to be done on the substance. The device is
designed for forensic analysis only and was not used to replace any laboratory drug
testing.</p><p>As both trained law enforcement and trained hospital clinicians and pharmacists used
the same device, this broadened our surveillance of the illicit drug supply in our
community as we were able to get information from both the law enforcement and
healthcare settings in our community. Working with our existing opioid safety
coalition, we developed plans to share information on what substances were detected
in our street drug supply on a scheduled basis with local hospitals, law
enforcement, substance use treatment programs, and other community organizations.
Information could also be shared through the opioid safety coalition on an urgent
basis if a new substance was detected that was particularly concerning or novel to
the community. We ultimately chose to house the device in our Emergency Department
as it is open 24 hours per day, the Emergency Department is a common site at which
patients with substance use seek care, and we have security in our hospital&#8217;s
Emergency Department to supervise use of the device and interact with law
enforcement.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="section7-22799036231166313"><title>Results</title><p>As a part of our preparation of this program, we identified that there were 17
different law enforcement agencies in our County. We were able to train 14 of those
agencies on how to use the device, the farthest of which was 65 miles away from our
hospital.</p><p>During the 10-month period after implementation from December 2021 to September 2022,
the device was used 236 times to scan substances that were thought to be illicit
drugs. We were not able to determine which scans were done by healthcare providers
and which scans were done by law enforcement. We identified 27 different substances
in our local illicit drug supply, including etizolam, fentanyl, acetyl fentanyl, and
acrylfentanyl. <xref rid="table1-22799036231166313" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
provides a complete list of all substances that were identified in our local illicit
drug supply, as well as how many times each substance was detected. More than one
substance was detected in nine scans: Mannitol + Inositol (four scans), Mannitol +
Lactose (two scans), Epsom Salt + Cellulose (two scans), and Lactose + Cellulose
(one scan). Of the 236 scans that were performed, 77 (27%) had results that were
inconclusive. Two cases involving use of the device stood out as particularly useful
that we felt were worth discussing individually.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table1-22799036231166313" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Complete list of all substances identified in our local illicit drug supply
during the 10 month period after implementation of the program (with the
number of times each substance was detected).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_22799036231166313-table1.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drugs of abuse</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Methamphetamine (21)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Cocaine (6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Fentanyl (5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Acryl fentanyl (3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Heroin (3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Ethanol (3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Amphetamine (1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Diazepam (1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Etizolam (1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Acetyl fentanyl (1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other substances</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Acetaminophen (43)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Mannitol (34)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Polystyrene (8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Aspirin (7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Lactose (6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Caffeine (5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Inositol (4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Polypropylene (3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Cellulose (3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Low density polyethylene (2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Ibuprofen (2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Epsom salt (2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Diphenhydramine (1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Sorbitol (1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Naproxen (1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Barium sulfate (1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Baking soda (1)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><list list-type="simple" id="list1-22799036231166313"><list-item><p><bold>Case 1.</bold> After confiscation from a justice-involved person, a
local law enforcement officer brought a small bag of pills to our hospital
to be tested using our handheld Raman spectrometer. The pills were blue in
color, with the marking &#8220;M 30&#8221; on them. These pills have been known in our
community to be sold on the street and to contain fentanyl based on our
previous experience treating patients using them. For this particular set of
pills, the officer used the device to analyze them and surprisingly did not
find fentanyl in the pills. The officer scanned multiple different pills
from the set and scanned pills in different locations on their surfaces. The
only substance detected was etizolam, a benzodiazepine that is not legal in
the US, as discussed above. This was novel information for our community
that blue M 30 pills contained etizolam, and we shared this information on
an urgent basis with physicians and first responders through our local
opioid safety coalition to warn of this finding in order to guide care of
patients using these pills.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Case 2.</bold> A 25-year-old female was referred to our Emergency
Department by a local drug treatment program as she appeared to be in severe
withdrawal from opiates when she arrived to enter the program. While sitting
in the waiting room, the triage nurse noted that the patient&#8217;s appearance
changed, so she went to assess the patient. The patient was found to have
clinical signs of an opiate overdose. Naloxone was immediately administered
and the patient was brought back to a resuscitation room for immediate
attention. During her resuscitation, a white powder was found in a container
on the patient&#8217;s person. This powder was confiscated as a suspected illicit
substance, and our Emergency Department pharmacist shortly after analyzed
the powder with the handheld Raman spectrometer which identified the
substance as fentanyl. We shared this information, namely that we had
detected fentanyl as a white powder, with physicians and first responders
through our local opioid safety coalition to warn of this finding, as most
of the fentanyl in the community to date had been in the form of counterfeit
pills.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section8-22799036231166313"><title>Discussion</title><p>Since implementation of this novel program, we have been able to identify multiple
substances in our street drug supply, some not previously known to have been in our
community. Our hospital&#8217;s urine drug screen does not test for many of these
substances, which has made understanding what substances are causing intoxication
and overdose extremely challenging. By using this handheld Raman spectrometer, we
have been able to inform our first responders, law enforcement, and health care
providers with more information about our community&#8217;s illicit drug supply than we
could have ever done just using our hospital&#8217;s routine urine drug screens. While we
ultimately cannot definitively identify every substance in our community using this
device, we are able to detect the substances that our patients are using more
comprehensively and more rapidly than before implementation. Information about
substances detected using the device&#8212;including substance form, color, street name,
and what the substance is sold as&#8212;is shared monthly with our physicians, first
responders, and local police departments. This information is also shared at all
scheduled meetings of our local substance use safety coalition. Additionally, while
fillers or cutting agents may be perceived as innocuous compared to the drugs of
abuse, several of the substances we detected are pharmaceutically active and could
affect a patient who took multiple doses of the illicit product, such as
acetaminophen and aspirin. As an example of how information detected by the device
is used by healthcare providers, we have discussed as a coalition that if we see an
increasing percentage of specimens that test positive for aspirin and acetaminophen
in the future, we could change our practice at the hospital to routinely obtaining
serum levels of these medications after an overdose out of concern for unexpected
toxicity due to the filler or cutting agent.</p><p>One finding that stands out in <xref rid="table1-22799036231166313" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> is the high frequency with which acetaminophen and mannitol were
detected. We suspect that this is due to the need to scan specimens multiple times
to detect all substances in the specimen, as substances may not be evenly
distributed through the specimen (such as with counterfeit pills). If a specimen was
scanned, and an illicit substance was suspected but only a common cutting agent was
detected, the specimen was re-scanned again multiple times on other areas so as to
detect any illicit substances in the specimen.</p><p>From a law enforcement, healthcare provider, and first responder standpoint, access
to this device is extremely useful as it allows safe and rapid testing. Currently,
when law enforcement agencies find illicit drugs in our community, they send them to
the Department of Justice (DOJ) for testing so as to determine what chemical or
chemicals were in the illicit drug product. Due to a high volume of specimens being
sent for analysis, testing by the DOJ can take up to several months to result, and
not all specimens end up getting tested. While awaiting test results, we as a
community of healthcare providers and first responders have no information about
what chemical or chemicals were in that illicit drug product sent for analysis. In
comparison, use of the handheld Raman spectrometer allows for the detection of
substances in the drug supply in real time. Additionally, by being able to scan
through plastic bags and non-opaque containers, this device allows healthcare
providers and law enforcement officers to safely test products quickly and easily
without being exposed to the substance being tested.</p><p>Another benefit of this program has been to strengthen the relationship between law
enforcement, first responders, and health care providers. Law enforcement is
frequently on our campus to use the device, which has involved collegial discussions
about our illicit drug supply and how to protect our community. From discussions
during the planning and implementation of this program, we have developed an
overdose response team to serve the surrounding area of the hospital that will
consist of hospital staff, law enforcement, and substance use providers. Our program
using the handheld Raman spectrometer has been viewed as so beneficial to the
community that another hospital in the county will be purchasing the device for use
on their own campus in a similar fashion to the program at our hospital. Currently,
all law enforcement agencies in our county can use the device in our hospital, and
the addition of a second device at another hospital in the county will reduce travel
time for officers and increase the surveillance of street drugs in our county. Both
hospitals are in our local opioid safety coalition and will work to share data about
what substances are detected to keep our community informed.</p><p>This program can be easily implemented at any hospital in the country in the opinion
of the authors. The device may be purchased from the manufacturer (Thermo
Scientific). From a law enforcement perspective, it is helpful for the officers to
have access to the device as it provides rapid and safe drug analysis. Given the
benefit to law enforcement and as law enforcement inherently works closely with
Emergency Departments (assault, violence, behavioral health holds, etc.), there is
minimal effort required to make contact with and get engagement from local law
enforcement agencies to build a program.</p><p>While overall, the implementation of this program has been highly successful in our
community, there are some limitations that must be considered. First, using the
handheld Raman spectrometer takes training, and an inexperienced user may not know
how to adequately test a specimen, resulting in a false negative for one or more
substances when the specimen is tested. To combat this, our users of the device were
trained to scan each specimen multiple times in multiple locations to maximize our
ability to detect each substance in a given specimen. A second limitation of our
program is that we were only able to review the scan data from the TruNarc device
and were not able to record how many times a single specimen was scanned. As such,
we do not precisely know how frequently various cutting agents are used, as many
specimens, once a cutting agent such as acetaminophen was detected, were scanned
multiple times. Third, the handheld Raman spectrometer only has a finite number of
chemicals that can be detected, so there could have been other chemicals that were
present but not detected. While the manufacturer regularly updates the database of
chemicals detected, &#8220;street&#8221; chemists are constantly detecting new substances that
can be used as recreational drugs. Fourth, as noted previously, even when used
correctly in one study, the TruNarc device may not detect all specimens in the
library (such as when a substance is present in a very small amount), so this may
have resulted in us not detecting some substances in the products we tested.
Finally, our surveillance of the illicit substances in our community is limited to
substances obtained by local law enforcement and substances found on the person of
patients seeking medical attention in our hospital and Emergency Department.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="section9-22799036231166313"><title>Conclusion</title><p>A novel hospital-based program of using a handheld Raman spectrometer in partnership
with law enforcement to detect substances in the local illicit drug supply in real
time has been feasible and effective in our community, and likely could be
beneficial in other communities if replicated. Benefits in our community included
improving collaboration between health care providers and law enforcement,
increasing local efforts to prevent overdoses, and providing real-time information
to the community on what substances are in our illicit drug supply and causing
overdoses.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the
research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or
publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Significance for public health:</bold> The United States is currently experiencing an unprecedented rise in fatal drug
overdoses as the US drug supply is increasingly contaminated with novel
substances, including fentanyl analogues. Our community opioid safety coalition,
which includes law enforcement, identified the need to be able to rapidly detect
novel substance in our illicit drug supply so as to be able to inform front line
medical providers as to what substances might be causing overdoses. We found the
use of a shared Raman spectrometry device available to health care providers and
law enforcement to be an effective way to identify novel substances in our drug
supply in our community. The information about what substances we have detected
has helped us to educate our front-line medical providers on how to respond to
overdoses in real time and helped us improve our substance use and overdose
prevention efforts.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Casey Grover <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="10.1177_22799036231166313-img1.jpg"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2930-9867" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2930-9867</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-22799036231166313"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vivolo-Kantor</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seth</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gladden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Vital signs: trends in
emergency department visits for suspected opioid overdoses &#8211; United States,
July 2016 &#8211; September 2017</article-title>. <source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly
Rep</source><year>2018</year>; <volume>67</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):
<fpage>279</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>285</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29518069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.15585/mmwr.mm6709e1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5844282</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-22799036231166313"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McAnich</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Emergency department visits and overdose deaths
from combined use of opioids and benzodiazepines</article-title>. <source>Am
J Prev Med</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>49</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>493</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>501</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26143953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amepre.2015.03.040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-22799036231166313"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gwira Baumblatt</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiedman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>High-risk use by patients
prescribed opioids for pain and its role in overdose deaths</article-title>.
<source>JAMA Intern Med</source>. <year>2014</year>;
<volume>174</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):
<fpage>796</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>801</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24589873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamainternmed.2013.12711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-22799036231166313"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paulozzi</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strickler</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreiner</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Controlled substance
prescribing patterns &#8211; prescription behavior surveillance system, eight
states, 2013</article-title>. <source>MMWR Surveill
Summ</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>64</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):
<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>14</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.15585/mmwr.ss6409a1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26469747</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-22799036231166313"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohm</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Vital signs: changes in
opioid prescribing in the United States, 2006&#8211;2015</article-title>.
<source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><year>2017</year>;
<volume>66</volume>(<issue>26</issue>):
<fpage>697</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>704</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28683056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.15585/mmwr.mm6626a4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5726238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-22799036231166313"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossen</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Provisional drug overdose death counts</source>.
<publisher-loc>Hyattsville, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National
Center for Health Statistics</publisher-name>,
<year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-22799036231166313"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The emerging role of toxic adulterants in street
drugs in the US illicit opioid crisis</article-title>. <source>Public Health
Rep</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>135</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>6</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31738861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0033354919887741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7119254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-22799036231166313"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiorentin</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fogarty</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Limberger</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Determination of cutting
agents in seized cocaine samples using GC-MS, GC-TMS, and
LC-MS/MS</article-title>. <source>Forensic Sci
Int</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>295</volume>:
<fpage>199</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>206</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30634141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.forsciint.2018.12.016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-22799036231166313"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Cardiac complications of
unwitting co-injection of quinine/quinidine with heroin in an intravenous
drug user</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern
Med</source><year>2012</year>; <volume>27</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):
<fpage>1722</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1725</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22592353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-012-2089-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3509315</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-22799036231166313"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiorentin</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analytical findings in used syringes from a
syringe exchange program</article-title>. <source>Int J Drug
Policy</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>81</volume>:
<fpage>102770</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32442881</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugpo.2020.102770</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-22799036231166313"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pergolizzi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magnusson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>LeQuang</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Illicitly manufactured
fentanyl entering the United States</article-title>.
<source>Cureus</source><year>2021</year>;
<volume>13</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): e17496.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.17496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8476199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34603876</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-22799036231166313"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abate</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Fentanyl and fentanyl-analog
involvement in drug related deaths</article-title>. <source>Drug Alcohol
Depend</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>196</volume>:
<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30658219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2018.12.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6447047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-22799036231166313"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McAuley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Etizolam: a rapid review on pharmacology,
non-medical use and harms</article-title>. <source>Drug Alcohol
Rev</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>39</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>330</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>336</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32243020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/dar.13052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-22799036231166313"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kranenburg</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verduin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Ridder</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Performance evaluation of
handheld Raman spectroscopy for cocaine detection on forensic case
samples</article-title>. <source>Drug Test Anal</source><year>2021</year>;
<volume>13</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):
<fpage>1054</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1067</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33354929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/dta.2993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8248000</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-22799036231166313"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spicher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeatman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alford</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The evaluation of portable
handheld Raman systems for the presumptive identification of narcotics:
thermo scientific TruNarc and Chemring detection systems
PGR-1064</article-title>. <publisher-name>Marshall
University</publisher-name>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.marshall.edu/forensics/files/SpicherCristina_FINAL-Research-Paper_8_3_-2016.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.marshall.edu/forensics/files/SpicherCristina_FINAL-Research-Paper_8_3_-2016.pdf</ext-link>
(<comment>accessed 10 April 2022</comment>).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>