<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2035</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">lwwopen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JS9</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Surgery (London, England)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1743-9191</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1743-9159</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Lippincott Open Access</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11020048</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11020048.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11020048</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11020048</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38265431</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JS9.0000000000001050</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJS-D-23-02422</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Easily applicable predictive score for MPR based on parameters before neoadjuvant chemoimmunotherapy in operable NSCLC: a single-center, ambispective, observational study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names initials="M">Mingming</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><email>hmn1618@163.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaomi</given-names></name><degrees>MSC</degrees><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref><email>xiaomili999@126.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names initials="H">Haifeng</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><email>yh1986_yuhan@126.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names initials="B">Baohua</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><email>octorbd@163.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qunhui</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><email>qunhui01@263.net</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names initials="L">Li</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><email>tongli79@163.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="H">Hongxia</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><email>doctor.hong@163.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Che</surname><given-names initials="N">Nanying</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><email>cheny0448@163.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname><given-names initials="S">Shaojun</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><email>huangsj2016@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yi</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><email>hanyeecn@163.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names initials="K">Kang</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><email>shikang_xk@163.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="C">Chenghai</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><email>lichenghai82@163.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="H">Hongmei</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>790016548@qq.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhidong</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><email>lzdzrd@163.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="T">Tongmei</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><email>tongmeibj@163.com</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>a</label>Department of Oncology</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>b</label>Department of Medical Imaging</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>c</label>Department of Pathology</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>d</label>Department of Thoracic Surgery, Beijing Chest Hospital, Capital Medical University</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>e</label>Department of Oncology, Beijing Institute of Tuberculosis and Chest Tumor, Beijing, People&#8217;s Republic of China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding authors. Address: Department of Thoracic Surgery, Beijing Chest Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing 101149, People&#8217;s Republic of China. Tel.: +10 895 093 26. E-mail: <email>lzdzrd@163.com</email> (Z. Liu); Department of Oncology, Beijing Chest Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing 101149, People&#8217;s Republic of China. Tel.: +10 895 093 09. E-mail: <email>tongmeibj@163.com</email> (T. Zhang).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>110</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">460114</issue-id><fpage>2275</fpage><lpage>2287</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>16</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>17</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-04-24 21:25:11.347"><day>24</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2024 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbysalicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License 4.0</ext-link>, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work, even for commercial purposes, as long as the author is credited and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="js9-110-2275.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="js9-110-2275.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Neoadjuvant chemoimmunotherapy (NACI) is promising for resectable nonsmall cell lung cancer (NSCLC), but predictive biomarkers are still lacking. The authors aimed to develop a model based on pretreatment parameters to predict major pathological response (MPR) for such an approach.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>The authors enrolled operable NSCLC treated with NACI between March 2020 and May 2023 and then collected baseline clinical-pathology data and routine laboratory examinations before treatment. The efficacy and safety data of this cohort was reported and variables were screened by Logistic and Lasso regression and nomogram was developed. In addition, receiver operating characteristic curves, calibration curves, and decision curve analysis were used to assess its power. Finally, internal cross-validation and external validation was performed to assess the power of the model.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>In total, 206 eligible patients were recruited in this study and 53.4% (110/206) patients achieved MPR. Using multivariate analysis, the predictive model was constructed by seven variables, prothrombin time (PT), neutrophil percentage (NEUT%), large platelet ratio (P-LCR), eosinophil percentage (EOS%), smoking, pathological type, and programmed death ligand-1 (PD-L1) expression finally. The model had good discrimination, with area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUC) of 0.775, 0.746, and 0.835 for all datasets, cross-validation, and external validation, respectively. The calibration curves showed good consistency, and decision curve analysis indicated its potential value in clinical practice.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>This real world study revealed favorable efficacy in operable NSCLC treated with NACI. The proposed model based on multiple clinically accessible parameters could effectively predict MPR probability and could be a powerful tool in personalized medication.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords:</title><kwd>major pathological response</kwd><kwd>neoadjuvant chemoimmunotherapy</kwd><kwd>nonsmall cell lung cancer</kwd><kwd>predictive model</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>SDC</meta-name><meta-value>T</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><boxed-text content-type="shaded" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Highlights</p></caption><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The efficacy and safety data of neoadjuvant chemoimmunotherapy in operable nonsmall cell lung cancer was demonstrated in a real-world setting with the largest population.</p></list-item><list-item><p>An applicable model to predicting major pathological response in nonsmall cell lung cancer received neoadjuvant chemoimmunotherapy from baseline clinical-pathology data and routine laboratory examinations before treatment was developed and validated.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The proposed model could effectively predict major pathological response probability and could be a potential tool in personalized medication.</p></list-item></list></boxed-text><p>It is estimated that there were 238&#160;340 new cases of lung cancer in the United States in 2023, with the incidence second only to prostate cancer in men and breast cancer in women; 127&#160;070 deaths from lung cancer, both in men and women, ranked first among all malignant tumors<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>. Nonsmall cell lung cancer (NSCLC) accounts for 85% of all types of lung cancer, of which about 30% are in the early stage at the first diagnosis<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>. Complete surgical resection remains the recommended therapeutic modality for these patients in the curable stage. Neoadjuvant therapy is a systemic antineoplastic therapy performed preoperatively with the purpose to degrade the tumor stage and increase the chance of complete resection, reduce micrometastases, and improve the tolerance to facilitate subsequent operations<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>. However, neoadjuvant chemotherapy only can increase survival rate by about 5%, and there is an urgent need for new treatment modalities to improve survival<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. In recent years, a number of prospective clinical trials have shown that immune checkpoint inhibitors (ICIs) combined with chemotherapy produced better major pathological response (MPR) and pathological complete response (pCR) than neoadjuvant chemotherapy alone, and preliminary results have indicated that it can translate into survival benefit<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. Therefore, the primary study endpoint of phase II and phase III clinical studies in the neoadjuvant stage is MPR or pCR<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>.</p><p>However, approximately only one-third of the patients benefit from ICIs. Until now, there are no recommended predictive markers to screen potential candidates in neoadjuvant settings<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>. At present, the companion diagnostics approved for ICIs in advanced NSCLC, such as PD-L1 expression through immunohistochemistry, tumor mutational burden (TMB), and microsatellite instability (MSI), do not perfectly distinguish between those who respond and those who do not. The determination of TMB/MSI was complicated and did not reach a good consensus in terms of the clinical application<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>. All of these could restrict some patients from accessing ICIs even though they could benefit from them, and it also does not accurately identify the patients most likely to respond. Given the potential hazard of ineffective treatment in a disease, which is typically characterized by aggressive tumor growth and then the loss of operation, there is an urgent need to develop a risk-scoring system to identify the right candidates for neoadjuvant chemoimmunotherapy (NACI). Several predictive models based on dynamic medical image mining, immune-related histological phenotype in tumor biopsy, and liquid immune cell profiling have been reported. While, models based on tumor computational images always rely on changes in the radiomic texture of CT patterns before and after immunotherapy, and thus cannot help us perform stratification before treatment<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. A vast amount of omics data are currently available for biomarker research, such as histological phenotype in tumor microenvironment, liquid immune cell profiling, and multigene panel sequencing, but their use is restricted because of the cost and complex processes as well as the relatively more demands for tissue samples<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>. Hence, the exploitation of novel, effective, and applicable biomarkers at a low-cost to select suitable patients who could benefit from NACI is necessary and meaningful.</p><p>By comparison, peripheral blood-related biomarkers have unique advantages of noninvasiveness, and convenient acquisition. At the same time, peripheral blood can provide a comprehensive immune status of the host, and can monitor the effect dynamically and longitudinally, therefore such results are frequently used in biomarker screening of ICI research<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>. It is expected that classical prognostic variables such as neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio (NLR) or serum lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) have been explored as potential predictors of response in a variety of solid tumors, mainly in patients with advanced disease<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup>. However, these routinely available peripheral blood markers, such as total cell counts and ratios, biochemistry, coagulation, and tumor markers have not been fully explored in neoadjuvant settings.</p><p>In this manuscript, we reported the efficacy and safety data from a NACI cohort conducted in the real world with the largest population, to my furthest knowledge. Sequentially, a predictive model for MPR was developed and validated by virtue of clinical-pathological factors and peripheral blood markers, both of which were routinely examined before the initiation of NACI before the treatment start. The developed model is likely to be a weakly supervised, easy-accessible, low-cost tool for NSCLC management.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Ethics standards</title><p>This observational cohort study was conducted at a single center and adhered to the ethical guidelines outlined in the Declaration of Helsinki. The study was approved by our institution&#8217;s review board (Approval Number: YNLX-2022-015). Due to the observational study design, the ethics committee approved a waiver of written informed consent. All procedures conducted in our study followed the criteria outlined in REMARK<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> (Supplemental Digital Content 1, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/B754" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/B754</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Study design and patient cohort</title><p>It was an ambispective (i.e. containing both retrospective and prospective stages of data collection), observational study designed to evaluate the effectiveness, treatment patterns, and safety of NACI in patients with operable NSCLC in routine clinical practice in our hospital. Data from patients who started treatment between 1 March 2020 and 30 July 2022, were retrospectively collected; data were then prospectively collected from 1 August 2022 to 1 October 2023. The ambispective design had no impact on the data collection process or the study methods that would require a separate analysis of the data collected retrospectively and prospectively.</p><p>Patients with NSCLC in our hospital were included: (1) pathologically proved, (2) clinical TNM staged I&#8211;III, (3) radical resection after neoadjuvant immunochemotherapy, and (4) sufficient organ function, including blood cell count, coagulation parameters, physical score, liver, and kidney function. Patients were excluded from this study when any of the following criteria were met: (1) neoadjuvant immunotherapy/chemotherapy alone, (2) previous radiotherapy, (3) neoadjuvant targeted therapy, (4) locally endoscopic therapy before surgery, (5) chronic viral infections, such as HBV, HCV, or HIV infection, (6) accompanied with active infection requires anti-infective treatment, (7) history of malignant tumor within 5 years, (8) pre-existing autoimmune diseases, (9) pre-existing allergic diseases, and (10) history of solid organ transplantation. Patients&#8217; clinical characteristics, including age, sex, smoking status, BMI, TNM stage, lesion location, pathology, and information regarding their laboratory tests, medication, and operation were gathered from the electronic database.</p></sec><sec><title>Biomarker measurement and data collection</title><p>To assess organ function, patients underwent routine peripheral blood tests within 1 week prior to treatment. In these laboratory data, coagulation tests and blood cell counts, along with some derived parameters, NLR, platelet-to-lymphocyte ratio (PLR), lymphocyte-to-monocyte ratio (LMR) were collected in this study. Some other parameters that have been reported as prognostic markers to programmed death-1 (PD-1) inhibitors were also extracted from database in this study, including LDH, C-reactive protein (CRP), albumin (ALB), carcino-embryonic antigen (CEA), and cytokeratin 19 fragment 21-1 (cyfra21-1)<sup><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>.</p><p>Tumor samples were obtained through tissue biopsy (bronchoscopy or lung puncture) and the expression of programmed death ligand-1 (PD-L1) in tumor cells was conventionally detected by immunohistochemical staining (Daco22C3). One hundred tumor cells were counted microscopically and the expression levels of PD-L1 protein were expressed according to the tumor proportion score (TPS). The percentage of stained cells &lt;1%, 1&#8211;49%, &#8805;50% was defined as negative, low expression, and high expression, respectively<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Treatment evaluation</title><p>All patients received adequate preoperative imaging, which consisted of chest/abdomen CT scan with contrast, MRI of the brain, ultrasound examination of superficial lymph nodes/abdomen and ECT of bone, while, positron emission tomography/CT scan, invasive staging of the mediastinal lymph nodes using either endobronchial ultrasound or mediastinoscopy, if necessary. The clinical stage was determined according to the eighth edition TNM stage classification of the International Association for the Study of Lung Cancer (IASLC)<sup><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>. The antitumor response was evaluated on the basis of the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors version 1.1 (RECIST v1.1) after every two treatment courses. Tumor responses were classified as complete response (CR) with definition of disappearance of all target lesions, partial response (PR, at least a 30% decrease in the sum of diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the baseline sum diameters), stable disease (SD, neither sufficient shrinkage to qualify for PR nor sufficient increase to qualify for PD (progressive disease), taking as reference the smallest sum diameters while on study), or PD (at least a 20% increase in the sum of diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the smallest sum on study). ORR was the percentage of patients who achieve CR or PR according to RECIST criteria<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup>.</p><p>Pathological response of neoadjuvant therapy was evaluated by two qualified pathologist based on H&amp;E staining. MPR refers to the induction and elimination of residual tumor from tumor pathology after neoadjuvant therapy in &#8804;10%. pCR is defined as complete tumor regression induced by neoadjuvant therapy without pathological residual tumor<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>. Adverse events were evaluated according to the National Cancer Institute General Toxicity Standard version 3.0<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Model development and validation</title><p>Given the inevitable problem of missing data, we used a multiple-imputation approach. The imputation method involved in continuous variables was predictive mean matching and the distributions of raw data and imputed values were viewed by density plots.</p><p>We used the patient cohort from March 2020 to May 2023 as the training set, while June 2023 to October 2023 as the validation set. We performed a univariate Logistic regression and Lasso regression to screen variables, respectively, and further fitted them by multivariate Logistic regression to determine factors associated with MPR based on the minimum Akaike information criterion (AIC) value. Factors found to be independent were utilized to create nomogram models. We plotted receiver operating characteristic curves (ROC) and calculated the area under the curve (AUC) to describe their discriminatory power. In addition, to assess the agreement between the observed and predicted probabilities, we created calibration plots using bootstrapping (1000 resamplings). A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value greater than 0.05 for the Hosmer&#8211;Lemeshow test indicates good agreement. To assess the utility of these findings in the clinical setting, we performed decision curve analysis (DCA). This study intends to use 10-fold 200 times cross-validation to verify the reproducibility of the model in the development process, and calculate the mean values of various indicators including AUC, R2, discrimination index, <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> test, Brier score, maximum offset, and minimum offset. Finally, the generalization evaluation of the model was performed in the validation set, ROC, calibration curve, and DCA curve were plotted, and the above indicators were calculated. The overall experimental design was depicted in Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The overall experimental design of this study. DCA, decision curve analysis; IV, intravenous injection; MPR, major pathological response; PD-L1, programmed death ligand-1; ROC, receiver operating characteristic. Created with BioRender.com.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="js9-110-2275-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>This study used R (version 4.2.0) and GraphPad Prism (version 8.0) to analyze and collate the data. Means&#177;SD and medians plus quartiles were used to represent normally and non-normally distributed continuous variables, respectively. Categorical variables were presented as absolute counts and percentages. Fisher&#8217;s exact test/&#967;<sup>2</sup> test and Kruskal&#8211;Wallis test were used to analyze categorical and continuous variables, respectively. Pearson &#967;<sup>2</sup> test or Fisher exact test was used to compare differences in response and clinical benefit between the groups. Univariate Logistic regression analysis was used to screen for the potentially important factors, and then multivariate Logistic regression analysis to identify the independent predictors, which could differentiate MPR group from the whole cohort. Moreover, the further significance of nomogram factors was identified using LASSO regression analysis. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values less than 0.05 were considered statistically significant, and all hypothesis tests were two-sided. The software packages involved in the study were &#8216;mice&#8217;, &#8216;plyr&#8221;, &#8216;MASS&#8217;, &#8216;glmnet&#8217;, &#8216;rms&#8217;, &#8216;rmda&#8217;, and &#8216;caret&#8217;.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Patient cohort</title><p>A total of 206 patients were enrolled in the final cohort between March 2020 and May 2023 (Fig. S1, Supplemental Digital Content 2, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755</ext-link>). Patients&#8217; baseline clinical characteristics are d<underline>i</underline>splayed in Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and more details are listed in Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, with a median age of 62.5 years (range 57.0&#8211;67.8 years) and the majority of patients were male (178, 86.4%). According to the IASLC eighth edition TNM classification for lung cancer, 156 (75.7%) patients had stage III disease, including 104 and 52 patients with stage IIIA and IIIB, respectively. One hundred and fifty-nine (77.2%) patients were former or current smokers and 47 (22.8%) patients were nonsmokers. In 206 patients, lung squamous cell carcinoma (LUSC) was the most common pathological type (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=149, 72.3%), while 51 (24.8%) cases were lung adenocarcinoma (LUAD). The most common site of tumor was the right upper lobe (RUL, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=60, 29.1%), followed by the left upper lobe (LUL, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=50, 24.3%), left lower lobe (LLL, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=39, 18.9%), right middle lobe (RML, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=32, 15.5%), right lower lobe (RLL, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=22, 10.7%), and left main bronchus (LMB, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=3, 1.5%).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Waterfall plot of pathological response of neoadjuvant chemoimmunotherapy of the 206 patients. Each bar represents one patient. The upper rows show clinical and pathological characteristics. CR, complete response; LUAD, lung adenocarcinoma; LUSC, lung squamous cell carcinoma; MPR, major pathological response; PD-1, programmed death-1; PR, partial response; RECIST, response evaluation criteria in solid tumors; RVT, residual viable tumor; SD, stable disease; TNM, tumor node metastasis; VATS, video-assisted thoracoscopic surgery.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="js9-110-2275-g002.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Patient baseline characteristics in MPR and non-MPR groups.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Characteristic</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Overall (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>=206)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Non-MPR (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>=96)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">MPR (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>=110)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.5 [57.0&#8211;67.8]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.5 [56.0&#8211;68.0]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.0 [58.0&#8211;67.0]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="5">Gender (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178 (86.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (80.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (91.8)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (13.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (19.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (8.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="5">Smoking status (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (22.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (30.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (16.4)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Current/former</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">159 (77.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (69.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (83.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="5">Pathological type (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;LUSC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149 (72.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (65.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (78.2)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;non-LUSC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (27.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (34.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (21.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="5">TNM stage (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;I&#8211;II</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (24.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (22.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (25.5)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;IIIA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104 (50.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (49.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (51.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;IIIB</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (25.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (28.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (22.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="5">ypTNM stage (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;ypT<sub>0</sub>N<sub>0</sub>M<sub>0</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76 (100.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;ypT<sub>0</sub>N<sub>1-2</sub>M<sub>0</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (100.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;ypT<sub>1</sub>N<sub>0</sub>M<sub>0</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (61.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (39.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;ypT<sub>1</sub>N<sub>1-2</sub>M<sub>0</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (91.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (8.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;ypT<sub>2-3</sub>N<sub>0</sub>M<sub>0</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (100.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;ypT<sub>2-3</sub>N<sub>1-2</sub>M<sub>0</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (100.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="5">Neoadjuvant treatment cycles (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8804;2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114 (55.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (55.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (55.5)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&gt;2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (44.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (44.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (44.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="5">PD-1 inhibitors</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Camrelizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (40.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (51.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (47.3)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Sintilimab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (25.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (26.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (25.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Tislelizumab</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (14.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (12.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (16.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Others</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (10.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (10.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (10.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.9 [21.9&#8211;26.5]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2 [22.4&#8211;26.7]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4 [21.5&#8211;26.4]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PD-L1 [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0 [1.0&#8211;70.0]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 [0.0&#8211;42.5]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.0 [1.0&#8211;80.0]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyfra21-1 [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6 [3.3&#8211;17.0]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4 [3.3&#8211;18.6]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 [3.6&#8211;15.8]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDH [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163.0 [145.0&#8211;189.5]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">166.5 [146.8&#8211;188.0]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">161.5 [143.2&#8211;192.2]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 [1.7&#8211;15.3]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 [1.8&#8211;13.8]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6 [1.7&#8211;19.0]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CEA [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2 [2.1&#8211;6.0]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 [2.2&#8211;7.3]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0 [2.1&#8211;5.0]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PT [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4 [10.8&#8211;11.9]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3 [10.6&#8211;11.8]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6 [11.0&#8211;12.2]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INR [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 [0.9&#8211;1.0]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 [0.9&#8211;1.0]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 [0.9&#8211;1.1]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PT% [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.7 [73.2&#8211;96.9]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.3 [77.4&#8211;100.6]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.2 [71.7&#8211;92.8]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTR [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 [0.9&#8211;1.0]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 [0.9&#8211;1.0]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 [1.0&#8211;1.0]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">APTT [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.3 [25.7&#8211;31.3]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.8 [25.2&#8211;30.4]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.6 [26.5&#8211;31.8]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FIB(S) [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8 [5.6&#8211;8.3]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6 [5.5&#8211;7.9]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 [5.7&#8211;8.4]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FIB [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 [2.8&#8211;4.4]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 [2.8&#8211;4.3]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 [2.8&#8211;4.6]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TT [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.7 [17.9&#8211;19.4]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.8 [17.8&#8211;19.4]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.6 [17.9&#8211;19.4]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D-Dimer [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 [0.3&#8211;0.6]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 [0.3&#8211;0.6]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 [0.3&#8211;0.6]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBC [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3 [6.1&#8211;8.6]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1 [6.1&#8211;8.6]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4 [5.8&#8211;8.5]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LY% [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.4 [20.7&#8211;31.0]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.6 [19.2&#8211;29.2]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.0 [21.5&#8211;31.6]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M0N0% [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 [5.5&#8211;7.6]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 [5.5&#8211;7.3]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 [5.5&#8211;7.6]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NEUT% [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.4 [58.9&#8211;70.4]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.4 [60.5&#8211;71.8]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.3 [58.1&#8211;68.7]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RBC [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6 [4.2&#8211;4.9]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5 [4.2&#8211;4.8]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6 [4.3&#8211;4.9]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HGB [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137.5 [126.0&#8211;147.8]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137.0 [127.8&#8211;146.0]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138.0 [124.2&#8211;149.0]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCT [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.8 [37.8&#8211;43.9]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.4 [38.3&#8211;43.6]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.0 [37.5&#8211;44.2]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCV [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.6 [86.9&#8211;92.9]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.8 [86.9&#8211;92.8]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.4 [87.0&#8211;92.7]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCH [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.3 [29.3&#8211;31.5]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.4 [29.3&#8211;31.4]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.1 [29.2&#8211;31.6]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCHC [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">336.0 [327.0&#8211;343.0]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">337.0 [328.0&#8211;344.0]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">335.0 [325.2&#8211;342.0]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RDW-CV [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6 [12.0&#8211;13.2]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4 [12.0&#8211;13.2]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6 [12.1&#8211;13.2]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLT [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">239.0 [198.0&#8211;291.2]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">235.5 [197.8&#8211;281.5]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245.0 [198.2&#8211;296.2]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPV [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0 [9.4&#8211;10.8]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9 [9.3&#8211;10.6]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1 [9.6&#8211;11.0]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-LCR [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0 [20.4&#8211;31.5]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.3 [19.4&#8211;29.0]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.7 [21.7&#8211;32.5]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDW [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4 [10.1&#8211;13.2]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9 [9.8&#8211;12.4]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7 [10.5&#8211;14.1]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EOS% [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4 [1.5&#8211;3.4]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 [1.5&#8211;2.8]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 [1.5&#8211;3.8]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BASO% [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 [0.3&#8211;0.6]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 [0.3&#8211;0.6]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 [0.3&#8211;0.6]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RDW-SD [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.3 [39.3&#8211;43.8]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.0 [39.3&#8211;43.6]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.3 [39.4&#8211;43.8]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NLR [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 [1.9&#8211;3.4]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 [2.1&#8211;3.8]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4 [1.8&#8211;3.2]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LMR [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 [3.0&#8211;5.2]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7 [2.8&#8211;5.0]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1 [3.2&#8211;5.3]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLR [median (IQR)]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5 [6.9&#8211;13.5]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2 [7.0&#8211;13.9]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3 [6.5&#8211;12.6]</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>APTT, partial thromboplastin time; BASO%, basophilic cells percentage; CEA, carcino-embryonic antigen; CRP, C-reactive protein; EOS%, eosinophilic cells percentage; FIB(S), fibrinogen time; FIB, fibrinogen content; HCT, hematocrit; HGB, hemoglobin; INR, international normalized ratio; LDH, lactate dehydrogenase; LMR, lymphocyte-to-monocyte ratio; LUSC, lung squamous cell carcinoma; LY%, lymphocyte percentage; M0N0%, monocyte percentage; MCH, mean corpuscular hemoglobin; MCHC, mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration; MCV, mean corpuscular volume; MPR, major pathological response; MPV, mean platelet volume; NEUT%, neutrophilic granulocyte percentage; NLR, neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio; PD-1, programmed death-1; PDW, platelet distribution width; P-LCR, platelet large cell ratio; PLR, platelet-to-lymphocyte ratio; PLT, platelet; PT%, prothrombin percentage; PT, prothrombin time; PTR, prothrombin ratio; RBC, red blood cell; RDW-CV, red blood cell distribution-coefficient of variation; RDW-SD, red cell distribution width-standard deviation; TNM, tumor node metastasis; TT, thrombin time; WBC, white blood cell.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>NACI regimen</title><p>All included patients received PD-1 inhibitor and platinum-based chemotherapy, including taxanes, pemetrexed, and gemcitabine, followed by surgical resection within 4&#8211;6 weeks after neoadjuvant therapy. Patients were treated intravenously with one of the following PD-1 inhibitors as neoadjuvant immunotherapy: camrelizumab, sintilimab, tislelizumab, toripalimab, palizumab, and nivolumab. More than half of the patients (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=108, 52.4%) received two cycles of drug, followed by three cycles (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=76, 36.9%), four cycles (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=13, 6.3%), one cycle (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=6, 2.9%), and five cycles (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=3, 1.5%). In addition, among these 206 patients, 159 (77.2%), 32 (15.5%), and 15 (7.3%) underwent lobectomy/bilobectomy/pneumonectomy, respectively, through video-assisted thoracoscopic surgery (VATS, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=90, 43.7%) or thoracotomy (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=116, 56.3%, Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). All cases achieved R0 resection.</p></sec><sec><title>Peripheral blood and biomarkers</title><p>For patients treated with NACI, 176 samples were investigated for PD-L1 expression in cancer tissues using immunohistochemistry (IHC). Forty-seven (26.7%) were negative for PD-L1 expression (TPS=0), 69 (39.2%) were positive for weak expression (TPS 1&#8211;49%), and 60 (34.1%) were positive for strong expression (TPS &#8805;50%). In 206 patients undergoing surgery, complete blood count, coagulation parameters, LDH, CRP, and CEA were missing to varying degrees (Fig. S2, Supplemental Digital Content 2, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755</ext-link>), and these test parameters and loss of PD-L1 expression in tissue were multiply imputed using a predictive mean matching method with five imputations and five iterations, and density plots (Fig. S3, Supplemental Digital Content 2, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755</ext-link>) showed that imputation was better for each variable.</p></sec><sec><title>Treatment outcomes and differences between groups</title><p>In this study, 201 NSCLC were evaluated with radiological imaging after receiving NACI, among whom, 1, 128 and 72 patients achieved CR, PR, and SD, respectively, with ORR of 64.2% (129/201) and no disease progression. Histopathological evaluation was performed in all patients after surgery, pCR was achieved in 36.9% (76/206) and MPR in 53.4% (110/206). MPR and pCR accounted for 69.8% (90/129) and 49.6% (64/129), respectively, in patients who achieved PR by imaging assessment, respectively. In patients who were classified in SD group, MPR and pCR accounted for 26.4% (19/72) and 15.3% (11/72), respectively. One hundred forty-six patients (70.9%) reported treatment-related adverse events, most of which were classified as grades 1&#8211;2. Grades 3&#8211;4 treatment-related adverse events were experienced by 42 patients (20.4%), with the most common being decreased white cell count in 19 patients (10.7%). The immune-related adverse effects (irAE) was occurred in 60 (29.1%) patients, the most common adverse event was reactive cutaneous capillary endothelial proliferation (RCCEP, 28/206), all of which were graded 1&#8211;2, followed closely by rash (22/206) and pneumonia (7/206). Grades 3&#8211;4 irAE were reported with maculopapular rash in 16 patients (7.8%), pneumonia in five patients (2.4%), diarrhea in two patients (1.0%), thyroiditis in one patient (0.5%) and myositis in one patients (0.5%). In this cohort, one patient experienced grade 3 rash and thyroiditis simultaneously, while another patient experienced grade 3 rash and pneumonia simultaneously. Grade 5 toxicities were never observed during the neoadjuvant treatment courses. We did not find any correlation between the irAE and the values of blood markers (Table S1, Supplemental Digital Content 2, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755</ext-link>).</p><p>The baseline comprehensive table showed differences in the distribution of patients&#8217; baseline characteristics between the MPR and non-MPR groups, with statistical differences found for prothrombin time (PT, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.004), prothrombin time percentage (PT%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.006), prothrombin ratio (PTR, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.008), neutrophil percentage (NEUT%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.013), platelet large cell ratio (P-LCR, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.016), platelet distribution width (PDW, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.041), eosinophils percentage (EOS%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.023), sex (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.026), smoking history (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.028), PD-L1 expression (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.0002). While the parameters related to the course of treatment, neither treatment cycles nor different PD-1 inhibitors, affect MPR significantly (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Because stage III is a very heterogeneous population, separate analyses was done and it showed that patients with IIIA and IIIB had similar benefits in different subgroups (Table S2, Supplemental Digital Content 2, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec><title>Variable screening and model building</title><p>We screened a total of 43 variables using Logistic regression and Lasso regression, respectively. Univariate Logistic regression showed that PT, PT%, NEUT%, P-LCR, PDW, EOS%, sex, smoking status, and PD-L1 expression were associated with MPR (Table S3, Supplemental Digital Content 2, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755</ext-link>). Multivariate Logistic regression further fitted the model and identified six independent predictors of MPR: PT, NEUT%, P-LCR, EOS%, smoking status, and PD-L1 expression. Taking into account the question of collinearity between these variables, we used two variable screening method to develop the model. Lasso regression established 10 variables associated with MPR: PT, NEUT%, MCHC, P-LCR, PDW, EOS%, sex, smoking status, pathological type, and PD-L1 expression; multivariate Logistic regression results showed that PT, NEUT%, P-LCR, EOS%, smoking status, pathological type, and PD-L1 expression fitted best (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A and B). Logistic and Lasso models had AIC values of 263.63 and 261.97, respectively, so seven variables in the Lasso regression were selected as final predictors. According to the variables mentioned above, we constructed a prognostic model while drawing a nomogram to predict the probability of MPR in NSCLC receiving NACI (Fig. <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Variable exploration and screening by Lasso regression. (A) Lasso regression model was employed to identify potential parameters from 43 variables, as evidenced by their coefficient profiles in this cohort. (B) Partial likelihood deviance analysis was constructed to determine significant combination of these variables using the Lasso regression model. The red dots represent detailed partial likelihood of deviance values while gray lines indicate standard error.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="js9-110-2275-g003.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Nomogram was developed based on clinical-pathological factors and peripheral blood parameters at baseline to predict probability of MPR. EOS, eosinophilic cells; LUSC, lung squamous cell carcinoma; NEUT, prothrombin time; PD-L1, programmed death ligand-1; PT, prothrombin time; P-LCR, platelet large cell ratio.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="js9-110-2275-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Model evaluation and validation</title><p>First of all, the calibration curves of the nomogram model demonstrated a satisfied agreement between the predicted and observed results in this cohort with a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value of 0.942, implying an almost identical probability to the actual one (Fig. <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>A). The ROC curve showed an AUC value of 0.775 (95% CI: 0.712&#8211;0.838), which indicated fine discrimination (Fig. <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>B). The decision curve showed that, especially when the threshold probability was &gt;0.2, the positive net benefit of this model for MPR probability prediction was more obvious compared with the &#8216;all&#8217; or &#8216;none&#8217; scheme (Fig. <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>C). In this study, 10-fold cross-validation was used to evaluate the repeatability of the model. We describes the mean values of various indicators of the model after all datasets (AUC=0.775) and 200 repeated internal validation in Table S4 (Supplemental Digital Content 2, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755</ext-link>) (AUC=0.746). A total of 40 patients were included as the validation cohort from June 2023 to October 2023. The model also showed good calibration, discrimination (AUC=0.835), and clinical decision-making ability in the validation set (Fig. <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>D-F and Table S4, Supplemental Digital Content 2, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755</ext-link>).</p><fig position="float" id="F5" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Evaluation of the effectiveness of the nomogram. (A) Calibration plots of the combination model. (B) The ROC curves of the combination model. (C) Decision curve analysis of the combination model. (D) Calibration plots in the external validation dataset. (E) The ROC curves in the external validation dataset. (F) Decision curve analysis in the external validation dataset.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="js9-110-2275-g005.jpg"/></fig><p>In addition, we used the seven variables described above to construct a predictive model using ORR as an outcome measure in a cohort of 201 patients who underwent radiographic assessment. At the same time, we plotted ROC curve (AUC=0.705, Fig S4a, Supplemental Digital Content 2, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755</ext-link>) and histogram of difference in total point score (TPS) between ORR group and non-ORR group (Fig S4b, Supplemental Digital Content 2, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755</ext-link>), although they were less powerful than the above model, they still showed some predictive ability.</p></sec><sec><title>Comparison with different nomograms</title><p>We used AUC values to compare the discriminatory power of different models or variables in predicting MPR, as displayed in Figure <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>. The AUC values of the models constructed by our combined model, clinical-pathological variables and peripheral blood indicators were 0.775, 0.600, and 0.755, respectively, while the AUC values of PD-L1 expression and NLR were 0.648 and 0.582 (Fig. <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>A and B). Meanwhile, our model was compared with other two models, which had been reported as prognostic biomarkers in advanced NSCLC treated with ICIs<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>. The result showed that, the AUC values of CRP combined with LDH, and smoking status combined with NLR were 0.488 and 0.617, respectively (Fig. <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>C).</p><fig position="float" id="F6" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>The contrast of ROC indicating MPR based on different combination models. (A) The comparison between our model with clinical-pathological or peripheral blood indicators alone. (B) The comparison between our model with NLR or PD-L1. (C) The comparison between our model with other two models developed in advanced NSCLC, that is, CRP combined with LDH and NLR combined smoking status, respectively. AUC, the area under the curve; CRP, C-reactive protein; LDH, lactate dehydrogenase; NLR, neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio; PD-L1, programmed death ligand-1.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="js9-110-2275-g006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Performance of the nomogram in stratifying patient risk</title><p>Finally, seven variables were included in the current nomogram, then participants were divided into four groups according to nomogram-based TPS quartiles. In comparison to lower quartile, increased TPS quartiles was correlated with favorable MPR probability (Fig. <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). The MPR percentage across increasing quartiles of TPS were 17.6, 50, 63.5, 82.4%, respectively (Fig. S5, Supplemental Digital Content 2, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/B755</ext-link>).</p><fig position="float" id="F7" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>The nomogram-based total score was presented a Sankey diagram. EOS, eosinophilic cells; LUSC, lung squamous cell carcinoma; MPR, major pathological response; NEUT, prothrombin time; PT, prothrombin time; P-LCR, platelet large cell ratio; PD-L1, programmed death ligand-1; TPS, total point score.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="js9-110-2275-g007.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Typical case image</title><p>Case 1: A 47-year-old male LUSC patient with a TPS of 126.84, cT2N2M0 in the upper lobe of the right lung, derived 70% residual viable tumor cell after three cycles of NACI and radical resection (camrelizumab+carboplatin+albumin-bound paclitaxel) (Fig. <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>A&#8211;D).</p><fig position="float" id="F8" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>A&#8211;D A 47-year-old male LUSC patient with PD-L1 expression=1%, PT=11.7s, NEUT%=69.8%, P-LCR=36%, EOS%=0.8%, without smoking history. (A) A mass in the upper lobe of the right lung near the hilar region, with obstructive pulmonary atelectasis. (B) Enlarged lymph nodes at 4R station. (C) LUSC confirmed by tracheoscopic biopsy (100&#215;). (D) Surgical specimens demonstrated 70% residual viable tumor in tumor bed (40&#215;). E&#8211;H A 60-year-old male LUSC patient with PD-L1 expression=20%, PT=11.5s, NEUT%=54.8%, P-LCR=29.5%, EOS%=5.4%, with tobacco use. (A) A mass in the upper lobe of the left lung near the hilar region. (B) Enlarged lymph nodes at six station. (C) LUSC confirmed by tracheoscopic biopsy (100&#215;). (D) Surgical specimens demonstrated cPR (40&#215;).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="js9-110-2275-g008.jpg"/></fig><p>Case 2: A 60-year-old male LUSC patient with a TPS of 181.37, cT2N2M0 in the upper lobe of the left lung achieved MPR after three cycles of NACI and radical resection (sintilimab+carboplatin+albumin-bound paclitaxel) (Fig. <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>E&#8211;H).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The use of ICI therapy is considered as a significant advance in the treatment of operable NSCLC and has been shown to be more effective than conventional chemotherapy. However, its benefits are limited to certain patients due to the lack of comprehensive biomarkers. Consequently, it is crucial to find biomarkers that can predict patients who will derive the greatest benefit from NACI. The majority of the patients in the study had stage III disease and seemed to benefit from the treatment approach with the same level, in terms of MPR percentage, compared to patients with stage I&#8211;II disease, highlighting the importance of this therapeutic pattern for patients with more locally advanced disease and worse prognosis.</p><p>In addition to assess the efficacy and safety of NACI in real world, our study investigated the pretreatment factors associated with MPR to establish and verify a risk-scoring system. Following a broad analysis of 43 easily accessible clinical-pathological and laboratory parameters, finally, we developed a novel combined model with good discrimination to screen patients who might benefit from therapeutic strategy. In this study, we identified seven factors, including PD-L1, pathology, smoking, PT, NEUT%, P-LCR, and EOS% in the final predictive model. As a classic predictor of immunotherapy, PD-L1 expression levels in the tumor tissue were included in this model. LUSC exhibited superior response rates compared to non-LUSC (MPR 42.1 vs.57.7%). The main histological subgroups of NSCLC, such as LUAD and LUSC, have been found to behave differently in neoadjuvant circumstances, due to different immune microenvironment profiles<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup>.</p><p>In our study, it was very interesting to find another significant correlation between PT and MPR. The coagulation and fibrinolysis processes in patients are often associated with tumor invasion, metastasis, and ultimately poorer outcomes. Hypercoagulability is a sign of a more aggressive phenotype. Higher levels of D-dimer, fibrinogen, and platelet count in the blood are linked to a worse prognosis in NSCLC<sup><xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup>. In summary, PT is a novel independent biomarker for predicting the response to NACI and should be evaluated in future studies to confirm its prognostic significance in operable NSCLC.</p><p>Additionally, we found that smoking is an actionable biomarker for predicting MPR with NACI. Similar results have been reported in advanced NSCLC<sup><xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup>. Moreover, in one study, smoking signature performed better than PD-L1 expression in predicting the pathological response in a neoadjuvant cohort, which might be explained by increased TMB and/or MSI resulted from tobacco exposure<sup><xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup>. Tobacco smoking has recently been demonstrated to induce specific activation of the ADAM12+ Treg subset, which interact with exhausted T cells in the tumor immune environment<sup><xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup>. Yin <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.<sup><xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup> study pointed out that after tobacco exposure, patients with a smoking history exhibited higher levels of TLS via the CCL21-dependent mechanism, while serum CCL21 was identified as a reliable biomarker for predicting more benefits from immunotherapy. The findings of current study also validated that smoking history was a promising predictor for MPR to NACI. Smoking status, which is easily available information, could be used as a predictor in clinical practice to select better treatment in the neoadjuvant setting for patients with operable NSCLC.</p><p>We found that the results of a few laboratory tests derived from cytometry were also correlated with our endpoint in this cohort, which included NEUT%, P-LCR, and EOS%. The importance of neutrophils in the immune response against cancer has been emphasized in recent years, although much remains unknown about their specific role. A large number of studies have reported that relative or absolute increases in neutrophil counts are associated with negative outcomes in advanced cancers treated with PD-1 inhibitors<sup><xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup>. As we expected, the percentage of neutrophil count maintained its significance in both Logistic and Lasso models. Eosinophils are a minor population of granulocytes that are more frequently explored in asthma and allergic disorders. Nonetheless, eosinophils infiltrate multiple solid tumor types and modulate tumor progression either directly by interacting with tumor cells or indirectly by shaping the tumor microenvironment<sup><xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="R54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></sup>. Across various types of cancer, several authors have demonstrated an association between blood eosinophils and ICI antibodies, however, the data exist in NSCLC was limited. The authors stated that there was a correlation between elevated blood eosinophils and a favorable clinical or radiological outcome<sup><xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="R56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup>. To our knowledge, this is the first study to report the role of blood eosinophils in predicting MPR in patients with resectable NSCLC receiving NACI. Clinical data suggests that raised blood eosinophils may reflect a favorable outcome in patients treated with ICIs for advanced NSCLC. Functional studies and more stringent clinical research are needed to further elucidate the role of eosinophils in lung cancer and their potential value as a biomarker. The P-LCR refers to the ratio of platelets with a volume greater than 12 femtolitre (fL) to the total platelet count. The activity and enzymes of larger platelets are more active compared to small platelets, and the release of thrombotic and inflammatory agents from them can lead to specific complications related to diseases<sup><xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></sup>. Previous studies have explored the use of platelet parameters to predict complications like diabetic kidney disease in type 2 diabetes, major adverse cardiovascular events in myocardial infarction<sup><xref rid="R58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="R59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup>. Although, platelet&#8217;s role was involved in immune system and surveillance, platelet indices has not been explored in cancer immunotherapy.</p><p>However, attention should be paid to the limitations of the present study. Initially, due to the inherent nature of retrospective study, selection bias was inevitable, although we reported the largest real world cohort to date. Hence, a series of large, multicenter and prospective studies should be conducted to verify our proposed model. Secondly, although 10-fold 200 cross-validations and time-series external validations were used to validate the model, data from other centers were indeed required to check its stability. Thirdly, the endpoint in this study was MPR, which was a surrogate indicator of DFS and OS. We will continue to follow up and look forward to the long-term results.</p><p>In conclusion, the nomogram constructed on readily available clinical-pathological characteristics and serum parameters was a simple and cost-effective predictive tool for patients with operable treated with NACI. The combined model achieved an AUC of 0.775 demonstrating a good consistency between the predicted and observed results. Although the efficiency of the proposed model is not sufficient as a direct determinant of MPR, it may help physicians potentially recognize NSCLC who might be sensitive to NACI.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>This observational cohort study was conducted at a single center and adhered to the ethical guidelines outlined in the Declaration of Helsinki. The study was approved by the Ethics Committee of Beijing Chest Hospital, Capital Medical University (Approval Number: YNLX-2022-015).</p></sec><sec><title>Consent</title><p>The study was approved by our institution&#8217;s review board (Approval Number: YNLX-2022-015). Due to the observational study design, the ethics committee approved a waiver of written informed consent.</p></sec><sec><title>Sources of funding</title><p>This study was supported by the Beijing Municipal Administration of Hospitals Incubating Program and Beijing Municipal Science and Technology Commission, Tongzhou Technology Project (code: PX2024058).</p></sec><sec><title>Author contribution</title><p>M.H.: conceptualization, data curation, formal analysis, and writing &#8211; original draft; X.L.: formal analysis, methodology, and writing &#8211; original draft; H.L.: formal analysis, investigation, and writing &#8211; original draft; B.L.: software and supervision; Q.W.: methodology and resources; L.T.: investigation and software; H.L.: supervision and validation; N.C.: resources, visualization, and writing &#8211; review and editing; S.H.: supervision and validation; Y.H.: resources and project administration; K.S.: methodology and project administration; C.L.: resources and supervision; H.Z.: conceptualization, methodology, resources, and validation; Z.L.: conceptualization and writing &#8211; review and editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest disclosure</title><p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></sec><sec><title>Research registration unique identifying number (UIN)</title><p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Name of the registry: Research Registry.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Unique identifying number or registration ID: researchregistry9649.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Hyperlink to your specific registration (must be publicly accessible and will be checked):<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.researchregistry.com/browse-theregistry#home/registrationdetails/653dd4a2a2ef180027f90e80/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.researchregistry.com/browse-theregistry#home/registrationdetails/653dd4a2a2ef180027f90e80/</ext-link>.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec><title>Guarantor</title><p>Tongmei Zhang.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The corresponding author can provide the datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study upon reasonable request.</p></sec><sec><title>Provenance and peer review</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="SD1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="js9-110-2275-s001.docx" id="d66e1504" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="js9-110-2275-s002.docx" id="d66e1505" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="equal"><p>Mingming Hu and Xiaomi Li have made the same contribution to this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>Sponsorships or competing interests that may be relevant to content are disclosed at the end of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="supplementary-material"><p>Supplemental Digital Content is available for this article. Direct URL citations are provided in the HTML and PDF versions of this article on the journal&#8217;s website, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.lww.com/international-journal-of-surgery" ext-link-type="uri">www.lww.com/international-journal-of-surgery</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal"><p>Published online 23 January 2024</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagle</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer statistics, 2023.</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>48</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36633525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3322/caac.21763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedlaender</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Addeo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Targeted therapies in early stage NSCLC: hype or hope?</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>6329</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32878298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms21176329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7504271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Donington</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Progress in the management of early-stage non-small cell lung cancer in 2017</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Oncol</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>767</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>778</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29654928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jtho.2018.04.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghadimi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hofheinz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Multimodal treatment of rectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Dtsch Arztebl Int</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>119</volume>:<fpage>570</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>580</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35791271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3238/arztebl.m2022.0254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9743213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Adjuvant immunotherapy in early-stage resectable non-small cell lung cancer: a new milestone</article-title>. <source>Front Oncol</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1063183</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36776323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fonc.2023.1063183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9909200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Provencio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadal</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Insa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Neoadjuvant chemotherapy and nivolumab in resectable non-small-cell lung cancer (NADIM): an open-label, multicentre, single-arm, phase 2 trial</article-title>. <source>The Lancet Oncology</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1413</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1422</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32979984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1470-2045(20)30453-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Neoadjuvant PD-1 inhibitor (Sintilimab) in NSCLC</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Oncol</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>816</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>826</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32036071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jtho.2020.01.017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Neoadjuvant sintilimab and chemotherapy for resectable stage IIIA non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>114</volume>:<fpage>949</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>958</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35176262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.athoracsur.2022.01.039</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forde</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spicer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Neoadjuvant nivolumab plus chemotherapy in resectable lung cancer</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>386</volume>:<fpage>1973</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1985</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35403841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMoa2202170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9844511</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Does major pathological response after neoadjuvant Immunotherapy in resectable non-small-cell lung cancers predict prognosis? a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Int J Surg</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>2794</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2807</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37247009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/JS9.0000000000000496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10498860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waser</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schweikert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>1243P Pathologic response as early endpoint for survival following neoadjuvant therapy (NEO-AT) in resectable non-small cell lung cancer (rNSCLC): Systematic literature review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>S806</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Menzies</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amaria</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rozeman</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pathological response and survival with neoadjuvant therapy in melanoma: a pooled analysis from the International Neoadjuvant Melanoma Consortium (INMC)</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>301</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>309</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33558722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41591-020-01188-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Expert consensus on neoadjuvant immunotherapy for non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Transl Lung Cancer Res</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>2696</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2715</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33489828</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.21037/tlcr-2020-63</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7815365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Canzoniero</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Peripheral blood immune cell dynamics reflect antitumor immune responses and predict clinical response to immunotherapy</article-title>. <source>J Immunother Cancer</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e004688</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35688557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/jitc-2022-004688</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9189831</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comprehensive 18F-FDG PET-based radiomics in elevating the pathological response to neoadjuvant immunochemotherapy for resectable stage III non-small-cell lung cancer: a pilot study</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>994917</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36466929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2022.994917</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9713843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dynamic alteration in SULmax predicts early pathological tumor response and short-term prognosis in non-small cell lung cancer treated with neoadjuvant immunochemotherapy</article-title>. <source>Front Bioeng Biotechnol</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1010672</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36277407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fbioe.2022.1010672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9582780</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Immune-related histologic phenotype in pretreatment tumour biopsy predicts the efficacy of neoadjuvant anti-PD-1 treatment in squamous lung cancer</article-title>. <source>BMC Med</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>403</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36280845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12916-022-02609-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9594940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>She</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Deep learning for predicting major pathological response to neoadjuvant chemoimmunotherapy in non-small cell lung cancer: a multicentre study</article-title>. <source>EBioMedicine</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>104364</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36395737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ebiom.2022.104364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9672965</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A support vector machine based on liquid immune profiling predicts major pathological response to chemotherapy plus anti-PD-1/PD-L1 as a neoadjuvant treatment for patients with resectable non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>778276</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35095850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2021.778276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8797141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haoran</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Utility of (18)F-FDG PET/CT uptake values in predicting response to neoadjuvant chemoimmunotherapy in resectable non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Lung Cancer</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>178</volume>:<fpage>20</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36764154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lungcan.2023.02.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Advances in efficacy prediction and monitoring of neoadjuvant immunotherapy for non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Front Oncol</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1145128</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37265800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fonc.2023.1145128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10229830</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marcos</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Everaert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Damme</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Circulating immune cell dynamics as outcome predictors for immunotherapy in non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>J Immunother Cancer</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e007023</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37536935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/jitc-2023-007023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10401220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubenich</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omizzollo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Tumor-neutrophil crosstalk promotes in vitro and in vivo glioblastoma progression</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1183465</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37292196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1183465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10244780</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sauerbrei</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McShane</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>REMARK guidelines for tumour biomarker study reporting: a remarkable history</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>128</volume>:<fpage>443</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>445</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36476656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41416-022-02046-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9938190</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prognostic nomogram on clinicopathologic features and serum indicators for advanced non-small cell lung cancer patients treated with anti-PD-1 inhibitors</article-title>. <source>Ann Transl Med</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1078</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33145297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.21037/atm-20-4297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7575979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorentzen</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjeldsen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehrnrooth</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term follow-up of anti-PD-1 naive patients with metastatic melanoma treated with IDO/PD-L1 targeting peptide vaccine and nivolumab</article-title>. <source>J Immunother Cancer</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e006755</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37217243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/jitc-2023-006755</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10230976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riedl</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barth</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brueckl</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>C-reactive protein (CRP) levels in immune checkpoint inhibitor response and progression in advanced non-small cell lung cancer: a bi-center study</article-title>. <source>Cancers (Basel)</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/cancers12082319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7464328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32824580</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Inflammation-nutritional markers of peripheral blood could predict survival in advanced non-small-cell lung cancer patients treated with PD-1 inhibitors</article-title>. <source>Thorac Cancer</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>2914</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2923</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34581010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/1759-7714.14152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8563162</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanbour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Serum immune mediators as novel predictors of response to anti-PD-1/PD-L1 therapy in non-small cell lung cancer patients with high tissue-PD-L1 expression</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1157100</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37256148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1157100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10225547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanna</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Temin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Therapy for stage IV non-small-cell lung cancer without driver alterations: ASCO and OH (CCO) joint guideline update</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>1608</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1632</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31990617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JCO.19.03022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldstraw</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chansky</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The IASLC Lung Cancer Staging Project: proposals for the revision of the TNM stage groupings in the forthcoming (seventh) edition of the TNM Classification of malignant tumours</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Oncol</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>706</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>714</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17762336</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/JTO.0b013e31812f3c1a</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisenhauer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Therasse</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bogaerts</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>New response evaluation criteria in solid tumours: revised RECIST guideline (version 1.1)</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>228</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>247</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19097774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ejca.2008.10.026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Travis</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dacic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wistuba</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>IASLC multidisciplinary recommendations for pathologic assessment of lung cancer resection specimens after neoadjuvant therapy</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Oncol</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>709</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>740</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32004713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jtho.2020.01.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8173999</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamashige</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arquilla</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Common terminology criteria for adverse events v3.0 (CTCAE)</article-title>. <source>Principl Pract Clin Trial Med</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>461</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>533</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>C-reactive protein and lactate dehydrogenase serum levels potentially predict the response to checkpoint inhibitors in patients with advanced non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Dis</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1892</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1900</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37197527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.21037/jtd-23-240</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10183533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prognostic value of hematologic parameters in advanced non-small cell lung cancer patients receiving anti-PD-1 inhibitors</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1003581</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36341410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2022.1003581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9631308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Interim analysis of the efficiency and safety of neoadjuvant PD-1 inhibitor (sintilimab) combined with chemotherapy (nab-paclitaxel and carboplatin) in potentially resectable stage IIIA/IIIB non-small cell lung cancer: a single-arm, phase 2 trial</article-title>. <source>J Cancer Res Clin Oncol</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>149</volume>:<fpage>819</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>831</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35192053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00432-021-03896-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11797525</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy, safety, and biomarker analysis of neoadjuvant camrelizumab and apatinib in patients with resectable NSCLC: a phase 2 clinical trial</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Oncol</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>780</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>791</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36870519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jtho.2023.02.019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Socinski</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Obasaju</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gandara</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinicopathologic features of advanced squamous NSCLC</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Oncol</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1411</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1422</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27296106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jtho.2016.05.024</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Serum fibrinogen is an independent prognostic factor in operable nonsmall cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>133</volume>:<fpage>2720</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2725</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23716344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ijc.28284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Preoperative plasma D-dimer levels predict survival in patients with operable non-small cell lung cancer independently of venous thromboembolism</article-title>. <source>Eur J Surg Oncol</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>951</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>956</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23810331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ejso.2013.06.008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandfeld-Paulsen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aggerholm-Pedersen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winther-Larsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pretreatment platelet count is a prognostic marker in lung cancer: a Danish registry-based cohort study</article-title>. <source>Clin Lung Cancer</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>175</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>183</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36646586</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cllc.2022.12.012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakahama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Izumi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshimoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of smoking history on the effectiveness of immune-checkpoint inhibitor therapy for non-small cell lung cancer: analysis of real-world data</article-title>. <source>Anticancer Res</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>2185</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2197</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37097681</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.21873/anticanres.16381</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Predictive value of oncogenic driver subtype, programmed death-1 ligand (PD-L1) score, and smoking status on the efficacy of PD-1/PD-L1 inhibitors in patients with oncogene-driven non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>125</volume>:<fpage>1038</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1049</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30548240</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cncr.31871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Tobacco exposure and immunotherapy response in PD-L1 positive lung cancer patients</article-title>. <source>Lung Cancer</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>150</volume>:<fpage>159</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>163</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33171404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lungcan.2020.10.023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of smoking status with efficacy of first-line immune checkpoint inhibitors in advanced non-small cell lung cancers: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>J Cancer</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>364</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>372</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35069886</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7150/jca.65374</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8771515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abuhelwa</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKinnon</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Smoking and immunotherapy efficacy in lung cancer by PDL1 subgroups: an individual participant data meta-analysis of atezolizumab clinical trials: Smoking and immunotherapy efficacy in lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>160</volume>:<fpage>279</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>281</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34862081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ejca.2021.10.020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Smoking signature is superior to programmed death-ligand 1 expression in predicting pathological response to neoadjuvant immunotherapy in lung cancer patients</article-title>. <source>Transl Lung Cancer Res</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>3807</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3822</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34733630</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.21037/tlcr-21-734</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8512473</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Exposure to tobacco smoking induces a subset of activated tumor-resident tregs in non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Transl Oncol</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>101261</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34768099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.tranon.2021.101261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8591366</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Tobacco exposure primes the secretion of CCL21 positively associated with tertiary lymphoid structure and response to immunotherapy</article-title>. <source>J Immunother Cancer</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e006939</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37369391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/jitc-2023-006939</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10410842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amulic</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Neutrophil phenotypes and functions in cancer: a consensus statement</article-title>. <source>J Experiment Med</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>219</volume>:<fpage>e20220011</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1084/jem.20220011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9086501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35522219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The role of neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio in predicting pathological response for resectable non-small cell lung cancer treated with neoadjuvant chemotherapy combined with PD-1 checkpoint inhibitors</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>1017</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1029</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34809413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4143/crt.2021.1007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9582471</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaffari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezaei</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Eosinophils in the tumor microenvironment: implications for cancer immunotherapy</article-title>. <source>J Transl Med</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>551</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37587450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12967-023-04418-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10433623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grisaru-Tal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Itan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klion</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A new dawn for eosinophils in the tumour microenvironment</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>594</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>607</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32678342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41568-020-0283-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sibille</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corhay</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Eosinophils and lung cancer: from bench to bedside</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>5066</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35563461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms23095066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9101877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanizaki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haratani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Peripheral blood biomarkers associated with clinical outcome in non-small cell lung cancer patients treated with nivolumab</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Oncol</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>105</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29170120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jtho.2017.10.030</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Halawi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prognostic value of evaluating platelet role, count and indices in laboratory diagnosis of different types of solid malignancies</article-title>. <source>Pak J Biol Sci</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>100</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>105</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35233997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3923/pjbs.2022.100.105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Becirovic</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ljuca</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becirovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prognostic value of decrease in mean platelet volume, platelet distribution width, and platelet-large cell ratio for major adverse cardiovascular events after myocardial infarction without ST-segment elevation: an observational study</article-title>. <source>Biomol Biomed</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>866</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>872</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37212038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.17305/bb.2023.9178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10494847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Predicting diabetic kidney disease for type 2 diabetes mellitus by machine learning in the real world: a multicenter retrospective study</article-title>. <source>Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1184190</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37469989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fendo.2023.1184190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10352831</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>