<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Addiction</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Addiction</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">319</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">nihpa</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Addiction (Abingdon, England)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0965-2140</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1360-0443</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>NIHPA Author Manuscripts</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11156545</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11156545.319</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11156545</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11156545</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id">NIHMS1983056</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38519819</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/add.16473</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHMS1983056</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHPA1983056</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">319</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Target trial emulation for comparative effectiveness research with observational data: Promise and challenges for studying medications for opioid use disorder</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1707-0761</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Christine</surname><given-names initials="PJ">Paul J.</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lodi</surname><given-names initials="S">Sara</given-names></name><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names initials="HE">Heather E.</given-names></name><xref rid="A4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bovell-Ammon</surname><given-names initials="B">Benjamin</given-names></name><xref rid="A5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names initials="S">Shapei</given-names></name><xref rid="A6" ref-type="aff">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernson</surname><given-names initials="D">Dana</given-names></name><xref rid="A7" ref-type="aff">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Novo</surname><given-names initials="P">Patricia</given-names></name><xref rid="A8" ref-type="aff">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names initials="JD">Joshua D.</given-names></name><xref rid="A9" ref-type="aff">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rotrosen</surname><given-names initials="J">John</given-names></name><xref rid="A8" ref-type="aff">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liebschutz</surname><given-names initials="J">Jane</given-names></name><xref rid="A10" ref-type="aff">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walley</surname><given-names initials="AY">Alexander Y.</given-names></name><xref rid="A6" ref-type="aff">6</xref><xref rid="A7" ref-type="aff">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larochelle</surname><given-names initials="MR">Marc R.</given-names></name><xref rid="A6" ref-type="aff">6</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Section of General Internal Medicine, Department of Medicine, University of Colorado School of Medicine, Aurora, CO, USA</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of General Internal Medicine, Denver Health and Hospital Authority, Denver, CO, USA</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Biostatistics, Boston University School of Public Health, Boston, MA, USA</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Pediatrics, Boston Medical Center and Boston University Chobanian &amp; Avedisian School of Medicine, Boston, MA, USA</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Departments of Medicine and Healthcare Delivery and Population Sciences, Baystate Health and University of Massachusetts Chan Medical School - Baystate, Springfield, MA, USA</aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Section of General Internal Medicine, Department of Medicine, Boston Medical Center and Boston University Chobanian &amp; Avedisian School of Medicine, Boston, MA, USA</aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Department of Public Health, Commonwealth of Massachusetts, Boston, MA, USA</aff><aff id="A8"><label>8</label>Department of Psychiatry, New York University Grossman School of Medicine, New York, NY, USA</aff><aff id="A9"><label>9</label>Department of Population Health, New York University Grossman School of Medicine, New York, NY, USA</aff><aff id="A10"><label>10</label>Division of General Internal Medicine, Center for Research on Health Care, Department of Medicine, University of Pittsburgh, UPMC, Pittsburgh, PA, USA</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="con" id="FN1"><p id="P1">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</p><p id="P2"><bold>Paul J. Christine:</bold> Conceptualization (equal); formal analysis (equal); investigation (equal); methodology (equal); writing&#8212;original draft (lead); writing&#8212;review and editing (lead). <bold>Sara Lodi:</bold> Conceptualization (equal); formal analysis (equal); funding acquisition (supporting); investigation (equal); methodology (equal); software (equal); supervision (equal); validation (equal); writing&#8212;original draft (supporting); writing&#8212;review and editing (supporting). <bold>Heather E. Hsu:</bold> Conceptualization (equal); formal analysis (equal); investigation (equal); methodology (equal); writing&#8212;original draft (supporting); writing&#8212;review and editing (supporting). <bold>Benjamin Bovell-Ammon:</bold> Conceptualization (equal); formal analysis (equal); investigation (equal); methodology (equal); writing&#8212;original draft (supporting); writing&#8212;review and editing (supporting). <bold>Shapei Yan:</bold> Data curation (equal); formal analysis (equal); investigation (equal); methodology (equal); software (equal); validation (equal); writing&#8212;original draft (supporting); writing&#8212;review and editing (supporting). <bold>Dana Bernson:</bold> Conceptualization (equal); data curation (equal); investigation (equal); methodology (equal); resources (equal); validation (equal); writing&#8212;original draft (supporting); writing&#8212;review and editing (supporting). <bold>Patricia Novo:</bold> Data curation (equal); project administration (equal); resources (equal); writing&#8212;original draft (supporting); writing&#8212;review and editing (supporting). <bold>Joshua D. Lee:</bold> Conceptualization (equal); investigation (equal); methodology (equal); resources (equal); validation (equal); writing&#8212;original draft (supporting); writing&#8212;review and editing (supporting). <bold>John Rotrosen:</bold> Conceptualization (equal); investigation (equal); methodology (equal); resources (equal); validation (equal); writing&#8212;original draft (supporting); writing&#8212;review and editing (supporting). <bold>Jane Liebschutz:</bold> Conceptualization (equal); investigation (equal); methodology (equal); writing&#8212;original draft (supporting); writing&#8212;review and editing (supporting). <bold>Alexander Y. Walley:</bold> Conceptualization (equal); investigation (equal); methodology (equal); writing&#8212;original draft (supporting); writing&#8212;review and editing (supporting). <bold>Marc Larochelle:</bold> Conceptualization (equal); data curation (equal); formal analysis (equal); funding acquisition (lead); investigation (lead); methodology (equal); project administration (lead); resources (lead); software (equal); supervision (lead); validation (equal); writing&#8212;original draft (supporting); writing&#8212;review and editing (supporting).</p></fn><corresp id="CR1"><bold>Correspondence</bold>: Paul J. Christine, Section of General Internal Medicine, Department of Medicine, University of Colorado School of Medicine, 12631 East 17th Avenue8th Floor, Academic Office 1, Mailstop B180Aurora, CO 80045, USA. <email>paul.christine@cuanschutz.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>119</volume><issue>7</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">464362</issue-id><fpage>1313</fpage><lpage>1321</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="nihms-submitted"><date><day>06</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-07-01 00:25:30.177"><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="nihms-1983056.pdf"/><abstract id="ABS1"><p id="P3">Medications for opioid use disorder (MOUD) increase retention in care and decrease mortality during active treatment; however, information about the comparative effectiveness of different forms of MOUD is sparse. Observational comparative effectiveness studies are subject to many types of bias; a robust framework to minimize bias would improve the quality of comparative effectiveness evidence. This paper discusses the use of target trial emulation as a framework to conduct comparative effectiveness studies of MOUD with administrative data. Using examples from our planned research project comparing buprenorphine-naloxone and extended-release naltrexone with respect to the rates of MOUD discontinuation, we provide a primer on the challenges and approaches to employing target trial emulation in the study of MOUD.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>causal inference</kwd><kwd>emulated trial</kwd><kwd>observational research</kwd><kwd>opioids</kwd><kwd>target trial emulation</kwd><kwd>substance use</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p id="P4">More than half a million individuals died of opioid overdoses in the United States in the two decades leading up to 2020 [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Despite this sobering statistic, one reason for optimism is the availability of highly effective medications for opioid use disorder (MOUD) [<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. As MOUD options increase, high-quality comparative effectiveness research would aid decision-making by patients, clinicians and policy makers.</p><p id="P5">RCTs are considered the gold standard to estimate the comparative effectiveness and safety of interventions, but are not always feasible because of financial, ethical or other constraints. Increasing types and availability of administrative datasets permit more rapid and less expensive observational comparative effectiveness research. Their large size also allows for easier study of relatively rare outcomes such as opioid overdose. However, observational studies are subject to several biases that limit causal inference.</p><p id="P6">Target trial emulation is a framework for observational comparative effectiveness research where researchers emulate the design and analysis of an RCT with the goal of avoiding biases resulting from poor observational study design [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. It is not a statistical method (a common misconception), but rather an approach to the analysis of observational data that minimizes biases arising from study design decisions. In this way, target trial emulation is more about the thinking that researchers must do before using sophisticated statistical methods.</p><p id="P7">As described by Hern&#225;n and Robins [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], the target trial emulation approach requires two steps. First, researchers articulate the causal question of interest and design or identify a hypothetical, or actual, RCT to answer that question, that is, the &#8216;target trial&#8217;. This involves pre-specifying the following key target trial components: eligibility criteria, treatment strategies, treatment assignment, time zero and start of follow-up, outcomes, causal contrasts (intention-to-treat and/or per-protocol effects) and the statistical analysis plan [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Second, the researchers attempt to emulate the design of the target trial as closely as possible using observational data. This process allows researchers to understand the potential limitations of the data, including imperfect proxy variables (variables that approximate the variable of interest), and incomplete data on treatments, outcomes and confounders. With the limitations clearly delineated, researchers can analyze and interpret the observational data transparently, noting areas where they were and were not able to successfully emulate the protocol of the target trial.</p><p id="P8">Although target trial emulations are increasingly popular [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], applications in addiction research remain rare. Our goal is to expand on existing introductory resources on target trial emulation [<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] by providing addiction researchers with examples of how the target trial approach may be applied to comparative effective studies of MOUD and highlighting common methodologic challenges for the field. As a motivating example, we describe a planned target trial emulation to compare retention rates for buprenorphine-naloxone (BUP-NX) versus extended-release naltrexone (XR-NTX) following medically managed opioid withdrawal, emulating the X:BOT RCT using a population-level administrative data warehouse in Massachusetts [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. These data, known as the Massachusetts Public Health Data Warehouse (PHD), include longitudinally linked records from multiple state and local sources, including the All-Payer Claims Database, the Bureau of Substance Addiction Services, the Registry of Vital Records and Statistics and the Prescription Monitoring Program. The X:BOT study was an open-label, randomized controlled, comparative effectiveness trial comparing BUP-NX and XR-NTX with respect to 24-week opioid relapse-free survival after discharge from medically managed opioid withdrawal treatment.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>APPLYING TARGET TRIAL EMULATION TO MOUD</title><p id="P9">For the proposed study used throughout this article as an example, our objective is to emulate a target trial using the Massachusetts PHD and benchmark results to a reanalysis of the X:BOT RCT when analyzed using a harmonized protocol. Below, we discuss the key steps for emulating the X:BOT target trial, which is summarized in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> with full details in our online protocol [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><sec id="S3"><title>Specifying the causal question of interest</title><p id="P10">The first step of a target trial emulation is articulating a causal question of interest that is specific and theoretically testable as a RCT. For our comparative effectiveness study, the causal question of interest is whether 24-week retention on MOUD is greater for BUP-NX versus XR-NTX for individuals discharged from inpatient medically managed opioid withdrawal treatment (MMOW), commonly referred to as &#8216;detox&#8217;.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Choosing eligibility criteria</title><p id="P11">Eligibility criteria determine who can be included in a study and how the results generalize to the broader patient population. Eligibility decisions balance tradeoffs between &#8216;real-world&#8217; representation and study participation. These decisions may be particularly complicated for studies of MOUD. Because of structural stigma, criminalization and complex comorbid conditions, individuals with opioid use disorder (OUD) are disproportionately unhoused, incarcerated or face other barriers to participating in studies that require regular follow-up. Furthermore, patient experiences, preferences, specifics of drug use and the care delivery model (e.g. office-based buprenorphine or naltrexone versus opioid treatment program-based methadone care in the United States) strongly influence medication acceptability [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In an RCT comparing the effectiveness of different MOUD, participants must be open to receiving any of the medications offered in the study. This flexibility in terms of medication acceptability is often not the case in clinical practice where patients seeking MOUD often have strong preferences for a particular medication and/or care delivery model (more so than is commonly seen with other chronic conditions) [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p id="P12">In our example, the eligibility criteria for the X:BOT trial and our proposed emulation are summarized in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> with full details in our online study protocol [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. We use only pre-treatment information to determine eligibility to avoid selection bias (when the exposure-outcome relationship is biased due to how participants were included in the study) caused by using posttreatment information [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. We first harmonized our inclusion criteria with that of X:BOT, mimicking the age requirements (&#8805;18 years old) and calendar dates (January 2014&#8211;May 2016) of that study. X:BOT required that individuals had a Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders-5 (DSM-5) diagnosis of OUD and had used non-prescribed opioids in the last 30 days, both of which were unavailable in our administrative data and were proxied by including individuals who attended MMOW [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p id="P13">We next sought to harmonize our exclusion criteria with X:BOT, which focused primarily on medical and social complexity that would complicate study participation. Importantly, many exclusion criteria in X:BOT (e.g. serious medical/psychiatric/substance use disorder that would prevent the participant from completing the study) were based on the assessment and judgement of a study physician at time of enrollment. As similar assessments do not exist in our administrative data, we proxied these exclusion criteria by identifying comorbid conditions using International Classification of Diseases (ICD) diagnostic codes from the All-Payer Claims Data. This use of proxy variables as a substitute for clinical judgement (e.g. ICD diagnosis of psychosis in the prior 6 months in administrative data vs a physician&#8217;s assessment of a psychiatric condition that would compromise study participation in X:BOT) might result in lower accuracy in the administrative data.</p><p id="P14">The biggest challenge in harmonizing the eligibility criteria was related to the acceptability of treatment. X:BOT enrolled individuals who were interested in initiating treatment with either an opioid agonist or antagonist. Interest in naltrexone and buprenorphine is not observable in our administrative data (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). To address this issue, we conducted separate analyses of two distinct observable populations: first, all patients discharged from MMOW, and second, individuals who started a medication within 28 days of discharge (see below for further discussion).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Treatment definition</title><p id="P15">Defining treatment groups is an important component of a study protocol and can be complicated. The X:BOT RCT randomized individuals to BUP-NX or XR-NTX for planned 24 weeks of follow-up. Randomization was completed while individuals were still inpatient for MMOW, and the medication could be initiated within 22 weeks of randomization.</p><p id="P16">In our trial emulation, we do not have data on treatment received while in MMOW. We elected to use a grace period of 28 days after MMOW discharge during which individuals could initiate treatment with BUP-NX or XR-NTX. We chose 28 days to balance the competing demands of allowing sufficient time to identify individuals initiating treatment while minimizing time during which outcomes may occur before initiating treatment. To harmonize X:BOT with our emulated trial using administrative data, we applied the same grace period of 28 days to initiate treatment after randomization. We did not specify any target dose, duration or frequency of dosing (for BUP-NX) as part of our treatment definition, although this could certainly be included in a treatment definition if it addressed the causal question of interest.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Treatment assignment</title><p id="P17">In RCTs, treatment is randomly assigned, whereas observational studies lack treatment randomization. RCTs can be analyzed to estimate either the intent-to-treat (ITT) effect, which is the effect of randomization group on the outcome regardless of compliance with the assigned treatment or the per-protocol effect, which is the effect of randomization group on the outcome had all individuals complied with the assigned treatment. Because randomization is not possible in observational studies, observational studies can only emulate the perprotocol analog of the target trial using a similar statistical analysis plan.</p><p id="P18">A key step is specifying the protocol for treatment assignment. For instance, a protocol deviation might be defined as a failure to initiate the assigned treatment and/or as a lack of compliance to the treatment throughout follow-up (e.g. treatment discontinuation). The statistical analyses to estimate the per-protocol effect require adjustment for baseline and post-baseline factors affecting protocol adherence.</p><p id="P19">In our example, X:BOT randomized individuals participating in MMOW to BUP-NX or XR-NTX for planned 24 weeks of follow-up. In the main report of the X:BOT trial, the authors present estimates of the intention-to-treat effect and of the per-protocol effect restricting to the subset of participants who initiated treatment within 22 weeks of randomization [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p id="P20">In the emulated trial based on administrative data, treatment assignment is based on the first receipt of BUP-NX or XR-NTX following discharge from MMOW. Individuals receiving methadone from an opioid treatment program or an opioid analgesic after discharge from MMOW are considered protocol deviations and are ineligible to initiate either BUP-NX or XR-NTX and should be censored at that time. We assume that receipt of oral naltrexone would not impact eligibility to initiate either treatment (see the online study protocol for full discussion).</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Defining the outcome</title><p id="P21">Outcomes measured in RCTs may differ from outcomes available in administrative data. In our example, the primary outcome for X:BOT was time to opioid relapse defined by urine toxicology and self-report. We are unable to identify this outcome in our emulated trial as there is no measure of substance use from self-report or from urine toxicology in our administrative data. As such, we defined the primary outcome in our emulated trial and the X:BOT reanalysis to be time to MOUD discontinuation, a composite endpoint including a &#8805;7-day gap in medication possession (consistent with quality measures on MOUD continuity) [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], readmission to MMOW, incarceration or death. Readmission to MMOW, incarceration and death were regarded as events leading to MOUD discontinuation (during the study period, receipt of MOUD during incarceration in Massachusetts was very rare).</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Defining &#8216;time zero&#8217; and follow-up</title><p id="P22">In RCTs, eligibility determination, treatment assignment and start of follow-up (time zero) occur at the same time. Failure to synchronize these features in an observational study can cause immortal time bias and selection bias [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Take, for example, a study comparing types of MOUD with respect to the risk for opioid overdose. To emulate an RCT, we need to define time zero when patients become eligible for treatment and start follow-up. When should this be? At OUD diagnosis? When initiating MOUD? What about individuals who do not initiate MOUD? Observational studies that begin follow-up before treatment has been assigned can introduce immortal time bias, where fewer outcomes are attributed to a treatment group because only patients who remained alive long enough to initiate the treatment could be assigned to the treatment group [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Similarly, beginning follow-up long after treatment initiation can induce prevalent user bias where those remaining on the medication at the start of follow-up are those most likely to &#8216;succeed&#8217; on treatment and least likely to discontinue [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The emulated trial framework encourages researchers to be thoughtful about defining time zero to guard against bias created by failing to align eligibility, treatment assignment and start of follow-up [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p id="P23">In our example, the X:BOT trial enrolled individuals undergoing MMOW who met the inclusion criteria and were randomized to either XR-NTX or BUP-NX. Eligibility determination, treatment assignment and time zero all occurred at the same time, with any outcomes beginning to accrue to the treatment groups after the day of randomization (even if a patient had not yet started the medication).</p><p id="P24">In our emulated trial using administrative data, we defined two alternative study populations and we found it advantageous to define time zero differently in these two respective analyses (see <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> for a depiction of time zeros comparing X:BOT to our administrative data analyses). In the first analysis, which included all discharges, time zero corresponds to the day of discharge from MMOW. Individuals are considered eligible for treatment with either XR-NTX or BUP-NX at that time and are eventually sorted into one of the treatment arms if they initiate either medication during a 28-day grace period (otherwise they are censored at the end of the grace period). To guard against immortal time bias, we used a method of cloning and censoring where any outcome event occurring in the grace period is attributed to both treatment groups [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. For details of this cloning and censoring procedure including a worked example and statistical code, see the <xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Data S1</xref> and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Data S2</xref>.</p><p id="P25">In our second analysis, which included only patients who initiated treatment, time zero is defined as the day when an individual initiated XR-NTX or BUP-NX during the 28-day grace period after discharge. Cloning and censoring are not needed in this analysis because outcomes can only begin to accrue after an individual has initiated treatment.</p><p id="P26">The difference between these approaches is subtle, but has important implications for what effects we can estimate. The first analysis estimates the effect of XR-NTX versus BUP-NX as the difference in risk of discontinuation under two scenarios, all individuals who were discharged from MMOW started XR-NTX within 28 days of discharge versus all individuals who were discharged from MMOW started BUP-NX within 28 days of discharge. The second analysis estimates the effect of XR-NTX versus BUP-NX as the difference in risk of discontinuation restricting to individuals who decided to initiate one of these medications 28 days after discharge (i.e. the effectiveness of the medications among those who received them).</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Causal contrast</title><p id="P27">The causal contrast of interest refers to what exposure groups will be compared and what treatment effect will be estimated. In our example, using the X:BOT RCT data, we can estimate both an intention-to-treat effect comparing those randomized to BUP-NX versus XR-NTX, and a per-protocol effect comparing those who initiated BUP-NX versus XR-NTX. Because we are unable to randomize individuals in our emulated trial using observational data, we can only calculate the per-protocol effect of initiating treatment based on medication dispensing data. Of note, in comparative effectiveness studies using observational data, the type of administrative pharmacy data available influences the framing of the question and population. For instance, electronic health record data may reflect a prescription for a medication that patient&#8217;s may or may not pick up, whereas pharmacy claims reflect medication dispensing that reached the patient [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="P28">The final step in creating an emulated trial protocol is pre-specifying the statistical analysis plan. In our example, we elected to perform a survival analysis using pooled logistic regression to generate predicted probabilities of MOUD discontinuation comparing patients who initiated BUP-NX versus XR-NTX. We control for confounders selected a priori based on the existing literature and content matter expertise using inverse probability weighting (see Methods and Techniques article by Chan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> for a review of these methods, as well as our online full study protocol for more details) [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="S11"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p id="P29">The target trial emulation approach provides a useful framework for the design and analysis of observational data that can be broadly applied to addiction health services research. By developing a protocol that attempts to mimic a RCT through specifying design decisions including eligibility criteria, time zero for the start of follow-up and treatment assignment, future comparative effectiveness research on MOUD can provide a more robust and standardized evidence base for comparing different forms of MOUD in differing contexts. As highlighted by our own study, emulating the protocol components of a target trial is often challenging, but it provides transparency regarding the limitations of observational data.</p><p id="P30">Target trial emulation may be particularly helpful for the addiction health services research community because of the rapidly changing treatment environment. For instance, RCTs studying the efficacy of MOUD for decreasing opioid-related adverse events were largely completed before the surge in synthetic opioids (e.g. fentanyl) that now constitute much of the street drug supply [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In many locations, treatment with MOUD has become more focused on harm reduction; calling into question how prior effect estimates from RCTs may apply to the current treatment-enrolled population. Target trial emulation provides a framework to help update the evidence base around MOUD using administrative data that may be more representative, lower cost, have more statistical power (particularly for relatively rare outcomes like fatal opioid overdose) and be more rapidly adaptable than some RCTs.</p><p id="P31">Although the target trial emulation approach can help researchers design observational comparative effectiveness studies to minimize various biases, the methods do not eliminate the risk of unmeasured confounding as a challenge. Furthermore, like more typical observational studies, target trial emulation still requires appropriate data analysis, including diligent model specification and assumption checking. Last, target trial emulation for MOUD may not be as straightforward as in other medical applications, as different MOUD options entail not only different medications, but often entirely different types of care delivery (e.g. opioid treatment program-based methadone vs office-based buprenorphine in the United States). The extent to which the medications themselves versus the mode of care delivery effect outcomes remains to be seen, and target trial emulation may be helpful to untangle and understand various treatment effects.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p id="P32">As unprecedented numbers of individuals continue to die from overdose, valid comparative effectiveness research is needed to inform treatment decisions. Target trial emulation is one approach to improve the rigor of observational comparative effectiveness work and strengthen the evidence-base for addiction treatment at a time when it is desperately needed.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="SD1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Data S2 Supporting Information</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="NIHMS1983056-supplement-Data_S2_Supporting_Information.docx" id="d67e432" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SD2" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Data S1 Supporting Information</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="NIHMS1983056-supplement-Data_S1_Supporting_Information.xlsx" id="d67e435" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S13"><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p id="P33">We acknowledge the Massachusetts Department of Public Health for creating the unique, cross-sector database that will be used for the described analysis and for providing technical support.</p><sec id="S14"><title>Funding information</title><p id="P34">National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA), Grant/Award Numbers: R01 DA054268 (to M.R.L.); NIDA U10/UG1 DA013035 (to J.R. &#8216;contact&#8217; PI; Nunes, J.R., mPIs), NIDA K01DA054328 (H.E.H).</p></sec></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2"><p id="P36">DECLARATION OF INTERESTS</p><p id="P37">J.R. has been a Principal Investigator or a Co-Investigator on studies for which support in the form of donated or discounted medication and/or funds has been, or will be, provided by Alkermes, PLC. Vivitrol (extended-release injectable naltrexone) has been, or will be, provided by Indivior, PLC (formerly Reckitt-Benckiser; Suboxone, buprenorphine-naloxone combination) and by Braeburn-Camurus (CAM-2038); and digital therapeutics by Pear Therapeutics, by ACHESS, and by Datacubed. For the X:BOT study, Vivitrol was purchased and buprenorphine-naloxone (Suboxone) was donated by Indivior. J.R. served as an uncompensated member of an Alkermes study Steering Committee. He has no relevant equity, intellectual property, compensated consulting, travel or other arrangements with any of these entities. J.D.L. is Principal Investigator of multiple National Institutes of Health-funded studies receiving in-kind study medication from Alkermes and Indivior. He is Co-Investigator of an Investigator Sponsored Study funded by Indivior. He has no relevant equity, intellectual property, compensated consulting, travel or other arrangements with Indivior or Alkermes. He is a Science Advisor at Oar Health. J.L is a consultant to Biomotivate, which did not have any relationship to this project.</p></fn><fn id="FN3"><p id="P38">SUPPORTING INFORMATION</p><p id="P39">Additional <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">supporting information</xref> can be found online in the <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supporting Information</xref> section at the end of this article.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="S15"><title>DATA AVAILABILITY STATEMENT</title><p id="P35">The X:BOT trial data are openly available in the NIDA Clinical Trials Network data share repository at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://datashare.nida.nih.gov/divisions/ctn" ext-link-type="uri">https://datashare.nida.nih.gov/divisions/ctn</ext-link>. The Massachusetts PHD data are available from the Massachusetts Department of Public Health. Restrictions apply to the availability of these data, which were used under license for this study. For details, see: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.mass.gov/info-details/public-health-data-warehouse-phd-how-to-collaborate-with-us" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.mass.gov/info-details/public-health-data-warehouse-phd-how-to-collaborate-with-us</ext-link>.</p></sec><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention National Center for Health Statistics</collab>. <source>National vital statistics system&#8212;mortality 1999&#8211;2020 on CDC WONDER online database</source>; <year>2021</year>. <date-in-citation>Accessed January 12, 2024</date-in-citation>. <comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://wonder.cdc.gov/mcd-icd10.html" ext-link-type="uri">http://wonder.cdc.gov/mcd-icd10.html</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Volkow</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wargo</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Overdose prevention through medical treatment of opioid use disorders</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>169</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>190</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M18-1397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29913514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#225;n</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#225;ndez-D&#237;az</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shrier</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>. <article-title>Specifying a target trial prevents immortal time bias and other self-inflicted injuries in observational analyses</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>70</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2016.04.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27237061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5124536</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#225;n</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leaf</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Target trial emulation: a framework for causal inference from observational data</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>328</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>2446</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2022.21383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36508210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#225;n</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robins</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Using big data to emulate a target trial when a randomized trial is not available</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>183</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>758</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwv254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26994063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4832051</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Szummer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dahabreh</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindahl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erlinge</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feychting</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal/><article-title>Comparing effect estimates in randomized trials and observational studies from the same population: an application to percutaneous coronary intervention</article-title>. <source>J Am Heart Assoc</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e020357</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/JAHA.120.020357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33998290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8483524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lodi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Costagliola</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abgrall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal/><article-title>Comparative effectiveness of immediate antiretroviral therapy versus CD4-based initiation in HIV-positive individuals in high-income countries: observational cohort study</article-title>. <source>Lancet HIV</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e335</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2352-3018(15)00108-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26423376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4643831</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneeweiss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <collab>RCT-DUPLICATE Initiative</collab>. <article-title>Emulation of randomized clinical trials with nonrandomized database analyses: results of 32 clinical trials</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>329</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>1376</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2023.4221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37097356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10130954</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robins</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>. <source>Causal Inference CRC Press</source>; <year>2023</year><comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://books.google.com/books?id=_KnHIAAACAAJ" ext-link-type="uri">https://books.google.com/books?id=_KnHIAAACAAJ</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>GCK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stjepanovic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal/><article-title>Causal inference with observational data in addiction research</article-title>. <source>Addiction</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>117</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2736</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/add.15972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35661462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9545953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>The Commonwealth of Massachusetts</collab>. <source>An assessment of fatal and nonfatal opioid overdoses in Massachusetts (2011-2015)</source>. <publisher-name>Massachusetts Department of Public Health</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>. <date-in-citation>Accessed August 15, 2022</date-in-citation>. <comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://pilot.mass.gov/files/documents/2017/08/31/legislative-report-chapter-55-aug-2017.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://pilot.mass.gov/files/documents/2017/08/31/legislative-report-chapter-55-aug-2017.pdf</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><name name-style="western"><surname>LaRochelle</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>. <source>COMPEET MOUD Aim 1 Protocol</source>. <comment>Published online</comment><month>January</month><day>22</day>, <year>2024</year>. <comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://osf.io/7jh4q" ext-link-type="uri">osf.io/7jh4q</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>EVJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Novo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal/><article-title>Comparative effectiveness of extended-release naltrexone versus buprenorphine-naloxone for opioid relapse prevention (X:BOT): a multicentre, open-label, randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet Lond Engl</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>391</volume>(<issue>10118</issue>):<fpage>309</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(17)32812-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5806119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29150198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><source>Quality ID #468 (NQF 3175): Continuity of Pharmacotherapy for Opioid Use DIsorder (OUD)</source>; <year>2017</year>. <date-in-citation>Accessed December 5, 2022</date-in-citation>. <comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://qpp.cms.gov/docs/QPP_quality_measure_specifications/CQM-Measures/2019_Measure_468_MIPSCQM.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://qpp.cms.gov/docs/QPP_quality_measure_specifications/CQM-Measures/2019_Measure_468_MIPSCQM.pdf</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Danaei</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tavakkoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#225;n</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Bias in observational studies of prevalent users: lessons for comparative effectiveness research from a Meta-analysis of statins</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>175</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>250</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwr301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22223710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3271813</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cain</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robins</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lanoy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Costagliola</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#225;n</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>. <article-title>When to start treatment? A systematic approach to the comparison of dynamic regimes using observational data</article-title>. <source>Int J Biostat</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <comment>Article 18</comment>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2202/1557-4679.1212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3406513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21972433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krupitsky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Illeperuma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gastfriend</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Injectable extended-release naltrexone for opioid dependence: a double-blind, placebo-controlled, multicentre randomised trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>377</volume>(<issue>9776</issue>):<fpage>1506</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60358-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21529928</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattick</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Breen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kimber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Buprenorphine maintenance versus placebo or methadone maintenance for opioid dependence</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>CD002207</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD002207.pub4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10617756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24500948</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Breen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kimber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Methadone maintenance therapy versus no opioid replacement therapy for opioid dependence</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>2009</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>CD002209</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD002209.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19588333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7097731</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p id="P40">Theoretical and observed populations of interest in the X:BOT clinical trial and the observational emulated trial using the Massachusetts administrative data (PHD). Boxes with solid outlines indicate observed populations in each dataset. Boxes with dashed outlines indicate theoretical but unmeasured/unidentifiable populations in each dataset. Abbreviations: ATS, acute treatment services (i.e. detox facilities); BSAS, Bureau of Substance Addiction Services; MMOW, medically managed opioid withdrawal; MOUD, medication for opioid use disorder; PHD, Public Health Data Warehouse. Boxes with solid outlines indicate observed populations in each dataset. Boxes with dashed outlines indicate theoretical but unmeasured/unidentifiable populations in each dataset.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-1983056-f0001.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p id="P41">Attempts to align eligibility determination, treatment assignment and start of follow-up in the X:BOT clinical trial and the observational emulated trial using the Massachusetts administrative data (PHD). Time 0 indicates the start of follow-up. Baseline eligibility assessment in X:BOT was conducted via clinician assessments during MMOW. Eligibility assessment in PHD was determined using International Classification of Diseases codes for various exclusion criteria in the 180 days preceding MMOW discharge. Note that in the original X:BOT trial, there was no 28-day grace period for MOUD initiation, and individuals were randomly assigned to treatment at time zero after which follow-up began. Abbreviations: BUP-NX, buprenorphine-naloxone; MMOW, medically managed opioid withdrawal; MOUD, medication for opioid use disorder; PHD, Public Health Data Warehouse; XR-NTX, extended-release naltrexone.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-1983056-f0002.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="landscape"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p id="P42">Components of target trial emulation protocol with examples from X:BOT clinical trial and observational emulated trial using the Massachusetts PHD.<sup><xref rid="TFN2" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></sup></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="top" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trial protocol component</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Target trial&#8211;X:BOT RCT</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emulated trial&#8211;observational data from Massachusetts PHD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population of interest</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Who does the study apply to?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Individuals in MMOW willing to receive agonist or antagonist based MOUD treatment</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two approaches<break/>(A) Individuals discharged from state funded MMOW<break/>(B) Individuals initiating MOUD within 28 days of MMOW discharge</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eligibility criteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Who is included in the study?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;18 years old, DSM-5 diagnosis of OUD, willing to accept agonist or antagonist based MOUD, good general health, no serious medical/psychiatric diagnoses that would preclude participation, not on methadone &gt;30 mg, no pending legal action</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;18 years old, discharged from voluntary MMOW, no diagnosis of psychosis in 6 months preceding MMOW, have not received methadone through OTP within 30 days of MMOW admission<break/><break/>Unable to emulate the following criteria: DSM-5 diagnosis of OUD, willingness to receive agonist or antagonist based MOUD, good general health, pending legal action</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment definition</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">What is the treatment of interest?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initiation of BUP-NX or XR-NTX within 22 weeks of randomization<sup><xref rid="TFN3" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></sup><break/><break/>Modified definition: Initiation of BUP-NX or XR-NTX within 28 days of randomization</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initiation of BUP-NX or XR-NTX within 28 days of discharge from MMOW</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment assignment</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">How is the treatment assigned to participants?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eligible participants not randomized but assigned based on observed treatment initiation&#8211;inverse probability weighting used to adjust for measured confounders</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">What outcomes will be compared among treatment groups?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Opioid relapse-free survival as defined by urine toxicology and self-report<break/><break/>Harmonized outcome: time to MOUD discontinuation defined as &gt;7-day gap in medication possession, readmission to MMOW, incarceration or death</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unable to emulate opioid relapse-free survival because of lack of data on toxicology and self-reported drug use<break/><break/>Time to MOUD discontinuation defined as &gt;7-day gap in medication possession, readmission to MMOW, incarceration or death</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">When will follow-up begin and how long will eligible participants be followed?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time zero: time of randomization<break/><break/>Follow-up until 24 weeks or outcome</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time zero: discharge from MMOW (or day of treatment initiation in additional analyses)<sup><xref rid="TFN4" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref></sup><break/><break/>Follow-up until 24 weeks or outcome</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Causal contrast of interest</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">What counterfactual contrasts will be estimated?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intention-to-treat effect: effect of being assigned to treatment group<break/><break/>Per-protocol effect: effect of initiating assigned treatment</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unable to emulate intention-to-treat effect because of lack of randomization<break/><break/>Per-protocol effect: effect of initiating treatment</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Statistical analysis</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">How will the causal contrasts of interest be estimated?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intention-to-treat effect: analysis comparing risk of treatment discontinuation among assigned treatment groups<break/><break/>Per-protocol effect: Inverse probability of treatment weighting to control for baseline and time-varying confounding</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unable to calculate intention-to-treat effect<break/><break/>Per-protocol effect: censoring clones and inverse probability weighting to control for baseline and time-varying confounding</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN1"><p id="P43">Abbreviations: BUP-NX, buprenorphine-naloxone; DSM-5, Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders-5; MMOW, medically managed opioid withdrawal: MOUD, medication for opioid use disorder; OUD, opioid use disorder; OTP, opioid treatment program; PHD, Public Health Data Warehouse; XR-NTX, extended-release naltrexone.</p></fn><fn id="TFN2"><label>a</label><p id="P44">See the online protocol for a full table [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] comparing X:BOT and emulated trial components, including a full list of eligibility criteria and confounders, which are abbreviated here for sake of space.</p></fn><fn id="TFN3"><label>b</label><p id="P45">Original X:BOT RCT allowed individuals to initiate treatment within 22 weeks of randomization. This was truncated to 28 days in an effort to balance sufficient time for individuals to start the medication and to limit the number of outcomes that accumulated during the treatment assignment period.</p></fn><fn id="TFN4"><label>c</label><p id="P46">We planned two analyses using the PHD data corresponding to two distinct causal questions: (1) What is the effect of BUP-NX vs XR-NTX on treatment retention if all individuals were hypothetically treated with one treatment vs the other?; and (2) What is the effect of BUP-NX vs XR-NTX on treatment retention in individuals who were actually treated with one treatment vs the other? For the former question, time zero corresponds to the day of discharge from MMOW, whereas for the latter question, time zero corresponds to the day of MOUD initiation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article></pmc-articleset>