<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="review-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Nurs Stud Adv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Nurs Stud Adv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4592</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ijnsa</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Nursing Studies Advances</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2666-142X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11342894</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11342894.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11342894</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11342894</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39184918</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijnsa.2024.100228</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2666-142X(24)00055-9</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100228</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Health economic evaluations of programs reducing preterm birth: A scoping review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chadha</surname><given-names initials="A">Anvitaa</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names initials="S">Suzanne</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0003"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kildea</surname><given-names initials="S">Sue</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0004"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yu</given-names></name><email>yu.gao@cdu.edu.au</email><xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">&#8270;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001">Molly Wardaguga Institute for First Nations Birth Rights, Faculty of Health, Charles Darwin University, Brisbane, Australia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor0001"><label>&#8270;</label>Corresponding author at: Charles Darwin University, Level 11(East Wing), 410 Ann Street, Brisbane City QLD 4000, Australia. <email>yu.gao@cdu.edu.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">466460</issue-id><elocation-id>100228</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>17</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>25</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>23</day><month>08</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-08-29 03:25:40.600"><day>29</day><month>08</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0001"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Preterm birth has lifelong implications, placing a burden on individuals, families, communities and the health system. While several interventions to reduce preterm birth have been economically evaluated, no scoping review has been undertaken.</p></sec><sec><title>Objective</title><p>To conduct a scoping review of economic evaluations of interventions that have reduced preterm birth, identify gaps in the literature and inform future health care providers and researchers on the economic value of preterm birth reduction interventions.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Databases such as PubMed, Cumulative Index to Nursing and Allied Health Literature, EBSCO, Medline (OVID), EMBASE, NHS Health Technology Assessment, the Cost-Effectiveness Analysis Registry, and the NHS Economic Evaluation Database and grey literature were comprehensively searched for economic evaluations of interventions that reduced preterm birth conducted since 2000. Items included: preterm birth reduction, intervention, method of economic evaluation, time-horizon of analysis, study population, perspective of evaluation, effectiveness, and costs. Review processes were undertaken by two reviewers, and disagreements were resolved by the larger team.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Fifteen publications met the inclusion criteria, including pharmacological interventions (5), telemedicine (1), diagnostic procedures (2), public and community health (2), prenatal care and nutrition (2), father's involvement (1), doula care (1) and a comprehensive maternity service redesign (1). Variations were observed in study design, time-horizon, study population and method of evaluation. Most studies (n = 13) adopted either a healthcare payer, provider, or system perspective. Shorter timehorizons for analysis were adopted in all studies, except one that conducted a lifetime economic evaluation. All included interventions, except one, were found to be costeffective, cost-beneficial or led to cost-savings.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Despite preterm birth placing a high economic burden on health systems and society, we found a dearth of long-term economic evaluations of prevention and reduction initiatives. Future research on preterm birth reduction initiatives should include economic evaluations.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="keys0001"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Cost-effectiveness</kwd><kwd>Costing</kwd><kwd>Economic evaluation</kwd><kwd>Preterm birth</kwd><kwd>Scoping review</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="para9001s">
<boxed-text id="tbox0002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>What is already known</title></caption><p id="para0006">
<list list-type="simple" id="celist0001"><list-item id="celistitem0001"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="para0007">There is limited evidence on the cost-effectiveness of interventions that have reduced preterm birth</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0002"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="para0008">Reviews of the available evidence have not previously been conducted</p></list-item></list>
</p><notes notes-type="alt-text" specific-use="for-accessibility" id="alte1"><p>Alt-text: Unlabelled box</p></notes></boxed-text>
<boxed-text id="tbox0003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>What this paper adds</title></caption><p id="para0009">
<list list-type="simple" id="celist0002"><list-item id="celistitem0003"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="para0010">Fifteen economic evaluations of diverse preterm birth reduction interventions, published, since 2000,were identified</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0004"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="para0011">The need for long-term economic evaluations has been demonstrated</p></list-item></list>
</p><notes notes-type="alt-text" specific-use="for-accessibility" id="alte2"><p>Alt-text: Unlabelled box</p></notes></boxed-text>
</p><sec id="sec0001"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="para0012">Preterm birth has been defined as &#8220;babies born alive before 37 weeks of gestation are completed&#8221; (<xref rid="bib0046" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organisation, 2018</xref>). Prematurity is the leading cause of infant (under 12 months) and child (under 5 years) morbidity and mortality accounting for 16 per cent of all child deaths and 35 % of new-born (&lt;28 days) deaths globally in 2016 (<xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">Hug et al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib0047" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organisation, 2022</xref>). Preterm birth is also associated long-term health consequences, such as cerebral palsy, retinopathy of prematurity and cognitive disabilities (<xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">Institute of Medicine, 2007</xref>, <xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr">Saigal and Doyle, 2008</xref>) and substantial economic burdens on healthcare systems (<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Mangham et al., 2009</xref>, <xref rid="bib0034" ref-type="bibr">Petrou, 2019</xref>).</p><p id="para0013">The rates of preterm birth vary by race and ethnicity globally and within countries. In 2014, of the 14.8 million babies born preterm (&lt;37 weeks), 80 % were in Asia and sub-Saharan Africa (<xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">Chawanpaiboon et al., 2019</xref>). In the United States, the preterm birth rate was 10.5 % in 2021, a 4 % increase from the previous year, with rates for African Americans and Native Indians being 14.7 % and 12.3 %, respectively (<xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">March of Dimes, 2022</xref>). In 2021, the overall rate of preterm birth in England and Wales was lower (6.2 %-7.2 %),however these rates were higher in non-White peoples compared to White peoples (8.7 % vs 7.4 %) (<xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">National Health Service (NHS), 2022</xref>, <xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">Office for National Statistics (ONS), 2023</xref>). Variation of preterm birth rates is often higher in non-White populations and the disparities exist regardless of socioeconomic status (<xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">Johnson et al., 2020</xref>). In Australia, the preterm birth rate in 2019 was 13.2 % for women having First Nations babies compared to 8.3 % for the rest of the population (<xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">Australian Institute of Health and Welfare, 2021</xref>).</p><p id="para0014">Interventions to reduce preterm birth have been reported in previous reviews (<xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">Karger et al., 2022</xref>, <xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr">Medley et al., 2018</xref>, <xref rid="bib0038" ref-type="bibr">Sandall et al., 2016</xref>). These include health service interventions such as improving maternal antenatal care access (<xref rid="bib0046" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organisation, 2018</xref>), midwife-led continuity of care models (<xref rid="bib0038" ref-type="bibr">Sandall et al., 2016</xref>), Vitamin D supplementation in pregnancy (<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">De-Regil et al., 2016</xref>), lower genital tract infection screening and treatment (<xref rid="bib0039" ref-type="bibr">Sangkomkamhang et al., 2015</xref>), and provision of zinc supplements to pregnant women in the absence of systemic infections (<xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">Ota et al., 2015</xref>). Previous reviews have also outlined interventions, programs or service that aim to reduce prematurity in culturally and linguistically diverse populations (<xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">Karger et al., 2022</xref>) and in low and middle-income countries (<xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">Wastnedge et al., 2021</xref>),and may be implemented from preconception to birth, and before planning subsequent pregnancies (<xref rid="bib0038" ref-type="bibr">Sandall et al., 2016</xref>). Few of these programs have included or reported economic evaluations.</p><p id="para0015">Preterm birth places increased healthcare and economic burden on the health system and society. In Australia, the cost of preterm birth for healthcare, including neonatal admission, primary and secondary care, and education has been estimated to be between AUD25,417 (late preterm) and AUD236,026 (extremely preterm) per child, from birth till age 18, estimated at AUD1.413 billion annually (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Newnham et al., 2022</xref>). Simlar variations have been observed in studies from the United Kingdom, United States and Canada (<xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">Institute of Medicine, 2007</xref>), reported on prematurity leading to greater costs from infancy to 18 years.</p><p id="para0016">Health economic evaluations enable researchers to analyze comparative interventions, resource utilization, associated costs, and effectiveness, which can inform decision-makers and stakeholders (<xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">Gomersall et al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">Hoch and Dewa, 2005</xref>). There are four types of health economic evaluations commonly used: cost-effectiveness analysis; cost-benefit analysis; cost-utility analysis and cost-minimization analysis. These analyses investigate the costs and effects of healthcare while using different approaches to present outcomes (<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">Drummond et al., 2005</xref>). Cost-effectiveness analysis considers costs and outcome effectiveness in its natural or physical unit, for example, cost per cardiovascular event avoided, and results are displayed as differences in cost or outcome when compared with an alternative. Cost-utility analysis uses health indices such as quality-adjusted life years or disability adjusted life years to highlight their results, for example, cost per quality-adjusted life year gained. The cost-benefit analysis quantifies the effects in monetary terms, as a net-monetary benefit and includes return-on-investment analysis which demonstrates the benefit as cost-offset to the initial investment while not presenting health benefits. Cost-minimization compares the costs of alternatives that have a similar outcome (<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">Drummond et al., 2005</xref>). These evaluations provide evidence that contributes to planning effective health services and programs. The purpose of this scoping review was to identify gaps in the literature and inform future health care providers and researchers on the value of preterm birth reduction interventions.</p></sec><sec id="sec0002"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><p id="para0017">The JBI Handbook for Systematic Review of Economic Evaluations (<xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">Aromataris and Munn, 2014</xref>) and JBI Evidence synthesis manual (<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">Aromataris and Munn, 2020</xref>) was referred to while designing the review and has used the <italic toggle="yes">PRISMA-scr</italic> guidelines for reporting (<xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Shamseer et al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="bib0042" ref-type="bibr">Tricco et al., 2018</xref>). Key terminologies referred to in this paper have been outlined in <xref rid="tbl0003" ref-type="table">Box 1</xref>. As this was conceptualized as part of a doctoral thesis, a protocol was not designed or registered with any scoping review registries such as Open Science Framework.</p><sec id="sec0003"><label>2.1</label><title>Search strategy and data sources</title><p id="para0018">Electronic searches were conducted in PubMed, EBSCO including Cumulative Index to Nursing and Allied Health Literature (CINAHL), MEDLINE (Ovid), Embase, Web of Science, EconLit, Cost-effectiveness analysis Registry, NHS Economic Evaluation Database (NHSEED) and NHS Health Technology Assessment (NHS HTA) (via The Centre for Reviews and Dissemination Library- CRD). The search strategy included keywords and Medical Subject Headings (MeSH) related to models of maternity care, health programs and interventions to reduce preterm birth rates and economic evaluation research searches were adapted for use in each database as below.</p><p id="para0019">The databases were searched for MeSH key terms associated with preterm birth prevention (&#8216;preterm&#8217;, &#8216;premature&#8217;, &#8216;labour&#8217;, &#8216;delivery&#8217;, &#8216;prevent&#8217;, &#8217;reduction&#8217;, &#8217;decrease&#8217;), programs or services (&#8216;best practice&#8217;, &#8216;strategy&#8217;, &#8216;intervention&#8217;), maternal health, &#8216;maternity&#8217;, &#8217;pregnancy&#8217;, &#8217;perinatal&#8217;) and health economic analysis and health outcomes (such as &#8216;cost&#8217;, &#8216;cost effectiveness analysis&#8217;, &#8217;cost benefit analysis, &#8216;economic evaluation&#8217;, &#8216;economic assessment&#8217;, &#8216;disability adjusted life year&#8217; and &#8216;quality adjusted life year&#8217;).</p><p id="para0020">The complete search strategy employed for PubMed is listed in Supplementary material 1A. The search strategies employed for Springer, EBSCO and Scopus databases were adjusted to accommodate for differences in these platforms and are included in Supplementary material 1B. Grey literature searches were conducted, and reference lists from other relevant systematic reviews and research papers were checked. Searches were concluded on 20 July 2023.</p></sec><sec id="sec0004"><label>2.2</label><title>Eligibility criteria</title><p id="para0021">Included articles were restricted to randomized controlled trials, cohort and longitudinal studies, with an accompanying economic evaluation, published in English between 2000&#8211;2023. Articles published before 2000 were deemed unacceptable as preterm birth preventative measures have largely changed since then.</p><p id="para0022">Economic evaluations included cost analysis or cost comparison studies where at least two alternate health programs or interventions are being assessed for costs and consequences via cost-effectiveness, cost-benefit or cost-utility analyses or economic modelling. For this review, economic evaluations of all-time horizons have been included, to ensure the maximum inclusivity of relevant studies. Commentaries, editorials, trial protocols and systematic reviews were excluded, but relevant references were included.</p><p id="para0023">EndNote x9 was used to manage search results including removal of duplicate records. Study selection and data extraction have been performed through the COVIDENCE review management system (<xref rid="bib0043" ref-type="bibr">Veritas Health Innovation, 2023</xref>). Further details on eligibility criteria have been summarized in <xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Inclusion and exclusion criteria.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0003">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PICOS</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inclusion criteria</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Exclusion criteria</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Population</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pregnant women at any stage of pregnancy</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-pregnant women</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Intervention</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Studies include an intervention that reduced preterm birth.<break/>The intervention could be delivered in person or virtually and is minimally invasive or non-invasive<break/>The interventions being considered for this review include but are not limited to:<break/>Pharmacological interventions, Diagnostic testing and screening, Ultrasounds, Health programs, Doula and Midwife-led interventions, Nutritional supplements, Mobile health or telehealth services, Mental health interventions</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Studies that did not reduce preterm birth or were invasive procedures and surgical in nature e.g., Cervical cerclage/ cervical stitch.<break/>Environmental interventions e.g., Air pollution mitigation</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Comparator</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Standard maternity care provision at a public or private hospital, antenatal clinic, or health care provider.</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Programs that did not aim to reduce preterm birth</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Outcome</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Costing data; Preterm birth reduction- number, percentage, odds-ratio, risk-ratios; Gestational age at delivery; Quality-adjusted life years (QALYs), Disability-adjusted Life Years (DALYs); Incremental Cost Effectiveness Ratio; Cost-benefit ratio; Net-monetary benefit.</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Studies that do not report on both costs and outcomes</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Study type</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Economic evaluations published in English<break/>Studies published between 01/01/2000 -20/07/2023<break/>Studies include randomized controlled trials and modelling studies<break/>Time-horizon - All studies have been included irrespective of time-horizon</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Economic evaluations published in language/s other than English<break/>Studies published 2000 and after July 2023<break/>Reviews, commentaries, and editorials</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0005"><label>2.3</label><title>Study selection</title><p id="para0024">The studies were independently examined against eligibility criteria by two authors (AC and SM), based on title and abstract screening, and full-text screening. Titles and abstracts accepted by both authors were included for full-text screening. Articles reporting a significant reduction in preterm birth were excluded (with reason) if they had not been economically evaluated. Discrepancies were resolved through discussion between the two reviewers and, if consensus was not reached, were reviewed by additional researchers (SK and YG).The study selection process has been depicted in <xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>.<fig id="fig0001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Study selection process.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0001">Fig 1:</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="celink0001" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec0006"><label>2.4</label><title>Data extraction and synthesis</title><p id="para0025">A data extraction form was developed based on similar reviews. The extraction process and collation of findings were carried out using Data Extraction 2.0 in COVIDENCE (Veritas Health Innovation). The characteristics and results of included studies were summarized using tables in Microsoft Excel and included the title, year of study, authors, intervention type, study setting, study population, method of economic evaluation, preterm birth reduction (%, RR, aOR), currency year, health index used (quality or disability-adjusted life year), cost estimates (incremental cost, cost savings, or net monetary benefit). Findings from the economic evaluations are presented as a narrative synthesis, detailing the type of intervention, method of economic evaluation, rate of preterm birth reduction, and other methodological features.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0007"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec0008"><label>3.1</label><title>Search results</title><p id="para0026">The electronic search strategy yielded 2014 articles. After removing 561 duplicates, 1453 studies were screened by title and abstract by AC and SM for eligibility, with 153 full-text articles included for final review. Full-text reports were unavailable for five studies: four conference abstracts and one thesis which could not be sourced. Details of all excluded full-text articles, along with a reason for exclusion, can be found in Supplementary material 1C. Of the 148 full-text reports, 133 studies did not meet the inclusion criteria and were excluded. Fifteen studies were included for analysis. Details of the process and reasons for exclusion are summarized in the PRISMA flowchart (<xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).<fig id="fig0002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>PRISMA flowchart.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0002">Fig 2:</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="celink0002" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec0009"><label>3.2</label><title>Scope of interventions and economic evaluations</title><p id="para0027">Key characteristics of studies included in the review have been summarized in <xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Most studies were from high-income countries with ten studies from the United States (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>), one from Austria (<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss et al., 2006</xref>), Australia (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>), and Canada (<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison et al., 2001</xref>), one study focused on six low and middle-income countries (<xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>), and one study from Vietnam (<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2020</xref>), a middle-income country.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0002" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>General characteristics of included economic evaluations</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0004">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Evaluation characteristics</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Evaluations (n = 15)</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Evaluation references</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Intervention type</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pharmacological</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson 2023</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Maternity service redesign</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao 2023</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Screening</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss, 2006</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Doula service and Prenatal care</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil 2016</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Community or public health programs</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison 2001</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Telemedicine</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison 2001</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nutrition</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo 2019</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Paternal involvement</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu 2014</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Study type</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Randomised controlled trial</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le 2020</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Retrospective cohort study</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick 2010</xref>, Gareau 2016, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu 2014</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prospective cohort observational study</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Polinski 2019</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-hoc cohort following randomized controlled trial</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson 2023</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-randomized interventional trial</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao 2023</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Economic modelling using observational data</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo 2019</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Type of evaluation</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cost-effectiveness analysis</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu 2014</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cost-benefit analysis</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo 2019</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Costing study</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski 2020</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Decision analytic modelling</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu 2014</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Country of evaluation</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">United States</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau 2016</xref>, Grabner 2012, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu 2014</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Australia</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao 2023</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Austria</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss 2006</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Canada</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison 2001</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vietnam</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le 2020</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Multiple countries</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson 2023</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Evaluation perspective</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Health system perspective</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison 2001</xref>, Kiss 2016, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski 2020</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Public, healthcare or payer or Third-party payer perspective</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le 2020</xref>, Salihu 201</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Societal perspective</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unclear or not reported</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam 2003</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time horizon</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;12 months</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu 2014</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 year</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau 2016</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2-4 years</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner 2021</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5-10 years</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kiss, 2016</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lifetime</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo 2019</xref></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0003" orientation="portrait"><label>Box 1</label><caption><p>Key terms</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0005">Box 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Term</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Definition</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cost-effectiveness analysis</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A method of economic evaluation where costs of alternative programs, related to the same effect or outcome, are compared. The results of these analyses are presented as the incremental cost per unit of the outcome (<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">Drummond et al., 2015</xref>).</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cost-benefit analysis</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A method of economic evaluation where both costs and outcomes are measured in monetary terms. The costs and outcomes are combined, and results presented as net monetary benefit (<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">Drummond et al., 2015</xref>).</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Perspective</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">It is the viewpoint from which the economic evaluation is conducted (<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">Drummond et al., 2015</xref>).</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Healthcare provider perspective</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">An analysis conducted from the health system perspective includes costs regardless of payer to provide healthcare and deliver services borne by the health system or provider (<xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr">Sittimart et al., 2024</xref>).</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Healthcare payer perspective</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">An analysis conducted from the healthcare payer perspective includes the costs incurred by a third-party health organisation related to health care services. This perspective does not include costs incurred by the broader health system or provider (<xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr">Sittimart et al., 2024</xref>).</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Societal perspective</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">An analysis conducted from the societal perspective is the broadest and includes all healthcare costs including costs of travel, loss of productivity including costs for a carer (<xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr">Sittimart et al., 2024</xref>).</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time-horizon</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The time horizon used for an economic evaluation is the duration over which health outcomes and costs are calculated (<xref rid="bib0049" ref-type="bibr">York Health Economics Consortium, 2016</xref>).</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><label>3.3</label><title>Type of interventions</title><p id="para0028">Interventions that reduced preterm birth included pharmacological treatments (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>), screening programs (<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss et al., 2006</xref>), nutrition supplements (<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>), telemedicine service (<xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison et al., 2001</xref>), doula and prenatal care (<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>), a public health smoking-cessation campaign (<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>), paternal involvement (<xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>), community antenatal care (<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison et al., 2001</xref>), and a comprehensive maternity service redesign (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec0011"><label>3.4</label><title>Characteristics of economic evaluations</title><p id="para0029">We identified ten full-economic evaluations (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>) (which included nine cost-effectiveness analysis and one cost-benefit analysis) and five cost-analyses (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison et al., 2001</xref>), with five studies that used decision-analytic modelling in their assessment (<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>). The studies provided details of their data sources, time horizon, method of analysis, year of pricing and costs included. All studies also described the study population, study setting, intervention, and outcome measure and compared the intervention with alternate or standard practice. General characteristics of included economic evaluations are described in <xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p><p id="para0030">The cost-effectiveness analyses examined the effects of subcutaneous tocolytics (subcutaneous terbutaline) compared to oral tocolytics (oral nifedipine) on reducing preterm birth in singleton-pregnancies (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2003</xref>) and twin-pregnancies (<xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2001</xref>); cervical pessaries in twin pregnancies in women with a short cervix (<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2020</xref>); a screen-and-treat program for vaginal infections in asymptomatic pregnant women (<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss et al., 2006</xref>); the effect that the father's involvement during pregnancy has on preterm birth (<xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>); the effects of a Doula service often opted for by low socioeconomic status and ethnically diverse pregnant women on preterm birth rates (<xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>); a comprehensive maternity service redesign (Birthing in Our Community) designed for First Nations women in Australia (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>); the effect of low-dose Aspirin on reducing preterm birth in nulliparous singleton pregnancies (<xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>); and a preterm birth prediction test evaluated using decision analytic modelling (<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>). The cost-benefit study used decision analytic modelling to assess the effect of a nutrition program on preventing and reducing preterm birth in a hypothetical cohort of 500,000 low-income pregnant women in California (<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>). The cost analyses examined: the effect of a telemedicine service on birth outcomes and recurrent preterm labour (<xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison et al., 2001</xref>); a community antenatal program providing at-home healthcare services for women following preterm labour which had been addressed (<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison et al., 2001</xref>); and cost-savings and return-on-investment through a prenatal smoking cessation program for low-income pregnant women in Colorado (<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>); and of group prenatal care compared with individual prenatal care on preterm birth reduction (<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p id="para0031">The perspectives adopted by included studies were either that of a healthcare provider/payer or from a societal perspective. Seven studies adopted a health system perspective (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>), including four studies from a healthcare payer perspective (<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>). Three studies were unclear about the perspective adopted for the evaluation (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2003</xref>). These studies included direct costs of the intervention and other costs associated with the hospital or health service, such as the cost of hospital admission and ongoing treatment. Economic evaluation of a nutrition program adopted a societal perspective (<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>), and evaluation of a comprehensive maternity service redesign conducted a sensitivity analysis from a societal perspective (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>).</p><p id="para0032">Most studies adopted a shorter time horizon (&lt;1 year) limited to the period of the intervention and for a follow-up period while a few opted for longer periods (&#8805;1 year). The shorter time horizons ranged from 11 weeks to 17 months except for one study (<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>) which adopted a lifetime horizon. Only six studies (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>), mentioned the time horizon for their evaluations and the others were inferred from the article text. Eleven studies (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>) adopted a time horizon of 12 months or less for both the mother and baby. Some studies had different time horizons for the mother and baby (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>). Three studies evaluated the baby for longer time horizons of one year (<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau et al., 2016</xref>), two and half years (<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>), six years (<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss et al., 2006</xref>), and over the baby's lifetime (<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>). Sensitivity analysis to establish confidence in results and account for uncertainty was conducted in eight studies (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>), while the others did not (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison et al., 2001</xref>). Further details on the characteristics of included studies can be found in Supplementary material 2.</p></sec><sec id="sec0012"><label>3.5</label><title>Source of evidence</title><p id="para0033">Study designs included three randomized controlled trials (<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>), one prospective non-randomized intervention trial (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>), one prospective cohort study (<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>), nine retrospective cohort studies (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>), and one study on a hypothetical cohort (<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p id="para0034">Several data sources were used to perform economic evaluations of interventions that reduced preterm birth, with all studies employing multiple data sources for clinical and cost data. Eleven studies used data obtained either from clinical hospital databases (<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison et al., 2001</xref>), insurance claims data (<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>), medical records (<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2020</xref>), or State and National in-patient and outpatient databases (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>). Three studies (<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>) used clinical data from their primary randomized controlled trials, and two studies (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison et al., 2001</xref>), used data collected during the primary roll-out of the service. One study (<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>) collected prospective clinical data during the study period while using secondary data sources for reference cohorts for comparison. Two studies (<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>) used statewide linked databases for costs and follow-up data. Studies also used a range of secondary data sources for clinical and cost data such as previous literature (<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>) related previous studies (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>), State and National survey data (<xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>), census data (<xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>), financial reports (<xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>), and Centre for Disease Control cost estimates (<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>) World Health Organization and World Bank reports (<xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>) and country-specific healthcare guidelines (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>).Two studies sought expert opinion for consensus on assumptions employed for cost data (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec0013"><label>3.6</label><title>Key data concerns</title><p id="para0035">Data concerns expressed in the studies included a lack of matching or randomization (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>), placebo controls (<xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2003</xref>), insufficient data on key demographic parameters (<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>), data not collected on racial and ethnic subgroups (<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>), lack of clarity on collection or control for potential confounders (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>), or failure to control for all identified potential confounders (<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>), and a lack of follow-up data (<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>). Most studies used secondary sources for costing data as their primary data source failed to capture them. These studies relied on published costings of goods and services from the relevant health services, published reports and hospital-level cost estimates (<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>).Data limitations included an inability to link data across hospitals in the study region (<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison et al., 2001</xref>); difficulty in actual cost estimation during the study period (<xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2003</xref>); access difficulties for clinical and cost data for out-of-hospital appointments (<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>); lack of generalizability of results due to patients not enrolled in national outpatient surveillance programs (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick et al., 2010</xref>), due to state or country-specific data, (<xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>) or due to chosen study methods (<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau et al., 2016</xref>); effectiveness of an intervention based on trial data and not country-specific estimates(<xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>); lack of data on indirect costs (<xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>), or on intervention parameters in the control group (<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>). The studies that used decision-analytic modelling as their methodology expressed concerns over parameter estimation (<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec0014"><label>3.7</label><title>Outcome measures</title><p id="para0036">Ten studies reported on cost savings achieved through the preterm birth-reducing intervention as compared to an alternative or standard care provision. Two studies presented cost-savings and return on investment through a smoking cessation program (<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>) and group prenatal care (<xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>). A cost-benefit study reported net-monetary benefit per quality-adjusted life year gained, and return-on-investment achieved through a nutrition program (<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>). A multi-country cost-effectiveness study reported cost-effectiveness per preterm birth averted and per disability-adjusted life year averted (<xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>). All studies presented an economic benefit, except one study where no significant cost savings were observed (<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison et al., 2001</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec0015"><label>3.8</label><title>Cost-effectiveness and cost-saving</title><p id="para0037">Thirteen of the fifteen studies reported cost-savings, including nine cost-effectiveness studies and four cost analyses. Three interventions (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2020</xref>) a doula service in the United States, a comprehensive maternity service redesign for First Nations women in Australia and a cervical pessary for preterm birth reduction in twin pregnancies, were intervention dominant (less costly and more effective than standard care or the comparator) demonstrated through sensitivity analysis. A doula service, compared to standard care (no doula service provision), was associated with 22 % reduced odds of preterm birth [aOR 0.77 (0.61,0.96) 95 % CI]. Through simulations, it was found that this option was cost-saving in 73.3 % of cases and cost-effective in 25.3 % of cases. A doula reimbursement of US$986 on average would need to be made to Medicaid-eligible participants for doula services (<xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>). The comprehensive maternity service redesign for First Nations women led to a 5.34 % (&#8722;8.69 %, &#8722;1.98 %, 95 % CI) reduction in the preterm birth rate among women having First Nations babies compared to women receiving standard care and was associated with a cost saving of AUD$4,810 [95 % CI &#8722;7519, &#8722;2101] per mother-baby pair. Sensitivity analysis was conducted from the societal perspective, and included out-of-pocket costs to the women which led to a cost-saving of AUD$4,835.39 (95 % CI &#8722;7558.47, &#8722;2112.30) per mother-baby pair (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>).</p><p id="para0038">A randomized trial of cervical pessaries compared to vaginal progesterone in women with twin pregnancies and cervical length &lt;38mm, resulted in 48.7 % preterm births in the cervical pessary group compared to 60.7 % in the vaginal progesterone group [RR 0.81 (0.66&#8211;0.99 95 % CI)] along with a cost-saving of &#8364;424 (95 % CI, &#8211;842 to &#8211;3 &#8364;) per woman. In 71.5 % of the simulations run as part of the sensitivity analysis, the pessary intervention was less costly and more effective compared to vaginal progesterone (<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2020</xref>).The effect of tocolytics on reducing recurrent preterm birth in singleton pregnancies was reported in two studies and cost estimates for both included antepartum, nursery and outpatient charges. Flick et.al examined the effect of treating recurrent preterm labour with subcutaneous terbutaline compared to oral nifedipine and found that this replacement led to an 8 % [(OR 0.72, (0.58,0.90 95 % CI)] reduction in preterm birth (&lt;37 weeks), reduced nursery admission and led to a mean cost-saving of US$2,738 for the Terbutaline group (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick et al., 2010</xref>). A similar study reported a 10.7 % reduction in preterm birth (&lt;35 weeks) and a mean cost-saving of US$5,286 per patient (excluding physician and delivery charges), while also reducing admissions to the neonatal intensive care unit (<xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2003</xref>). The effect of subcutaneous terbutaline compared with oral tocolytics for recurrent preterm labour in twin pregnancy showed a 13.9 % reduction in preterm birth (&lt;35 weeks) with a median cost-saving of US$17,109/pregnancy (<xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2001</xref>).</p><p id="para0039">A preterm birth prediction test predicted the likelihood of spontaneous preterm birth and hence prevented preterm birth through case management and pharmacological measures (<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>). This approach could lead to a 20 % reduction in preterm birth with a cost savings of US$863 per pregnant woman enrolled and additional savings of US$61,581 per preterm birth prevented. Cost estimates for any neonatal or childhood developmental issues arising due to preterm birth were included. Screening for vaginal infections reduced preterm births, with preterm births in the intervention group being 3 % (2.30,3.80 95 %CI) compared to 5.3 % in the control group (4.40,6.40,95 %CI). Net cost savings of &#8364;620 per woman screened, including costs of screening and ongoing treatment if needed. T\An additional savings of &#8364;56,228 per preterm birth prevented was estimated and included costs for hospitalization, treatment costs and any outpatient costs from birth to 6 years had the baby been born preterm (<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss et al., 2006</xref>).</p><p id="para0040">A group prenatal care program, CenteringPregnancy decreased the risk of preterm birth by 36 % [RR = 0.64 (0.52-0.79)]. It led to a cost-savings of US$22,667/preterm birth prevented on health expenses for the first year of the infant's life and a return-on-investment of $1,814 per participant on average when compared to individual prenatal care. The authors concluded that group prenatal care can (<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau et al., 2016</xref>). Paternal involvement during pregnancy led to a preterm birth reduction of 3 % compared to when the father was uninvolved and a cost saving of US$1827 per birth from avoiding future health expenditure. Sensitivity analysis for parameter uncertainty showed that the results were intervention-dominant with cost-savings (<xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p id="para0041">A telehealth service was assessed for cost-effectiveness using cost analysis methodology, among women with preterm labour who had been stabilized (<xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison et al., 2001</xref>).The group that received telemedicine services had a greater gestational age of 38.2 weeks (about 9 months) compared to 35.3 weeks (about 8 months) and showed a 35.8 % reduction in preterm birth at &lt;35 weeks GA (<xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison et al., 2001</xref>).The telemedicine cohort showed an average cost-savings of $14,459 ($3,342&#8211;$25,575 95 %CI), per pregnancy compared to the control group. The Baby and Me Tobacco Free program for low-income women who had self-reported as smokers 3 months before pregnancy, was aimed at improving birth outcomes and cost-savings, compared with two reference groups (<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>).The incidence of preterm birth in the intervention group was 9 % (7.80,10.20 95 % CI) compared to 12.4 % (11.90,12.90 95 % CI) and 11.4 % (8.20,14.70 95 %CI) in the reference groups. The cost-savings for this program ranged between US$2,182 and US$6,040 per person enrolled in the program, with a return on investment of US$2.79 and US$7.79 compared with the reference groups (<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p id="para0042">The cost-effectiveness of low-dose aspirin provided daily to nulliparous women with singleton pregnancies compared to standard care was assessed in a multi-country study focused on low and middle-income countries. The cost-effectiveness analysis was based on a previous randomized controlled trial and utilized the data collected at the time. The low-dose aspirin cohort reduced preterm birth [RR 0.89(0.81-0.98)] and averted 141 (85.80--185.80,95 % CI) preterm births per 10000 pregnancies. The median cost-effectiveness was US$248 (187&#183;97&#8211;407&#183;16) per preterm birth averted. There were no significant cost-savings through an in-home nursing program following preterm labour among women who were being monitored at home (<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison et al., 2001</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec0016"><label>3.9</label><title>Cost-benefit</title><p id="para0043">A cost-benefit study reported a net monetary benefit per participant of US$3489/quality-adjusted life year gained with a return-on-investment of US$2.48 (US$1.24 to US$6.83) for every US$1 spent on a nutrition program for women, infants, and children in California. It was shown through decision analytic modelling that this intervention would prevent 2.69 % of preterm births, with a cost-saving of US$1,239 per preterm birth prevented (<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0017"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="para0044">To our knowledge, this review is the first of its kind to examine the economic impact of health programs and interventions that have reduced preterm birth. A carefully designed search strategy identified fifteen studies between 2000&#8211;2023. Interventions were diverse in their type, design, location, method of evaluation, costs considered, outcome measures, data sources, perspective, and time horizon of the evaluation. Similarly, studies followed different economic methodologies: cost-effectiveness, cost-benefit and cost savings and return-on-investment analyses. The studies informed by randomized controlled trials (<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kiss et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>) and the cohort studies (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Flick et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Gareau et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harrison et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Morrison et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>) had access to patient-level data, while other evaluations (<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>) relied on National or regional health databases, insurance and healthcare claims data, or published sources that provided aggregate data for a country or region for the economic evaluation. As economic evaluations inform decision-making and are instrumental in policy decisions, ensuring that results are robust is key. Sensitivity analyses provide robustness to the findings and enable the generalizability of results to wider populations, especially where multiple data sources are employed (<xref rid="bib0044" ref-type="bibr">Walker and Fox-Rushby, 2001</xref>). These are recommended for economic modelling studies where assumptions are used (<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">Drummond et al., 2015</xref>). All five modelling studies (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Grabner et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Patterson et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Salihu et al., 2014</xref>) conducted a sensitivity analysis for uncertainty.</p><p id="para0045">In this review a nutrition program and a smoking cessation intervention designed for women of low socio-economic status (<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Nianogo et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Polinski et al., 2020</xref>), a doula service catering to and used by ethnic minorities (<xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kozhimannil et al., 2016</xref>), and a maternity service redesign, which was codesigned with First Nations communities for First Nations women in Australia (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2023</xref>) were the only programs catering to culturally and socio-economically diverse population where the highest preterm birth rates are seen. <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">Doran et al. (2022)</xref> reported on the dearth of programs aimed at diverse populations, as well as the paucity of economic evaluations, in a recent systematic review.</p><p id="para0046">The healthcare perspective considers healthcare costs such as costs of intervention, inpatient and outpatient costs, patient services, and medication. A societal perspective includes societal costs such as direct, and indirect economic consequences as well as intangible costs such as loss of productivity and/or wages due to an illness, prolonged disability, or premature death (<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">Drummond et al., 2015</xref>), of which are more complex to measure. The perspective is a key criterion for decision-making purposes while conducting evaluations of this nature, and the choice of time horizon is dependent upon the intervention and condition under study (<xref rid="bib0049" ref-type="bibr">York Health Economics Consortium, 2016</xref>). However, these are often challenging to conduct as could necessitate lengthy longitudinal studies dependent on the study duration and are therefore not always feasible.</p><p id="para0047">Decision analytic modelling is relied on as a tool to conduct short and long-term economic evaluations through forecasting and analyzing trends in the data. The results from economic evaluations that have adopted shorter time horizons could be used to inform and conduct longer evaluations using decision analytic modelling. Adopting a lifetime horizon to fully understand the effects of an intervention is recommended, especially for chronic conditions or those having lifelong implications (<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">Drummond et al., 2015</xref>). Despite the heterogeneity of interventions and economic evaluations, studies included reported lower costs and improved outcomes overall.</p><p id="para0048">Our review was limited to successful interventions published since the year 2000, to ensure the most recent advances in preterm birth reduction were included. We acknowledge our selection may have resulted in the elimination of some successful programs still in practice. We also acknowledge the potential bias of selecting only successful interventions, as we cannot definitively report on the cost-effectiveness of all preterm birth reduction interventions.</p></sec><sec id="sec0018"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="para0049">Economic evaluations provide much needed evidence of the economic benefit to health services and the community. Preterm birth places a high economic burden on health systems and society, yet our review found limited economic evaluations of successful prevention and reduction initiatives, including long-term benefits. We recommend that economic evaluations, including those that analyse costs over a long period, be incorporated in all future programs that aim to reduce preterm birth.</p></sec><sec id="sec0020"><title>Funding</title><p id="para0051">AC is a recipient of a Charles Darwin University International PhD student scholarship. This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</p></sec><sec id="sec0001a"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="para0008a"><bold>Anvitaa Chadha:</bold> Writing &#8211; original draft, Methodology, Formal analysis, Data curation, Conceptualization. <bold>Suzanne Moore:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Validation, Supervision, Methodology, Conceptualization. <bold>Sue Kildea:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Supervision, Conceptualization. <bold>Yu Gao:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Supervision, Conceptualization.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="para0055">There is no conflict of interest to be disclosed</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebibl1"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0001"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0001"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aromataris</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munn</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>JBI manual for evidence synthesis</article-title><source>JBIMES-20-01</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0002">Aromataris, E., Munn, Z., 2014. JBI Manual for evidence synthesis 2014: the systematic review of economic evaluation evidence. Adelaide.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0003"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0003"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Australian Institute of Health and Welfare</collab></person-group><part-title>Australia's mothers and babies</part-title><year>2021</year><publisher-name>AIHW</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Canberra</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0004"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0004"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chawanpaiboon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moller</surname><given-names>A.-B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lumbiganon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petzold</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Landoulsi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jampathong</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kongwattanakul</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laopaiboon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rattanakanokchai</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>D.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thinkhamrop</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watananirun</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#252;lmezoglu</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global, regional, and national estimates of levels of preterm birth in 2014: a systematic review and modelling analysis</article-title><source>Lancet Glob. Health</source><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>e37</fpage><lpage>e46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30389451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2214-109X(18)30451-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6293055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0005"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De-Regil</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palacios</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lombardo</surname><given-names>L.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pe&#241;a-Rosas</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vitamin D supplementation for women during pregnancy</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst. Rev.</source><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">Cd008873</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD008873.pub3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26765344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0006"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0006"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doran</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langham</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bainbridge</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Begg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Potts</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scope and quality of economic evaluations of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander health programs: a systematic review</article-title><source>Aust. N. Z. J. Public Health</source><volume>46</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35298065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/1753-6405.13229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0007"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0007"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sculpher</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Claxton</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoddart</surname><given-names>G.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torrance</surname><given-names>G.W.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Methods for the economic evaluation of health care programmes</part-title><year>2015</year><publisher-name>Oxford university press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0008"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0008"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sculpher</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torrance</surname><given-names>G.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoddart</surname><given-names>G.L.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Methods for the Economic Evaluation of Health Care Programmes</part-title><year>2005</year><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0009"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0009"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flick</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de la Torre</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roca</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Istwan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhea</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desch</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez-Quintero</surname><given-names>V.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An examination of the clinical benefits and cost-effectiveness of tocolytic replacement following recurrent preterm labor</article-title><source>Am. J. Perinatol.</source><volume>27</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19823965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1055/s-0029-1241734</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chadha</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kruske</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watego</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tracy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kildea</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Birthing on Country service compared to standard care for First Nations Australians: a cost-effectiveness analysis from a health system perspective</article-title><source>Lancet Reg. Health Western Pacific</source><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100722</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lanwpc.2023.100722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10240371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37283966</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0011"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0011"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gareau</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#242;pez-De Fede</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loudermilk</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardin</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Picklesimer</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crouch</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Covington-Kolb</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Group prenatal care results in medicaid savings with better outcomes: a propensity score analysis of centeringpregnancy participation in South Carolina</article-title><source>Matern. Child Health J.</source><volume>20</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1384</fpage><lpage>1393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26979611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10995-016-1935-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0012"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0012"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomersall</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jadotte</surname><given-names>Y.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lockwood</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riddle</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Preda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conducting systematic reviews of economic evaluations</article-title><source>JBI. Evid. Implement.</source><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>170</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/XEB.0000000000000063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26288063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0013"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0013"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grabner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burchard</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gangan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boniface</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zupancic</surname><given-names>J.A.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanek</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cost-effectiveness of a proteomic test for preterm birth prediction</article-title><source>Clinicoecon. Outcomes. Res.</source><volume>13</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>809</fpage><lpage>820</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34548799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/CEOR.S325094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8449551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0014"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0014"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kushner</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benzies</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimak</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>B.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In-home nursing care for women with high-risk pregnancies: outcomes and cost</article-title><source>Obstet. Gynecol.</source><volume>97</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2001</year><fpage>982</fpage><lpage>987</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11384707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0029-7844(01)01360-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoch</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dewa</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An introduction to economic evaluation: what's in a name?</article-title><source>Canad. J. Psychiatry</source><volume>50</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15830826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/070674370505000305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0016"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0016"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hug</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharrow</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Levels and trends in child mortality: report 2017</part-title><year>2017</year><publisher-name>The World Bank</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0017"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0017"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Institute of Medicine</collab></person-group><part-title>Preterm Birth: Causes, Consequences, and Prevention</part-title><year>2007</year><publisher-name>The National Academies Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20669423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0018"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0018"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vladutiu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manuck</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>44: Racial disparities in prematurity persist among women of high socioeconomic status (SES)</article-title><source>Am. J. Obstet. Gynecol.</source><volume>222</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>S37</fpage><lpage>S38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajogmf.2020.100104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7654959</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33179010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0019"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0019"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karger</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bull</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Enticott</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callander</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Options for improving low birthweight and prematurity birth outcomes of indigenous and culturally and linguistically diverse infants: a systematic review of the literature using the social-ecological model</article-title><source>BMC. Pregnancy. ChildBirth</source><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>3</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34979997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12884-021-04307-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8722221</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0020"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pichler</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petricevic</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Husslein</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cost effectiveness of a screen-and-treat program for asymptomatic vaginal infections in pregnancy: towards a significant reduction in the costs of prematurity</article-title><source>Eur. J. Obstet. Gynecol. Reprod. Biol.</source><volume>127</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16303228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ejogrb.2005.10.017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0021"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0021"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozhimannil</surname><given-names>K.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardeman</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alarid-Escudero</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogelsang</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blauer-Peterson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling the cost-effectiveness of doula care associated with reductions in preterm birth and cesarean delivery</article-title><source>Birth</source><volume>43</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26762249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/birt.12218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5544530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0022"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0022"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergauer</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacques</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanziano</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical and cost-effectiveness of continuous subcutaneous terbutaline versus oral tocolytics for treatment of recurrent preterm labor in twin gestations</article-title><source>J. Perinatol.</source><volume>21</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2001</year><fpage>444</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11894512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.jp.7210553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0023"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0023"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Istwan</surname><given-names>N.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacques</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanziano</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Managing perinatal outcomes: the clinical benefit and cost-effectiveness of pharmacologic treatment of recurrent preterm labor</article-title><source>Manage Care</source><volume>12</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12891954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0024"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0024"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Le</surname><given-names>K.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>L.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>L.T.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mol</surname><given-names>B.W.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>V.Q.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cervical pessary vs vaginal progesterone for prevention of preterm birth in women with twin pregnancy and short cervix: economic analysis following randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>Ultrasound. Obstet. Gynecol.</source><volume>55</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31432562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/uog.20848</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0025"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mangham</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>L.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Draper</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marlow</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cost of preterm birth throughout childhood in England and Wales</article-title><source>Pediatrics.</source><volume>123</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>e312</fpage><lpage>e327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19171583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1542/peds.2008-1827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0026">March of Dimes, 2022. The 2022 March of Dimes report card: Stark and unacceptable disparities persist alongside a troubling rise in preterm birth rates.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0027"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0027"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Medley</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Care</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alfirevic</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interventions during pregnancy to prevent preterm birth: an overview of Cochrane systematic reviews</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst. Rev.</source><volume>11</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2018</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CD012505</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD012505.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6516886</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30480756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0028"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0028"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergauer</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacques</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanziano</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Telemedicine: cost-effective management of high-risk pregnancy</article-title><source>Manage Care</source><volume>10</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2001</year><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><comment>48</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11761593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0029">National Health Service (NHS), 2022. NHS Maternity Statistics, England - 2021-22. England.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="optlYLqO98RcL"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newnham</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skubisz</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rynne</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arrese</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The health and educational costs of preterm birth to 18 years of age in Australia</article-title><source>Aust. N. Z. J. Obstet. Gynaecol.</source><volume>62</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ajo.13405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34268727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0030"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nianogo</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basurto-Davila</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nobari</surname><given-names>T.Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prelip</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arah</surname><given-names>O.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whaley</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Economic evaluation of California prenatal participation in the Special Supplemental Nutrition Program for Women, Infants and Children (WIC) to prevent preterm birth</article-title><source>Prev. Med.</source><volume>124</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30998955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ypmed.2019.04.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6696990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0031"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0031"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Office for National Statistics (ONS)</collab></person-group><part-title>Birth characheteristics in England and Wales:2021</part-title><year>2023</year><publisher-name>ONS website, statistical bulletin</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0032"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0032"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ota</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Middleton</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tobe-Gai</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahomed</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhutta</surname><given-names>Z.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zinc supplementation for improving pregnancy and infant outcome</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst. Rev.</source><volume>2015</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2015</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CD000230</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD000230.pub5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7043363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25927101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0033"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0033"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neuwahl</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goco</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goudar</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Derman</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metgud</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Somannavar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kavi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okitawutshu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lokangaka</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tshefu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bose</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mwapule</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mwenechanya</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chomba</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlo</surname><given-names>W.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chicuy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>N.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jessani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saleem</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldenberg</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurhe</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hibberd</surname><given-names>P.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Achieng</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyongesa</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esamai</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bucher</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liechty</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bresnahan</surname><given-names>B.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koso-Thomas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McClure</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cost-effectiveness of low-dose aspirin for the prevention of preterm birth: a prospective study of the Global Network for Women's and Children's Health Research</article-title><source>Lancet Glob. Health</source><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>e436</fpage><lpage>e444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36796987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2214-109X(22)00548-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10288322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0034"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0034"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health economic aspects of late preterm and early term birth</article-title><source>Semin. Fetal. Neonatal. Med.</source><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30274904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.siny.2018.09.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0035"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Polinski</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juhl</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perraillon</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levinson</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crume</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of an incentive-based prenatal smoking cessation program for low-income women in Colorado</article-title><source>Public Health Nurs.</source><volume>37</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31692104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/phn.12682</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6957669</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0036"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0036"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saigal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>L.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An overview of mortality and sequelae of preterm birth from infancy to adulthood</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>371</volume><issue>9608</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18207020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(08)60136-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0037"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0037"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salihu</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salemi</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mbah</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alio</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing the economic impact of paternal involvement: a comparison of the generalized linear model versus decision analysis trees</article-title><source>Matern. Child Health J.</source><volume>18</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>1380</fpage><lpage>1390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24158503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10995-013-1372-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0038"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0038"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandall</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soltani</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gates</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shennan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Devane</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Midwife-led continuity models versus other models of care for childbearing women</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst. Rev.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CD004667</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD004667.pub5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8663203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27121907</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0039"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0039"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sangkomkamhang</surname><given-names>U.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lumbiganon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasertcharoensuk</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laopaiboon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antenatal lower genital tract infection screening and treatment programs for preventing preterm delivery</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst. Rev.</source><issue>2</issue><year>2015</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CD006178</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD006178.pub3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8498019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25922860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0040"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shamseer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghersi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liberati</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petticrew</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shekelle</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preferred reporting items for systematic review and meta-analysis protocols (PRISMA-P) 2015: elaboration and explanation</article-title><source>BMJ: Br. Med. J.</source><volume>349</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>g7647</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.g7647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25555855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0041"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0041"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sittimart</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rattanavipapong</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirelman</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dabak</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Downey</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jit</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teerawattananon</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An overview of the perspectives used in health economic evaluations</article-title><source>Cost Effect. Resour. Alloc.</source><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>41</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12962-024-00552-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11092188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38741138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0042"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0042"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tricco</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillie</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zarin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>K.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colquhoun</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levac</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horsley</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weeks</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PRISMA extension for scoping reviews (PRISMA-ScR): checklist and explanation</article-title><source>Ann. Intern. Med.</source><volume>169</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30178033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7326/M18-0850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0043"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0043"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Veritas Health Innovation</collab></person-group><part-title>Covidence systematic review software</part-title><year>2023</year><publisher-name>Veritas Health Innovation</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Melbourne, Australia</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0044"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0044"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fox-Rushby</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allowing for uncertainty in economic evaluations: qualitative sensitivity analysis</article-title><source>Health Policy Plan</source><volume>16</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2001</year><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11739369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/heapol/16.4.435</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0045"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wastnedge</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGowan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chipeta</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyondo-Mipando</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gadama</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gadama</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masamba</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malata</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taulo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dube</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawaza</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khomani</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whyte</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crampin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freyne</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interventions to reduce preterm birth and stillbirth, and improve outcomes for babies born preterm in low- and middle-income countries: a systematic review</article-title><source>J. Glob. Health</source><volume>11</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>04050</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35003711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7189/jogh.11.04050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8709903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0046">World Health Organisation, 2018. Preterm Birth.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0047">World Health Organisation, 2022. Preterm birth: 2022 Factsheet.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0049">York Health Economics Consortium, 2016. Time Horizon [online].</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="sec0023" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix</label><title>Supplementary materials</title><p id="para0053a">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ecom0001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Image, application 1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ecom0002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc2.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Image, application 2</alt-text></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="refdata001"><title>Data availability</title><p id="para9001">
<list list-type="simple" id="dacelist0001"><list-item id="rdlistitem0001"><p id="para9002">The data supporting the findings of this study are available in the Supplementary materials. Additional data can be obtained from the authors upon request.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="sec0022" fn-type="supplementary-material"><p id="para0006a">Supplementary material associated with this article can be found, in the online version, at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijnsa.2024.100228" id="interref0001">doi:10.1016/j.ijnsa.2024.100228</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>