<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3211</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jamasd</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JAMA Network Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2574-3805</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>JAMA Network</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10220513</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10220513.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10220513</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10220513</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37234005</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.15823</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zoi230477</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Investigation</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="online-only"><subject>Online Only</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="subject-area"><subject>Health Policy</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Assessment of Medical and Public Assistance Expenditures and Employment Among US Adults With Cancer Diagnoses</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="headline">Medical and Public Assistance Expenditures and Employment for Adults With Cancer</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Medical and Public Assistance Expenditures and Employment for Adults With Cancer</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grabowski</surname><given-names initials="DC">David C.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="zoi230477aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kansal</surname><given-names initials="AR">Anuraag R.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="zoi230477aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names initials="DP">Dana P.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="zoi230477aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lakdawalla</surname><given-names initials="DN">Darius N.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="zoi230477aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="zoi230477aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Health Care Policy, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts</aff><aff id="zoi230477aff2"><label>2</label>GRAIL, LLC, Menlo Park, California</aff><aff id="zoi230477aff3"><label>3</label>Alfred Mann School of Pharmacy and Sol Price School of Public Policy, University of Southern California, Los Angeles</aff><author-notes><title>Article Information</title><p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> April 16, 2023.</p><p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published:</bold> May 26, 2023. doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.15823</uri></p><p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-nc-nd-license-permissions" ext-link-type="uri">CC-BY-NC-ND License</ext-link>. &#169; 2023 Grabowski DC et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic>.</p><corresp id="zoi230477cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> David C. Grabowski, PhD, Department of Health Care Policy, Harvard Medical School, 180 Longwood Ave, Boston, MA 02115 (<email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="grabowski@med.harvard.edu">grabowski@med.harvard.edu</email>).</corresp><p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Dr Grabowski had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Concept and design:</italic> All authors.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> Grabowski, Lakdawalla.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Grabowski.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Critical revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> Kansal, Goldman, Lakdawalla.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Statistical analysis:</italic> Grabowski.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Obtained funding:</italic> Grabowski, Kansal, Goldman.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Goldman.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Supervision:</italic> Grabowski, Lakdawalla.</p><p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr Grabowski reported receiving personal fees from GRAIL, LLC during the conduct of the study; receiving personal fees from AARP, the Analysis Group, the Medicare Payment Advisory Commission, Bluestone Physician Services, and Health Care Lawyer PLC outside the submitted work; and receiving research support from AARP, the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality, the Commonwealth Fund, the Donaghue Foundation, GRAIL, the John and Laura Arnold Foundation, the National Institutes of Health, the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation, and the Warren Alpert Foundation. Dr Goldman reported receiving personal fees for serving on the scientific advisory board from GRAIL during the conduct of the study; receiving grants from Amgen, The Aspen Institute, GRAIL, Blue Cross Blue Shield of Arizona, Bristol Myers Squibb, Cedars-Sinai Health System, Edwards Lifesciences, Gates Ventures, Genentech, Gilead Sciences, Johnson &amp; Johnson, Kaiser Family Foundation, Novartis, Pfizer, Roche, and Walgreens Boots Alliance; receiving personal fees from the National Railway Labor Conference, Precision Medicine Group, and Biogen; and being a cofounder with equity of EntityRisk outside the submitted work. Dr Lakdawalla reported receiving personal fees for consulting services from Amgen, Genentech, Gilead, GRAIL, Mylan, Novartis, Otsuka, Perrigo, Pfizer, and Sorrento Therapeutics; owning equity and serving as a consultant for Precision Medicine Group; and being a cofounder and chief scientific officer for EntityRisk, Inc outside the submitted work. No other disclosures were reported.</p><p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> The study was funded by GRAIL, LLC.</p><p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> GRAIL, LLC had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p><p content-type="data-sharing-statement"><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> See the <xref rid="note-ZOI230477-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement</xref>.</p><p><bold>Additional Contributions:</bold> Charles Hanzel, BA (National Bureau of Economic Research), provided research assistance and was compensated.</p></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-05-26T10:00"><day>26</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">436793</issue-id><elocation-id>e2315823</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>26</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>28</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-05-29 06:25:09.373"><day>29</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright 2023 Grabowski DC et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic>.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY-NC-ND License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2315823.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2315823.pdf">jamanetwopen-e2315823.pdf</self-uri><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.15823"/><abstract abstract-type="teaser" specific-use="electronic"><p>This cross-sectional study uses data from the Medical Expenditure Panel Study to assess the association of cancer history with employment, income, receipt of disability insurance, and medical expenditures in the US.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="key-points"><title>Key Points</title><sec id="ab-zoi230477-1"><title>Question</title><p>Is a cancer history associated with the receipt of disability insurance, income, employment, and medical spending in the US?</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230477-2"><title>Findings</title><p>In this cross-sectional study of 39&#8201;439 respondents to the Medical Expenditure Panel Study, cancer survivors had a lower likelihood of employment and a greater likelihood of a work-limiting disability compared with respondents without a history of cancer. Cancer accounted for 505&#8201;768 fewer employed individuals in the population aged 50 to 64 years and was associated with significantly higher medical and public assistance expenditures.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230477-3"><title>Meaning</title><p>In this study, cancer history was associated with increased likelihood of disability and decreased likelihood of employment.</p></sec></abstract><abstract><sec id="ab-zoi230477-4"><title>Importance</title><p>Prior research suggests significant social value associated with increased longevity due to preventing and treating cancer. Other social costs associated with cancer, such as unemployment, public medical spending, and public assistance, may also be sizable.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230477-5"><title>Objective</title><p>To examine whether a cancer history is associated with receipt of disability insurance, income, employment, and medical spending.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230477-6"><title>Design, Setting, and Participants</title><p>This cross-sectional study used data from the Medical Expenditure Panel Study (MEPS) (2010-2016) for a nationally representative sample of US adults aged 50 to 79 years. Data were analyzed from December 2021 to March 2023.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230477-7"><title>Exposure</title><p>Cancer history.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230477-8"><title>Main Outcomes and Measures</title><p>The main outcomes were employment, public assistance receipt, disability, and medical expenditures. Variables for race, ethnicity, and age were used as controls. A series of multivariate regression models were used to assess the immediate and 2-year association of a cancer history with disability, income, employment, and medical spending.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230477-9"><title>Results</title><p>Of 39&#8201;439 unique MEPS respondents included in the study, 52% were female, and the mean (SD) age was 61.44 (8.32) years; 12% of respondents had a history of cancer. Individuals with a cancer history who were aged 50 to 64 years were 9.80 (95% CI, 7.35-12.25) percentage points more likely to have a work-limiting disability and were 9.08 (95% CI, 6.22-11.94) percentage points less likely to be employed compared with individuals in the same age group without a history of cancer. Nationally, cancer accounted for 505&#8201;768 fewer employed individuals in the population aged 50 to 64 years. A cancer history was also associated with an increase of $2722 (95% CI, $2131-$3313) in medical spending, $6460 (95% CI, $5254-$7667) in public medical spending, and $515 (95% CI, $337-$692) in other public assistance spending.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230477-10"><title>Conclusions and Relevance</title><p>In this cross-sectional study, a history of cancer was associated with increased likelihood of disability, higher medical spending, and decreased likelihood of employment. These findings suggest there may be gains beyond increased longevity if cancer can be detected and treated earlier.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="H1-1-ZOI230477"><title>Introduction</title><p>In 1971, President Richard Nixon signed the National Cancer Act, signifying the beginning of the war on cancer. At that time, cancer was the second leading cause of death in the US. It remains so today with an estimated 606&#8201;520 US individuals dying of cancer in 2020.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> As a result, President Joseph Biden launched the Cancer Moonshot with the mission of reducing cancer mortality by at least one-half and improving the experience of individuals living with and surviving cancer.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup></p><p>Over the past 50 years, various innovations have been developed to treat a range of different cancers. A key policy issue is whether these cancer treatments offer value given their high cost. Some critics have argued that certain cancer treatments have not been cost-effective. That is, some of these treatments marginally prolong life at a high cost.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> However, other studies have pointed to the increase in cancer survival over the past 2 decades, particularly for breast cancer, colon cancer, and non-Hodgkin lymphoma.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230477r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230477r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Some of this increase has been associated with earlier cancer screening, while some has been associated with innovations in treatment.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></p><p>The prior cancer literature has predominantly focused on the gains associated with increased longevity due to preventing and treating cancer.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> However, there may be other gains beyond longevity if cancer can be detected and treated earlier. For example, if earlier detection or more effective treatment improves a patient&#8217;s eventual health outcome, economic outcomes like income or employment might improve too.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230477r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230477r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> There remains an unmet need for improved economic outcomes among patients with cancer. Studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> have found that cancer survivors are less likely to be employed and more likely to be receiving sick leave or disability assistance. A 2009 meta-analysis of 36 studies found that cancer survivors had roughly double the probability of being unemployed compared with those without a history of cancer.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Earnings may also decrease, with one estimate indicating that cancer survivors had 10% lower earnings in the 3 years following their cancer diagnosis.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> A US study found that a cancer diagnosis was associated with reductions in the probability of work by 10%, in individual earnings by 40% after 2 years, and in family earnings by 20%, although family earnings recovered more over time.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> Similarly, a US study found that severe health shocks, including incident cancer, had negative downstream consequences for household income and wealth.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup></p><p>Medical costs are another large social cost associated with cancer. In 2020, the national cancer-attributed medical care costs in the US were estimated at $208.9 billion.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> In the year after cancer diagnosis, individuals (and their insurers) faced costs of nearly $16&#8201;000, including both medical spending and estimated lost wages from a reduced likelihood of working and increased days of work missed.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> Importantly, the largest source of expenditures for patients with cancer is Medicare, with spending of $8000 to $10&#8201;000 per patient with cancer aged 65 years or older.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> Thus, cancer is associated with an especially large burden on government budgets relative to other funding sources.</p><p>Cancer can lead to increased spending on disability insurance that typically occurs during later stage cancers. As of 2019, roughly 300&#8201;000 US individuals were receiving benefits through the Social Security Disability Insurance or Supplemental Security Income programs because of a neoplasm.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> Although the specific cost of the program for these recipients is unclear, they make up roughly 3% of all recipients, and total spending in 2019 on these programs was $200 billion dollars, suggesting that annual disability costs associated with cancer are in the billions.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230477r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> In this study, we sought to examine whether a history of cancer is associated with income, employment, medical spending, and the receipt of disability insurance.</p></sec><sec id="H1-2-ZOI230477"><title>Methods</title><p>This cross-sectional study used Integrated Public Use Microdata Series (IPUMS) data from the Medical Expenditure Panel Study (MEPS), focusing on 2010 to 2016. The sample was restricted to adults aged 50 to 79 years. MEPS is a panel study conducted over a 2-year period, in which each respondent participates in 2 waves. It collects basic demographic, economic, and health information, with the survey instruments designed to gather information on annual medical expenditures in each of the respondent&#8217;s 2 years of participation. This study was deemed to be exempt from review by the Harvard Medical School institutional review board; informed consent was not obtained because the study involved the secondary analysis of existing data. We followed the Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/strobe/" ext-link-type="uri">STROBE</ext-link>) reporting guideline for cross-sectional studies.</p><p>Our main analysis used a MEPS question asked of each respondent in 2 waves for respondents beginning before 2016, roughly a year apart, about whether they had ever been diagnosed with cancer. For those who had been diagnosed with cancer, the MEPS also collected data on the type of cancer, breaking it into 12 categories. Our primary measure of reported cancer history was defined as listing any type of past cancer diagnosis other than nonmelanoma skin cancers. We examined several outcome measures, including employment and income, public assistance and Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program (SNAP) receipt, disability, and medical expenditures.</p><p>Employment was defined as having been employed during the reference period for the current survey wave. People who did not work were then asked why; the reason was used to define our disability measure, including those who reported that they did not work during the reference period due to illness or disability. MEPS asked about annual income in each year that the person was in the survey. We used this question to define our measures of earnings and public assistance income. Individual earnings were collected directly as a category for wage and salary income, while public assistance income was defined as the sum of unemployment benefits, supplemental security income, income from other welfare programs (eg, Temporary Assistance for Needy Families), and Social Security income (which was collected as a combined measure for disability and older-age benefits) for those younger than 62 years (or &lt;65 years if they listed having a disability that prevented work). Individuals were also asked whether they received SNAP benefits during the reference period.</p><p>Lastly, we used aggregated annual medical expenditure variables from IPUMS MEPS. The measures of annual expenditures for different payer groups (eg, out of pocket, private insurance, and Medicare) are a mix of self-reported and validated responses. People are asked about their medical care use and spending across a broad suite of procedures and medications. Then MEPS follows up with insurers and health care practitioners to get information on expenditures. In terms of accuracy, MEPS has been found to underestimate total medical spending compared with aggregate national health accounts data.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> However, after adjusting for the population and services included, the underestimate is smaller. Compared with health expenditure measures from the Bureau of Labor Statistics consumer expenditure survey, the MEPS captures more spending.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> We created both total medical spending and public medical spending variables. The public medical spending measure included Medicare, Medicaid, Veterans Health Administration, Tricare, and 3 other public variables (for other federal, state, and unidentified public expenditures).</p><p>We also used variables for race, ethnicity, and age as controls because gradients in cancer prevalence exist across all 3 measures. The race and ethnicity measures were self-reported, with categories reported as in IPUMS MEPS data with 3 exceptions: we reported Hispanic ethnicity separately from non-Hispanic racial groups, combined the Asian and Pacific Islander categories, and combined all multiracial groups into 1 category. These categorizations were primarily made for simplifying the presentation and because several groups had small sample sizes. The resulting categories were Asian or Pacific Islander, Black, Hispanic, Native American or Alaska Native, White, and multiracial.</p><sec id="H2-1-ZOI230477"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Data were analyzed from December 2021 to March 2023. To estimate the association between cancer history and the aforementioned outcomes, we ran a set of regressions with the calculation</p><disp-formula id="zoi230477ea"><italic toggle="yes">Y<sub>i</sub></italic>&#8201;=&#8201;&#945;&#8201;+&#8201;(&#946;&#8201;&#215;&#8201;<italic toggle="yes">EverCancer<sub>i</sub></italic>)&#8201;+&#8201;(&#948;&#8201;&#215;&#8201;<italic toggle="yes">X<sub>i</sub></italic>)&#8201;+&#8201;&#1013;<italic toggle="yes"><sub>i</sub></italic>,</disp-formula><p>where <italic toggle="yes">Y<sub>i</sub></italic> is the outcome; &#945; is the intercept; &#946; is the coefficient of interest; <italic toggle="yes">EverCancer<sub>i</sub></italic> is the variable for whether the respondent had ever been diagnosed with cancer; &#948;&#8201;&#215;&#8201;<italic toggle="yes">X<sub>i</sub></italic> is the vector of race, ethnicity, age, and age-squared controls; and &#1013;<italic toggle="yes"><sub>i</sub></italic> is the error term. As suggested when using the MEPS, we used the svyset command in Stata, version 15 (StataCorp LLC) to estimate our regression models. This allowed us to incorporate the survey weights, multiple waves, and sampling structure. Using the weights constructed by MEPS, we were able to generate national estimates of the number of people with a reported cancer history by adding together their weights. We then estimated the national costs associated with reported cancer history by multiplying the coefficients on cancer report by the sum for the corresponding sample age range (50-64 years, 50-79 years).</p><p>For binary outcomes, we estimated a linear probability model to facilitate interpretation of the coefficient estimates. These results were robust to those generated from a logistic regression model. For the expenditure outcomes, we estimated 2-part models to account for the skewed nature of health care spending using the twopm command in Stata.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> The first stage was estimated using a probit model, whereas the second stage was estimated using ordinary least squares. We combined the 2 stages and presented the overall marginal effects and SEs generated using the delta method.</p><p>Additionally, the longitudinal nature of the MEPS allowed us to separate the immediate and longer-term associations of cancer history with the outcomes. Because some individuals who entered the survey before 2016 were diagnosed between the first and second time that they were asked about their cancer status, we examined the association of cancer with the outcomes within individuals over time. In this model, we demeaned all variables by calculating the person-level mean and then subtracting the round-specific values from that mean. We then estimated the aforementioned model without the race and ethnicity controls, as these were only collected once and were thus time invariant. All variables except employment and disability were collected as annual measures (income and expenditures) or were collected only once per year (cancer, SNAP). The employment outcomes were collected in each round, so these were mapped to the year in which the first report of cancer occurred. Our estimation approach was mathematically equivalent to including individual fixed effects in the regression model. That is, the model estimated the mean 1-year difference in outcomes before and after a person&#8217;s cancer diagnosis compared with the 1-year difference in outcomes for other individuals who had not been diagnosed with cancer within that past year. Finally, we estimated models that relied only on data from each respondent&#8217;s second year in the survey; this allowed us to separately analyze the incidence of cancers that were diagnosed within the past year and cancers that were diagnosed more than a year earlier. Two-sided <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.05 was considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-3-ZOI230477"><title>Results</title><p>Of 39&#8201;439 unique MEPS respondents included in the study, 52% were female and 48% were male; the mean (SD) age was 61.44 (8.32) years (<xref rid="zoi230477t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). A total of 5% of individuals were Asian or Pacific Islander; 11%, Black; 10%, Hispanic; 1% Native American or Alaska Native; 73%, White; and 1%, multiracial. A total of 12% of respondents had a prior cancer diagnosis excluding nonmelanoma skin cancers. National estimates of the number of people with a reported cancer history were 5.7 million people aged 50 to 64 years and 13.1 million people aged 50 to 79 years in 2016. Because of the MEPS panel structure, each individual had numerous observations (typically 6; individuals were surveyed 5 times but were given a sixth observation for the combined, annual measures in their second year). However, most variables used in our analysis were constant within each person-year. The most common cancers in the sample were breast, prostate, melanoma, and other. As reported in <xref rid="zoi230477t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, cancer survivors were more likely to be White, to not be working, to be older, and to have lower earnings and higher medical expenditures.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi230477t1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1. </label><caption><title>Descriptive Statistics of Variables Used in Analysis</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="41.95%" span="1"/><col width="19.35%" span="1"/><col width="19.35%" span="1"/><col width="19.35%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1"/><th colspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Mean (SD)<xref rid="zoi230477t1n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">All</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer history</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No cancer history</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reported cancer history<xref rid="zoi230477t1n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Any</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (32)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 (0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Bladder</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (18)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (18)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Breast</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (44)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (44)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Colon</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (25)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (25)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Lung</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (18)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (18)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Lymphoma</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (19)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (19)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Melanoma</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (32)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (32)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (42)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (42)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Prostate</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (38)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (38)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Uterine</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (22)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (22)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cervical</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (22)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (22)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Individual earnings, $<xref rid="zoi230477t1n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42&#8201;159.24 (46&#8201;085.73)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38&#8201;240.27 (47&#8201;610.72)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42&#8201;506.51 (45&#8201;932.03)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Employed<xref rid="zoi230477t1n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (45)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (49)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (44)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Work-limiting disability<xref rid="zoi230477t1n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (29)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (39)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (28)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public assistance income</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1183.98 (4207.64)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1438.83 (4732.17)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1150.27 (4132.10)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Received supplemental nutrition assistance program</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (28)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (28)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (28)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public medical expenditures, $</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3839.84 (13&#8201;112.04)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8016.66 (21&#8201;315.06)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3287.33 (11&#8201;487.19)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total medical expenditures, $</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8448.45 (19&#8201;136.49)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8201;099.58 (30&#8201;527.46)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7568.63 (16&#8201;874.38)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, y</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.44 (8.32)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.43 (8.22)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.91 (8.19)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race and ethnicity<xref rid="zoi230477t1n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Asian or Pacific Islander</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (21)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (14)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (22)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Black</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (28)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (31)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hispanic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (30)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (24)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (31)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Native American or Alaska Native</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (45)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (39)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (45)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Multiracial</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (50)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (49)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (50)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (50)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (49)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (50)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observations, No.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195&#8201;360</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#8201;289</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175&#8201;071</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="zoi230477t1n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Data are presented as mean (SD) percentage of patients unless otherwise indicated.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230477t1n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Cancer history was defined as reporting a past cancer diagnosis but excluded those whose only reported diagnosis was a nonmelanoma skin cancer. Cancer type categories do not sum to 1 because of individuals who had been diagnosed with multiple types.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230477t1n3"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>Employment-related outcomes were restricted to individuals younger than 65 years.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230477t1n4"><label>
<sup>d</sup>
</label><p>Race and ethnicity groups were defined to be mutually exclusive, so multiracial and Hispanic individuals are not included in other categories.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Based on multivariate regression analyses (<xref rid="zoi230477t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), a history of cancer was associated with a statistically significant 9.08 (95% CI, 6.22-11.94) percentage point reduction in the probability of employment, a 9.80 (95% CI, 7.35-12.25) percentage point increase in the probability of having a work-limiting disability, and a 1.45 (95% CI, 0.39-2.51) percentage point increase in SNAP receipt. Nationally, these results indicated that cancer accounted for 505&#8201;768 fewer employed individuals in the population aged 50 to 64 years, 545&#8201;873 more individuals with a work-preventing disability in the population aged 50 to 64 years, and 189&#8201;876 more SNAP recipients in the population aged 50 to 79 years. Based on 2-part regression models (<xref rid="zoi230477t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>), a cancer history was associated with $2722 (95% CI, $2131-$3313) greater medical spending, $6460 (95% CI, $5254-$7667) greater public medical spending, and $515 (95% CI, $337-$692) greater other public assistance spending.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi230477t2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2. </label><caption><title>Association of Cancer History With Employment, Disability, and Receipt of SNAP<xref rid="zoi230477t2n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="23.99%" span="1"/><col width="22.07%" span="1"/><col width="32.21%" span="1"/><col width="21.73%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Employed</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Work-limiting disability</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Received SNAP</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reported cancer history, regression coefficient (SE), percentage points</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;9.08 (1.46)<xref rid="zoi230477t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.80 (1.25)<xref rid="zoi230477t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45 (0.54)<xref rid="zoi230477t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population estimate, No.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">505&#8201;768</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">545&#8201;873</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189&#8201;876</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observations, No.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113&#8201;550</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113&#8201;550</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168&#8201;090</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R</italic>
<sup>2</sup>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviation: SNAP, Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program.</p><fn id="zoi230477t2n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Regression estimates are based on linear probability models. Nonmelanoma skin cancers were removed from the cancer variable. Age, age-squared, sex, and race and ethnicity were included as controls in the regression model. Population estimates are derived from multiplying the coefficient on cancer history by Medical Expenditure Panel Study estimates of the population aged 50 to 64 years who reported ever having cancer (employed and work-limiting disability) or aged 50 to 79 years who reported ever having cancer (received SNAP).</p></fn><fn id="zoi230477t2n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi230477t3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3. </label><caption><title>Association of Cancer History With Earnings, Public Assistance, and Medical Expenditures<xref rid="zoi230477t3n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="21.73%" span="1"/><col width="19.56%" span="1"/><col width="19.57%" span="1"/><col width="19.57%" span="1"/><col width="19.57%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Individual earnings<xref rid="zoi230477t3n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public assistance income<xref rid="zoi230477t3n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public medical expenditures<xref rid="zoi230477t3n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total medical expenditures<xref rid="zoi230477t3n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reported cancer history, coefficient estimate (SE), $</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;270 (1748)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">515 (90)<xref rid="zoi230477t3n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6460 (616)<xref rid="zoi230477t3n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2722 (302)<xref rid="zoi230477t3n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observations, No.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113&#8201;550</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168&#8201;090</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168&#8201;090</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168&#8201;090</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="zoi230477t3n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>The 2-part models are from a probit regression for having a nonzero value for each outcome and an ordinary least squares regression for the continuous outcome conditional on having a nonzero value. The models were combined into a single marginal effect using the margins, dydx Stata option. Nonmelanoma skin cancers were removed from the cancer variable. Age, age-squared, sex, and race and ethnicity were included as controls.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230477t3n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Sample restricted to people aged 50 to 64 years.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230477t3n3"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>Sample restricted to people aged 50 to 79 years.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230477t3n4"><label>
<sup>d</sup>
</label><p><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>When we examined the within-person association of reporting a new cancer for the first time with the outcomes (<xref rid="zoi230477t4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>), we found that an initial cancer diagnosis was associated with a statistically significant $15&#8201;398 (95% CI, $7235-$23&#8201;561) increase in total medical expenditures and a $9087 (95% CI, $2151-$16&#8201;023) increase in public medical expenditures. When we examined the timing of a cancer diagnosis (<xref rid="zoi230477t5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>), the estimates were generally larger for cancers first reported more recently, although the smaller number of people receiving a recent initial report added some noise to these estimates. Nonetheless, we found a significant association between a cancer report and the outcome variables after more than 1 year.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi230477t4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4. </label><caption><title>Association of New Cancer Report With Outcomes<xref rid="zoi230477t4n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="14.31%" span="1"/><col width="12.23%" span="1"/><col width="12.25%" span="1"/><col width="12.23%" span="1"/><col width="12.25%" span="1"/><col width="12.23%" span="1"/><col width="12.25%" span="1"/><col width="12.25%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Employed, percentage points<xref rid="zoi230477t4n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Work-limiting disability, percentage points<xref rid="zoi230477t4n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public assistance income, $<xref rid="zoi230477t4n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Individual earnings, $<xref rid="zoi230477t4n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Received SNAP, percentage points<xref rid="zoi230477t4n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total medical expenditures, $<xref rid="zoi230477t4n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public medical expenditures, $<xref rid="zoi230477t4n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">New cancer report, coefficient estimate (SE)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;2.05 (1.41)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 (0.74)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112.0 (269.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;656.7 (3851)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81 (1.12)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8201;398 (4165)<xref rid="zoi230477t4n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9087 (3539)<xref rid="zoi230477t4n5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>e</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observations, No.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113&#8201;550</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113&#8201;550</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168&#8201;090</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113&#8201;550</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168&#8201;090</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168&#8201;090</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168&#8201;090</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviation: SNAP, Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program.</p><fn id="zoi230477t4n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>The coefficients are from regressions of the demeaned outcome on the demeaned cancer report variable. Coefficients can be interpreted as the association between a new cancer report and the outcomes of interest. Nonmelanoma skin cancers were removed from the cancer variable. Age and age-squared were included as controls.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230477t4n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Sample restricted to people aged 50 to 64 years.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230477t4n3"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>Sample restricted to people aged 50 to 79 years.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230477t4n4"><label>
<sup>d</sup>
</label><p><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.01.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230477t4n5"><label>
<sup>e</sup>
</label><p><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi230477t5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5. </label><caption><title>Cancer Outcomes by Timing<xref rid="zoi230477t5n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="13.79%" span="1"/><col width="11.74%" span="1"/><col width="11.63%" span="1"/><col width="11.51%" span="1"/><col width="11.99%" span="1"/><col width="10.86%" span="1"/><col width="14.24%" span="1"/><col width="14.24%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Employed, percentage points<xref rid="zoi230477t5n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zoi230477t5n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Work-limiting disability, percentage points<xref rid="zoi230477t5n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zoi230477t5n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public assistance income, $<xref rid="zoi230477t5n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zoi230477t5n5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>e</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Individual earnings, $<xref rid="zoi230477t5n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zoi230477t5n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Received SNAP, percentage points<xref rid="zoi230477t5n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zoi230477t5n5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>e</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total medical expenditures, $<xref rid="zoi230477t5n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zoi230477t5n5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>e</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public medical expenditures, $<xref rid="zoi230477t5n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="zoi230477t5n5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>e</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">New cancer report, coefficient estimate (SE)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;11.0 (4.62)<xref rid="zoi230477t5n6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>f</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.32 (3.10)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500.3 (244.8)<xref rid="zoi230477t5n6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>f</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;552.9 (4524)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.37 (2.04)<xref rid="zoi230477t5n6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>f</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8201;046 (4033)<xref rid="zoi230477t5n7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>g</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8206 (2543)<xref rid="zoi230477t5n7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>g</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Old cancer report, coefficient estimate (SE)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;8.85 (1.71)<xref rid="zoi230477t5n7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>g</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.30 (1.47)<xref rid="zoi230477t5n7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>g</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">543.9 (103.2)<xref rid="zoi230477t5n7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>g</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1394 (1892)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.57)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5912 (794.0)<xref rid="zoi230477t5n7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>g</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2344 (330.1)<xref rid="zoi230477t5n7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>g</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observations, No.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55&#8201;011</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55&#8201;011</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83&#8201;484</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55&#8201;011</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83&#8201;484</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83&#8201;484</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83&#8201;484</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviation: SNAP, Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program.</p><fn id="zoi230477t5n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Regressions included only the second year of Medical Expenditure Panel Study respondents&#8217; time in the survey so that we could distinguish between the first time a past cancer was reported and the second time. Nonmelanoma skin cancers were removed from the cancer variable. Age, age-squared, sex, and race and ethnicity were included as controls. A new cancer report was one within the past year and old, longer than 1 year ago.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230477t5n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Regression estimates are based on linear probability models.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230477t5n3"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>Sample restricted to people aged 50 to 64 years.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230477t5n4"><label>
<sup>d</sup>
</label><p>The 2-part model results are from a probit regression for having a nonzero value for each outcome and an ordinary least squares regression for the continuous outcome conditional on having a nonzero value. The models were combined into a single marginal effect using the margins, dydx Stata option.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230477t5n5"><label>
<sup>e</sup>
</label><p>Sample restricted to people aged 50 to 79 years.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230477t5n6"><label>
<sup>f</sup>
</label><p><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.05.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230477t5n7"><label>
<sup>g</sup>
</label><p><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="H1-4-ZOI230477"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, we found that a history of cancer was associated with significant social costs, including increased likelihood of disability, higher medical care spending, and decreased likelihood of employment. These costs are typically not considered when evaluating the high societal burden of cancer. Given current disparities in cancer rates by geography, income, education, and race,<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> these costs may be particularly high for more disadvantaged groups.</p><p>Prior research in the US,<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> UK,<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> and Germany<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> found that health shocks were associated with significant increases in the likelihood of leaving the labor force. Moreover, the burdens of health shocks were typically greater for individuals with the least earning potential. This result suggests that future research may help in understanding of the equity implications of the employment and medical expenditure associations with cancer history. Cong et al<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> found that reductions in employment in the US market were greater for individuals diagnosed with metastatic cancer compared with those diagnosed with nonmetastatic cancer. This finding suggests that further study of how reducing the incidence or the burden of late stage cancer either through earlier detection or more effective treatment may impact the associations found in our study and potentially ameliorate some of the disparities found in prior studies.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230477r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230477r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230477r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup></p><p>A large body of research literature has examined the underlying reasons for health care disparities. Potential explanations include differences in insurance coverage,<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> income,<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> environment,<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> and access to high-quality health care.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> Policy efforts to address these underlying factors would help to address variation in the outcomes for cancer survivors found in this study. Some of the observed disparities may also be related to differential access to early detection<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> and treatment,<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> especially during the COVID-19 pandemic.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> Efforts to increase screening and treatment for historically disadvantaged groups have the potential to mitigate disparities connected to the social costs found in our study.</p><p>Our research builds on earlier studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> that found that cancer history was associated with lower employment and less earnings. A 2009 meta-analysis of 36 studies concluded that cancer survivors had roughly double the probability of being unemployed compared with those without a cancer history.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Using more recent data, our study found that cancer survivors were roughly one-third more likely to be unemployed than those without a cancer history. Although the gap remains sizeable, our study suggests that more recent data show progress in reducing it. In terms of earnings, prior studies have found a short-term decline in earnings ranging from 10% to 40%.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230477r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> However, we did not observe a statistically significant association between cancer history and earnings in the short term (&lt;1 year) or long term. Finally, a number of studies have documented the financial toxicity associated with cancer treatment.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> Our study extends this result by showing that this financial burden may persist for years after cancer diagnosis. For example, we found that a cancer history was associated with an increase in annual total medical spending of almost one-third.</p><sec id="H2-2-ZOI230477"><title>Limitations</title><p>This analysis was limited in several ways. First, MEPS does not ask about cancer stage or metastasis. Late-stage cancers may have an association with worse employment and income-related outcomes analyzed in this study.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> Second, our results do not account for survivor&#8217;s bias, in which cancer survivors will inevitably differ from the full set of individuals diagnosed with cancer. For example, our estimates on earlier screening for cancer would lead not only to downstaging among existing cancer survivors but also to increasing the number and types of individuals surviving cancer. However, although patients with cancer experience diminished well-being in the short term across a variety of measures, cancer survivors do as well as or better than US residents of similar age and demographic characteristics in the long term.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> Third, there may be some measurement error associated with self-reported cancer diagnosis. For example, cervical cancer has been found to be misclassified in self-reported data.<sup><xref rid="zoi230477r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup></p><p>Fourth, although we controlled for the available covariates in our models, other unobserved factors may be correlated with cancer risk and our outcomes of interest. Our model that controlled for person-level fixed effects could address those unobserved person-level factors, but that model only examined the short-term outcomes associated with new cancers.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-5-ZOI230477"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In this cross-sectional study of US data, cancer survivors were found to have a lower likelihood of employment and a greater likelihood of a work-limiting disability compared with individuals without a history of cancer. Nationally, our results indicated that cancer accounted for 505&#8201;768 fewer employed individuals in the population aged 50 to 64 years and was associated with significantly higher medical and public assistance expenditures.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="REF-ZOI230477"><title>References</title><ref id="zoi230477r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Farrelly</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>50 Years of the &#8220;war on cancer&#8221;: lessons for public health and geroscience</article-title>. <source>Geroscience</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1229</fpage>-<lpage>1235</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11357-021-00366-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33860442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8049618</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>The White House</collab></person-group>. Fact sheet: President Biden reignites cancer moonshot to end cancer as we know it. February 2, <year>2022</year>. Accessed April 22, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefing-room/statements-releases/2022/02/02/fact-sheet-president-biden-reignites-cancer-moonshot-to-end-cancer-as-we-know-it/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefing-room/statements-releases/2022/02/02/fact-sheet-president-biden-reignites-cancer-moonshot-to-end-cancer-as-we-know-it/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tabatabai</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ohn</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Curry</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Association between clinical value and financial cost of cancer treatments: a cross-sectional analysis</article-title>. <source>J Natl Compr Canc Netw</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1349</fpage>-<lpage>1353</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6004/jnccn.2020.7574</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33022648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8354655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chernew</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelgawad</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sollano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Grabowski</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>New anticancer drugs associated with large increases in costs and life expectancy</article-title>. <source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1581</fpage>-<lpage>1587</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2016.0286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27605636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lakdawalla</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jena</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Philipson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>An economic evaluation of the war on cancer</article-title>. <source>J Health Econ</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>333</fpage>-<lpage>346</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhealeco.2010.02.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20363520</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seabury</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Quantifying gains in the war on cancer due to improved treatment and earlier detection</article-title>. <source>Forum Health Econ Policy</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>141</fpage>-<lpage>156</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/fhep-2015-0028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31419891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jena</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lakdawalla</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Philipson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The contributions of improved therapy and earlier detection to cancer survival gains, 1988-2000</article-title>. <source>Forum Health Econ Policy</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2202/1558-9544.1195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Philipson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lakdawalla</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Corral</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Conti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>An analysis of whether higher health care spending in the United States versus Europe is &#8216;worth it&#8217; in the case of cancer</article-title>. <source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>667</fpage>-<lpage>675</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2011.1298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22492882</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3829769</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Riphahn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Income and employment effects of health shocks: a test case for the German welfare state</article-title>. <source>J Popul Econ</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>363</fpage>-<lpage>389</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001480050104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Healthy bodies and thick wallets: the dual relation between health and economic status</article-title>. <source>J Econ Perspect</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>144</fpage>-<lpage>166</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1257/jep.13.2.145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15179962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3697076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Disney</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Emmerson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wakefield</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Ill health and retirement in Britain: a panel data-based analysis</article-title>. <source>J Health Econ</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>621</fpage>-<lpage>649</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhealeco.2005.05.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16678924</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Taskila</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ojaj&#228;rvi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>van Dijk</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Verbeek</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer survivors and unemployment: a meta-analysis and meta-regression</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>301</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>753</fpage>-<lpage>762</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2009.187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19224752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The long-term effects of cancer on employment and earnings</article-title>. <source>Health Econ</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>671</fpage>-<lpage>684</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hec.3342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27045223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zajacova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dowd</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schoeni</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Employment and income losses among cancer survivors: Estimates from a national longitudinal survey of American families</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>121</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>4425</fpage>-<lpage>4432</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cncr.29510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26501494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4670608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>National Cancer Institute</collab></person-group>. Financial burden of cancer care. Accessed May 13, 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://progressreport.cancer.gov/after/economic_burden" ext-link-type="uri">https://progressreport.cancer.gov/after/economic_burden</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>GP</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ekwueme</surname><given-names>DU</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yabroff</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Economic burden of cancer survivorship among adults in the United States</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>30</issue>):<fpage>3749</fpage>-<lpage>3757</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2013.49.1241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24043731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3795887</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Look</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Health care expenditure burden of cancer care in the United States</article-title>. <source>Inquiry</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<elocation-id>46958019880696</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0046958019880696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31583928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6778988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">Social Security Administration. Annual statistical report on the Social Security Disability Insurance Program, 2020. Accessed April 22, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ssa.gov/policy/docs/statcomps/di_asr/2020/index.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ssa.gov/policy/docs/statcomps/di_asr/2020/index.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>Center on Budget and Policy Priorities</collab></person-group>. Chart book: Social Security Disability Insurance. <year>2021</year>. Accessed April 22, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cbpp.org/research/social-security/social-security-disability-insurance-0" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cbpp.org/research/social-security/social-security-disability-insurance-0</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Selden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Catlin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heffler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Reconciling medical expenditure estimates from the MEPS and NHEA, 2007</article-title>. <source>Medicare Medicaid Res Rev</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<elocation-id>mmrr.002.04.a09</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5600/mmrr.002.04.a09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24800157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4006479</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>Bureau of Labor Statistics</collab></person-group>. Data comparisons. Accessed March 31, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.bls.gov/cex/cecomparison/meps_profile.htm" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.bls.gov/cex/cecomparison/meps_profile.htm</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Belotti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Deb</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>twopm: Two-part models</article-title>. <source>Stata J</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1536867X1501500102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>American Cancer Society</collab></person-group>. Cancer facts &amp; figures 2022. April 22, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures/2022/2022-cancer-facts-and-figures.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures/2022/2022-cancer-facts-and-figures.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. Productivity loss associated with late versus early stage cancer diagnosis. Paper presented at: National Comprehensive Cancer Network Annual Conference; March 31, 2022; New York, New York.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Begg</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Racial differences in the treatment of early-stage lung cancer</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>341</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>1198</fpage>-<lpage>1205</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM199910143411606</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10519898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Keating</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Racial differences in breast cancer stage at diagnosis in the mammography era</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>103</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>170</fpage>-<lpage>176</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2011.300550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22698058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3518347</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>DeSantis</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer statistics for African Americans, 2016: progress and opportunities in reducing racial disparities</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>290</fpage>-<lpage>308</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/caac.21340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26910411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>American Association for Cancer Research</collab></person-group>. AACR cancer disparities progress report 2022. April 13, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.CancerDisparitiesProgressReport.org/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.CancerDisparitiesProgressReport.org/</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-22-0542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35675281</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sohn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Racial and ethnic disparities in health insurance coverage: dynamics of gaining and losing coverage over the life-course</article-title>. <source>Popul Res Policy Rev</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>181</fpage>-<lpage>201</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11113-016-9416-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28366968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5370590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Braveman</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cubbin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Egerter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pamuk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Socioeconomic disparities in health in the United States: what the patterns tell us</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>)(<supplement>suppl 1</supplement>):<fpage>S186</fpage>-<lpage>S196</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2009.166082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20147693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2837459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Environmental health disparities in housing</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>101</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>)(<supplement>suppl 1</supplement>):<fpage>S115</fpage>-<lpage>S122</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2010.300058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21551378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3222490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Landon</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Onnela</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Meneades</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Malley</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Keating</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of racial disparities in primary care physician specialty referrals</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<elocation-id>e2029238</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.29238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33492373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7835717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ashrafzadeh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Asgari</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Geller</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The need for critical examination of disparities in immunotherapy and targeted therapy use among patients with cancer</article-title>. <source>JAMA Oncol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1115</fpage>-<lpage>1116</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaoncol.2021.1322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34042941</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Racial and ethnic disparities in cancer care during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<elocation-id>e2222009</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.22009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35834248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9284331</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ehsan</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Minasian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Financial toxicity among patients with breast cancer worldwide: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<elocation-id>e2255388</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.55388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36753274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9909501</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thornton Snider</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>van Eijndhoven</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Okoro</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Batt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>DeLeire</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The well-being of long-term cancer survivors</article-title>. <source>Am J Manag Care</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>188</fpage>-<lpage>195</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29668209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230477r37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The help of HPV integration testing to avoid the misdiagnosis of a patient with stage IA1 cervical cancer: a case report and literature review</article-title>. <source>Pharmgenomics Pers Med</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1457</fpage>-<lpage>1461</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/PGPM.S310345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34819743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8608241</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><notes notes-type="supplementary-material" id="note-ZOI230477-1"><supplementary-material id="note-ZOI230477-1-s" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplement.</label><caption><p>
Data Sharing Statement
</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2315823-s001.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></notes></back></article></pmc-articleset>