<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="brief-report" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Health Forum</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Health Forum</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3211</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jamasd</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JAMA Health Forum</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2689-0186</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>JAMA Network</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11065164</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11065164.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11065164</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11065164</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38607643</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamahealthforum.2024.0501</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">abr240001</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="domain" specific-use="print"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Brief Report</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="online-only"><subject>Online Only</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="allowCommenting"><subject>Comments</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>High-Acuity Alcohol-Related Complications During the COVID-19 Pandemic</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="headline">High-Acuity Alcohol-Related Complications During the COVID-19 Pandemic</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">High-Acuity Alcohol-Related Complications During the COVID-19 Pandemic</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shuey</surname><given-names initials="B">Bryant</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="abr240001aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="abr240001aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Halbisen</surname><given-names initials="A">Alyssa</given-names></name><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="abr240001aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lakoma</surname><given-names initials="M">Matthew</given-names></name><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="abr240001aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="F">Fang</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="abr240001aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Argetsinger</surname><given-names initials="S">Stephanie</given-names></name><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="abr240001aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names initials="EC">Emily C.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="abr240001aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="abr240001aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Druss</surname><given-names initials="BG">Benjamin G.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="abr240001aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names initials="H">Hefei</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="abr240001aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wharam</surname><given-names initials="JF">J. Franklin</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="abr240001aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="abr240001aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref><xref rid="abr240001aff7" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="abr240001aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Population Medicine, Harvard Pilgrim Health Care Institute, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts</aff><aff id="abr240001aff2"><label>2</label>Now with Center for Research on Health Care, Division of General Internal Medicine, Department of Medicine, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania</aff><aff id="abr240001aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Health Systems and Population Health, University of Washington School of Public Health, Seattle</aff><aff id="abr240001aff4"><label>4</label>Health Services Research and Development, Center of Innovation for Veteran-Centered and Value-Driven Care, Veterans Affairs Puget Sound Health Care System, Seattle, Washington</aff><aff id="abr240001aff5"><label>5</label>Rollins School of Public Health, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia</aff><aff id="abr240001aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Medicine, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina</aff><aff id="abr240001aff7"><label>7</label>Duke-Margolis Institute for Health Policy, Durham, North Carolina</aff><author-notes><title>Article Information</title><p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> February 15, 2024.</p><p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published:</bold> April 12, 2024. doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamahealthforum.2024.0501</uri></p><p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-license-permissions" ext-link-type="uri">CC-BY License</ext-link>. &#169; 2024 Shuey B et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Health Forum</italic>.</p><corresp id="abr240001cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Bryant Shuey, MD, MPH, Center for Research on Health Care, Division of General Internal Medicine, Department of Medicine, University of Pittsburgh, 200 Meyran Ave, Pittsburgh, PA 15201 (<email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bryant.shuey@pitt.edu">bryant.shuey@pitt.edu</email>).</corresp><p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Dr Wharam had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Concept and design:</italic> Shuey, Williams, Druss, Wen, Wharam.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> Shuey, Halbisen, Lakoma, Zhang, Argetsinger, Wen, Wharam.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Shuey.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> All authors.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Statistical analysis:</italic> Shuey, Lakoma, Zhang, Wharam.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Obtained funding: </italic>Williams, Wen, Wharam.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Halbisen, Argetsinger, Wharam.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Supervision:</italic> Williams, Wen, Wharam.</p><p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr Zhang reported receiving postmarket safety study stipends from Pfizer and GlaxoSmithKline outside the submitted work. No other disclosures were reported.</p><p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> This work was supported by a grant from the National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (R01AA029819 to Dr Wharam, Dr Wen, Dr Zhang, Dr Druss, Mr Lakoma, and Ms Argetsinger). Dr Shuey was supported for this work by the Department of Population Medicine in the Harvard Pilgrim Health Care Institute, which is connected to the Institutional National Research Service Awards T32HP32715 and T32HP42013. Dr Shuey was also supported for this work by a grant from the National Institute on Drug Abuse (K12DA050607).</p><p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The funders had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p><p content-type="data-sharing-statement"><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> See <xref rid="note-ABR240001-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>.</p></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2024-04-12T10:00"><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">461510</issue-id><elocation-id>e240501</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>12</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>03</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-03 10:25:15.480"><day>03</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright 2024 Shuey B et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Health Forum</italic>.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jamahealthforum-e240501.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamahealthforum-e240501.pdf">jamahealthforum-e240501.pdf</self-uri><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/channels/health-forum/fullarticle/10.1001/jamahealthforum.2024.0501"/><abstract abstract-type="teaser" specific-use="electronic"><p>This cohort study assesses trends in people with high-acuity alcohol-related complications admitted to the emergency department, observation unit, or hospital during the COVID-19 pandemic, focusing on demographic differences.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="key-points"><title>Key Points</title><sec id="ab-abr240001-1"><title>Question</title><p>Was the COVID-19 pandemic associated with increased rates of high-acuity alcohol-related complications?</p></sec><sec id="ab-abr240001-2"><title>Findings</title><p>In this cohort study of a US national, commercially insured population, high-acuity alcohol-related complication episodes increased beyond what was expected in 4 of 18 pandemic months. Women aged 40 to 64 years experienced increases of 33.3% to 56.0% in high-acuity complication episodes in 10 of 18 pandemic months, a pattern associated with a large and sustained increase in high-acuity alcohol-related liver disease complications.</p></sec><sec id="ab-abr240001-3"><title>Meaning</title><p>Findings underscore the need for increased attention to alcohol use disorder risk factors, alcohol use patterns, alcohol-related health effects, and alcohol regulations and policies, especially among women aged 40 to 64 years.</p></sec></abstract><abstract><sec id="ab-abr240001-4"><title>Importance</title><p>Research has demonstrated an association between the COVID-19 pandemic and increased alcohol-related liver disease hospitalizations and deaths. However, trends in alcohol-related complications more broadly are unclear, especially among subgroups disproportionately affected by alcohol use.</p></sec><sec id="ab-abr240001-5"><title>Objective</title><p>To assess trends in people with high-acuity alcohol-related complications admitted to the emergency department, observation unit, or hospital during the COVID-19 pandemic, focusing on demographic differences.</p></sec><sec id="ab-abr240001-6"><title>Design, Setting, and Participants</title><p>This longitudinal interrupted time series cohort study analyzed US national insurance claims data using Optum&#8217;s deidentified Clinformatics Data Mart database from March 2017 to September 2021, before and after the March 2020 COVID-19 pandemic onset. A rolling cohort of people 15 years and older who had at least 6 months of continuous commercial or Medicare Advantage coverage were included. Subgroups of interest included males and females stratified by age group. Data were analyzed from April 2023 to January 2024.</p></sec><sec id="ab-abr240001-7"><title>Exposure</title><p>COVID-19 pandemic environment from March 2020 to September 2021.</p></sec><sec id="ab-abr240001-8"><title>Main Outcomes and Measures</title><p>Differences between monthly rates vs predicted rates of high-acuity alcohol-related complication episodes, determined using claims-based algorithms and alcohol-specific diagnosis codes. The secondary outcome was the subset of complication episodes due to alcohol-related liver disease.</p></sec><sec id="ab-abr240001-9"><title>Results</title><p>Rates of high-acuity alcohol-related complications were statistically higher than expected in 4 of 18 pandemic months after March 2020 (range of absolute and relative increases: 0.4-0.8 episodes per 100&#8201;000 people and 8.3%-19.4%, respectively). Women aged 40 to 64 years experienced statistically significant increases in 10 of 18 pandemic months (range of absolute and relative increases: 1.3-2.1 episodes per 100&#8201;000 people and 33.3%-56.0%, respectively). In this same population, rates of complication episodes due to alcohol-related liver disease increased above expected in 16 of 18 pandemic months (range of absolute and relative increases: 0.8-2.1 episodes per 100&#8201;000 people and 34.1%-94.7%, respectively).</p></sec><sec id="ab-abr240001-10"><title>Conclusions and Relevance</title><p>In this cohort study of a national, commercially insured population, high-acuity alcohol-related complication episodes increased beyond what was expected in 4 of 18 COVID-19 pandemic months. Women aged 40 to 64 years experienced 33.3% to 56.0% increases in complication episodes in 10 of 18 pandemic months, a pattern associated with large and sustained increases in high-acuity alcohol-related liver disease complications. Findings underscore the need for increased attention to alcohol use disorder risk factors, alcohol use patterns, alcohol-related health effects, and alcohol regulations and policies, especially among women aged 40 to 64 years.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="H1-1-ABR240001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Alcohol use and alcohol-related deaths increased over the past decade, with mortality rising faster among women than men.<sup><xref rid="abr240001r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="abr240001r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Alcohol use complications are highest between the fourth and sixth decades of life, often due to alcohol-related liver disease (ALD) development.<sup><xref rid="abr240001r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="abr240001r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> The COVID-19 pandemic was associated with increased alcohol consumption, particularly among women, likely due to social isolation and stress.<sup><xref rid="abr240001r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> While several studies have examined differences in alcohol-related hepatitis hospitalizations or alcohol-related mortality in 2020 compared with prior years,<sup><xref rid="abr240001r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="abr240001r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="abr240001r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="abr240001r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="abr240001r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> a rigorous analysis of the pandemic&#8217;s effect on a broader set of high-acuity alcohol-related complications is lacking. Such analyses could provide granular information about how socially disruptive phenomena such as the COVID-19 pandemic affect alcohol use&#8211;related presentations to the health system. We hypothesized that the pandemic would be associated with increased high-acuity alcohol-related complications caused by higher alcohol consumption and barriers to outpatient treatment services.</p></sec><sec id="H1-2-ABR240001"><title>Methods</title><sec id="H2-1-ABR240001"><title>Study Design</title><p>We studied commercial claims data from Optum&#8217;s deidentified Clinformatics Data Mart database from March 2017 to September 2021. We conducted a longitudinal interrupted time series study of a rolling cohort aged 15 years and older with at least 6 months of continuous insurance enrollment. We measured presentations to the emergency department, observation unit, or hospital using claims-based algorithms and alcohol-specific <italic toggle="yes">International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems, Tenth Revision,</italic> diagnosis codes (eAppendix in <xref rid="note-ABR240001-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). We defined high-acuity alcohol-related complication episodes as conditions representing acute decompensation of chronic alcohol-related diseases that necessitated urgent or emergent management by a medical professional (eAppendix and eTable 1 in <xref rid="note-ABR240001-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).</p><p>The Duke University and Harvard Pilgrim Health Care Institute institutional review boards approved this study and waived need for informed consent because deidentified data were used. This report adheres to the Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/strobe/" ext-link-type="uri">STROBE</ext-link>) reporting guidelines.</p></sec><sec id="H2-2-ABR240001"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>We ran regression models with generalized estimating equations, an identity link, and robust standard errors to compare observed monthly rates after March 2020 to rates predicted by the trajectory of the March 2017 to February 2020 baseline fitted trend (eAppendix in <xref rid="note-ABR240001-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). Models adjusted for age group (15-39, 40-64, 65-74, and &#8805;75 years), sex, US division (9 divisions), poverty level of residence, and seasonality using quarterly indicators (eAppendix in <xref rid="note-ABR240001-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). Additional analyses were stratified by age group and sex. We also separately analyzed rates of high-acuity ALD episodes over time. We describe COVID-19 pandemic era trends (April 2020 to September 2021) and present estimates of differences between monthly rates of high-acuity alcohol-related complication episodes vs predicted rates.</p><p>The statistical analysis was performed using Stata, version 16 (StataCorp), and SAS Studio software, release 3.7, enterprise edition (SAS Institute). Results are reported based on 2-sided tests of statistical significance, defined as <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-3-ABR240001"><title>Results</title><p>Study characteristics in April 2017, April 2020, and April 2021 are summarized in eTable 2 in <xref rid="note-ABR240001-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>. Among high-acuity diagnoses, 54% to 66% were ALD related, 29% to 39% were alcohol withdrawal or alcohol-related mood disorders, 3% to 5% were alcohol-related cardiomyopathy, and 1% to 3% were alcohol-related gastritis with bleeding (eTable 3 in <xref rid="note-ABR240001-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). Other than a transient decrease in April 2020 and a reduction that was not statistically significant in February 2021, monthly rates of high-acuity alcohol-related complication episodes were higher than predicted in all follow-up months (<xref rid="abr240001f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> and the <xref rid="abr240001t1" ref-type="table">Table</xref>), though only 4 of 18 reached statistical significance. The range of absolute and relative increases in these 4 months was 0.4 to 0.8 episodes per 100&#8201;000 people and 8.3% to 19.4%, respectively.</p><fig position="float" id="abr240001f1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1. </label><caption><title>Monthly Rates of High-Acuity Alcohol-Related Complication Episodes Among a National Commercially Insured Population</title><p>Fitted and predicted rates were generated using unadjusted segmented regression. Absolute change estimates and 95% CIs (error bars) were generated from regression model coefficients using nonlinear combinations of parameters adjusted for member-level age category, sex, US division, seasonality, and poverty level of residence based on 5-digit zip code. A, Complication episodes across all age groups comprise diagnoses representing acute decompensation of chronic alcohol-related diseases presenting to the emergency department, observation unit, or hospital such as acute alcohol-related hepatitis, alcohol-related cardiomyopathy, or alcohol gastritis with bleeding. Diagnoses were independently developed and cross-verified by 2 authors (B.S. and J.F.W.). There was 95% agreement with classifications, and differences were reviewed and reconciled. B, Adults aged 40 to 64 years are shown because this age category had high rates of alcohol-related morbidity and mortality. Age category was not included in the regression model for analyses depicted. C and D, Male and female adults aged 40 to 64 years are shown to highlight differences in high-acuity alcohol-related complications. Age category and sex were not included in the regression models for analyses depicted. The vertical blue line indicates the time of declaration of the COVID-19 public health emergency.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jamahealthforum-e240501-g001.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="abr240001t1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table. </label><caption><title>Absolute and Relative Changes in Monthly Rates of High-Acuity Alcohol-Related Complication Episodes vs Predicted Rates During the April 2020 to September 2021 COVID-19 Pandemic Era<xref rid="abr240001t1n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="7.89%" span="1"/><col width="14.49%" span="1"/><col width="9.28%" span="1"/><col width="13.94%" span="1"/><col width="8.84%" span="1"/><col width="13.94%" span="1"/><col width="8.84%" span="1"/><col width="13.94%" span="1"/><col width="8.84%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Month</th><th colspan="8" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Change in composite high-acuity alcohol-related complications per 100&#8201;000 people</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Aged &#8805;15 y</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Aged 40-64 y</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Men aged 40-64 y</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Women aged 40-64 y</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Absolute (95% CI)<xref rid="abr240001t1n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative %<xref rid="abr240001t1n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absolute (95% CI)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative %</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absolute (95% CI)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative %</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absolute (95% CI)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative %</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.7 (&#8722;1.2 to &#8722;0.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;13.6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.6 (&#8722;1.8 to 0.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;6.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.4 (&#8722;3.2 to 0.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;11.6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (&#8722;0.7 to 1.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">May 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (&#8722;0.2 to 0.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.2 to 2.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (&#8722;0.8 to 2.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8 (0.7 to 2.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jun 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0 to 0.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0 to 2.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (&#8722;0.3 to 3.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (&#8722;0.4 to 1.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jul 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (&#8722;0.1 to 1.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 (&#8722;0.1 to 3.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (&#8722;0.5 to 3.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (&#8722;0.1 to 2.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aug 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0 to 1.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (&#8722;0.4 to 2.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (&#8722;1.5 to 2.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.3 to 2.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sep 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0 to 1.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.1 to 2.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (&#8722;1.2 to 2.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 (0.8 to 2.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oct 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (&#8722;0.2 to 0.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (0.3 to 2.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (&#8722;0.4 to 2.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 (0.3 to 2.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nov 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (&#8722;0.4 to 0.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 (&#8722;0.9 to 1.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.6 (&#8722;2.3 to 1.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;3.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (&#8722;0.1 to 2.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dec 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (&#8722;0.3 to 0.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (&#8722;0.3 to 1.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (&#8722;1.1 to 1.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (&#8722;0.1 to 1.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jan 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (&#8722;0.2 to 0.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (0 to 2.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (&#8722;0.5 to 3.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.2 to 2.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.3 (&#8722;0.7 to 0.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;6.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (&#8722;0.5 to 1.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (&#8722;1.4 to 2.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (&#8722;0.1 to 1.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 (&#8722;0.5 to 0.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 (0.1 to 2.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (&#8722;1.1 to 2.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 (0.8 to 3.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (&#8722;0.1 to 1.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (&#8722;0.6 to 2.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (&#8722;1.6 to 2.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (&#8722;0.1 to 2.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">May 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (0 to 1.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (0.4 to 3.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 (&#8722;0.3 to 5.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (0.5 to 2.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jun 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0 to 1.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (0.5 to 2.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (&#8722;0.6 to 3.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 (1.0 to 2.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jul 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (0.1 to 1.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (0.4 to 3.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (&#8722;0.6 to 4.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (0.8 to 3.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aug 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (&#8722;0.6 to 0.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (&#8722;1.1 to 2.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (&#8722;2.2 to 3.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (&#8722;0.5 to 2.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sep 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (&#8722;0.5 to 1.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (&#8722;0.9 to 2.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (&#8722;2.4 to 3.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (0.2 to 3.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="abr240001t1n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Absolute and relative changes vs predicted rates are presented for people with high-acuity alcohol-related complications presenting to the emergency department, observation unit, or hospital. Models for absolute changes adjusted for member-level age category, sex, US division, seasonality, and poverty level of residence based on 5-digit zip code. Age category was not included in models stratified by age, and sex was and not included in models stratified by sex.</p></fn><fn id="abr240001t1n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Absolute change estimates and 95% CIs were generated from adjusted regression model coefficients using nonlinear combinations of parameters.</p></fn><fn id="abr240001t1n3"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>Given that the adjusted relative changes are sensitive to the referent group chosen for each covariate in each model, unadjusted relative changes were calculated. Relative change estimates were calculated by dividing the unadjusted absolute change (unadjusted observed rate minus unadjusted predicted rate) by the unadjusted predicted rate for each pandemic month.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The subgroup of members aged 40 to 64 years had a similar but more pronounced pattern of pandemic-era increases. The magnitude of all monthly estimates after April 2020 was higher than predicted, with 9 reaching statistical significance. The range of absolute and relative increases in these 9 months was 1.1 to 2.1 episodes per 100&#8201;000 people and 16.9% to 35.9%, respectively. Women in this age group experienced statistically significant increases in 10 of 18 pandemic months, with a range of absolute and relative increases of 1.3 to 2.1 episodes per 100&#8201;000 people and 33.3% to 56.0%, respectively. Men in this age group did not experience statistically significant changes, though most pandemic-era estimates were positive in magnitude. Additional subgroup analyses by age group and sex revealed no consistent pandemic-era patterns and few statistically significant changes (eTable 4 in <xref rid="note-ABR240001-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).</p><p>The overall pattern of high-acuity ALD-related episode rates was similar to that of the broad complication outcome among the overall sample, the subgroups of members aged 40 to 64 years, and women and men in this age group (<xref rid="abr240001f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). However, women aged 40 to 64 years experienced statistically significant increases in 16 of 18 pandemic months, with a range of absolute and relative increases of 0.8 to 2.1 episodes per 100&#8201;000 people and 34.1% to 94.7%, respectively. Additional subgroup analyses of high-acuity ALD-related episodes by age group and sex revealed no consistent pandemic-era patterns among subgroups and few statistically significant changes (eTable 5 in <xref rid="note-ABR240001-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="abr240001f2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2. </label><caption><title>Monthly Rates of High-Acuity Alcohol-Related Liver Disease Complication Episodes Among a National Commercially Insured Population</title><p>Fitted and predicted rates were generated using unadjusted segmented regression. Absolute change estimates and 95% CIs (error bars) were generated from regression model coefficients using nonlinear combinations of parameters adjusted for member-level age category, sex, US division, seasonality, and poverty level of residence based on 5-digit zip code. A, Complication episodes across all age groups comprise alcohol-related liver disease diagnoses representing acute decompensation of chronic alcohol-related diseases presenting to the emergency department, observation unit, or hospital. Diagnoses were independently developed and cross-verified by 2 authors (B.S. and J.F.W.). There was 95% agreement with classifications, and differences were reviewed and reconciled. B, Adults aged 40 to 64 years are shown because this age category had high rates of alcohol-related morbidity and mortality. Age category was not included in the regression model for analyses depicted. C and D, Male and female adults aged 40 to 64 years are shown to highlight differences in high-acuity alcohol-related complications. Age category and sex were not included in the regression models for analyses depicted. The vertical blue line indicates the time of declaration of the COVID-19 public health emergency.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jamahealthforum-e240501-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="H1-4-ABR240001"><title>Discussion</title><p>The COVID-19 pandemic was associated with increases in high-acuity alcohol-related complication episodes in half of follow-up months among members aged 40 to 64 years in a national, commercially insured population. Women in this age group experienced increases in 10 of 18 follow-up months, which appeared to be associated with major relative increases in high-acuity ALD-related presentations in 16 of 18 pandemic months.</p><p>The increase in ALD-related complication episodes that we detected is consistent with recent analyses that have demonstrated increases in ALD-related hospitalizations and deaths, as well as alcohol-related deaths during the pandemic era.<sup><xref rid="abr240001r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="abr240001r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="abr240001r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="abr240001r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="abr240001r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="abr240001r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> Moreover, we add the key findings that the pandemic was associated with increases in a broader measure of alcohol-related complications and that changes primarily occurred among women aged 40 to 64 years. Rates of alcohol-related complications in this group remained elevated into late 2021, suggesting potentially sustained increases in alcohol-related harms. Although estimates among men aged 40 to 64 years did not reach statistical significance, they were consistently higher than predicted after April 2020, warranting further investigation with additional data sources.</p><p>Recent epidemiological patterns in alcohol use might help explain these results. Over the past decade, the 2-week prevalence of having 5 or more drinks in a row increased twice as quickly among women aged 35 to 50 years compared with men.<sup><xref rid="abr240001r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Unlike men, women had considerably more heavy drinking days (&#8805;4 drinks within a few hours) in 2020 compared with 2019.<sup><xref rid="abr240001r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Thus, longer-term increases in alcohol consumption might have increased the risk of ALD among women aged 40 to 64 years prior to the pandemic, then pandemic-related increases in alcohol consumption may have contributed to new or worsening ALD complications.</p><p>These findings imply a need for increased attention to alcohol use disorder (AUD) risk factors, alcohol use patterns, alcohol-related health effects, and related interventions, especially among women aged 40 to 64 years. Clinicians and population health managers should consider increasing screening efforts in this population. Policymakers should consider enhancing access to interventions including AUD treatment early in the disease process and closer collaboration with addiction clinicians and hepatologists. Evidence-based policies to reduce the aforementioned harms include increasing alcohol taxes, setting minimum alcohol prices, and limiting alcohol advertising.<sup><xref rid="abr240001r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> The persistent elevations in alcohol-related complications we detected in a relatively small population subgroup suggest a need for more granular public health monitoring. This study adds a novel, broad measure of acute decompensation of chronic alcohol-related diseases that might reflect alcohol consumption levels in the community, access to AUD treatment, and access to specialists such as hepatologists. Monitoring this measure could complement monitoring less common outcomes such as alcohol-related mortality, allowing identification of smaller, at-risk patient subgroups that require urgent and early interventions.</p><sec id="H2-3-ABR240001"><title>Limitations</title><p>Study limitations include underestimating high-acuity alcohol-related complications due to use of alcohol-specific billing codes, and potential changes in insurance enrollment patterns from before to after the pandemic. Further research is needed to determine whether the increases we observed persist several years after the pandemic onset.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-5-ABR240001"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In this cohort study, high-acuity alcohol-related complications, especially those associated with ALD, increased during the COVID-19 pandemic period among adults aged 40 to 64 years, particularly women. Findings underscore the need for increased attention to alcohol use disorder risk factors, alcohol use patterns, alcohol-related health effects, and alcohol regulations and policies, especially among women aged 40 to 64 years.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="REF-ABR240001"><title>References</title><ref id="abr240001r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miech</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Malley</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. Monitoring the future panel study annual report: national data on substance use among adults ages 19 to 60, 1976-2022. <person-group><collab>Institute for Social Research, University of Michigan</collab></person-group>. Accessed March 7, 2024. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://monitoringthefuture.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/mtfpanel2023.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://monitoringthefuture.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/mtfpanel2023.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="abr240001r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karaye</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maleki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yunusa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Trends in alcohol-related deaths by sex in the US, 1999-2020</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<elocation-id>e2326346</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.26346</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37505494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10383009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="abr240001r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Runyon</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Alcoholic hepatitis: a clinician&#8217;s guide</article-title>. <source>Clin Liver Dis</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>371</fpage>-<lpage>385</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cld.2012.03.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22541704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="abr240001r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Curtin</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Garnett</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. Alcohol-induced death rates in the United States, 2019&#8211;2020. <person-group><collab>National Center for Health Statistics</collab></person-group>. November <year>2022</year>. Accessed January 2, 2024. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/products/databriefs/db448.htm" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/products/databriefs/db448.htm</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="abr240001r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>HD</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in adult alcohol use and consequences during the COVID-19 pandemic in the US</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<elocation-id>e2022942</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.22942</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32990735</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7525354</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="abr240001r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sohal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhry</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on alcohol-related hepatitis admissions: analysis of nationwide data 2016-2020</article-title>. <source>Am J Med Sci</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>366</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>209</fpage>-<lpage>218</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjms.2023.06.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37315782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10259164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="abr240001r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marlowe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liangpunsakul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemic within a pandemic: alcohol-associated hepatitis and COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Alcohol Clin Exp Res (Hoboken)</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1883</fpage>-<lpage>1889</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/acer.15162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37553753</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="abr240001r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wadhwa</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kanwal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chhatwal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Alcohol-associated liver disease mortality rates by race before and during the COVID-19 pandemic in the US</article-title>. <source>JAMA Health Forum</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<elocation-id>e230527</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamahealthforum.2023.0527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37083825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10122166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="abr240001r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Castle</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hingson</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Koob</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Alcohol-related deaths during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>327</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>1704</fpage>-<lpage>1706</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2022.4308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35302593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8933830</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="abr240001r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Deutsch-Link</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peery</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barritt</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bataller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Alcohol-associated liver disease mortality increased from 2017 to 2020 and accelerated during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source>Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2142</fpage>-<lpage>2144.e2</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cgh.2022.03.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35314353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8933289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="abr240001r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">Implementing community-level policies to prevent alcohol misuse. <person-group><collab>Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration</collab></person-group>. Accessed March 7, 2024. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://store.samhsa.gov/sites/default/files/pep22-06-01-006.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://store.samhsa.gov/sites/default/files/pep22-06-01-006.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><notes notes-type="supplementary-material" id="note-ABR240001-1"><supplementary-material id="note-ABR240001-1-s" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplement 1.</label><caption><p>
eAppendix.
</p><p><bold>eTable 1.</bold> ICD-10 diagnostic billing codes used to identify high-acuity alcohol-related complications</p><p><bold>eTable 2.</bold> Population characteristics (n, %) in April 2017, April 2020, and April 2021</p><p><bold>eTable 3.</bold> Diagnostic clusters of high-acuity alcohol-related complications among a national commercially insured population aged 15 years and older presenting to the emergency department, observation unit, and hospital during the pre- and post-pandemic period</p><p><bold>eTable 4.</bold> Absolute and relative changes in monthly rates of high-acuity alcohol-related complication episodes versus predicted rates during the April 2020 to September 2021 pandemic era</p><p><bold>eTable 5.</bold> Absolute and relative changes in monthly rates of high-acuity alcohol-related liver disease complication episodes versus predicted rates during the April 2020 to September 2021 pandemic era</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jamahealthforum-e240501-s001.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplement 2.</label><caption><p>Data Sharing Statement</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jamahealthforum-e240501-s002.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></notes></back></article></pmc-articleset>