<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2757</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cureus</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11309071</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11309071.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11309071</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11309071</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39119443</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.64161</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Cardiology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Outcomes of ST-Elevation Myocardial Infarction in Patients With Opioid Dependence: A National Inpatient Sample Study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names initials="A">Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names initials="JR">John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names initials="AR">Abdel-Rhman</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelrahman</surname><given-names initials="A">Ahmad</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names initials="M">Momin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salih</surname><given-names initials="A">Ayman</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hersi</surname><given-names initials="J">Jama</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alharbi</surname><given-names initials="A">Abdulmajeed</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moustafa</surname><given-names initials="A">Abdelmoniem</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eltahawy</surname><given-names initials="E">Ehab</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Internal Medicine, The University of Toledo Medical Center, Toledo, USA </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Internal Medicine, The University of Toledo College of Medicine and Life Sciences, Toledo, USA </aff><aff id="aff-3">
<label>3</label>
Cardiovascular Medicine, The University of Toledo Medical Center, Toledo, USA </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Abdel-Rhman Mohamed <email>abdelrhman.mohamed@utoledo.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>9</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>7</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">465840</issue-id><elocation-id>e64161</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>09</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>08</day><month>08</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-08-28 17:25:27.790"><day>28</day><month>08</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2024, Mohamed et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Mohamed et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000064161.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/256093-outcomes-of-st-elevation-myocardial-infarction-in-patients-with-opioid-dependence-a-national-inpatient-sample-study">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/256093-outcomes-of-st-elevation-myocardial-infarction-in-patients-with-opioid-dependence-a-national-inpatient-sample-study</self-uri><abstract><p>Background: ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI) is a critical condition characterized by the sudden obstruction of one or more coronary arteries, resulting in diminished blood flow to the heart muscle. This acute ischemic event demands swift and precise intervention to minimize myocardial damage and preserve cardiac function. Opioids, a class of potent analgesic medications, are frequently utilized in the management of STEMI-related chest pain. Despite their efficacy in alleviating discomfort, their use in this context warrants careful consideration due to potential adverse effects and interactions.&#160;</p><p>Methods:&#8239;In this large nationwide retrospective observational study, we evaluated the effect of opioid dependence on inpatient mortality, length of hospitalization, and cost of hospitalization of patients with STEMI. Data was collected for 2019 from various hospitals across the United States using the National Inpatient Sample (NIS) through the Healthcare Cost and Utilization Project (HCUP). Using the International Classification of Diseases-10 codes (ICD-10), we identified a primary diagnosis of STEMI in patients over the age of 18, as well as a secondary diagnosis of opioid dependence.&#8239; Complex samples and multivariable logistic and linear regression models were used to determine the association of opioid dependence on inpatient mortality, length of hospitalization, and cost of hospitalization of patients with STEMI. Of the patients who fit our criteria, we identified other comorbidities and diagnoses associated with them as potential confounders including drug abuse, hypertension, diabetes, alcohol use, obesity, peripheral vascular disease, and chronic lung disease. Other confounders that&#160;were adjusted for include race, Charlson Comorbidity index, median household income,&#160;insurance, hospital region in the US, hospital bed size, and teaching status of the hospital.&#160;</p><p>Results:&#8239;A total of 661,990 patients presented to a hospital with a primary diagnosis of STEMI in 2019. The majority of the patients were male&#160;with a mean age of 62.5+/-3.4 and were Caucasian American. Patients who were opioid dependent were found to be on average younger, earned less than the 25th percentile household income, had a higher history of illicit drug and alcohol use, and had Medicaid. They were also found to have higher rates of chronic lung disease at 39.2%, compared to 21.4.% in patients who were not opioid-dependent. Patients who were not opioid dependent were found to have higher rates of hypertension and type 2 diabetes mellitus. Inpatient mortality and cost of hospitalization in STEMI patients with opioid dependence were not statistically different compared to those who were not opioid dependent. However, STEMI patients who were opioid dependent did have an associated longer length of hospitalization.&#160;</p><p>Conclusion:&#8239;Opioid use for pain relief in acute coronary syndrome, particularly STEMI, is a mainstay of treatment. Our retrospective cohort dived into assessing the relationship between opioid dependence on its effect on inpatient mortality, length of stay, and cost of hospitalization in STEMI patients. Our study showed that opioid dependence has no significant impact on inpatient mortality. However, it was associated with a longer length of hospital stay in STEMI patients. Further studies may be warranted into the effects of opioid dependence on the length of hospitalization in STEMI patients.&#8239;&#160;</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>illicit drug use</kwd><kwd>national inpatient sample (nis) and the healthcare cost and utilization project (hcup)</kwd><kwd>cad: coronary artery disease</kwd><kwd>opiate misuse</kwd><kwd>st-elevation myocardial infarction (stemi)</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Acute coronary syndromes (ACS), including ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI), non-STEMI (NSTEMI), and unstable angina, are responsible for one-third of total deaths in people older than 35 and affect&#160;about 15.5 million people in the United States [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. STEMI&#160;is a critical condition characterized by the sudden obstruction of one or more coronary arteries, resulting in diminished blood flow to the heart muscle. This acute ischemic event demands swift and precise intervention to minimize myocardial damage and preserve cardiac function. While the primary treatment for STEMI involves reperfusion strategies such as percutaneous coronary intervention or thrombolytic therapy, adjunctive pharmacotherapy plays a crucial role in managing associated symptoms and optimizing patient outcomes [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>Opioids, a class of potent analgesic medications, are frequently utilized in the management of STEMI-related chest pain. Despite their efficacy in alleviating discomfort, their use in this context warrants careful consideration due to potential adverse effects and interactions. Opioids exert their analgesic effects primarily through binding to opioid receptors in the central nervous system, thereby modulating pain perception and transmission. By mitigating the intensity of chest pain, opioids offer significant relief to STEMI patients, facilitating their comfort and cooperation during critical phases of diagnosis and treatment. Alternative analgesic strategies, such as nitroglycerin and nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), may be considered in select cases to minimize opioid exposure and mitigate potential complications. Bedson et al. investigated the risks associated with long-term opioid prescribing for musculoskeletal pain using data from the UK Clinical Practice Research Datalink. The results revealed dose-dependent increases in serious adverse events including major trauma, intentional overdose, addiction, falls, accidental poisoning, gastrointestinal pathology, and iron deficiency anemia. Higher opioid doses were associated with elevated risks across all outcomes [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>Despite the efficacy of opioids in alleviating discomfort, their use in ACS warrants careful consideration due to potential adverse effects and interactions. These potential adverse effects and interactions include, but are not limited to, hypotension, CNS depression, and sedation, as well as respiratory drive depression [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The administration of opioids in STEMI must be judiciously balanced with several considerations. Firstly, opioids can induce systemic vasodilation and hypotension, which may exacerbate myocardial ischemia and compromise cardiac perfusion&#160;[<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Additionally, these medications can depress respiratory drive and impair oxygenation, particularly in individuals with pre-existing respiratory conditions or compromised pulmonary function. Furthermore, opioids carry a risk of sedation and altered mental status, potentially masking clinical deterioration and delaying timely intervention. Therefore, clinicians must exercise caution when prescribing opioids to STEMI patients, carefully weighing the benefits of pain relief against the risks of adverse effects. This brings to question whether there are adverse outcomes of opioid use, particularly a history of opioid dependence, in the setting of STEMI. What we found was that inpatient mortality and total hospital charges in STEMI patients who were opioid dependent were not statistically different compared to those who were not opioid&#160;dependent. However, the length of stay of STEMI patients who were opioid dependent was statistically different compared to those who were not opioid dependent.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>Study design<italic toggle="yes">&#160;</italic>
</p><p>This is a retrospective observational study of patients over the age of 18 hospitalized with a primary diagnosis of STEMI and secondary diagnosis of opioid dependence in various hospitals across the United States in the year 2019.&#8239;&#8239;&#160;</p><p>Data source and sample&#160;</p><p>Data was collected using the National Inpatient Sample (NIS) through the Healthcare Cost and&#160;Utilization Project (HCUP). The primary diagnosis was identified using International&#160;Classification of Disease-10 codes (ICD).&#160;No approval from an ethical committee was warranted as no patient identifiers were used.</p><p>Variables of interest&#160;</p><p>Of the patients who fit our criteria, we identified other comorbidities and diagnoses associated with them as potential confounders including&#160;drug abuse, hypertension, diabetes, alcohol use, obesity, peripheral vascular disease, and chronic lung disease. Other confounders that were adjusted for include race, Charlson Comorbidity index, median household income, insurance, hospital region in the US, hospital bed size, and teaching status of the hospital.&#160;</p><p>Statistical analysis</p><p>Univariate and multivariable logistic and linear regression models were used to determine the association between opioid dependence on inpatient mortality, length of hospitalization, and cost of hospitalization of patients with STEMI. The statistical analysis was carried out using the STATA version 17.0 software (StataCorp LLC, College Station, Texas, USA). The study was not reported by STROBE guidelines. The data for categorical variables was expressed as percentages, whereas for continuous variables, mean &#177; SD was used. The test of normality was not performed as it was unable to be done using the STATA software analysis of the National Inpatient Sample. Student's t-test was used for comparing continuous variables, while the chi-square test was used for categorical variables. For the primary and secondary outcomes, unadjusted odds ratios were calculated using univariate regression analysis. To adjust for potential confounders and calculate adjusted odds ratios (aOR), multivariate regression analysis was used. Binary outcomes were analyzed using a logistic regression model, while continuous outcomes were analyzed using linear regression. The models were constructed by incorporating the variables associated with the outcome of interest in the univariable regression analysis, with a cut-off p-value of 0.02. This cut-off was used to be more accurate. All p-values were two-tailed, and the threshold for statistical significance was set at 0.05.&#160;</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>Patient demographics&#8239;<italic toggle="yes">&#160;</italic>
</p><p>A total of 661,990 patients presented to a hospital with a primary diagnosis of STEMI in 2019. The majority of the patients were male 61.8% with a mean age of 62.5+/-3.4 and were Caucasian Americans (Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Patients who were opioid dependent were found to be on average younger, earned less than the 25th percentile household income, had a higher history of illicit drug and alcohol use, and had Medicaid as their insurance. They were also found to have higher rates of chronic lung disease at 39.2%, compared to 21.4.% in patients who were not opioid dependent. Patients who were not opioid dependent were found to have higher rates of hypertension and type 2 diabetes mellitus, as well as be on Medicaid (Table <xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Demographics of STEMI patients with and without opioid dependence</title><p>Univariable regression analysis conducted to obtain the p-value. &#160;</p><p>p-value&lt;0.05 indicates statistical significance. STEMI: ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">STEMI with Opioid Use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">STEMI without Opioid Use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of patients</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5428 (0.82%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">656562 (99.18%)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.98</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female gender (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.26%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.25%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.1651</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Race (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.68%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.17%</td><td rowspan="11" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black or African-American</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.65%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.47%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian or Pacific Islander</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native American</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Charlson Comorbidity Index (%)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.41%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.87%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.06%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.34%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 or more</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.54%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.79%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Median Household Income in patients zip code (%)</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0-25th percentile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.51%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.09%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26th-50th percentile
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.83%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.53%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51st-75th&#160; percentile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.17%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.03%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76th-100th&#160; percentile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.49%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.35%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Insurance</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medicare</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.99%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.66%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medicaid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.56%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.99%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Private insurance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.43%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.85%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-pay</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.02%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Comorbidities of STEMI patients with and without opioid dependence.</title><p>Univariable regression analysis conducted to obtain the p-value.</p><p>p-value&lt;0.05 indicates statistical significance. STEMI: ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbidities</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">STEMI &#160;with Opioid Use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">STEMI without Opioid Use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug Abuse (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.92%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension, complicated (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.37%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.74%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.0955</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension, uncomplicated (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.09%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.03%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes, complicated (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.53%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.93%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.3130</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes, uncomplicated (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.77%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.33%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol use (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.68%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obesity (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.63%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.98%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.2921</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peripheral Vascular Disease (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.69%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.62%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.9437</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic Lung Disease (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.26%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.35%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Inpatient mortality outcome<italic toggle="yes">&#160;</italic>
</p><p>The total number of inhospital mortality was 29630 (4.5%). Inpatient mortality in STEMI patients who were opioid dependent was not statistically different compared to those who were not opioid&#160;dependent (aOR 0.798; CI 95% 0.553-1.151, p=0.226). We found that a higher&#8239;Charlson Comorbidity Index score was related to an increased inpatient mortality (aOR 1.154; CI 95% 1.139-1.169, p=0.01). Other factors that had a significant correlation with increased mortality include age (p=0.01) and Asian and Pacific Islanders (p=0.02), as well as those who self-paid costs of hospitalization (p=0.01) (Table <xref rid="TAB3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Inhospital mortality results of STEMI patients with opioid dependence</title><p>Univariable regression analysis conducted to obtain the p-value.</p><p>p-value&lt;0.05 indicates statistical significance. STEMI: ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjust Odds Ratio</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% Confidence Interval</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhospital mortality with opioid dependence</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.798</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.553</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.151</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.226</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.038</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.035</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Race</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.916</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.833</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.071</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.958</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.869</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.056</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.387</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian or Pacific Islander</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.206</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.031</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.411</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native American</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.151</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.819</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.616</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.416</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other race</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.271</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.087</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.487</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.003</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Median household income in patients zip code (%)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26th-50th percentile
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.855</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.991</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.027</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51st-75th percentile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.899</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.831</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.974</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.009</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76th-100th percentile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.928</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.848</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.106</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Charlson Comorbidity Index of 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.154</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.139</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.169</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Insurance</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medicaid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.962</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.246</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.170</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Private insurance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.937</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.855</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.029</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.177</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-pay</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.573</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.341</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.845</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Hospital region</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midwest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.912</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.829</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.054</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">South</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.991</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.909</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.081</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.837</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">West</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.119</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.019</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Hospital length of stay&#160;</p><p>The average mean of length of stay (LOS) for patients who were not opioid dependent was about&#160;4.39 days, while the average mean of LOS for patients who were opioid dependent was&#160;about 5.07 days. The LOS in STEMI patients who were opioid dependent was statistically different compared to those who were not opioid dependent (average mean: 0.617; CI 95%&#160;0.283-0.951, p=0.01). Other factors that also had a significant correlation include age, Asian and Pacific Islanders, a higher Charlson Comorbidity Index, and teaching status of the hospital (p&lt;0.01) (Table <xref rid="TAB4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Inhospital length of stay results of STEMI patients with opioid dependence</title><p>Univariable regression analysis conducted to obtain the p-value.</p><p>p-value&lt;0.05 indicates statistical significance. STEMI: ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coefficient</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% Confidence Interval</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay in opioid dependence</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.617</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.283</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.951</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p&lt;0.0</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p&lt;0.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.054</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.112</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.072</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Race</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.073</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.172</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.426</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.131</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.274</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.073</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian or Pacific Islander</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.468</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.235</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.701</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p&lt;0.0</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native American</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.177</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.188</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.542</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.341</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.452</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.198</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.706</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Median household income in patients zip code (%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26th-50th percentile
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.049</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.141</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.295</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51st-75th percentile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.199</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.078</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76th-100th percentile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.139</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.259</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.022</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Charlson Comorbidity Index of 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.609</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.586</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.633</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Teaching institution</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.859</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.776</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.942</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Hospital region</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midwest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.718</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.322</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">South</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.148</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.341</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.135</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">West</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.741</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.947</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.535</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Hospital size</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medium bed size</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.463</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.338</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.587</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large bed size</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Hospital cost&#160;</p><p>Opioid dependence was not associated with a significant increase in total hospital charges when compared with those who were non-opioid dependent (average mean: -7306.439, CI 95% -14897.28-284.406, p=0.059). Factors that were statistically significant that affected the cost of hospitalization include age, female gender, a higher Charlson Comorbidity Index, and teaching status of the hospital (p&lt;0.01) (Table <xref rid="TAB5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Hospital admission total charges results of STEMI patients with opioid dependence</title><p>Univariable regression analysis conducted to obtain the p-value.</p><p>p-value&lt;0.05 indicates statistical significance. STEMI: ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coefficient</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% Confidence Interval</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total charges in opioid dependence</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7306.439</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-14897.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">284.406</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.059</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-482.611</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-548.006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-417.216</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-13782.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-15326.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-12238.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Race</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-9761.547</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-13945.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-5577.398</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15563.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9098.454</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22028.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian or Pacific Islander</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20141.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9498.198</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30784.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native American</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3460.156</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-16580.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9299.869</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.581</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24368.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14322.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34414.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Median household income in patients zip code (%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26th-50th percentile
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1016.861</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2522.588</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4556.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.573</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51st-75th&#160; percentile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2089.921</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2147.656</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6327.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.334</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76th-100th&#160; percentile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6278.453</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">458.372</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12098.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.034</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Charlson Comorbidity Index of 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6845.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6192.352</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7499.304</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Teaching institution</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21304.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17747.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24860.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Hospital region</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midwest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-11779.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-19978.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3580.789</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.005</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">South</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11287.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2528.583</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20047.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.012</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">West</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27953.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16593.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39313.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Hospital size</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medium bed size</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13848.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7202.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20494.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large bed size</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29611.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23031.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36192.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt;0.01</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our study looks at the outcomes of patients admitted for STEMI in those&#160;who are&#160;opioid na&#239;ve compared to those with a history of opioid use. What we found was that inhospital mortality was not significantly different in patients with opioid dependence as compared to patients without. However, opioid dependence was associated with a statistically significant longer length of hospital stay.</p><p>In the context of ever-increasing opioid dependence and cardiovascular diseases, including STEMI in the US, this study provides new information and understanding of what effects these two conditions have on hospital stay,&#160;mortality, and cost. Pain management in the acute phase of ACS is recommended according to European and American guidelines [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Morphine and other opioids have widely been used in daily practice in STEMI patients. In our study, we found an increased length of hospital stay for opioid-dependent patients compared to non-opioid-dependent patients. This is consistent with previous studies that have shown poor prognosis after STEMI in patients with opioid dependence. Our study showed that opioid dependence is associated with an increased LOS, which sheds some light on possible opioid-related side effects on STEMI patients. To the best of our knowledge, this is the largest analysis to date that explores the outcomes of STEMI in this patient population. This study considered demographic factors (age, race, gender, insurance type, household income), the severity of illness, inhospital mortality, total hospital charges, and LOS in both opioid dependents and nonopioid dependents. Trends of coexisting comorbidities among STEMI hospitalizations were also explored. Recent evidence suggests that opioids may delay and inhibit the absorption of antiplatelet agents [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>-<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], which may have a more pronounced impact on clinical outcomes in STEMI patients.</p><p>While the exact mechanism is not well understood, there have been a few theories posed as to why opioid use may worsen outcomes in those with ST-elevation myocardial infarctions. Those who present with ST-elevation myocardial infarctions are typically patients with suboptimal cardiovascular health, to begin with, and so several may have previous stents placed or are taking platelet inhibitors. It is known that coronary stent re-thrombosis infarctions are associated with increased mortality [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>A cohort study by Korsgaard et al. found that patient outcomes are worse for opioid-dependent patients compared to non-opioid users [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Although there are several studies showing worse STEMI outcomes for opioid users, there are no randomized clinical trials or any robust studies that show a clear association between poor STEMI outcomes and chronic opioid use.&#160;In other studies, opium consumption was associated with the increased odds of both ischemic heart disease and myocardial infarction (MI) diseases and mortality. These findings were consistent with similar studies. Niaki et al. showed that opium consumption was a significant risk factor for MI with an AOR of 26.3 [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Sadeghian et al. presented that opium abuse was a major risk factor for ischemic heart disease [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>The 2018 review article by Tavenier et&#160;al. found that morphine&#8217;s effects on the GI tract inhibit the absorption of orally administered platelet inhibitors which are vital for treatment [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Patients with right-sided STEMI and those involving the right coronary artery with right ventricular failure are pre-load dependent and can have fatal outcomes when morphine, a known vasodilator, is given&#160;as it accentuates these hemodynamic changes. Those patients on chronic opioids have an increased risk of respiratory depression because respiratory depression tolerance is slower and more prolonged than analgesic tolerance seen in this subset of patients. This risk of respiratory depression will in turn put the patient at higher risk for hypoxemia, which is not prognostically favorable in STEMI patients. The heart has opioid receptors, and endogenous opioid peptide (EOP) dynorphin has also been found in the heart. These EOPs are released during myocardial ischemia and can cause arrhythmias, bradycardia, and hypotension. In a 1993 journal article from the European Heart Journal, it was concluded that opioid agonists potentiated the fatal complications secondary to myocardial ischemia, giving yet another possible mechanism for the worse outcomes reported [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Furthermore, a 2013 Journal of Internal Medicine article conducted a nested case-control study to answer the question of whether opioid use for non-cancer patients was associated with an increased risk for MI among adults [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The primary working theory from that study was whether the risk of MI was related to opioid-induced hypogonadism. The thinking is that since the morbidity and mortality rates from CAD are 2.5 to 4.5-fold higher in men than in women, with the gap narrowing after menopause, there must be some level of influence that sex hormones have on the cardiovascular system. They reported that the use of opioid prescriptions was associated with a 1.53-fold risk of MI amongst men, whereas no association was seen amongst women. They found a 1.3-fold increase in MI for current opioid users overall.</p><p>In our study, there were no significant differences in inhospital mortality rates between opioid-dependent and non-opioid-dependent patients. However, higher Charlson Comorbidity Index scores, Asian and Pacific Islanders, and out-of-pocket payment for hospitalization were associated with increased inpatient mortality. The bulk of these patients were young white males with a history of polysubstance use and comorbid lung conditions. In contrast to our findings, Ranka et al. found higher all-cause mortality among patients who were opioid-dependent compared to non-opioid-dependent patients [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In line with this, a cohort study to assess the one-year mortality of opioid users who had myocardial infarction Korsgaard et al. demonstrated that the high frequency of comorbid conditions in opioid-dependent patients contributes to their all-cause mortality [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. More studies are needed to better elucidate the mortality rates of opioid-dependent patients with STEMI.</p><p>The combined cost of cardiovascular disease and stroke was $327 billion between 2013 and 2014 [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In addition, the economic cost of opioid use disorder was $1.02 trillion [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Our study found no significant difference in total charges in STEMI patients who were opioid dependent compared to those without opioid dependence.</p><p>Now, while there is a scarcity of information on the actual pathophysiology, it resoundingly seems that there are multiple factors contributing to the reported worse outcomes in STEMI patients with opioid use as opposed to those without. With the ubiquity of long-term opioid usage, and the ever-growing number of acute coronary syndrome cases, the interplay and prognostic implication one has on the other is a medical curiosity needing to be pondered. In the literature, opioid use has been shown to increase the risk for MI by nearly 2.25-fold compared to those using NSAIDs. With such figures, it is important to continue research on this topic and fill the paucity of information regarding it.</p><p>Limitations&#160;</p><p>Given its observational nature, there is a possibility for selection and unmeasured bias. However, this was controlled using a p-value of less than 0.05. Additionally, information on out-of-hospital mortality, short-term outcomes that did not lead to hospitalizations, and long-term outcomes were not available in the NIS dataset. Despite these limitations, the NIS database provides an invaluable population-based resource for evaluating national trends.&#8239;&#160;</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Opioid use is one of the pillars for pain relief in&#160;ACS, particularly STEMI. Our retrospective cohort dived into assessing the relationship between opioid dependence on its effect on inpatient mortality, LOS, and cost of hospitalization in STEMI patients. Our study showed that opioid dependence has no significant impact on inpatient mortality. However, it was associated with a longer length of hospitalization and in patients with STEMI. Further studies may be warranted into the effects of opioid dependence on the length of hospitalization in STEMI patients.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study.</p><p><bold>Animal subjects:</bold> All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#160; Abdel-Rhman Mohamed, Ehab Eltahawy, Abdelmoniem Moustafa, Abdulmajeed Alharbi, Ahmad Abdelrahman, Momin Shah, Ayman Salih, Jama Hersi</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#160; Abdel-Rhman Mohamed, Abdelmoniem Moustafa, Abdulmajeed Alharbi, Jama Hersi</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#160; Abdel-Rhman Mohamed, Ahmad Abdelrahman, Momin Shah, Ayman Salih, Jama Hersi</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#160; Abdel-Rhman Mohamed, Ehab Eltahawy, Abdelmoniem Moustafa, Abdulmajeed Alharbi, Ahmad Abdelrahman, Momin Shah</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold>&#160; Abdel-Rhman Mohamed</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>Acute coronary syndrome</article-title><source>StatPearls [Internet]</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Museedi</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-loc>Treasure Island (FL)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>StatPearls Publishing</publisher-name><year>2024</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK459157/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK459157/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29083796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Diagnosis and treatment of acute coronary syndromes: a review</article-title><source>JAMA</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatt</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>662</fpage><lpage>675</lpage><volume>327</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35166796</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2022.0358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Risk of adverse events in patients prescribed long-term opioids: a cohort study in the UK Clinical Practice Research Datalink</article-title><source>Eur J Pain</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashworth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>908</fpage><lpage>922</lpage><volume>23</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30620116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ejp.1357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Opioids in myocardial ischaemia: potentiating effects of dynorphin on ischaemic arrhythmia, bradycardia and cardiogenic shock following coronary artery occlusion in the rat</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>1273</fpage><lpage>1277</lpage><volume>14</volume><year>1993</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7901021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/eurheartj/14.9.1273</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>2017 ESC Guidelines for the management of acute myocardial infarction in patients presenting with ST-segment elevation: The Task Force for the management of acute myocardial infarction in patients presenting with ST-segment elevation of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC)</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibanez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agewall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><volume>39</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28886621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/eurheartj/ehx393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>2013 ACCF/AHA guideline for the management of ST-elevation myocardial infarction: a report of the American College of Cardiology Foundation/American Heart Association Task Force on Practice Guidelines</article-title><source>Circulation</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Gara</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kushner</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ascheim</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>425</lpage><volume>127</volume><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/CIR.0b013e3182742cf6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23247304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Morphine interaction with prasugrel: a double-blind, cross-over trial in healthy volunteers</article-title><source>Clin Res Cardiol</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hobl</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reiter</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoergenhofer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><volume>105</volume><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26493304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00392-015-0927-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4805697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Morphine decreases clopidogrel&#160;concentrations and effects: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hobl</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stimpfl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>630</fpage><lpage>635</lpage><volume>63</volume><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24315907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jacc.2013.10.068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Morphine delays and attenuates ticagrelor exposure and action in patients with myocardial infarction: the randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled IMPRESSION trial</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kubica</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adamski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ostrowska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><volume>37</volume><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26491112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/eurheartj/ehv547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4712351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Opioid use for noncancer pain and risk of myocardial infarction amongst adults</article-title><source>J Intern Med</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Setoguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cabral</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><volume>273</volume><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23331508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/joim.12035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Preadmission opioid use and 1-year mortality following incident myocardial infarction: a Danish population-based cohort study (1997-2016)</article-title><source>J Am Heart Assoc</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Korsgaard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horv&#225;th-Puh&#243;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>12</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/JAHA.122.026251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10111518</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36892067</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Evaluation of the role of opium addiction in acute myocardial infarction as a risk factor</article-title><source>Caspian J Intern Med</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Niaki</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farshidi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadpour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omran</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>589</lpage><volume>4</volume><year>2013</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3762234/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3762234/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24009941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3762234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The association of opium with coronary artery disease</article-title><source>Eur J Cardiovasc Prev Rehabil</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadeghian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darvish</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davoodi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salarifar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmoodian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fallah</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>717</lpage><volume>14</volume><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17925633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/HJR.0b013e328045c4e9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Risks of opioids in ST-elevation myocardial infarction: a review</article-title><source>Drug Saf</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tavenier</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hermanides</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ottervanger</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ter Horst</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kedhi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van 't Hof</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>1303</fpage><lpage>1308</lpage><volume>41</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30155802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40264-018-0710-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Comparison of hospitalization trends and outcomes in acute myocardial infarction patients with versus without opioid use disorder</article-title><source>Am J Cardiol</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ranka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalia</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><volume>145</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33454349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amjcard.2020.12.077</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Heart disease and stroke statistics-2018 update: a report from the American Heart Association</article-title><source>Circulation</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Virani</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>137</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/CIR.0000000000000558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29386200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The economic burden of opioid use disorder and fatal opioid overdose in the United States, 2017</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Florence</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>108350</fpage><volume>218</volume><year>2021</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.108350">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.108350</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33121867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.108350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8091480</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>