<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Addict Sci Clin Pract</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Addict Sci Clin Pract</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1002</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ascp</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Addiction Science &amp; Clinical Practice</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1940-0632</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1940-0640</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10210339</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10210339.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10210339</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10210339</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37231486</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13722-023-00389-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">389</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Timing of hepatitis C treatment initiation and retention in office-based opioid treatment with buprenorphine: a retrospective cohort study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Geist</surname><given-names initials="ML">Mary L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Radick</surname><given-names initials="AC">Andrea C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsui</surname><given-names initials="JI">Judith I.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blalock</surname><given-names initials="KL">Kendra L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adwell</surname><given-names initials="A">Addy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamru</surname><given-names initials="E">Elsabeth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names initials="NC">Nancy C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1980-6579</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names initials="JR">Jocelyn R.</given-names></name><address><email>jorose@uw.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.34477.33</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000122986657</institution-id><institution>University of Washington School of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>1959 NE Pacific St, Seattle, WA 98195 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.34477.33</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000122986657</institution-id><institution>Division of General Internal Medicine, Department of Medicine, Harborview Medical Center, </institution><institution>University of Washington School of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>325 Ninth Avenue, P. O. Box 359780, Seattle, WA 98104 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412618.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0433 5561</institution-id><institution>Harborview Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>325 Ninth Avenue, P.O. Box 359780, Seattle, WA 98104 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">424967</issue-id><elocation-id>33</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>8</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>25</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>26</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-05-26 12:25:09.717"><day>26</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="13722_2023_Article_389.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">This study examined associations between receipt of hepatitis C (HCV) treatment and retention in office-based opioid treatment (OBOT) care.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">We conducted a retrospective cohort study of HCV-infected patients who initiated OBOT treatment between December 2015 and March 2021 to characterize HCV treatment and assess associations with OBOT retention. HCV treatment was characterized as no treatment, early treatment (&lt;&#8201;100&#160;days since OBOT initiation) or late treatment (&#8805;&#8201;100&#160;days). We evaluated associations between HCV treatment and cumulative days in OBOT. A secondary analysis using Cox Proportional Hazards regression was done to determine the rate of discharge over time when comparing those who did versus did not receive HCV treatment as a time-varying covariate. We also analyzed a subset of patients retained at least 100&#160;days in OBOT care and evaluated whether HCV treatment during that period was associated with OBOT retention beyond 100&#160;days.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Of 191 HCV-infected OBOT patients, 30% initiated HCV treatment, of whom 31% received early treatment and 69% received late treatment. Median cumulative duration in OBOT was greater among those who received HCV treatment (any: 398&#160;days, early: 284&#160;days and late: 430&#160;days) when compared to those who did not receive treatment (90&#160;days). Compared to no HCV treatment, there were 83% (95% CI: 33&#8211;152%, P&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001), 95% (95% CI: 28%-197%, p&#8201;=&#8201;0.002 and 77% (95% CI: 25&#8211;153%, p&#8201;=&#8201;0.002) more cumulative days in OBOT for any, early and late HCV treatment, respectively. HCV treatment was associated with a lower relative hazard for discharge/drop-out, although results did not meet statistical significance (aHR&#8201;=&#8201;0.59;95% CI: 0.34&#8211;1.00; p&#8201;=&#8201;0.052). Among the subset of 84 patients retained in OBOT at least 100&#160;days, 18 received HCV treatment during that period. Compared to those who did not receive treatment within the first 100&#160;days, those who received treatment had 57% (95% CI: -3%-152%, p&#8201;=&#8201;0.065) more subsequent days in OBOT.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">A minority of HCV-infected patients received HCV treatment after initiating OBOT treatment, but those who did had better retention. Further efforts are needed to facilitate rapid HCV treatment and evaluate whether early HCV treatment improves OBOT engagement.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Hepatitis c treatment</kwd><kwd>Office-based buprenorphine treatment</kwd><kwd>Buprenorphine retention</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000026</institution-id><institution>National Institute on Drug Abuse</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>R25DA050985</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsui</surname><given-names>Judith I.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; Evans Medical Foundation, Inc. and BioMed Central Ltd. 2023</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">While historically, hepatitis C infection (HCV) in the United States primarily affected the &#8220;baby-boomer&#8221; birth cohort, the current epidemic of HCV is closely associated with injection drug use related to the opioid epidemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. High transmission and prevalence among people who use drugs (PWUD) make HCV a threat to public health as well as a major contributor to chronic liver disease, multi-system disease, and mortality. Eliminating this public health threat requires identifying and curing HCV among PWUD and is made feasible thanks to significant advances in direct-acting antiviral (DAA) treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Recent data showing reduced prevalence of HCV viremia after regional scale-up of DAA treatment among people who inject drugs in Scotland provides real-world evidence to support a &#8220;treatment as prevention&#8221; approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">Oral DAA medications have greatly simplified HCV treatment for the majority of individuals and have cure rates of greater than 95% in clinical trial settings and only slightly lower rates in real-world studies, including among PWUD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Among PWUD, receipt of medication for opioid use disorder (MOUD) (e.g. methadone, buprenorphine) is associated with increased HCV treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] and decreased risk of reinfection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. PWUD have historically faced barriers to HCV treatment, including concerns about adherence and side effects during the interferon-based era [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], as well as absintence requirements that were written into many state Medicaid coverage guidelines for DAAs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. More recent guidelines specify PWUD as a priority population for HCV treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]; however, barriers to care remain, including unstable housing or homelessness, superceding social issues, distrust in the medical system and patient concern about treatment side effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. In 2018, Washington State launched a hepatitis C virus elimination campaign that includes a pharmacy policy that removes a requirement for abstinence and other coverage restrictions for Medicaid patients; the state also partnered with AbbVie to provide glecaprevir/pibrentasvir without prior authorization to Medicaid patients using a modified subscription model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Colocalization of HCV and opioid use disorder (OUD) care is an important strategy to improve HCV treatment engagement and outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Whether HCV treatment in turn benefits retention in OUD treatment is largely unknown but of high importance, given that MOUD is life-saving [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. A recent study found a positive association between HCV treatment and retention at an opioid treatment program (OTP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Qualitative studies support that HCV cure increases self-efficacy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], an important component of substance use treatment engagement, and it is possible that this benefit of HCV treatment would contribute to improved retention in substance use care. We aimed to address gaps in knowledge about relationships between HCV treatment and OUD care by evaluating associations between prevalence and timing of HCV treatment and OBOT retention among persons with HCV in a hospital-associated OBOT program.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Material and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Design overview</title><p id="Par7">We retrospectively examined patients enrolled in an OBOT program between December 2015 and March 2021 who had HCV infection (i.e., a detectable HCV RNA result). We described demographic and clinical characteristics by time of HCV treatment initiation, and we examined associations between HCV treatment, timing of HCV treatment and retention in OBOT care. Our specific research questions were, 1) Do patients who receive HCV treatment have better retention in OBOT, and 2) Among patients who remain in OBOT treatment at least 100&#160;days, do those who receive HCV treatment within that 100-day period have better subsequent retention in OBOT, compared to those whose HCV was not treated within that 100-day period? This second research question was included to address the possibility of reverse causality, i.e., that longer duration of OBOT treatment provides more opportunities for HCV treatment.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study setting and participants</title><p id="Par8">The study was conducted within an OBOT program of a safety-net hospital in Seattle, WA (Harborview Medical Center). The OBOT program encompasses four clinical settings: two primary care clinics, a behavioral health program, and a transitional clinic that provides follow-up care and referral for patients without established primary care who have visited the emergency department or been hospitalized. The program provides medication for OUD based on a collaborative care model, utilizing nurse care managers and physicians qualified to prescribe buprenorphine. The study sample consisted of patients who initiated OBOT care between the program&#8217;s inception in December 2015 and March 2021 and who had known HCV, diagnosed either prior to or following initiation of OBOT care. We defined initiation of OBOT care as having received at least one buprenorphine prescription from the OBOT program. While we did not intentionally exclude patients on injectable naltrexone, we found that in our OBOT program, all patients with a detectable HCV RNA had received a prescription for buprenorphine. HCV infection was defined as having detectable HCV RNA by laboratory records. Patients with HCV who received a DAA prescription prior to OBOT intake were excluded.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Data sources</title><p id="Par9">The study utilized data from the electronic health record (EHR) accessed via a clinical and administrative data repository and imported into REDCap. Data elements included demographic information (age at first OBOT intake, sex, race/ethnicity and insurance status), psychiatric diagnoses (depression, bipolar disorder, anxiety, post-traumatic stress disorder, schizophrenia and other psychotic disorders) and major medical diagnoses (human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), diabetes, coronary artery disease, chronic kidney disease and cirrhosis). HCV RNA (result and date) and date of first DAA prescription were based on laboratory and medication data from the EHR. OBOT program data collected for the purposes of reporting to state and federal funders were used to define the sample and characterize OBOT treatment episodes and measures of OBOT retention. The study was reviewed by the University of Washington Institutional Review Board, which determined that it did not qualify as human subjects research.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Measures</title><p id="Par10">HCV treatment initiation (hereafter, &#8220;HCV treatment&#8221;) was defined as receipt of a prescription for a DAA medication. Treatment could be provided through on-site providers or through referral to a specialty clinic and could occur at any time following OBOT intake, within the study period. To address our first question (Do patients who receive HCV treatment have better retention in OBOT?), HCV treatment was the primary exposure of interest and was categorized both as a dichotomous variable of any HCV treatment vs no treatment and as a three-level variable according to time between OBOT intake and receipt of first DAA prescription [no HCV treatment after OBOT intake, early HCV treatment (within 100&#160;days of OBOT intake) and late HCV treatment (&#8805;&#8201;100&#160;days after OBOT intake)]. The key outcome of interest was cumulative retention in OBOT, calculated as the sum of the days patients spent in all OBOT treatment episodes (i.e., the days between intake and discharge dates for each treatment episode) within the study period. In this analysis, we did not distinguish between HCV treatment that occurred during OBOT care and HCV treatment that took place in between or following episodes of OBOT care. To address temporal concerns, we performed a secondary survival analysis using a Cox-Proportional Hazards model to evaluate time to first OBOT discharge, with a time-varying covariate for receipt of HCV treatment, classified as treated vs. not treated. Including a covariate for a time-varying exposure was done to control for immortal time bias that could result from misclassifying the follow-up time among participants who did not receive their DAA prescription until some time after the start of their OBOT initiation.</p><p id="Par11">To address our second question (Among patients who remain in OBOT treatment for at least 100&#160;days, do those who receive HCV treatment within that 100-day period have better subsequent retention in OBOT, compared to those whose HCV was not treated within that 100-day period?), our sample was limited to those whose first treatment episode lasted at least 100&#160;days. The exposure of interest was HCV treatment within that 100-day period, and OBOT retention was calculated as cumulative retention beyond the first 100&#160;days of OBOT treatment.</p><p id="Par12">Discharge date was based on OBOT program files and was defined as the date 30&#160;days after the last prescription would be expected to run out for each OBOT episode. Within OBOT treatment episodes, we did not further characterize frequency or patterns of buprenorphine prescriptions or clinic appointments. Within the program, lost to follow up is the most common reason for discharge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par13">Descriptive statistics were calculated for variables of interest. Fisher&#8217;s exact tests were used to compare binary and categorical variables by HCV treatment status (no treatment, early treatment and late treatment). Cumulative days in OBOT treatment was analyzed as a count outcome variable in negative binominal regression models to account for over-dispersed outcome data. A variable was included in the models to adjust for the fact that patients contributed different amounts of observation time (i.e., were enrolled in OBOT at different times during the study period). The variable was calculated as the time between OBOT enrollment and the final discharge date, or the date of data extraction if no discharge date occurred (i.e., if the patient remained in OBOT at the conclusion of the study period). A secondary analysis using a Cox Proportional Hazards regression model was done to determine the rate of discharge over time when comparing those who did versus did not receive HCV treatment as a time-varying covariate, and the outcome event defined as time to first discharge occurrence after OBOT initiation. Given the modest sample size and limited outcomes, we pursued a parsimonious model selection strategy. Models were adjusted for HIV status only, as it was the sole covariate that demonstrated statistically significant difference in HCV treatment receipt (p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05; Fisher&#8217;s exact tests&#8212;results not shown).</p><p id="Par14">Statistical analyses were conducted using Stata statistical software (16.1, StataCorp LLC, College Station, TX). All analyses are reported with 95% confidence intervals and 2-sided tests of the null hypothesis at a significance level of 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><p id="Par15">The study cohort was comprised of 191 OBOT patients with HCV infection with a mean age of 45&#8201;&#177;&#8201;12.4&#160;years. Twenty-nine percent of patients were identified as female; for the majority of the study period, the EHR did not provide the option to identify as non-binary or transgender. Seventy-seven percent were white, 15.2% were Black and 7.9% identified as other/multiracial. Mental health disorders were common (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic and clinical characteristics of OBOT patient sample by HCV treatment status (N&#8201;=&#8201;191)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristics, n (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Total (N&#8201;=&#8201;191)</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">No treatment (n&#8201;=&#8201;133)</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Any treatment (n&#8201;=&#8201;58)</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Early treatment,&#8201;&lt;&#8201;100&#160;days (n&#8201;=&#8201;18)</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Late treatment,&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;100&#160;days (n&#8201;=&#8201;40)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age at first OBOT program start</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;20&#8211;34</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.4%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.5%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.0%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.7%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.0%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;35&#8211;44</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.3%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.3%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.9%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.8%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.0%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;45&#8211;64</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.9%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.4%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.6%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.0%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.0%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;65&#8201;+&#8201;</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.4%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.8%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.6%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.6%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.0%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.3%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.8%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.9%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.8%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.0%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;White/Caucasian</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">147</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.0%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.4%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75.9%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.8%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75.0%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Black/African American</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.2%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.0%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.5%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.1%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other/multiracial<sup>1</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.9%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.5%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.6%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.1%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hispanic/LatinX ethnicity</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.9%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.5%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.2%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.6%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.0%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Primary insurance<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Medicaid</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">120</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.8%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.4%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71.9%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.2%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.0%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Medicare</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.8%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.1%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.0%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.6%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Self-pay</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.3%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other<sup>3</sup></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.8%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.1%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.0%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.7%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time of HCV test positive<sup>4</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Prior to or at OBOT start</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">119</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.0%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69.2%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.2%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.4%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.3%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;After OBOT start</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.0%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.8%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.8%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.7%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.7%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medical co-morbidities</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;HIV</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.6%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.4%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.4%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.3%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Diabetes</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.2%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.0%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.5%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.7%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.0%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Coronary artery disease</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.6%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.5%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.2%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.7%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Chronic kidney disease</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.2%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.0%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.0%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.2%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Cirrhosis</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.1%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.5%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.0%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.2%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Psychiatric co-morbidities</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Depression</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.4%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.8%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.2%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.6%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Anxiety/post-traumatic stress disorder</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.5%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58.6%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.7%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.0%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Schizophrenia/psychotic disorder</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.9%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.0%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.7%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Bipolar disorder</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.9%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.3%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.0%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.2%</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median duration in OBOT in days (IQR)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">146</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(58&#8211;382)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(46&#8211;216)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">398</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(157&#8211;854)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">284</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(157&#8211;796)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">430</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(148&#8211;860)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>1</sup>&#8220;Other&#8221; includes American Indian or Alaskan Native, Asian, or Native Hawaiian or other Pacific Islander</p><p><sup>2</sup>Percentages do not total to 100% due to missing data</p><p><sup>3</sup>Other includes &#8220;other,&#8221; &#8220;commercial,&#8221; and &#8220;worker&#8217;s compensation&#8221;</p><p><sup>4</sup>Two patients who received treatment did not have a test date</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par16">One hundred thirty-three (69.6%) people with HCV did not have evidence of receiving a DAA prescription during the study period. Fifty-eight patients (30.4%) did receive HCV treatment with DAAs, namely ledipasvir/sofosbuvir, velpatasvir/sofosbuvir and glecaprevir/pibrentasvir. Of these, 18/58 (31.0%) patients received early treatment and 40/58 (69.0%) received late treatment. There were no significant differences in demographic characteristics or psychiatric conditions according to HCV treatment status (none, early, late). HIV was more common in the early HCV treatment group (6/18, 33.3%) than among those who received no HCV treatment (11/131, 8.4%) or late HCV treatment (7/40, 17.5%) (p&#8201;=&#8201;0.009). The majority (63.0%) of patients had a positive HCV test prior to or at their first OBOT start; having a positive test prior to OBOT start was more common in the early treatment compared to the late treatment group (82.4% v. 33.3%; p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001). Among the total cohort of OBOT patients with HCV infection, 44/191 (23.0%) had more than one OBOT treatment episode, 84/191 (44.0%) were retained in OBOT care for at least 100&#160;days, and the median cumulative duration of OBOT care was 146&#160;days (interquartile range or IQR, 58&#8211;382). Median cumulative duration of OBOT was longer among those who received HCV treatment (any, early and late) when compared to those who did not receive treatment (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par17">For the entire cohort of 191 patients, negative binomial regression models of cumulative days in OBOT according to HCV treatment status used no HCV treatment as the reference group. Compared to no HCV treatment, there were 83% (95% CI: 33&#8211;152%, P&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001), 95% (95% CI: 28&#8211;197%, p&#8201;=&#8201;0.002) and 77% (95% CI: 25&#8211;153%, p&#8201;=&#8201;0.002) more cumulative days in OBOT for any, early and late HCV treatment, respectively. The Cox-Proportional Hazards model using a time-varying covariate for HCV treatment demonstrated that HCV treatment was associated with a lower relative hazards for discharge/drop-out, although results did not meet statistical significance (aHR&#8201;=&#8201;0.59;95% CI: 0.34&#8211;1.00; p&#8201;=&#8201;0.052).</p><p id="Par18">Among the 84 patients with HCV who were retained at least 100&#160;days in OBOT, a negative binomial regression model was used to examine cumulative OBOT retention beyond 100&#160;days according to whether patients received HCV treatment within that 100-day period, using no HCV treatment within 100&#160;days as the reference group. Compared to those who did not receive treatment within the first 100&#160;days, those who received treatment had 57% (95% CI: &#8722;&#160;3&#8211;152%, p&#8201;=&#8201;0.065) more subsequent days in OBOT.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par19">In this retrospective cohort study of patients with HCV enrolled in an OBOT program at a single academic medical center, patients who received HCV treatment following OBOT enrollment had greater cumulative retention in OBOT over the follow-up period compared to those who had not received HCV treatment. OBOT retention was highest for HCV treatment that occurred &#8220;early,&#8221; i.e., within 100&#160;days of OBOT enrollment, but only a small minority of patients received treatment within that time frame. In a survival analysis to better account for temporality of HCV treatment and OBOT care, HCV treatment was associated with a lower relative hazards for discharge/drop-out, although the results did not reach statistical significance. Similarly, among patients with HCV who were retained at least 100&#160;days in OBOT, those who received HCV treatment within that 100-day period (n&#8201;=&#8201;18) had greater subsequent OBOT retention than did those who were treated later or not treated, although this finding was also not statistically significant.</p><p id="Par20">A recent case&#8211;control study by Severe et al. evaluated patients with HCV who were engaged in care at an opioid treatment program (OTP) and found that compared to those who did not receive HCV treatment, those whose HCV was treated at the OTP were 2.22 times more likely to be retained in OTP care for the duration of the study period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Although our study evaluated patients in an OBOT program and had multiple methodological differences compared to the study by Severe et al. we found a similar degree of association between receipt of HCV treatment and retention. That, in our study, the group of patients who received HCV treatment early had the highest cumulative days in OBOT, might suggest that prompt HCV treatment is more strongly associated with retention in OBOT. This is important because OBOT programs provide access to evidence-based, life-saving treatment with buprenorphine for people with OUD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]; expanding OUD treatment is a key strategy to address overdose deaths in the U.S., which now number more than 100,000 annually [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p><p id="Par21">The 191 patients with detectable HCV RNA in our sample comprised 22.4% of the total population of 854 patients who initiated OBOT treatment during the study period. The true number of patients with hepatitis C viremia was likely higher, as we found that only 70.8% of our patients were screened. Though we did not have rigorous processes in place to ensure universal HCV screening, we have since implemented such protocols. For comparison, a prior study by Carey et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] found that 32% of patients in an OBOT program had detectable HCV RNA.</p><p id="Par22">We found that 30.4% of patients with HCV received HCV treatment after enrolling in OBOT. While this figure compares favorably to a study of patients enrolled in an OBOT program between 2003 and 2013 (i.e., prior to and early in the DAA era), when only 2.21% of viremic patients were found to have received HCV treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], it is only slightly higher than that found among a non-treatment seeking population of people who inject drugs and have HCV in Seattle, WA, based on a 2018 survey. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] We also found that although 63.0% of patients were diagnosed with HCV before or at OBOT start, only a small minority received early HCV treatment. We believe that this suggests missed opportunities to provide prompt treatment, which is important to reduce viral transmission and is now explicitly recommended by guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Emergency department or inpatient stays for PWUD may provide opportunities to facilitate early HCV treatment through HCV testing, initial HCV treatment evaluation (e.g., HBV antigen screening and tests to assess fibrosis/cirrhosis) and linkages to care, although evidence to date suggests ongoing gaps between screening and linkage to care, especially for PWUD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], and further study is needed.</p><p id="Par23">It is notable that of 17 patients with psychotic disorders in our sample, only one (2.5%) received HCV treatment. This important HCV care gap may be due to limited HCV treatment availability at our mental health based OBOT clinic, cognitive and/or communication barriers to medical care among people with psychotic disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], fragmentation of the healthcare system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] or other factors. However, specific data on access and barriers to DAA treatment for people with psychotic disorders is lacking, and further study is needed. Importantly, real-world evidence among people with HIV and HCV co-infection suggests that DAA therapy is effective among people with psychotic disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p><p id="Par24">On the other hand, patients with HIV were over-represented in the any and early HCV treatment groups in this study. In our hospital system, people with HIV receive care in a dedicated clinic with infectious disease trained providers with expertise managing HCV and with more wraparound services than other settings, which could lead to improved OBOT retention. However, when adjusted for HIV status, the relationship between HCV treatment and OBOT retention persisted.</p><p id="Par25">There were limitations to this study. First, the study was observational and cannot establish a causal relationship between HCV treatment and OBOT retention. It is possible that this association is explained by residual confounding factors, e.g., personal or clinical characteristics that contribute to engagement or perceived engagement in both addiction and HCV care. Additionally, the design of our study did not allow us to account for temporal relationships between HCV treatment and OBOT retention among our full cohort, nor did it allow us to distinguish patients whose HCV was treated during OBOT care from those whose HCV was treated following or in between episodes of OBOT care. Our analysis of HCV treatment vs. no treatment in the first 100&#160;days and OBOT retention beyond 100&#160;days among the 84 patients who were retained in OBOT for at least that duration addresses these temporal concerns, including the concern of reverse causality. The analysis found a consistent positive association that did not reach statistical significance. Our analyses were limited by a modest sample size with a limited number of patients who received HCV treatment and a small number of patients who were treated early. In our view, relationships between addiction and HCV treatment are most likely bi-directional, and our study leaves open the possibility that early HCV treatment promotes retention in OBOT care.</p><p id="Par26">Additional limitations of our study include reliance on the EHR (treatment for HCV that occurred outside of the healthcare system could have been missed) and use of data from a single site and period of time. Changes in professional society guidelines, DAA availability and costs, insurance coverage and prescribing restrictions occurred during the study period, and this data may not accurately reflect current care. Results may also not be generalizable to other settings with differing coverage and prescribing policies&#8212;e.g., many states&#8217; Medicaid policies continue to restrict access to HCV treatment, including for PWUD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], whereas treatment of HCV among high-risk populations and addressing stigma are explicit aims of Washington State&#8217;s initiative to eliminate HCV [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par27">In this retrospective study of OBOT patients with HCV infection, patients who received HCV treatment had greater retention in OBOT. More research is needed to explore how HCV and OUD care can be leveraged to optimize treatment of both conditions. Controlled and/or larger observational studies that can account for temporal ordering would be helpful to clarify whether there is a causal relationship between HCV treatment and OBOT retention and to better define the role of early HCV treatment.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to acknowledge Ayushi Gupta and H. Nina Kim for their assistance with data acquisition and Kevin A. Hallgren for his input on study design and analyses.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>All authors had a role in study conception and design. AR and KB were primarily responsible for data management and analyses. MG, AR, KB, AA, JT and JJ assisted with interpretation of the data. MG and AR wrote the initial draft and JT and JJ also made substantial contributions to the writing of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>The research reported was supported by the National Institute on Drug Abuse of the National Institutes of Health, Award Number R25DA050985. The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not neccessarily represent the official views of the National Institutes of Health. The National Institutes of Health did not have any role in the design, data collection, analysis or interpretation of the data, nor in writing the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par28">The University of Washington Institutional Review Board waived review after determining that this study did not constitute human subjects research.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par29">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par30">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Viral hepatitis surveillance report 2018&#8212;hepatitis C. Updated August 28, 2020. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/hepatitis/statistics/2018surveillance/HepC.htm">https://www.cdc.gov/hepatitis/statistics/2018surveillance/HepC.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 4 Feb 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vickerman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combination interventions to prevent HCV transmission among people who inject drugs: modeling the impact of antiviral treatment, needle and syringe programs, and opiate substitution therapy</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2013</year><volume>57</volume><issue>Suppl 2</issue><fpage>S39</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/cit296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23884064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3722076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Committee on a National Strategy for the Elimination of Hepatitis B, Board on Population H, Public Health P, et al. In: Buckley GJ, Strom BL, eds. Eliminating the Public Health Problem of Hepatitis B and C in the United States: Phase One Report. National Academies Press (US). Copyright 2016 by the National Academy of Sciences. All rights reserved; 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dore</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alavi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grebely</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global elimination of hepatitis C virus by 2030: why not?</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-019-0706-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32047317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmateer</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McAuley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dillon</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reduction in the population prevalence of hepatitis C virus viraemia among people who inject drugs associated with scale-up of direct-acting anti-viral therapy in community drug services: real-world data</article-title><source>Addiction</source><year>2021</year><volume>116</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2893</fpage><lpage>2907</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/add.15459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33651446</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bachhuber</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High HCV cure rates for people who use drugs treated with direct acting antiviral therapy at an urban primary care clinic</article-title><source>Int J Drug Policy</source><year>2017</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>196</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugpo.2017.07.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28811158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5822435</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dore</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Altice</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Litwin</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Elbasvir-grazoprevir to treat hepatitis C virus infection in persons receiving opioid agonist therapy: a randomized trial</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>165</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>625</fpage><lpage>634</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M16-0816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27537841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grebely</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalgard</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sofosbuvir and velpatasvir for hepatitis C virus infection in people with recent injection drug use (SIMPLIFY): an open-label, single-arm, phase 4, multicentre trial</article-title><source>Lancet Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><year>2018</year><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2468-1253(17)30404-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29310928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajarizadeh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Law</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dore</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grebely</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct-acting antiviral treatment for hepatitis C among people who use or inject drugs: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Lancet Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><year>2018</year><volume>3</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>754</fpage><lpage>767</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2468-1253(18)30304-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30245064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iversen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dore</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catlett</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grebely</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between rapid utilisation of direct hepatitis C antivirals and decline in the prevalence of viremia among people who inject drugs in Australia</article-title><source>J Hepatol</source><year>2019</year><volume>70</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2018.09.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30367897</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The impact of current opioid agonist therapy on hepatitis C virus treatment initiation among people who use drugs from the direct-acting antiviral (DAA) era: a population-based study</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2022</year><volume>74</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>575</fpage><lpage>583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/ciab546</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34125883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8886915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajarizadeh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valerio</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis C reinfection after successful antiviral treatment among people who inject drugs: A meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Hepatol</source><year>2020</year><volume>72</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>643</fpage><lpage>657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2019.11.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31785345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NIH Consensus Development Program. Management of hepatitis C. National Institutes of Health; 1997; p. 1&#8211;41.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Restrictions of hepatitis C treatment for substance-using medicaid patients: cost versus ethics</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source><year>2017</year><volume>107</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>893</fpage><lpage>899</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2017.303748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28426313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5425868</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Hepatitis C information. 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/hepatitis/hcv/hcvfaq.htm#d7;%20AASLD/IDSA%20guideline:%20hcvguidelines.org">https://www.cdc.gov/hepatitis/hcv/hcvfaq.htm#d7;%20AASLD/IDSA%20guideline:%20hcvguidelines.org</ext-link>. Accessed 4 Feb 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grebely</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajarizadeh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazarus</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruneau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Treloar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><collab>International Network on Hepatitis in Substance U</collab></person-group><article-title>Elimination of hepatitis C virus infection among people who use drugs: ensuring equitable access to prevention, treatment, and care for all</article-title><source>Int J Drug Policy</source><year>2019</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugpo.2019.07.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31345644</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rance</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hull</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Treloar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Making sense of 'side effects': counterpublic health in the era of direct-acting antivirals</article-title><source>Int J Drug Policy</source><year>2019</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugpo.2019.06.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31221475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Health Care Authority. Eliminating Hepatitis C in Washington State. Clinical quality and care transformation. 2019. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.hca.wa.gov/assets/program/HCA-HCV-elimination-breif.pdf">https://www.hca.wa.gov/assets/program/HCA-HCV-elimination-breif.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 13 Jan 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santo</surname><given-names>T</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of opioid agonist treatment with all-cause mortality and specific causes of death among people with opioid dependence: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>JAMA Psychiat</source><year>2021</year><volume>78</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>979</fpage><lpage>993</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2021.0976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8173472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34076676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Severe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tetrault</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heimer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Co-Located hepatitis C virus infection treatment within an opioid treatment program promotes opioid agonist treatment retention</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source><year>2020</year><volume>213</volume><fpage>108116</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.108116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32599493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Batchelder</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peyser</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nahvi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnsten</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Litwin</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>"Hepatitis C treatment turned me around:" Psychological and behavioral transformation related to hepatitis C treatment</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source><year>2015</year><volume>153</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2015.06.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26096534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4759650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goutzamanis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Experiences of liver health related uncertainty and self-reported stress among people who inject drugs living with hepatitis C virus: a qualitative study</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>151</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-018-3057-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29609552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5879642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsui</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayfield</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Speaker</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association between methamphetamine use and retention among patients with opioid use disorders treated with buprenorphine</article-title><source>J Subst Abuse Treat</source><year>2020</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2019.10.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31810594</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sordo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrio</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bravo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mortality risk during and after opioid substitution treatment: systematic review and meta-analysis of cohort studies</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2017</year><volume>357</volume><fpage>j1550</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.j1550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28446428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5421454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ahmad F, Rossen L, Sutton P, National Center for Health Statistics. Provisional drug overdose death counts. National Center for Health Statistics,. Updated May 12, 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nvss/vsrr/drug-overdose-data.htm">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nvss/vsrr/drug-overdose-data.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 14 Feb 2022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linas</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsui</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis C virus testing and treatment among persons receiving buprenorphine in an office-based program for opioid use disorders</article-title><source>J Subst Abuse Treat</source><year>2016</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2016.01.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26988423</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5097249</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corcorran</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsui</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dombrowski</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glick</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age and gender-specific hepatitis C continuum of care and predictors of direct acting antiviral treatment among persons who inject drugs in Seattle</article-title><source>Washington. Drug Alcohol Depend.</source><year>2021</year><volume>220</volume><fpage>108525</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2021.108525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33461152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7938869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Houri</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horowitz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katchman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Emergency department targeted screening for hepatitis C does not improve linkage to care</article-title><source>World J Gastroenterol</source><year>2020</year><volume>26</volume><issue>32</issue><fpage>4878</fpage><lpage>4888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3748/wjg.v26.i32.4878</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32921964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7459203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predictors of linkage to care for a nontargeted emergency department hepatitis C screening program</article-title><source>Am J Emerg Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>38</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1396</fpage><lpage>1401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajem.2019.11.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31836342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7255936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mascio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Botelle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cognitive impairments in schizophrenia: a study in a large clinical sample using natural language processing</article-title><source>Front Digit Health.</source><year>2021</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>711941</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fdgth.2021.711941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34713182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8521945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horvitz-Lennon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kilbourne</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pincus</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From silos to bridges: meeting the general health care needs of adults with severe mental illnesses</article-title><source>Health Aff (Millwood).</source><year>2006</year><volume>25</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.25.3.659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16684729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nance</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams-Nguyen</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of direct-acting antiviral therapy in patients with human immunodeficiency virus-hepatitis C virus coinfection in routine clinical care: a multicenter study</article-title><source>Open Forum Infect Dis</source><year>2019</year><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>ofz100</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofz100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30949539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6441587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Center for Health Law and Policy Innovation &amp; National Viral Hepatitis Roundtable. Hepatitis C: state of medicaid access, National Summary Report. 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://stateofhepc.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/State-of-Hep-C-Report_2022-1.pdf">https://stateofhepc.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/State-of-Hep-C-Report_2022-1.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Washington State Health Care Authority. Eliminating hepatitis C. 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.hca.wa.gov/about-hca/clinical-collaboration-and-initiatives/eliminating-hepatitis-c#strategy">https://www.hca.wa.gov/about-hca/clinical-collaboration-and-initiatives/eliminating-hepatitis-c#strategy</ext-link>. Accessed 31 Jul 2022.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>