<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Global Spine J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Global Spine J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2276</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">gsj</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GSJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Global Spine Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2192-5682</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2192-5690</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10556919</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10556919.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10556919</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10556919</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35014544</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/21925682211049166</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_21925682211049166</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Marijuana Use is Not a Contraindication for Tranexamic Acid Utilization in Lumbar Spine Surgery</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakoi</surname><given-names initials="AM">Andre M.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1-21925682211049166" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0959-0222</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirchner</surname><given-names initials="GJ">Gregory J.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MPH</degrees><xref rid="aff2-21925682211049166" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="corresp1-21925682211049166" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6517-4472</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Lieber</surname><given-names initials="AM">Alexander M.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff3-21925682211049166" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalsa</surname><given-names initials="AS">Amrit S.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff4-21925682211049166" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1-21925682211049166"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution content-type="university">Orthopedic Health of Kansas City</institution></institution-wrap>, Kansas City, MO, USA</aff><aff id="aff2-21925682211049166"><label>2</label>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="Ringgold">12310</institution-id><institution content-type="university">Penn State Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</institution></institution-wrap>, Hershey, PA, USA</aff><aff id="aff3-21925682211049166"><label>3</label>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="Ringgold">5944</institution-id><institution content-type="university">Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</institution></institution-wrap>, New York, NY, USA</aff><aff id="aff4-21925682211049166"><label>4</label>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="Ringgold">6572</institution-id><institution content-type="university">The University of Pennsylvania</institution></institution-wrap>, Philadelphia, PA, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-21925682211049166">Gregory J. Kirchner, MD, MPH, Department of Orthopaedic Surgery Penn State Milton S. Hershey Medical Center, 500 University Drive Mail Code H089, Hershey, PA 17033, USA. Email: <email>kirchnergj@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>7</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">446853</issue-id><fpage>1771</fpage><lpage>1776</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>11</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>07</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-09-25 17:25:35.677"><day>25</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2022</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">AO Spine, unless otherwise noted. Manuscript content on this site is licensed under Creative Commons Licenses</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work as published without adaptation or alteration, without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10.1177_21925682211049166.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Study Design</title><p>Retrospective cohort study</p></sec><sec><title>Objective</title><p>The purpose of this study was to evaluate safety in lumbar spinal fusion with tranexamic acid (TXA) utilization in patients using marijuana.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>This was a retrospective cohort study involving a single surgeon&#8217;s cases of 1 to 4 level lumbar fusion procedures. Two hundred and ninety-four patients were followed for ninety days post-operatively. Consecutive patients were self-reported for daily marijuana use (n = 146) and compared to a similar cohort of patients who denied usage of marijuana (n = 146). Outcomes were collected, which included length of stay (LOS), estimated blood loss (EBL), post-operative myocardial infarction, seizures, deep venous thrombosis, pulmonary embolus, death, readmission, need for further surgery, infection, anaphylaxis, acute renal injury, and need for blood product transfusion.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Patients in the marijuana usage cohort had similar age (58.9&#160;years &#177;12.9 vs 58.7&#160;years &#177;14.8, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .903) and distribution of levels fused (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .431) compared to the non-usage cohort. Thromboembolic events were rare in both groups (marijuana usage: 1 vs non-usage: 2). Compared to the non-usage cohort, the marijuana usage cohort had a similar average EBL (329.9 &#177; 298.5&#160;mL vs 374.5 &#177; 363.8&#160;mL; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .254). Multivariate regression modeling demonstrated that neither EBL (OR 1.27, 95% CI 0.64-2.49) nor need for transfusion (OR 1.56, 95% CI 0.43-5.72) varied between cohorts. The non-usage cohort had twice the risk of prolonged LOS compared to the marijuana usage cohort (OR 2.05, 95% CI 1.15-3.63).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Marijuana use should not be considered a contraindication for TXA utilization in lumbar spine surgery.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>cannabis</kwd><kwd>marijuana use</kwd><kwd>spinal fusion</kwd><kwd>tranexamic acid</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>typesetter</meta-name><meta-value>ts10</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec6-21925682211049166"><title>Introduction</title><p>In the United States, the use of recreational and medicinal marijuana has become significantly more widespread by adults of all sexes, races, and socioeconomic statuses over the past 2 decades.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup> Increasingly permissive legislatures in many states, in addition to changing societal attitudes that promote recreational marijuana use, have helped spur this increase in consumption.<sup><xref rid="bibr2-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr3-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> While multiple studies have reported that the largest increase in marijuana use has been among young adults, a considerable increase in marijuana use has also been documented in older populations.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr4-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Given this, it is ever more prudent to investigate and define the effects marijuana use may have on common practices within spine surgery.</p><p>While there is considerable research on the effects of marijuana misuse on psychiatric conditions and co-substance use, the impact of marijuana on spine surgery has not been extensively studied.<sup><xref rid="bibr5-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="bibr6-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> A recent study indicated that patients who use marijuana daily have similar rates of post-operative complications, functional outcome scores, and radiological evidence of fusion following transformational lumbar interbody fusion compared to patients who do not use marijuana.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr7-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
</sup> However, patients who use marijuana and undergo primary total knee arthroplasty have been reported to have higher rates of complications resulting in higher rates of readmission and hospital costs.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr8-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
</sup></p><p>Due to these discrepancies within the orthopaedic literature regarding post-operative complications in patients who use marijuana, further investigation is warranted. In particular, investigation of the effect of marijuana use on intraoperative blood loss is important to establish. There is evidence in the basic science literature suggesting that marijuana causes anticoagulant effects and limits platelet aggregation.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="bibr10-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> However, tranexamic acid (TXA) is routinely used in spine surgery to limit blood loss without evidence of increased risk of thromboembolic complications.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr11-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
</sup> The use of TXA in patients undergoing spine surgery who also use marijuana remains unexplored. Given the widespread use of TXA in patients undergoing lumbar fusion, it is necessary to clearly delineate if TXA affects patient safety among those who use marijuana prior to spine surgery.</p><p>The purpose of this study was to retrospectively compare blood loss and risk of transfusion following lumbar fusion with TXA utilization between patients who use marijuana daily and patients who do not use marijuana. A secondary objective was to also compare risk of perioperative complications. Considering the recent literature, we hypothesize that patients who use marijuana have higher mean blood loss and greater risk of transfusion compared to non-users who undergo lumbar spinal fusion with adjunct use of TXA.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec7-21925682211049166"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec8-21925682211049166"><title>Patient Selection</title><p>Two hundred and ninety-four patients who underwent 1 to 4 level lumbar fusions by one of the senior authors (AMJ) between January 2017 and February 2020 comprised the cohort for retrospective analysis. Approval was obtained for this investigation through the operating surgeon&#8217;s institutional review board. The procedures performed on each patient included open posterolateral fusion, open transforaminal lumbar interbody fusion, minimally invasive transforaminal lumbar interbody fusion, lateral interbody fusion with posterolateral fusion, or anterior interbody fusion with posterolateral fusion. No patient had the use of recombinant human bone morphogenetic protein-2 (rhBMP-2). No patient had a prior history of myocardial infarction (MI), cardiac or vascular stenting procedures, deep venous thrombosis (DVT), pulmonary embolus (PE), renal failure, or epilepsy.</p><p>Patients with daily marijuana use were selected on a consecutive basis and matched one-to-one with patients who underwent a similar procedure during the study period on a non-consecutive basis. Patients involved in trauma requiring surgical intervention, patients with malignancy or undergoing treatment for malignancy with or without spine involvement, or patients with prior lumbar procedures were eliminated from consideration for this study. All patients included in this study denied nicotine usage. Patients previously placed (preoperatively) on anticoagulation, including aspirin, were excluded from this study. No patients were placed on pharmacologic anticoagulation post-operatively for at least 90&#160;days unless they had a DVT, PE, or cardiac event that required it. Every patient had a 10&#160;mg/kg preload bolus of TXA given within 30&#160;minutes prior to incision.</p><p>Patients in the marijuana cohort admitted to marijuana use at each of their preoperative visits and post-operative visits. Any patient who either started or ceased usage was no longer included in the study. Marijuana usage was defined as smoking or ingesting at least once per day. While marijuana largely remains illegal according to the laws in the state where patient collection occurred, penalties for recreational use were significantly reduced in 2014 and medicinal use was approved in 2018.<sup><xref rid="bibr12-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="bibr13-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="sec9-21925682211049166"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Descriptive statistics are reported as means with standard deviations or as counts with percentages, as indicated. Comparative statistics were employed to investigate differences between 2 cohorts: patients who self-reported marijuana usage vs patients who did not report usage. Univariate comparisons consisted of the independent two-sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test for continuous variables, and chi-square or Fischer&#8217;s exact tests for categorical variables. In order to control for independent variables, a multivariate logistic regression model was created to investigate independent risk factors for 4 outcomes: prolonged length of stay (LOS), 90-day readmission, excessive estimated blood loss (EBL), and transfusion. Prolonged LOS was defined as greater than 2&#160;days, which was the median for the sample. Similarly, excessive EBL was defined as EBL greater than the median for the sample, or 300&#160;mL.</p><p>Statistical significance was defined as a two-tailed alpha (p) &lt; .05. To determine the appropriate sample size, a power analysis was performed with the parameters of an effect size of 10%, an alpha of .05, and a beta of .80 (80% power). The appropriate sample size required to minimize Type II error was 61 patients in each group. All statistical analyses were performed using SPSS Statistics for Macintosh (version 26.0, IBM, Armonk, NY, USA).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec10-21925682211049166"><title>Results</title><p>The age range of patients in the sample was 29 to 88&#160;years (59.0 &#177; 13.9&#160;years). There were 115 (39.4%) females in the sample. A total of 146 (50.0%) patients self-reported marijuana usage (<xref rid="table1-21925682211049166" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), among whom 53 (36.3%) consumed marijuana via inhalation, 84 (57.5%) via ingestion, and 9 (6.2%) via either inhalation or ingestion (<xref rid="table2-21925682211049166" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="table1-21925682211049166" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Patient Characteristics and Perioperative Outcomes.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" specific-use="table1-21925682211049166" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_21925682211049166-table1.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Marijuana</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes (n = 146)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No (n = 146)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female (n, %)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (41.1%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (37.7%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.632</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (mean years, SD)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.9 (12.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.7 (14.8)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.903</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body mass index (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.839</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&gt;40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (21.2%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (22.6%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;35&#8211;39.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (24/0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (26.7%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;30&#8211;34.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (21.9%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (22.6%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&lt;30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (32.9%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (28.1%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Procedure</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.435</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;PSF</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.1%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Open TLIF</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (23.3%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (24.0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;MIS TLIF</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (27.4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (35.6%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;ALIF/PSF</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (26.0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (18.5%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;LLIF/PSF</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (21.9%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (19.9%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levels fused (n, %)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.431</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (50.7%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (51.4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (24.0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (22.6%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (23.3%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (21.2%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (8.9%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (4.8%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimated blood loss (mean mL, SD)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">329.9 (298.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">374.5 (363.8)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.254</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay (mean days, SD)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47 (1.14)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.92 (1.32)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Readmission within 90&#160;days (n, %)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (5.5%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (5.5%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.999</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complications (n, %)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Myocardial infarction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Seizure</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Deep vein thrombosis</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (.7%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (.7%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.999</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Pulmonary embolism</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Anaphylaxis</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Acute kidney injury</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (.7%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.495</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Transfusion</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (3.4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (6.2%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.151</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Death</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Abbreviations: PSF, posterolateral segmental fusion; TLIF, transforaminal lumbar interbody fusion; MIS, minimally invasive surgery; ALIF, anterior lumbar interbody fusion; LLIF, lateral lumbar interbody fusion.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="table2-21925682211049166" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Type of Marijuana Use.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" specific-use="table2-21925682211049166" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_21925682211049166-table2.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhalation</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (36.3%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ingestion<sup>
<xref rid="table-fn1-21925682211049166" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>
</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84 (57.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhalation or ingestion<sup>
<xref rid="table-fn1-21925682211049166" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>
</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (6.2%)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1-21925682211049166"><p><sup>a</sup>Includes oral use (e.g.,, tincture) and enteral use (e.g.,, edible product).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Comparing cohorts, the average age of the marijuana usage cohort (58.9 &#177; 12.9&#160;years) was similar to the non-usage cohort (58.7 &#177; 14.8&#160;years; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .903; <xref rid="table1-21925682211049166" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The proportion of females in the marijuana usage cohort (60, 41.1%) was also similar to the non-usage cohort (55, 37.7%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .632). Body mass index (BMI) was similar between the marijuana usage cohort (33.6 &#177; 7.5&#160;kg/m<sup>2</sup>) and the non-usage cohort (33.9 &#177; 7.7&#160;kg/m<sup>2</sup>; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .678). Overall, the procedure types performed were similar between groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .435). There was no difference between cohorts regarding number of levels fused (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .431). There was no difference in fusion mass based on X-ray imaging and evaluation by one of the senior authors (AMJ).</p><p>Univariate analysis of outcomes demonstrated that the marijuana usage cohort had a similar average EBL compared to the non-usage group (329.9 &#177; 298.5&#160;mL vs 374.5 &#177; 363.8&#160;mL; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .254; <xref rid="table1-21925682211049166" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Furthermore, the average LOS in the marijuana usage cohort (2.47 &#177; 1.14&#160;days) was less than that of the non-usage cohort (2.92 &#177; 1.32&#160;days; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .002). The rate of 90-day readmission was equal between groups, with 8 (5.5%) in each cohort (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .999). Post-operative complications were rare with the exception of transfusion, which occurred in 5 (3.4%) patients in the marijuana usage cohort compared to 9 (6.2%) in the non-usage cohort (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .151). One thromboembolic event (DVT) occurred in each cohort (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .999).</p><p>Multivariate logistic regression modeling revealed that patients in the non-usage cohort had twice the risk of prolonged LOS compared to the marijuana usage cohort (odds ratio [OR] 2.05, 95% confidence interval [CI] 1.15-3.63; <xref rid="table3-21925682211049166" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Independent of marijuana usage, risk of prolonged LOS was less in patients with one-level fusion (OR .08, 95% CI 0.02-.32). Compared to the marijuana usage cohort, the non-usage cohort did not differ regarding risk of 90-day readmission (OR .87, 95% CI 0.29-2.61), excessive EBL (OR 1.27, 95% CI 0.64-2.49), or transfusion (OR 1.56, 95% CI 0.43-5.72). Risk of excessive EBL was associated with BMI &gt;40&#160;kg/m2 (OR 2.76, 95% CI 1.06-7.17) and BMI 30-34.9 (OR 3.18, 95% CI 1.24-8.16). One-level fusion independently conferred lesser risk of excessive EBL (OR .09, 95% CI 0.01-.55), lesser risk of prolonged LOS (OR .08, 95% CI 0.02-.32), as well as lesser risk of transfusion (OR .06, 95% CI 0.01-.61). Among the other independent variables controlled for within the multivariate model, none significantly affected risk of any of the 4 outcomes with the exception of procedure type. Compared to lateral lumbar interbody fusion with posterolateral fusion, all other procedure types conferred significantly increased risk of prolonged LOS and excessive EBL.<table-wrap position="float" id="table3-21925682211049166" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Adjusted Risk<sup>*</sup> of Outcome Metrics.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" specific-use="table3-21925682211049166" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_21925682211049166-table3.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prolonged LOS<sup>
<xref rid="table-fn2-21925682211049166" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>
</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Readmission</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excessive EBL<sup>
<xref rid="table-fn3-21925682211049166" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref>
</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transfusion</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marijuana</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05 (1.15-3.63)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.87 (.29-2.61)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 (.64-2.49)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56 (.43-5.72)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.67 (.37-1.19)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.49 (.16-1.52)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55 (.76-3.14)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.32 (.07-1.40)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age group</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8804;48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.59 (.24-1.14)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94 (.39-9.64)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.73 (.29-1.84)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.54 (.07-4.10)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;49&#8211;58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29 (.56-3.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.30 (.03-3.21)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.94 (.36-2.46)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (.17-7.16)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;59&#8211;69</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 (.53-2.51)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06 (.42-10.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.81 (.31-2.14)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.32 (.05-2.13)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&gt;70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&gt;40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.87 (.39-1.93)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.25 (.56-18.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.76 (1.06-7.17)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (.12-8.76)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;35&#8211;39.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.94 (.44-2.01)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.90 (.12-7.07)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69 (.66-4.32)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82 (.29-11.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;30&#8211;34.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 (.59-2.82)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.22 (1.28-40.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.18 (1.24-8.16)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.47 (.71-28.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&lt;30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Procedure</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;PSF</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.86 (.40-37.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Open TLIF</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.05 (3.00-21.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66 (.41-6.70)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 (30-487)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;MIS TLIF</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00 (3.07-20.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.53 (.10-2.93)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.28 (1.82-21.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;ALIF/PSF</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.43 (.93-6.36)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.23 (.02-2.24)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.57 (1.43-14.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;LLIF/PSF</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levels fused</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.08 (.02-.32)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.61 (.10-3.65)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.09 (.01-.55)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.06 (.01-.61)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.30 (.08-1.18)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.52 (.08-3.42)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.25 (.04-1.65)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.13 (.01-1.30)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90 (.44-8.16)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.93 (.15-5.93)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26 (.36-14.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.47 (.07-3.20)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Abbreviations: LOS, length of stay; EBL, estimated blood loss; BMI, body mass index; NC, not calculable due to insufficient sample size.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>*</sup>Odds ratio (95% confidence interval).</p></fn><fn id="table-fn2-21925682211049166"><p><sup>a</sup>Defined as &gt;2&#160;days.</p></fn><fn id="table-fn3-21925682211049166"><p><sup>b</sup>Defined as &gt;300&#160;mL.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec11-21925682211049166"><title>Discussion</title><p>While TXA and marijuana do not appear to be independent risk factors for adverse events in spine surgery,<sup><xref rid="bibr7-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="bibr11-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> the effect of TXA utilization in spine surgery patients who chronically use marijuana remains unexplored. Our study examined if patients who underwent lumbar fusion surgery with adjunct TXA therapy were at greater risk of blood loss, transfusion, and perioperative complications as a factor of daily marijuana usage. Using a retrospective cohort design, we compared 146 patients with self-reported marijuana usage to 146 patients who denied marijuana usage. Using a multivariate logistic regression model, we determined that marijuana usage was only independently associated with lower risk of prolonged LOS. We found that excessive EBL and transfusion, risk of readmission, and complications were similar irrespective of marijuana usage.</p><p>Risk of excessive EBL and transfusion were similar between groups, indicating that chronic daily marijuana use does not affect the efficacy of TXA in lumbar spine surgery. To our knowledge, this is the first study to investigate the use of TXA in patients with chronic daily marijuana use. Despite evidence that pharmacologically active constituents of marijuana inhibit coagulation and platelet aggregation, this effect has been challenged within the literature.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="bibr10-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> For example, there is evidence that delta-9-tetrahydrocannibinol can also have a pro-aggregation effect on platelets, although this effect has only been demonstrated <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr14-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
</sup> Therefore, the results of this study suggest that chronic marijuana does not affect blood loss during elective spine surgery, and there is no increased risk of deep vein thrombosis or thromboembolic events with the concomitant use of TXA. While our study demonstrates that TXA maintains efficacy and safety in patients with a history of chronic daily marijuana use, further investigation is warranted to determine how the constituents of marijuana interact with human platelets in the setting of TXA.</p><p>The only significant difference among outcomes examined using multivariate modeling was shorter LOS among the marijuana usage group. This finding is consistent with previous spine surgery literature.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr7-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
</sup> While post-operative pain scores were not collected in our study, a hypothesis for this finding is that patients with history of chronic marijuana use experience less post-operative pain. However, this hypothesis has been refuted in studies of orthopedic surgery patients. For example, in a study of patients who underwent total knee arthroplasty, patients with self-reported marijuana use required similar morphine milligram equivalents for post-operative pain control compared to non-usage patients.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr15-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
</sup> Furthermore, in a study of trauma patients, chronic marijuana use was associated with higher patient-reported pain scores and higher opioid consumption compared to non-users.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr16-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
</sup> However, both of these studies relied on patient records to determine marijuana usage, and neither study examined spine surgery patients. Further investigation is needed to determine why marijuana usage is associated with decreased LOS following spine surgery, with particular focus on post-operative pain and mobility.</p><p>BMI was associated with increased risk of excessive blood loss among patients with BMI 30-34.9&#160;kg/m<sup>2</sup> and &gt;40&#160;kg/m<sup>2</sup>. Increasing BMI is a known risk factor for increased blood loss in lumbar spine surgery.<sup><xref rid="bibr17-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="bibr18-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> In our analysis, BMI 35-39.9&#160;kg/m<sup>2</sup> was not significantly associated with excessive blood loss, which is likely due to a combination of unknown factors rather than a direct effect of BMI. While BMI has been associated with increased blood loss in lumbar spine surgery with patients in the prone position due to increased intra-abdominal pressure,<sup>
<xref rid="bibr19-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
</sup> BMI does not directly correlate to body composition. Patients with higher proportions of fat distributed to the abdomen are more likely to have higher intra-abdominal pressures intraoperatively, thus more closely correlating to increased blood loss. This variable was not tracked in our study, but it may be one of many reasons for the finding that BMI 35-39.9&#160;kg/m<sup>2</sup> was not significantly associated with excessive blood loss.</p><p>The orthopaedic literature presents a mixed picture regarding chronic marijuana use and risk of perioperative complications. In a recent single-center retrospective comparison of marijuana users and non-users who underwent transforaminal interbody lumbar fusion (TLIF), Jakoi et al.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr7-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
</sup> did not appreciate any significant differences in perioperative complications with a minimum 12-month follow-up. Furthermore, overall 90-day complications were similar between marijuana users and non-users who underwent thoracolumbar or cervical fusions in analyses of the New York Statewide Planning and Research Cooperative System between 2009 and 2013.<sup><xref rid="bibr20-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="bibr21-21925682211049166" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> However, none of the previous studies reported on the use of TXA in the study populations.</p><p>Our study has several limitations. First, while the single surgeon design minimizes treatment variability, selection bias potentially occurred while determining surgical candidates. Second, we did not control for patient characteristics other than sex, age, and BMI. Incorporating additional patient characteristics, such as additional demographics and comorbidities, might have elicited greater differences between groups. Third, our study did not compare TXA utilization vs no TXA utilization within the marijuana usage group, which could potentially reveal subtle consequences specific to TXA utilization in this population. Next, we relied on patient-reported data regarding marijuana usage and non-usage. The retrospective nature of our study obviated the ability to confirm usage or non-usage using laboratory screening. Furthermore, we did not collect data on the volume or dosage of marijuana used, and therefore cannot make any conclusions regarding the dose-effect relationship between marijuana, TXA, and its effects on blood loss or other complications. Finally, the duration of surgery was not factored into our analysis. While other factors such as levels fused and procedure type serve as a proxy to surgery length, using duration of surgery would have been more appropriate given our investigation of factors such as blood loss and need for transfusion; however, this information was not available for our analysis.</p><p>Lumbar fusion with adjunct TXA therapy among patients who use marijuana daily does not increase bleeding risk compared to those who do not use marijuana. Findings such as this, which demonstrate a similar safety profile for patients with a history of chronic daily marijuana use compared to those who do not, are critical for practicing spine surgeons as they continue to navigate spine pathologies in patient populations with increasing proportions of marijuana use. Our findings suggest that marijuana use should not be considered a contraindication for TXA utilization in lumbar spine surgery.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Author&#8217;s note:</bold> Institutional review board approval was obtained for this research through the institution of lead author Andre M. Jakoi (Protocol no. 433-2881).</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn></fn-group><sec id="sec12-21925682211049166"><title>ORCID iDs</title><p>Gregory J. Kirchner <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0959-0222" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0959-0222</ext-link></p><p>Alexander M. Lieber <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6517-4472" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6517-4472</ext-link></p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-21925682211049166"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasin</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerridge</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Prevalence of Marijuana use disorders in the United States between 2001-2002 and 2012-2013</article-title>. <source>JAMA Psychiatry</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1235</fpage>-<lpage>1242</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2015.1858</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26502112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5037576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-21925682211049166"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pacek</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mauro</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Perceived risk of regular cannabis use in the United States from 2002 to 2012: differences by sex, age, and race/ethnicity</article-title>. <source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>149</volume>:<fpage>232</fpage>-<lpage>244</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2015.02.009</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25735467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4361312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-21925682211049166"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carliner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>QL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasin</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarvet</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cannabis use, attitudes, and legal status in the U.S.: a review</article-title>. <source>Prev Med</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ypmed.2017.07.008</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28705601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6348863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-21925682211049166"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanza</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasilenko</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dziak</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Butera</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Trends among U.S. high school seniors in recent Marijuana use and associations with other substances: 1976-2013</article-title>. <source>J Adolesc Health</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>198</fpage>-<lpage>204</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jadohealth.2015.04.006</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26206440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4629476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-21925682211049166"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasin</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerridge</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Prevalence and correlates of DSM-5 Cannabis use disorder, 2012-2013: findings from the national epidemiologic survey on alcohol and related conditions-III</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatr</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>173</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>588</fpage>-<lpage>599</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2015.15070907</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26940807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5026387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-21925682211049166"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stinson</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pickering</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cannabis use disorders in the USA: prevalence, correlates and co-morbidity</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1447</fpage>-<lpage>1460</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291706008361</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16854249</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-21925682211049166"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakoi</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirchner</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerbel</surname><given-names>YE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iorio</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalsa</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effects of Marijuana use on lumbar spinal fusion</article-title>. <source>Spine</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>629</fpage>-<lpage>634</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/BRS.0000000000003321</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31770339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-21925682211049166"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vakharia</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sodhi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anis</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehiorobo</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mont</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roche</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Patients who have Cannabis use disorder have higher rates of venous thromboemboli, readmission rates, and costs following primary total knee arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>997</fpage>-<lpage>1002</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2019.11.035</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31973970</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-21925682211049166"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coetzee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levendal</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van de Venter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anticoagulant effects of a Cannabis extract in an obese rat model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Phytomedicine</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>333</fpage>-<lpage>337</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phymed.2006.02.004</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16644197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-21925682211049166"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Angelis</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koekman</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weeterings</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Endocannabinoids control platelet activation and limit aggregate formation under flow</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e108282</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108282</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25264625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4180465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-21925682211049166"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Systematic review and meta-analysis of perioperative intravenous tranexamic acid use in spinal surgery</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e55436</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0055436</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23424632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3570541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-21925682211049166"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vallone</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Marijuana law in Missouri eases up with new year</article-title>. <publisher-name>Columbia Missourian</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-21925682211049166"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Missouri voters approve medical marijuana with a constitutional amendment</article-title>. <publisher-name>The Kansas City Star</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-21925682211049166"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deusch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kraft</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozek-Langenecker</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The procoagulatory effects of delta-9-tetrahydrocannabinol in human platelets</article-title>. <source>Anesth Analg</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1127</fpage>-<lpage>1130</lpage>. <comment>table of contents</comment>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1213/01.ANE.0000131505.03006.74</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15385362</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-21925682211049166"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angerame</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eschen</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phocas</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cannabis use does not affect outcomes after total knee arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1667</fpage>-<lpage>1669</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2019.04.015</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31072746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-21925682211049166"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salottolo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peck</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanner Ii</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The grass is not always greener: a multi-institutional pilot study of marijuana use and acute pain management following traumatic injury</article-title>. <source>Patient Saf Surg</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13037-018-0163-3</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29946360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6007004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-21925682211049166"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flippin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paxton</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Effect of body mass index on patient outcomes of surgical intervention for the lumbar spine</article-title>. <source>J Spine Surg</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>349</fpage>-<lpage>357</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jss.2017.06.15</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29057342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5637189</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-21925682211049166"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Villavicencio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee Nelson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajpal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vivek</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burneikiene</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of BMI on operating room time, blood loss, and hospital stay in patients undergoing spinal fusion</article-title>. <source>Clin Neurol Neurosurg</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>179</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>22</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clineuro.2019.02.012</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30784895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-21925682211049166"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Son</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of body mass index on intra-abdominal pressure and blood loss in lumbar spine surgery</article-title>. <source>J Korean Neurosurg Soc</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>81</fpage>-<lpage>85</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3340/jkns.2012.51.2.81</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22500198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3322212</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-21925682211049166"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moattari</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavian</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The impact of preoperative cannabis on outcomes following cervical spinal fusion: a propensity score-matched analysis</article-title>. <source>Spine J</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>S8</fpage>-<lpage>S9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10777691</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38213849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-21925682211049166"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavian</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moattari</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The impact of preoperative cannabis use on outcomes following thoracolumbar spinal fusion: a propensity score-matched analysis</article-title>. <source>Spine J</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>S227</fpage>-<lpage>S228</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>