<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Gen Intern Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Gen Intern Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">227</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jgimed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of General Internal Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0884-8734</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1525-1497</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11254873</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11254873.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11254873</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11254873</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38332442</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-024-08664-3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">8664</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Factors Associated with Smoking Cessation and the Receipt of Cessation Services in a Public, Safety-Net Primary Care System</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7009-184X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names initials="D">Dian</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><address><email>Dian.Gu@ucsf.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rafferty</surname><given-names initials="H">Henry</given-names></name><degrees>MS, MPA</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vijayaraghavan</surname><given-names initials="M">Maya</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MAS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.266102.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2297 6811</institution-id><institution>Center for Tobacco Control Research and Education, </institution><institution>University of California, San Francisco, </institution></institution-wrap>San Francisco, CA USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.266102.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2297 6811</institution-id><institution>Division of General Internal Medicine, San Francisco General Hospital, </institution><institution>University of California, San Francisco, </institution></institution-wrap>San Francisco, CA USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/017ztfb41</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410359.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0461 9142</institution-id><institution>San Francisco Department of Public Health, </institution></institution-wrap>San Francisco, CA USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>39</volume><issue>9</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">466972</issue-id><fpage>1657</fpage><lpage>1665</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>08</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>19</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-07-19 00:25:26.347"><day>19</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="11606_2024_Article_8664.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Prevalence of smoking is high among patients receiving care in safety-net settings, and there is a need to better understand patient factors associated with smoking cessation and receipt of cessation services.</p></sec><sec><title>Objective</title><p id="Par2">To identify patient factors associated with smoking cessation attempts and receipt of cessation counseling and pharmacotherapy in a large safety-net health system.</p></sec><sec><title>Design</title><p id="Par3">We conducted a retrospective cohort analysis using EHR data in a safety-net system in San Francisco, CA.</p></sec><sec><title>Participants</title><p id="Par4">We included 7384 adult current smokers who had at least three unique primary care encounters with documented smoking status between August 2019 and April 2022.</p></sec><sec><title>Main measures</title><p id="Par5">We assessed four outcomes using multivariate generalized estimating equation models: (1) any cessation attempt, indicating a transition in smoking status from &#8220;current smoker&#8221; to &#8220;former smoker&#8221;; (2) sustained cessation, defined as transition in smoking status from current smoker to former smokers for two or more consecutive visits; (3) receipt of smoking cessation counseling from healthcare providers; and (4) receipt of pharmacotherapy.</p></sec><sec><title>Key Results</title><p id="Par6">Of 7384 current adult smokers, 17.6% had made any cessation attempt, and of those 66.5% had sustained cessation. Most patients (81.1%) received counseling and 41.8% received pharmacotherapy. Factors associated with lower odds of any cessation attempt included being aged 45&#8211;64, non-Hispanic black, and experiencing homelessness. The factor associated with lower odds of sustained cessation was being male. Factors associated with lower odds of receiving counseling were being insured by Medicaid or being uninsured. Factors associated with lower odds of receiving pharmacotherapy included speaking languages other than English, being male, and identifying as racial and ethnic minorities.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par7">Health system interventions could close the gap in access to smoking cessation services for unhoused and racial/ethnic minority patients in safety-net settings, thereby increasing cessation among these populations.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>KEY WORDS</title><kwd>associated factors</kwd><kwd>smoking cessation</kwd><kwd>cessation service</kwd><kwd>safety-net setting</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100005188</institution-id><institution>Tobacco-Related Disease Research Program</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>28CP-0038</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Vijayaraghavan</surname><given-names>Maya</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100007316</institution-id><institution>Division of Cancer Prevention, National Cancer Institute</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>CA-113710</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Dian</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; Society of General Internal Medicine 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p id="Par8">Cigarette smoking prevalence among adults in the United States (US) has been declining, with a prevalence of 20.9% in 2005 to 11.5% in 2021.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> Despite this improvement, smoking is concentrated among priority populations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> In 2021, smoking prevalence was higher among low-income adults (18.3%) and those uninsured (20.0%) or insured by Medicaid (21.5%) compared to their counterparts. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup></p><p id="Par9">Tobacco use remains the leading preventable cause of morbidity and mortality, contributing to over 60% of annual healthcare costs covered by Medicare and Medicaid.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup> A 1% reduction of smoking prevalence is associated with $2.5 billion in annual Medicaid savings.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> Safety-net health systems are the primary source of low or no-cost healthcare for low-income populations. Improving access to smoking cessation care in safety-net settings can reduce tobacco-related health disparities.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup> Cessation interventions that have included engagement with quitline or in-person tobacco treatment have shown cost savings for safety-net practices<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> and patients insured by Medicaid.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup></p><p id="Par10">Within health systems, healthcare providers can help people who smoke to quit by using guideline-recommended 5As for smoking cessation (Ask, Advise, Assess, Assist, and Arrange) and pharmacotherapy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup> While most providers Ask, Advise, and Assess for tobacco use, the proportion of providers assisting with quit attempts and arranging for follow-up is much lower.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup> Digital interventions including reminders in the electronic health record (EHR) have increased provider delivery of 5As.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> Moreover, medical teams can use the EHR to receive automatic reminders for tobacco screening,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup> refer for smoking cessation services (e.g., behavioral counseling and pharmacotherapy),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> and monitor receipt of services.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup></p><p id="Par11">Starting in 2009, the federal government put into effect the Meaningful Use criteria, where healthcare systems that had implemented an EHR could receive annual incentive payments from the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid if they met tobacco screening and referral targets.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> The implementation of the Meaningful Use EHR guideline for tobacco screening and treatment was associated with an increase in receipt of cessation services among patients who smoked in some health systems.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup></p><p id="Par12">However, only a few studies used the EHR to assess patient characteristics associated with cessation behaviors and receipt of cessation services in safety-net settings.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> The results varied depending on the clinical setting and patient population. A study using 2014&#8211;2016 EHR data from safety-net clinics in the Oregon Community Health Information Network showed that Medicare patients were less likely to receive counseling and racial and ethnic minorities were less likely to have cessation medications prescribed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> In an EHR-based study from the San Francisco Health Network, a network of safety-net clinics in San Francisco, California, uninsured or patients insured by Medicaid were less likely to receive cessation counseling.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> In the same setting, patients who were older, were insured by Medicaid or uninsured, and had limited English proficiency had a lower likelihood of quit attempts.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup></p><p id="Par13">These studies were done before the COVID-19 pandemic when most cessation services were provided in-person. However, since the pandemic, health systems, including the San Francisco Health Network, have transitioned to providing tobacco treatment using telehealth models of care.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> In this study, we extend our prior work<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> by describing previously unexplored patient factors associated with receipt of cessation services, quit attempts, and sustained cessation during the pandemic. Social determinants of health like housing are linked with tobacco use,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> and we were able to obtain information on housing status for the present analysis. Our study has two objectives: (1) describe the proportion of smoking cessation attempts, sustained cessation, and receipt of cessation services (counseling and pharmacotherapy) among adult smokers in primary care clinics within the San Francisco Health Network; and (2) identify patient factors associated with those outcomes. We hypothesized that unhoused populations would be less likely to have any cessation and sustained cessation attempts compared to housed populations.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>METHODS</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study Design and Data Source</title><p id="Par14">We conducted a retrospective cohort study between August 2019 and April 2022 using EHR data from adult patients in 12 primary care clinics within the San Francisco Health Network, a network of primary care clinics that serve San Francisco&#8217;s diverse low-income populations. The population includes residents who are low- or very low&#8211;income including those experiencing homelessness, and who represent the age, sex, and racial/ethnic diversity of people living in San Francisco. Three clinics were academic primary care practices in a safety-net hospital; the remaining clinics were community-based clinics in San Francisco. At each clinic visit, medical assistants screen patients for current smoking, and document smoking status in EHR as &#8220;current smoker,&#8221; &#8220;former smoker,&#8221; or &#8220;never smoker.&#8221; Medical assistants refer all current smokers to cessation resources (e.g., quitline, or on-site referrals to the medical team), and document referrals within EHR. The medical team, including health care providers and behavioral health care staff, provides tobacco treatment and documents provision of smoking cessation counseling and/or pharmacotherapy during clinical encounters. We extracted data using Structured Query Language (SQL) from the EHR on any patient of the 12 clinics who had at least three unique primary care encounters with documented smoking status between April 2019 and April 2022. The index visit was the first encounter closest to the study&#8217;s start date in April 2019. This study was approved by the University of California, San Francisco Committee on Human Research (#18&#8211;26,398).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Ascertainment of Study Cohort</title><p id="Par15">We included adult patients who were aged 18 or over and had at least three unique primary care encounters with documented smoking status. We identified current smokers based on their recorded smoking status at the index visit. Patients could have at minimum three visits and up to nine visits with a documented smoking status throughout the study duration.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Outcome Variables</title><p id="Par16">The two binary smoking cessation outcomes were (1) any cessation attempt, defined as a transition in smoking status from &#8220;current smoker&#8221; at the index visit to &#8220;former smoker&#8221; at any of the subsequent visits, and (2) sustained cessation, defined as transition in smoking status from current smoker at the index visit to former smokers for two or more consecutive visits until the end of the study. The two binary cessation services outcomes for current smokers were (1) receipt of smoking cessation counseling from one or more members of the medical team (i.e., health care provider, medical assistant, or behavioral health staff) at any visit, and (2) receipt of pharmacotherapy including nicotine replacement therapy (NRT) and/or non-NRT at any visit.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Independent Variables</title><p id="Par17">We assessed independent variables at the patients&#8217; index visit including patient demographics (age [18&#8211;44, 45&#8211;64, 65&#8201;+],<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> sex [male vs. female], race/ethnicity [non-Hispanic White [NHW], Hispanic, non-Hispanic Black [NHB], non-Hispanic Asian [NHA], and non-Hispanic other [NHO]], and primary language), social determinants of health (health insurance and housing status [experiencing homelessness or housed]), and comorbidity burden (number of smoking-related comorbidities [0, 1, 2,&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;3] including heart failure, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, kidney disease, coronary artery disease, depression, diabetes, HIV, hyperlipidemia, and hypertension). We identified comorbidities using ICD-10 codes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> We included intensity of primary care (number of visits during the study period) in the models exploring cessation outcomes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p id="Par18">First, we used bivariate analysis <italic toggle="yes">&#967;</italic><sup>2</sup> tests to examine the association of independent and cluster variables with each outcome. Then, to determine factors associated with each outcome, we conducted four separate generalized estimating equation (GEE) logistic models, accounting for clustering within the two clinic types (academic vs. community) with an exchangeable structure in each model. We clustered by clinic because patient populations seeking care in academic and community clinics had different demographic characteristics that might be relevant to tobacco use.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> The four models estimating the odds of any cessation attempt (model 1), sustained cessation (model 2), receipt of any cessation counseling (model 3), and receipt of pharmacotherapy (model 4) controlled for independent variables from the index visit. Models 1, 3, and 4 were conducted among all current smokers and model 2 was conducted among current smokers who had any cessation attempt. We did not include receipt of cessation services as variables in the models of any cessation attempt or sustained cessation because these services were provided only to patients who were current smokers. Including them in the models would erroneously suggest that current smokers who received cessation services were less likely to quit smoking. To account for time-lapsed between visits, we included average time between visits as a variable in the model for sustained cessation and found no association between sustained cessation and length of time between visits. We chose not to include this variable in the sustained cessation model. All analyses were performed using SAS V.9.4 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA). Estimates were considered to be statistically significant if the two-tailed <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>RESULTS</title><p id="Par19">The analytic sample included 7384 adult patients who were current smokers. We excluded 71 patients with incomplete information for the outcome and independent variables. Of the 7384 adult patients who were current smokers, 1302 (17.6%) made any cessation attempt. Of those who made any cessation attempt, 866 (66.5%) made a sustained cessation attempt.</p><sec id="Sec9"><title>Sample Characteristics and Factors Associated with Cessation Outcomes</title><p id="Par20">Patients who were younger, identified as Hispanic/Latino, were non-English speaking, had Healthy San Francisco/Healthy Workers coverage, and were housed were more likely to make any cessation attempt (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In multivariable analysis, being Hispanic (adjusted odds ratio [AOR] 1.53, 95% confidence interval [CI] 1.26&#8211;1.86) and number of visits (AOR 1.28, 95%CI 1.24&#8211;1.32) were associated with higher odds of making any cessation attempt (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Factors associated with lower odds of any cessation attempt included older age (45&#8211;64&#160;years) (AOR 0.75, 95%CI 0.64&#8211;0.87), being NHB (AOR 0.82, 95%CI 0.68&#8211;0.97), and experiencing homelessness (AOR 0.53, 95%CI 0.45&#8211;0.63). Being male was associated with lower odds of sustained cessation (AOR 0.75, 95%CI 0.58&#8211;0.96; Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), while number of visits (AOR 1.11, 95%CI 1.04&#8211;1.19) was associated with higher odds.<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;1</label><caption><p>Characteristics by Any Cessation Attempt Among Current Smokers (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;7384) and Sustained Cessation Among Currents Smokers Who Made Any Cessation Attempt (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1302)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patients with any cessation attempt (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1302)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patients with sustained cessation (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;866)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Demographics</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Age</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5183</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;18&#8211;44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">408 (20.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">279 (68.4%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;45&#8211;64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">632 (15.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">411 (65.0%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;65&#8201;+&#8201;</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">262 (19.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">176 (67.2%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Sex</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0024</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0227</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">483 (19.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">340 (70.4%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">819 (16.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">526 (64.2%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Race/ethnicity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3253</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;NHW</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">305 (15.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">193 (63.3%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Hispanic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">361 (25.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">248 (68.7%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;NHB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">305 (14.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">195 (63.9%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;NHA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">216 (17.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">152 (70.4%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;NHO</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">115 (18.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78(67.8%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Language</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4121</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;English</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">949 (16.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">625 (65.9%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">353 (22.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">241 (68.3%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Social determinants of health</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Health insurance</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0070</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4868</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Healthy San Francisco, Healthy Workers</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">261 (21.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">179 (68.6%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Medicaid</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">728 (16.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">486 (66.8%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Medicare</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">261 (16.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">170 (65.1%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Uninsured/self-pay</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37 (17.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (64.9%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Commercial/other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (20.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (46.7%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Housing status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8584</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Experiencing homelessness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">182 (10.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">120 (65.9%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Housed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1120 (19.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">746 (66.6%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Comorbidity burden</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Number of comorbidities</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1509</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4659</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">313 (18.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">204 (65.2%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">400 (17.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">270 (67.5%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">261 (15.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">182 (69.7%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">328 (18.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">210 (64.0%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Intensity of primary care*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Number of visits during the study period</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001&#8224;</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (3)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0220&#8224;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Cluster variable</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Primary care center</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5465</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0639</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Academic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">524 (18.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">364 (69.5%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Community</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">778 (17.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">502 (64.5%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">NHW</italic>, non-Hispanic White; <italic toggle="yes">NHB</italic>, non-Hispanic Black; <italic toggle="yes">NHA</italic>, non-Hispanic Asian; <italic toggle="yes">NHO</italic>, non-Hispanic other</p><p>*Median (interquartile range). &#8224;<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value from the Kruskal&#8211;Wallis test</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;2</label><caption><p>Factors Associated with Cessation Outcomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 1 outcome: Any cessation attempt</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 2 outcome: Sustained cessation</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AOR (95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AOR (95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Demographics</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Age</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;18&#8211;44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;45&#8211;64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.75 (0.64&#8211;0.87)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0002</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.85 (0.63&#8211;1.14)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2805</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;65&#8201;+&#8201;</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.98 (0.78&#8211;1.22)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8265</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (0.65&#8211;1.53)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9911</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Sex</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.88 (0.77&#8211;1.01)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0609</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.75 (0.58&#8211;0.96)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0223</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Race/ethnicity</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;NHW</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Hispanic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.53 (1.26&#8211;1.86)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.23 (0.85&#8211;1.77)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2722</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;NHB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.82 (0.68&#8211;0.97)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0249</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.96 (0.69&#8211;1.35)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8282</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;NHA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.93 (0.74&#8211;1.16)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5060</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.43 (0.95&#8211;2.16)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0891</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;NHO</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.15 (0.9&#8211;1.46)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2723</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.21 (0.76&#8211;1.91)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4293</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Language</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;English</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.07 (0.89&#8211;1.29)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4604</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97 (0.69&#8211;1.37)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8677</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Social determinants of health</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Health insurance</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Healthy San Francisco, Healthy Workers</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Medicaid</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.88 (0.73&#8211;1.05)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1571</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.93 (0.66&#8211;1.3)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6644</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Medicare</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.84 (0.66&#8211;1.06)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1359</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.88 (0.57&#8211;1.36)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5562</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Uninsured/self-pay</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.05 (0.71&#8211;1.57)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7969</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.88 (0.42&#8211;1.84)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7304</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Commercial/other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.15 (0.63&#8211;2.11)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6522</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.39 (0.13&#8211;1.14)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0844</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Housing status</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160; &#160; Housed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160; &#160; Experiencing homelessness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.53 (0.45&#8211;0.63)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12 (0.79&#8211;1.58)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5290</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Comorbidity burden</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Number of comorbidities</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.96 (0.81&#8211;1.13)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6011</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12 (0.81&#8211;1.55)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4961</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.83 (0.69&#8211;1.01)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0688</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.21 (0.83&#8211;1.76)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3230</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#8805;&#8201;3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94 (0.77&#8211;1.14)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5289</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.93 (0.64&#8211;1.35)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6995</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Intensity of primary care</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Number of visits during the study period</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.28 (1.24&#8211;1.32)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.11 (1.04&#8211;1.19)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0023</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">AOR</italic>, adjusted odds ratio; <italic toggle="yes">95% CI</italic>, 95% confidence interval; <italic toggle="yes">NHW</italic>, non-Hispanic White; <italic toggle="yes">NHB</italic>, non-Hispanic Black; <italic toggle="yes">NHA</italic>, non-Hispanic Asian; <italic toggle="yes">NHO</italic>, non-Hispanic other</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Sample Characteristics and Factors Associated with Receipt of Cessation Services</title><p id="Par21">Most patients who were current smokers received counseling or pharmacotherapy during one or more of their encounters. Among all encounters with counseling, 67% were offered by medical assistants, 0.3% by behavioral health providers, and 33% by healthcare providers (data not shown). Of the 7384 current smokers, 5985 (81.1%) received any counseling and 3088 (41.8%) received pharmacotherapy (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). For receipt of both cessation services, statistically significant differences were found for similar characteristics, except for homelessness status which was not associated with receipt of counseling (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). In multivariable analyses, factors associated with receipt of any counseling and pharmacotherapy were older age (45&#8211;64&#160;years) (AOR 1.35, 95%CI 1.17&#8211;1.56) and having more comorbidities (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Factors associated with lower odds of receiving any cessation counseling included having Medicaid (AOR 0.79, 95%CI 0.66&#8211;0.95), being uninsured/self-paid (AOR 0.70, 95%CI 0.49&#8211;0.99), and having commercial/other insurances (AOR 0.58, 95%CI 0.34&#8211;0.98) compared to having &#8220;Healthy San Francisco and Healthy Workers.&#8221; In contrast, factors associated with higher odds of receiving pharmacotherapy included having Medicare (AOR 1.31, 95%CI 1.12&#8211;1.52) and Medicaid (AOR 1.32, 95%CI 1.10&#8211;1.60). Being male (AOR 0.87, 95%CI 0.78&#8211;0.96), speaking a language other than English (AOR 0.66, 95% CI 0.56&#8211;0.77), and being NHA (AOR 0.61, 95%CI 0.51&#8211;0.73), NHB (AOR 0.7, 95%CI 0.7&#8211;0.90), and NHO (AOR 0.77, 95%CI 0.64&#8211;0.93) were factors associated with lower odds of receiving pharmacotherapy.<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;3</label><caption><p>Characteristics by the Receipt of Cessation Services Among Current Smokers (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;7384)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patients receiving counseling (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;5985)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patients receiving pharmacotherapy (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;3088)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Demographics</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Age</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;18&#8211;44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1498 (74.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">759 (37.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;45&#8211;64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3331 (83.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1783 (44.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;65&#8201;+&#8201;</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1156 (84.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">546 (40.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Sex</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0028</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1957 (79.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1110 (44.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4028 (82.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1978 (40.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Race/ethnicity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;NHW</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1559 (81.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">944 (49.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Hispanic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1075 (75.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">530 (37.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;NHB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1767 (81.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">980 (45.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;NHA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1088 (87.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">366 (29.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;NHO</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">496 (79.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">268 (42.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Language</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0185</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;English</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4653 (80.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2636 (45.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1332 (83.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">452 (28.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Social determinants of health</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Health insurance</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Healthy San Francisco, Healthy Workers</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1035 (84.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">368 (30.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Medicaid</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3413 (79.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1915 (44.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Medicare</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1326 (84.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">710 (45.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Uninsured/self-pay</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">157 (74.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65 (31.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Commercial/other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54 (73.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (40.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Housing status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0829</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Experiencing homelessness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1387 (82.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">768 (45.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Housed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4598 (80.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2320 (40.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Comorbidity burden</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Number of comorbidities</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1303 (76.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">554 (32.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1836 (80.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">897 (39.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1353 (82.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">732 (44.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#8805;&#8201;3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1493 (85.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">905 (51.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Cluster variable</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Primary care center</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Academic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2155 (73.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1326 (45.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Community</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3830 (85.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1762 (39.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">NHW</italic>, non-Hispanic White; <italic toggle="yes">NHB</italic>, non-Hispanic Black; <italic toggle="yes">NHA</italic>, non-Hispanic Asian; <italic toggle="yes">NHO</italic>, non-Hispanic other</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;4</label><caption><p>Factors Associated with Receipt of Cessation Services</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 3 outcome: Counseling</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 4 outcome: Pharmacotherapy</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AOR (95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AOR (95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Demographics</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Age</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;18&#8211;44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;45&#8211;64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.35 (1.17&#8211;1.56)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.18 (1.04&#8211;1.33)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0076</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;65&#8201;+&#8201;</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.19 (0.96&#8211;1.47)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1144</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.89 (0.75&#8211;1.07)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2105</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Sex</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12 (0.99&#8211;1.27)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0678</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.87 (0.78&#8211;0.96)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0081</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Race/ethnicity</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;NHW</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Hispanic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.83 (0.69&#8211;1.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0526</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.77 (0.66&#8211;0.90)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0008</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;NHB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.99 (0.85&#8211;1.16)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9036</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.80 (0.70&#8211;0.90)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0004</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;NHA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.41 (1.12&#8211;1.76)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0030</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.61 (0.51&#8211;0.73)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;NHO</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.01 (0.81&#8211;1.27)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8997</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.77 (0.64&#8211;0.93)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0071</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Language</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;English</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03 (0.86&#8211;1.25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7364</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.66 (0.56&#8211;0.77)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Social determinants of health</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Health insurance</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Healthy San Francisco, Healthy Workers</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Medicaid</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.79 (0.66&#8211;0.95)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0145</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.31 (1.12&#8211;1.52)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0006</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Medicare</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95 (0.75&#8211;1.20)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6724</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.32 (1.10&#8211;1.60)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0035</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Uninsured/self-pay</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.70 (0.49&#8211;0.99)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0461</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.88 (0.63&#8211;1.22)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4397</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Commercial/other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.58 (0.34&#8211;0.98)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0426</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.33 (0.81&#8211;2.17)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2579</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Housing status</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160; &#160; Housed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref </td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160; &#160; Experiencing homelessness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.15 (0.99&#8211;1.33)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0650</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02 (0.91&#8211;1.15)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7460</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Comorbidity burden</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Number of comorbidities</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.19 (1.02&#8211;1.38)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0271</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.27 (1.11&#8211;1.45)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.34 (1.12&#8211;1.60)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0013</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.56 (1.35&#8211;1.81)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#8805;&#8201;3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.46 (1.21&#8211;1.77)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.14 (1.84&#8211;2.49)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">AOR</italic>, adjusted odds ratio; <italic toggle="yes"> 95% CI</italic>, 95% confidence interval; <italic toggle="yes">NHW</italic>, non-Hispanic White; <italic toggle="yes">NHB</italic>, non-Hispanic Black; <italic toggle="yes">NHA</italic>, non-Hispanic Asian; <italic toggle="yes">NHO</italic>, non-Hispanic other</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p id="Par22">In this retrospective study of patients seeking primary care in a safety-net health system, we found that 17.6% of patients who smoked attempted to quit smoking, and of those who attempted to quit, 66.5% were able to sustain their quit attempt across two or more visits. Most patients who smoked received cessation counseling, and about half received pharmacotherapy. Quit attempt rates were higher than the spontaneous population-level quitting rate of 5%, but lower than the 30&#8211;40% quitting rate observed in 8&#8211;12-week clinical trials of behavioral counseling and pharmacotherapy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup></p><p id="Par23">In a previous study conducted between 2016 and 2019 in the San Francisco Health Network that examined smoking status across three primary care visits, 26.5% of patients attempted any cessation attempt, and 34% of those who attempted to quit smoking had sustained cessation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> In a related cross-sectional study with a similar population focusing on four safety-net clinics, 17.6% had made any cessation attempt.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> The difference in any cessation attempts may be due to unmeasured factors like change in patient population between studies, and the increase in any sustained attempts may be due to following patients over longer periods of time.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> The present study showed a higher rate of sustained cessation with a stricter measure, a marker of long-term quitting,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> and highlighted that most patients were receiving at least one cessation intervention during one or more routine primary care visits. Patients who had a greater number of visits were more likely to make a quit attempt and achieve sustained abstinence.</p><p id="Par24">In the year prior to and during the time of COVID-19 pandemic, the SFHN implemented several quality improvement initiatives to support tobacco treatment efforts,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> including a tobacco coordinator who trained clinic staff on how to outreach to patients who smoked, use tobacco registries, implement practice changes in delivering tobacco treatment, and document these interventions in the EHR.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> The SFHN also had a robust IT infrastructure that helped transition the health system from an in-person model of healthcare delivery to telehealth model, including for tobacco treatment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> These initiatives may have played a role in increasing patients&#8217; receipt of tobacco treatment, and in turn, their attempts to quit smoking.</p><p id="Par25">Our study highlighted several patient groups that could benefit from expanded and intensive tobacco treatment efforts. People experiencing homelessness had a lower likelihood of any cessation attempts. People experiencing homelessness have high rates of tobacco use, with a prevalence of 70%, but rates of successful cessation are low.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> In our study, we found that compared to housed individuals, fewer people who were homeless were making any cessation attempts and there was no association with sustained cessation. Our findings suggest that once an attempt is initiated, people experiencing homelessness were no different in sustaining that attempt compared to those who were housed. Therefore, there may be a role for interventions within EHR to increase motivation to quit.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup></p><p id="Par26">Our study found that male patients were less likely to sustain their cessation compared to women. Men have been shown to have higher nicotine dependence than women,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> which is a known barrier to cessation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup> NHB patients were less likely to make any attempts compared to NHW patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> Despite smoking at lower rates, NHB patients who smoke have higher levels of nicotine dependence. They are less likely to quit successfully despite making more quit attempts than White smokers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup> They may also experience barriers to receiving tobacco treatment,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> which we observed in our study and could explain their lower cessation attempt rate. Tobacco retail density tends to be higher in communities where NHB populations reside; the increased availability of tobacco products may influence cessation rates. EHR reminders, although potentially contributing to provider fatigue,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup> and tobacco registries that systematically address equity gaps may mitigate racial/ethnic disparities in access to tobacco treatment,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> may in turn increase cessation attempts.</p><p id="Par27">Patients who were insured by Medicare and Medicaid were more likely to receive cessation pharmacotherapy&#8212;a covered benefit&#8212;than those covered through Healthy San Francisco where there may have been coverage gaps. In contrast, patients covered through Healthy San Francisco/Healthy Workers were more likely to receive counseling than those on Medicaid. While these findings are consistent with those in our prior study,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> they are paradoxical as we expect that Medicaid and Medicare would similarly cover counseling and pharmacotherapy interventions. We speculate that certain omitted variable correlated with one of the cessation services and health insurance coverage affected the direction of this relationship. One of the omitted variables could be providers&#8217; awareness of services covered; most providers may be aware that insurance covers pharmacotherapy but may be less aware that counseling is also a covered benefit. The mechanism of the relationship between health insurance coverage and the receipt of different cessation services warrants further investigation. There may be a need for provider education on the newer recommendations for varenicline<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> and/or combination NRT for cessation pharmacotherapy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup></p><p id="Par28">Racial/ethnic minorities and non-English speaking patients had lower odds of receiving pharmacotherapy. Racial and ethnic minorities tend to have lower rates of pharmacotherapy prescribed than White patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup> due to competing priorities among patients and providers, low rates of provider adherence to tobacco treatment guidelines, and implicit bias around adherence to pharmacotherapy among providers of non-White patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup> These barriers may be addressed by creating equity or care gap reminders within the EHR to encourage practice changes around tobacco treatment. Providing education to patients on the benefits of tobacco treatment in a culturally and linguistically concordant manner may also dispel some of the misconceptions around the use of cessation medications among racial/ethnic minority groups.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup></p><p id="Par29">Consistent with our previous studies,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> medical assistants delivered counseling at higher rates than behavioral health and healthcare providers. This is normative in team-based care settings where the ownership of providing tobacco treatment is distributed among the medical team. However, our results also suggest that while medical assistants may provide the initial referral to treatment, behavioral health and healthcare providers&#8217; support could be enlisted for subpopulation of patients highlighted in this analysis who may benefit from intensive treatments.</p><p id="Par30">Our study had limitations. First, EHR smoking status was based on self-report, potentially resulting in classification errors. Self-report measurements of smoking status have high sensitivity and specificity compared to biochemical validation;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup> we expect the misclassification rate to be low.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> Second, nicotine dependence measures were not included in the EHR, highlighting a potential gap in EHR measurements of tobacco use status, which may impact practice changes in prescribing pharmacotherapy. Third, cessation behaviors and service receipt in SFHN may vary from that in other safety-net systems in other geographic areas; therefore, our results may lack external generalizability. Fourth, all the outcomes of interest in the four models were not relatively rare (&gt;&#8201;10%), so the AORs in our results might have led to an overestimation of the association strength.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> Fifth, because EHR data reflect data captured from clinical encounters, we can only ascertain if and when quitting took place. We are unable to determine whether a lack of transition from current to past smoking was because of lack of motivation to quit or a failed quit attempt. Sixth, we were unable to assess delivery of cessation services between telehealth and in-person encounters, warranting further research to analyze patient characteristics across different methods of delivery.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p id="Par31">This study identified subpopulations that could benefit from tailored intensive cessation interventions during primary care. The EHR is a good tool to assess provision of guideline-recommended tobacco treatment to meet performance-based incentive programs for healthcare systems. It is also an effective tool to identify tobacco-related disparities in healthcare settings, allowing healthcare providers and health systems to tailor tobacco treatment to those groups that have the highest gaps in receipt of cessation services. The EHR has the potential to expand collection of social determinants of health metrics, which could provide a deeper understanding of the context of tobacco use and the extent to which tobacco treatment services are reaching disproportionately impacted populations.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Tobacco-Related Disease Research Program (28CP-0038) and&#160;Division of Cancer Prevention, National Cancer Institute (CA-113710).</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p id="Par32">The authors declare that they do not have a conflict of interest.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><bold>Jamal A, King BA, Neff LJ, Whitmill J, Babb SD, Graffunder CM.</bold> Current Cigarette Smoking Among Adults - United States, 2005-2015. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2016;65(44):1205-11.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.15585/mmwr.mm6544a2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27832052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelius</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loretan</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jamal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tobacco product use among adults - United States, 2021</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep.</source><year>2023</year><volume>72</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7218a1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37141154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10168602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pechacek</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Annual healthcare spending attributable to cigarette smoking: an update</article-title><source>Am J Prev Med.</source><year>2015</year><volume>48</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2014.10.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25498551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4603661</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glantz</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of 1-year changes in Medicaid expenditures associated with reducing cigarette smoking prevalence by 1%</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open.</source><year>2019</year><volume>2</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e192307</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.2307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30977860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6481435</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krist</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mangione</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interventions for tobacco smoking cessation in adults, including pregnant persons</article-title><source>JAMA.</source><year>2021</year><volume>325</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>265</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.25019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33464343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drouin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drehmer</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cost-effectiveness of a smoking cessation intervention for parents in pediatric primary care</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open.</source><year>2021</year><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e213927</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.3927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33792730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8017473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mundt</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piper</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiore</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Paying low-income smokers to quit? The cost-effectiveness of incentivizing tobacco quit line engagement for Medicaid recipients who smoke</article-title><source>Value Health.</source><year>2019</year><volume>22</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jval.2018.08.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30711062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6362459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiore</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaen</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Treating tobacco use and dependence: 2008 update US Public Health Service Clinical Practice Guideline executive summary</article-title><source>Respir Care.</source><year>2008</year><volume>53</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1217</fpage><lpage>1222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18807274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vijayaraghavan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gregorich</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Disparities in receipt of 5As for smoking cessation in diverse primary care and HIV clinics</article-title><source>Prev Med Rep.</source><year>2017</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pmedr.2017.02.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28271025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5334546</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Satterfield</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gregorich</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalkhoran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Computer-facilitated 5A&#8217;s for smoking cessation: a randomized trial of technology to promote provider adherence</article-title><source>Am J Prev Med.</source><year>2018</year><volume>55</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2018.04.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29929682</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6020838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kharrazi</surname><given-names>HHK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huerta</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electronic medical record reminders and smoking cessation activities in primary care</article-title><source>Addict Behav.</source><year>2018</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.addbeh.2017.10.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29065376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schindler-Ruwisch</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abroms</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heminger</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A content analysis of electronic health record (EHR) functionality to support tobacco treatment</article-title><source>Transl Behav Med.</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13142-016-0446-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27800564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5526802</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gubner</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Recent cessation attempts and receipt of cessation services among a diverse primary care population &#8211; a mixed methods study</article-title><source>Prev Med Rep.</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>100907</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pmedr.2019.100907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31193606</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6536779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huerta</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The electronic medical record&#8217;s role in support of smoking cessation activities</article-title><source>Nicotine Tobacco Res.</source><year>2016</year><volume>18</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1019</fpage><lpage>1024</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntv270</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26659415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blumenthal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tavenner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The, &#8220;Meaningful Use&#8221; regulation for electronic health records</article-title><source>N Engl J Med.</source><year>2010</year><volume>363</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMp1006114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20647183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>ASL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Young-Wolff</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter-Harris</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salloum</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disparities in the receipt of tobacco treatment counseling within the US context of the Affordable Care Act and Meaningful Use implementation</article-title><source>Nicotine Tob Res.</source><year>2018</year><volume>20</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1474</fpage><lpage>1480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntx233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29059372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6454423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heintzman</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Smoking-cessation assistance: Before and after stage 1 Meaningful Use implementation</article-title><source>Am J Prev Med.</source><year>2017</year><volume>53</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2017.02.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28365090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5522621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silfen</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farley</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shih</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increases in smoking cessation interventions after a feedback and improvement initiative using electronic health records &#8211; 19 community health centers, New York City, October 2010-March 2012</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep.</source><year>2014</year><volume>63</volume><issue>41</issue><fpage>921</fpage><lpage>924</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25321069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4584749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gubner</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Recent cessation attempts and receipt of cessation services among a diverse primary care population - a mixed methods study</article-title><source>Prev Med Rep.</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>100907</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pmedr.2019.100907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31193606</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6536779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suen</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rafferty</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with smoking cessation attempts in a public, safety-net primary care system</article-title><source>Prev Med Rep.</source><year>2022</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>101699</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pmedr.2022.101699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35145838</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8802046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rafferty</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suen</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vijayaraghavan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>System-level quality improvement initiatives for tobacco use in a safety-net health system during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>J Prim Care Community Health.</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>21501319221107984</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/21501319221107984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35748431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9234926</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baggett</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tobey</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rigotti</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tobacco use among homeless people&#8211;addressing the neglected addiction</article-title><source>N Engl J Med.</source><year>2013</year><volume>369</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMp1301935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23863048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><bold>Fiore MC, Ja&#233;n C, Baker T, et al.</bold> Treating tobacco use and dependence: 2008 update. Clinical Practice Guideline. Rockville, MD: US Dept of Health and Human Services, Public Health Service; 2008.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilpin</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farkas</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Duration of smoking abstinence and success in quitting</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst.</source><year>1997</year><volume>89</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>572</fpage><lpage>576</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/89.8.572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9106646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vijayaraghavan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elser</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frazer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apollonio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interventions to reduce tobacco use in people experiencing homelessness</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev.</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>CD013413</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33284989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD013413.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8130995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alberg</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saladin</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Motivating the unmotivated for health behavior change: a randomized trial of cessation induction for smokers</article-title><source>Clin Trials.</source><year>2010</year><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1740774510361533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20338901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2902976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiffman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paton</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Individual differences in smoking: gender and nicotine addiction</article-title><source>Nicotine Tob Res.</source><year>1999</year><volume>1 Suppl 2</volume><fpage>S153</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14622299050011991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11768174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piper</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Time to first cigarette in the morning as an index of ability to quit smoking: implications for nicotine dependence</article-title><source>Nicotine Tob Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>9 Suppl 4</volume><issue>Suppl 4</issue><fpage>S555</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18067032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/14622200701673480</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2933747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyland</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giovino</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predictors of cessation in a cohort of current and former smokers followed over 13 years</article-title><source>Nicotine Tob Res.</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><issue>Suppl 3</issue><fpage>S363</fpage><lpage>S369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14622200412331320761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15799599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hooper</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larry</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okuyemi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Culturally specific versus standard group cognitive behavioral therapy for smoking cessation among African Americans: an RCT protocol</article-title><source>BMC Psychol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>15</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2050-7283-1-15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25566367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4269979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bacio</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>IY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differences in quit attempts between non-Hispanic Black and White daily smokers: the role of smoking motives</article-title><source>Addict Behav.</source><year>2014</year><volume>39</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1769</fpage><lpage>1772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.addbeh.2014.07.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25123344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4320691</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Houston</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scarinci</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Person</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patient smoking cessation advice by health care providers: the role of ethnicity, socioeconomic status, and health</article-title><source>Am J Public Health.</source><year>2005</year><volume>95</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1056</fpage><lpage>1061</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2004.039909</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15914833</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1449308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGreevey</surname><given-names>JD</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mallozzi</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shelov</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reducing alert burden in electronic health records: state of the art recommendations from four health systems</article-title><source>Appl Clin Inform.</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0039-3402715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31893559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6938713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rigotti</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kruse</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Livingstone-Banks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann-Boyce</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of tobacco smoking: a review</article-title><source>JAMA.</source><year>2022</year><volume>327</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2022.0395</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35133411</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hooper</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tobacco cessation pharmacotherapy use among racial/ethnic minorities in the United States: considerations for primary care</article-title><source>Fam Med Community Health.</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15212/FMCH.2017.0138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cartmell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alberg</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Misperceptions of nicotine replacement therapy within racially and ethnically diverse smokers</article-title><source>J Natl Med Assoc.</source><year>2011</year><volume>103</volume><issue>9&#8211;10</issue><fpage>885</fpage><lpage>894</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22364057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0027-9684(15)30444-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3372924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amodei</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Over-the-counter nicotine replacement therapy: can its impact on smoking cessation be enhanced?</article-title><source>Psychol Addict Behav.</source><year>2008</year><volume>22</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>472</fpage><lpage>485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0893-164X.22.4.472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19071972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3577424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheadle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diehr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koepsell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The validity of self-reported smoking: a review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Am J Public Health.</source><year>1994</year><volume>84</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1086</fpage><lpage>1093</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.84.7.1086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8017530</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1614767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dowd</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maciejewski</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Odds ratios-current best practice and use</article-title><source>JAMA.</source><year>2018</year><volume>320</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2018.6971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29971384</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>