<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ Open Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ Open Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3334</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmjophth</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmjophth</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMJ Open Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2397-3269</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11877224</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11877224.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11877224</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11877224</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40032557</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjophth-2024-002012</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bmjophth-2024-002012</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1506</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cornea specialists are the highest opioid prescribers at a large academic eye institute in the USA</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2674-0835</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Boychev</surname><given-names initials="N">Nikolay</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1215-4571</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names initials="LY">Lisa Y.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4269-4413</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Tainsh</surname><given-names initials="LT">Laurel T.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5310-4055</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Aicher</surname><given-names initials="SA">Sue A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3026-6155</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Galor</surname><given-names initials="A">Anat</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6223-3091</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciolino</surname><given-names initials="JB">Joseph B.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Massachusetts Eye and Ear Department of Ophthalmology</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Boston</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Massachusetts</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">Chemical Physiology &amp; Biochemistry</institution>, <institution>Oregon Health &amp; Science University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Portland</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Oregon</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="department">Bascom Palmer Eye Institute</institution>, <institution>University of Miami Miller School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Miami</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Florida</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution content-type="department">Surgical Services</institution>, <institution>Miami Veterans Hospital</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Miami</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Florida</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">DrJoseph B.Ciolino; <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="joseph_ciolino@meei.harvard.edu">joseph_ciolino@meei.harvard.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn4"><p>One of the co-authors is an editor.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">480211</issue-id><elocation-id>e002012</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>05</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>03</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>04</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-03-06 14:25:29.127"><day>06</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2025. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See:&#160;<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bmjophth-10-1.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmjophth-10-1.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Aabstract</title></sec><sec><title>Background/aim</title><p>To evaluate the opioid prescription patterns across ophthalmic subspecialties at a large academic eye centre.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>A single site, retrospective cross-sectional study. Electronic medical records from the year 2018 were screened. Ophthalmology patients &#8805;18 years of age were included. The main outcome measures were patient demographics, outpatient opioid prescriptions, ophthalmic procedure and prescriber details, including department and training level.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>1654 opioid prescriptions were written, accounting for 2.2% of all ophthalmic procedures in a calendar year. Of the patients who received prescriptions, 51.4% were female (n=851) with a mean age of 52.3&#177;18.5 (range 18&#8211;95 years). In general, the morphine equivalent dose was low, with an average of 12.4&#177;6.75 pills dispensed (range 1&#8211;60) with 0.0&#177;0.01 refills (range 0&#8211;3). Cornea specialists were the highest opioid prescribers (22.7% of all providers who wrote a prescription), followed by oculoplastics (22.2%) and retina (18.4%). The most common procedure for which an opioid was prescribed was cornea crosslinking (14.3% of all opioid prescriptions).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>While opioid prescriptions are generally low for ophthalmic procedures across departments, cornea specialists accounted for nearly a third of opioid prescriptions. Over half of corneal crosslinking patients received opioid prescriptions; there remains an unmet need for opioid-sparing therapy for these patients and others with severe eye pain.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Cornea</kwd><kwd>Drugs</kwd><kwd>Public health</kwd><kwd>Medical Education</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>NIH/NINDS</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>1UG3 NS131518-01</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><sec><title>WHAT IS ALREADY KNOWN ON THIS TOPIC</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>The opioid epidemic, declared a public health crisis in 2017, has resulted in a significant number of overdose deaths, with a notable increase from 47 000 in 2018 to 81 000 000 in 2023. Previous research indicates that many heroin users were initially introduced to opioids through prescription drugs. While primary care and pain management specialists prescribe the majority of opioids, surgical specialties, including ophthalmology, also contribute to opioid prescriptions. Despite ophthalmologists prescribing fewer opioids than average, there has been a reported increase in opioid prescriptions following ocular surgeries.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title>WHAT THIS STUDY ADDS</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>This study reveals that the cornea department at a large academic eye centre is responsible for a third of all opioid prescriptions, with over 50% of corneal crosslinking patients receiving opioids postprocedure. The study highlights that most of these prescriptions had low morphine equivalent doses and limited refills. Additionally, it was found that trainees, particularly fellows, wrote a significant portion of these prescriptions, indicating a potential gap in opioid prescribing training among ophthalmology trainees.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title>HOW THIS STUDY MIGHT AFFECT RESEARCH, PRACTICE OR POLICY</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>The findings emphasise the need for standardised opioid prescribing guidelines in ophthalmology, particularly for corneal procedures, to mitigate opioid misuse. The study suggests that future guidelines should be distributed to both trainees and faculty to ensure comprehensive education on opioid management. Moreover, the results underscore the importance of developing opioid-sparing pain therapies and addressing geographic disparities in opioid prescribing patterns. This study could inform policy changes and training programmes to better equip ophthalmologists in managing postoperative pain while reducing the risk of long-term opioid dependence.</p></list-item></list></sec></boxed-text><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p> The opioid epidemic was declared a public health crisis in 2017,<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> and the current opioid epidemic has led to a staggering number of deaths per year from drug overdose, with nearly 47 000 deaths in 2018 alone,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> and almost doubling to a record 81 000 deaths in 2023.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> This is notable since approximately 645 000 deaths were reported from prescription or illicit opioid overdose in the 22 years between 1999 and 2021.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> While primary care providers and pain management specialties prescribe the most opioids overall, surgical specialties also contribute to opioid prescriptions in routine postoperative care.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> Prior investigations for opioid-na&#239;ve patients undergoing major and minor surgical procedures suggest that about 6% continue to fill opioid prescriptions more than 3 months later.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Opioid use following ophthalmic surgeries has been recently noted to predispose patients significantly more to opioid overdose, hospitalisations and mortality.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Thus, it is important to continue to understand and raise awareness of surgeons&#8217; opioid prescription patterns for postoperative pain control in the current opioid epidemic.</p><p>Opioid management training for prescribers varies across the USA. Several national surveys of trainees from different surgical specialties (eg, general surgery, plastic surgery, cardiac surgery and otolaryngology) found a high variability in the amount of training received for opioid prescribing during medical school and residency.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Moreover, a survey of general surgery training programmes found that roughly two-thirds of surgical residents reported feeling that they had received inadequate training in prescribing opioids.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> A quality improvement study of over 5000 ophthalmic surgeries showed a reduction of overprescribing opioids in opioid-na&#239;ve patients after implementation of a standardised opioid prescribing guideline at a single academic institution.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> These guidelines have been supported by the American Board of Ophthalmology and can be reviewed for maintenance of certification credit for all participating ophthalmologists.<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Similar guidelines have been demonstrated to be effective in other specialties as well.<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref></p><p>Postoperative opioid prescribing for pain management is of particular interest to cornea surgeons given the unique sensory characteristics of the cornea.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1 14 15</sup></xref> The cornea is the most densely innervated tissue in the human body, with approximately 7000 nociceptors per square millimetre, making it 300 to 600 times more sensitive than skin.<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> This dense sensory innervation originates from the ophthalmic division of the trigeminal ganglion, with extensive branching into the subbasal nerve plexus that supplies the corneal epithelium.<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> As a result, even minor corneal injuries can cause significant pain and frequently prompt emergency department visits.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> For corneal surgical procedures, such as photorefractive keratectomy (PRK), phototherapeutic keratectomy and corneal crosslinking, postoperative pain is common and often severe, correlating with nerve fibre exposure, epithelial damage and stromal tissue ablation.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14 15</sup></xref> Given the acute pain associated with these procedures and the relatively slow recovery of corneal nerves, opioids are frequently prescribed for short-term pain management.<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></p><p>With this growing insight into the role ophthalmologists may play in the current opioid epidemic, as well as the variability in opioid management education among trainees, we sought to evaluate the opioid prescription pattern across ophthalmic subspecialties at a large academic eye centre. We also examined the level of prescriber training to better understand who is prescribing opioids.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>We conducted a retrospective cohort study at a single academic ophthalmology centre. All opioid prescriptions written for patients 18 years or older in the year 2018 were included in our analysis. Prescriptions were identified through electronic medical records. For each prescription, the patient demographics, the associated primary procedure or diagnosis code and the prescriber information were collected. All opioid prescriptions were collected, regardless of association with a procedure. A prescription was considered a duplicate and excluded if it included identical prescription information and was written within 1&#8201;hour of each other. If an alternate prescription was written within 1&#8201;hour of the first prescription, then this first prescription was excluded, and the latter prescription data was collected.</p><p>The department of the prescriber was categorised into subspecialties including cornea, oculoplastics, retina, strabismus, glaucoma, comprehensive ophthalmology or uveitis. The training level of each prescriber was categorised as either an attending, fellow or resident.</p><p>Descriptive statistics were calculated with means&#177;SD for continuous variables, as well as frequencies and percentages for categorical variables. Statistical analysis was performed using SAS software (V.9.2, USA).</p><sec id="s2-1"><title>Research ethics approval</title><p>Massachusetts General Brigham&#8217;s Institutional Review Board (IRB) declared this study (2019P000259) exempt from review as all data were deidentified; thus, patient consent was waived. Hence, the IRB/Ethics Committee ruled that approval was not required for this study. All research adhered to the tenets of the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Patient and public involvement statement</title><p>Patients and the public were not involved in any way.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3-1"><title>Total unique opioid prescriptions and patient characteristics</title><p>Our study found that in 2018, a cumulative 75 412 ophthalmic procedures were performed at Massachusetts Eye and Ear (MEE) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>), large academic eye centre and 1654 (2.2%) unique opioid prescriptions were written (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>). The patients who received prescriptions were 51.4% (n=851) female, 65.56% (n=1084) White and with an average age of 52.3&#177;18.5 (range 18&#8211;95 years) (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Prescribed opioid-containing medications and corresponding dosages</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medication type</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morphine equivalent dose</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxycodone 5&#8201;mg tablet</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">553 (33.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydrocodone 5 mg acetaminophen 300&#8201;mg tablet</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">381 (23.0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxycodone-acetaminophen 5&#8211;325 mg tablet</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">368 (22.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetaminophen 300 mg&#8211;codeine 15&#8201;mg tablet</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">315 (19.0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxycodone 10&#8201;mg tablet</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (0.8)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tramadol 50&#8201;mg tablet</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (0.7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxycodone 30&#8201;mg tablet</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (0.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other<xref rid="T1_FN1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (0.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>TOTAL</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1654</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T1_FN1" fn-type="other"><label>*</label><p>Others include 1one prescription of each of the following: Bbutalbital 50mg&#8201;mg acetaminophen 325 mg-&#8211;caffeine 40 mg-&#8211;codeine 30mg&#8201;mg capsule; Ooxycodone 5mg&#8201;mg/5ml&#8201;mL oral solution; Ooxycodone 10mg&#8201;mg tablet Eextended Rrelease 12hr&#8201;hours; Ooxycodone 20mg&#8201;mg tablet Eextended Rrelease 12hr&#8201;hours; Ooxycodone-acetaminophen 10mg-325mg&#8201;mg&#8211;325 mg tablet, Ooxycodone-aspirin 4.8355mg-325mg&#8201;mg&#8211;325 mg tablet; Ttramadol 37.5 mg-&#8211;acetaminophen 325mg&#8201;mg tablet.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Demographics of patients who received an opioid prescription in 2018 at a single academic ophthalmology institution</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Demographics of patients who received any opioid prescription</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Years&#177;SD</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Mean</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.3&#177;18.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Range</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8211;95 years</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>N (%)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">851 (51.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">803 (48.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>N (%)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;White or Caucasian</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1084 (65.6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Other</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245 (14.8)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Black</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137 (8.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Unknown/Declined to say</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126 (7.6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Asian</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (3.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Native Hawaiian or Pacific Islander</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (0.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Hispanic or Latino</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.1)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Patients and ophthalmic procedures receiving an opioid prescription. The % of procedures receiving an opioid prescription was calculated as the number of patients receiving opioids/number of total procedures performed for each type of procedure. Orbitotomy/orbital fracture repair procedures included those with or without bone flap; eyelid procedures included blepharoplasty, lid ptosis repair, entropion/ectropion repair and canthoplasty; vitrectomy/retinal detachment repair procedures included those with or without scleral buckle.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjophth-10-1-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Opioid prescriptions and their morphine equivalent dose (MED)</title><p>Oxycodone 5&#8201;mg tablets were most prescribed (n=553, 33.4%), followed by hydrocodone 5mg-acetaminophen 300&#8201;mg tablets (n=381, 23.0%) and oxycodone 5 mg&#8211;acetaminophen 325&#8201;mg tablets (n=368, 22.2%) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>). In terms of morphine equivalent dose (MED), 7.5 MED was the most prescribed dosage (n=921, 55.7%). Most prescriptions were written for 10 pills (mean 12.4&#177;6.6 pills, median 10, mode 10). The range of pills dispensed was from 1 pill to 60 pills. Most had 0 refills (mean 0.0&#177;0.01 refills, median 0, mode 0), with a single prescription of 1 refill and a single prescription of 3 refills.</p></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>Patients and ophthalmic procedures receiving opioids</title><p>Of the 453 opioid prescriptions from the cornea department, the majority were for cornea crosslinking (237 prescriptions, 52.3% of all crosslinking procedures) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>). Other less common cornea procedures associated with an opioid prescription included PRK (96), superficial keratectomy (53), phototherapeutic keratectomy (36), penetrating keratoplasty (31), pterygium excisions (28), deep anterior lamellar keratoplasty (9), conjunctival biopsy (8), Descemet membrane endothelial keratoplasty (7), Descemet stripping endothelial keratoplasty or Descemet stripping automated endothelial keratoplasty (7), laser-assisted in situ keratomileusis (LASIK) or LASIK revisions (7), amniotic membrane grafting (6) and cryotherapy (3). Additional opioid prescriptions were given for cornea diagnoses but had no associated procedure, including Acanthamoeba keratitis (9), ocular graft-versus-host disease (oGVHD) (3), recurrent corneal erosion (3), corneal chemical injury (2) and zoster ophthalmicus (1).</p><p>Of the 367 opioid prescriptions from the oculoplastics department, the majority were for blepharoplasty (185 prescriptions, 17.8% of all blepharoplasty procedures) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>). Other opioid prescriptions associated with common oculoplastics procedures included enucleation or eviscerations (73, 50.7%), ptosis repair (43, 2.3%), entropion or ectropion repair (24, 4.3%), dacryocystorhinostomy (19, 3%), orbitotomy/orbital fracture repair/orbital decompression (18, 4.5%), brow ptosis repair (six prescriptions, 1%) or canalicular repair or punctoplasty (five prescriptions, 2.3%). Other less common procedures associated with an opioid prescription included post-Mohs reconstruction (22), eyelid or conjunctival biopsy (11), incision and drainage of abscess (2) and temporal artery biopsy (2). Other opioid prescriptions for oculoplastics diagnosis but without an associated procedure included orbital fractures without repair (3) and facial cellulitis (1).</p><p>Of the 305 opioid prescriptions from the retina department, the majority were for pars plana vitrectomy (136 prescriptions, 1.8% of pars plana vitrectomy procedures) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>). Other retina procedures that had associated opioid prescriptions included tantalum marker ring placement (89, 26.1%) and scleral buckle (60, 7.3%). Other less common procedures associated with an opioid prescription included intravitreal injections (6), panretinal photocoagulation (4) and transscleral biopsy (2). Other opioid prescriptions for retina diagnoses without an associated procedure included panuveitis or scleritis (4), vitreous haemorrhage secondary to trauma (2) and retinal necrosis (1).</p><p>There were 127 opioid prescriptions following strabismus surgery (11.2% of all strabismus surgeries) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>). 97 were following cyclophotocoagulation (9.6% of all cyclophotocoagulations). 37 opioid prescriptions were following open globe repairs (17% of all open globe repairs). 10 were following small incisional cataract surgery (0.1% of all cataract surgeries).</p></sec><sec id="s3-4"><title>Opioid prescription patterns of ophthalmology prescribers and departments</title><p>Analysis of the prescription by individual prescriber revealed 97 unique prescribers, over half of which were trainees (25.8% residents and 27.8% fellows) (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>). Analysis of the prescribers per individual prescription showed that 283 (17.1%) prescriptions written by residents versus 521 (31.5%) prescriptions were written by fellows (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Unique opioid prescribers and individual opioid prescription patterns per ophthalmic department</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="bottom" colspan="1"/><td colspan="4" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Number of unique opioid prescribers per department, N (% of total prescribers)</td><td colspan="4" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Number of individual opioid prescriptions written per department, N (% of total prescriptions)</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resident</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fellow</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attending</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Department</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resident</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fellow</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attending</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Department</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resident</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (25.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (25.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">283 (17.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">283 (17.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cornea</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (7.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (15.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (22.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144 (8.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">399 (24.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">543 (32.8)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oculoplastics</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (7.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (10.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (2.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">334 (20.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">367 (22.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retina</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (11.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (11.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (22.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">262 (15.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (2.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">305 (18.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strabismus</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (5.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (4.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (9.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (4.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (1.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88 (5.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glaucoma</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (4.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (5.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (0.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (2.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (3.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comprehensive</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (0.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (0.7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uveitis</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>TOTAL</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>25(25.8)</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>27(27.9)</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>45(46.4)</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>97</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>283(17.1)</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>521(31.5)</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>850(51.4)</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1654</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>When looking by department, the departments with the most unique prescribers were cornea (22; 22.7%) and retina (22; 22.7%) (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>). This analysis excluded residents who are not assigned to a specific department, but overall had the highest percentage of individual prescribers (25; 25.8%). We also examined the total number of individual opioid prescriptions, since some providers will write more than one and a few patients received more than one prescription. For the total number of prescriptions, most were written by the cornea (32.8%) department, followed by the oculoplastics (22.2%) and retina departments (18.5%) (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Ophthalmologists, like other providers, must balance adequate management of acute post-operative pain with long-term risks of opioid dependence to help reduce opioid misuse.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> This is especially true, since it was reported that about 10% of patients do not experience sufficient postoperative pain control.<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> Overall, ophthalmologists in the USA prescribe opioids less than some providers, accounting for an estimated 4&#8211;8% of the total ophthalmic prescriptions;<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> yet a recent study found a sustained increase in filled opioid prescriptions due to ocular surgeries between 2000 and 2016.<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> A large healthcare claims-based study found that 3.4% of opioid-na&#239;ve patients who received an initial opioid prescription at the time of incisional ophthalmic surgery had new, persistent opioid use after the perioperative period.<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> Therefore, ophthalmologists still play an important role in the opioid epidemic.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">114 16 20 23</xref><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></p><p>In our study, the opioid prescriptions had a low MED with an average of 7.5. The opioid prescriptions also had a limited number of pills dispensed (12.4&#177;6.75), and most were without refills (0.0&#177;0.01, range 0&#8211;3). While the overall prescriptions were low and had a low MED in our study, patients who were prescribed opioids within 7&#8201;days of ambulatory surgery were reported to be 44% more likely to become long-term users.<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> Also, a short course of prescribed opioids after ophthalmic surgery was recently reported to significantly increase the rates of patient chronic opioid overdose, hospitalisations and mortality.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Importantly, a large study on opioid-na&#239;ve patients undergoing ophthalmic surgery suggested that 3.4% of patients continued to use opioids, despite low morphine equivalents.<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> These reports are notable when considering strategies to mitigate opioid abuse, since ophthalmologists are known to typically prescribe 5-day opioid supplies.<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> Approaches for reducing opioid prescriptions, while still effectively managing postoperative pain due to ophthalmic surgeries, have ranged from oral or intravenous non-narcotic alternatives including pregabalin, acetaminophen and ibuprofen, ketorolac, memantine and local anaesthetics (eg, bupivacaine, lidocaine, diluted proparacaine) that prevent pain development<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> to novel therapies, such as a tetracaine-eluting contact lens that provides sustained and controlled pain relief.<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref></p><p>Corneal injury represented an estimated 337 000 annual emergency department visits in the USA between 2010 and 2018,<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> and cornea specialists are some of the most frequent opioid prescribers as their patients are often predisposed to significant pain.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1 14 15</sup></xref> The cornea has more nerve endings than any other part of the body, and current pain control methods for the ocular surface are limited.<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> Topical anaesthetics are well known to cause ocular morbidities,<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> particularly corneal toxicity,<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> so systemic opioids may be prescribed for severe pain. Indeed, we found that most opioid prescriptions at our institution came from the cornea department. Similarly, a cohort study of patients undergoing cornea surgery found that 70% to 90% of patients received an opioid prescription, likely due to the high proportion undergoing surface ablative procedures.<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> Another more recent study reported a range of 77.2 to 83.9% of cornea physicians prescribing opioids.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Furthermore, we found that 2.2% of all ophthalmic procedures were associated with an opioid prescription. A similar rate of opioid prescriptions was reported by a large study on US insurer&#8217;s claims database, which found that 1.9% of incisional ocular surgeries had an associated opioid prescription, but the rate increased to 6.1% for corneal surgeries alone.<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> The procedure with the highest associated opioid prescription was corneal crosslinking, where 52.3% of procedures received an associated opioid prescription. No previous study to our knowledge has reported on opioid prescription patterns associated with corneal crosslinking, despite it being well established that cornea specialists are frequent opioid prescribers.</p><p>Opioid prescriptions were also provided in the non-operative setting for ocular pain control. Within the cornea department, opioid prescriptions were provided for cornea diagnoses such as Acanthamoeba keratitis, oGVHD, recurrent corneal erosions, zoster ophthalmicus and corneal chemical injuries. Thus, ophthalmologists, and in particular cornea specialists who are prescribing opioids for pain management, should be aware of the potential need for additional pain control for their patients in the non-operative setting. This is of particular importance as there is strong evidence for only minimal short-term benefits to opioid prescribing, while research on the potential long-term benefits remains limited.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref></p><p>This study also highlights the role of trainees, particularly fellows, in prescribing opioids postoperatively at our institution. Of the 97 unique providers who wrote opioid prescriptions, about half were trainees (25.8% residents, 27.8% fellows, 46.4% attendings). Of the total 1655 unique opioid prescriptions written, 17.0% were written by residents, 31.5% by fellows and 60.1% by attendings. While several studies have highlighted a lack of opioid training among surgical residents,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> there are no surveys on opioid training among ophthalmology residents or fellows. It is possible that similar medical school curricula have left a gap in knowledge in this area. A small survey of general surgical residents found that the majority expressed a preference for more formal training or guidelines for opioid prescriptions for routine postoperative management.<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> There has been a recent call to standardise opioid prescriptions and create guidelines within ophthalmology,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> and our study suggests that future guidelines should be distributed to trainees as well as faculty to reach the most common prescribers. For instance, a study evaluating the effect of state-level policies on opioid prescribing patterns showed that the enactment of the Michigan Opioid Laws in 2017 and 2018 led to a reduced number of opioid prescriptions for oculoplastic procedures.<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> Similarly, another more recent study including almost 20 000 ophthalmologists across the USA reported a significant annual reduction in prescribed opioids from 2016 to 2018 for the cornea, retina, glaucoma and comprehensive ophthalmology subspecialties.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> However, these state-level policies are variable and may not uniformly impact trainees. This agrees with our findings, where although the cornea, oculoplastics and retina subspecialties consistently had the most opioid prescribers at our institute as across the USA, each one prescribed about three to four times less than the national average in 2018: cornea (77.2% vs 32.8%), oculoplastics (86% vs 22.2%) and retina (54.5% vs 18.5%).<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Our findings further suggest a geographic disparity in opioid prescribing patterns, which was previously reported as well.<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> Additionally, the fact that trainees may train for residency in one state and undergo fellowship in another may additionally pose a challenge for trainees.</p><p>The strengths of this study include that it was performed at a large academic eye institute, with a wide range of procedures performed and subspecialties surveyed. Moreover, we contributed data to the limited knowledge on opioid prescribing patterns regarding procedures and subspecialties previously not reported. This further included newly found differences in prescribing habits between trainee and non-trainee ophthalmologists. In terms of study limitations, the retrospective chart-based review prevents us from confirming whether the opioid prescriptions were actually filled or taken. However, this provides data on the ophthalmologists&#8217; perception of post-operative pain needs and is not necessarily representative of the patients&#8217; actual pain medication needs. Additionally, the results reflect the practice patterns of only a single institution and are extracted based on primary procedure codes. Therefore, the results may reflect individual or departmental practices rather than overall field trends and may not capture the full extent of the surgery if multiple procedures were performed. We also did not assess whether the patient was opioid-na&#239;ve, which may necessitate higher MED for equivalent pain control. Finally, another limitation is that an evaluation of the association between provider and patient characteristics to opioid prescribing was not performed.</p><p>The opioid epidemic in the USA has spurred significant changes in prescribing practices across medical specialties, including ophthalmology.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Regulatory frameworks, such as the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention opioid prescribing guidelines and Drug Enforcement Administration oversight, have tightened access to opioids, encouraging clinicians to seek non-opioid alternatives wherever possible.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> Globally, approaches to corneal pain management and opioid prescribing vary widely, influenced by healthcare infrastructure, cultural attitudes and regulatory policies.<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31 32</sup></xref> In high-resource settings such as Europe and Australia, opioid use is also limited, with greater emphasis on non-opioid therapies and multidisciplinary approaches.<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> In contrast, low-resource settings often face significant barriers to care, including limited access to advanced diagnostic tools and medications, resulting in a reliance on traditional remedies or over-the-counter analgesics.<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> Middle-income countries, such as India and Brazil, are navigating an intermediate landscape, with increasing access to advanced care but ongoing variability in provider training and opioid regulation.<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref></p><p>Furthermore, specialised pain clinics in many high-income countries serve as a structured and safer pathway for opioid access when necessary. These clinics, often led by anaesthesiologists with multidisciplinary teams, provide comprehensive pain management, integrating psychological support and non-opioid therapies alongside carefully monitored opioid prescriptions to minimise misuse risk.<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33 34</sup></xref> Given their success in balancing pain relief with opioid stewardship, expanding access to specialised pain clinics in the USA may offer a safer, more controlled alternative to widespread opioid prescribing. The American Society of Interventional Pain Physicians (ASIPP) has published guidelines emphasising the importance of comprehensive assessment and monitoring in specialised settings to ensure safe opioid use within a structured framework.<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> This model could ensure that patients requiring opioids receive them within a multidisciplinary framework that prioritises both efficacy and safety.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref></p><p>Research on practice-specific postoperative opioid prescribing for pain management in ophthalmology continues to be of importance. Addressing the opioid epidemic in the field of ophthalmology will require raised awareness and better understanding of the practice patterns of opioid prescriptions, both in the operative and non-operative setting. While opioid prescriptions are generally low for ophthalmic procedures across departments, this study highlights that cornea specialists accounted for nearly a third of opioid prescriptions. Further understanding of postprocedural corneal surface pain management, opioid tapering guidelines, geographic disparities and developing opioid-sparing pain therapies is needed.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This study was funded by NIH/NINDS (1UG3 NS131518-01) for JC, MD.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Data availability free text:</bold> The datasets used and analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient consent for publication:</bold> Not applicable.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer-reviewed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient and public involvement:</bold> Patients and/or the public were not involved in the design, conduct, reporting or dissemination plans of this research.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>ZT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elsharawi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Analysis of ophthalmology subspecialty opioid prescribing patterns during the opioid public health crisis</article-title><source>Can J Ophthalmol</source><year>2024</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>e16</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcjo.2022.11.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36463965</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darnall</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Incidence of and Risk Factors for Chronic Opioid Use Among Opioid-Naive Patients in the Postoperative Period</article-title><source>JAMA Intern Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>1286</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2016.3298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27400458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6684468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossen</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Provisional Drug Overdose Death Counts</source><publisher-name>National Center for Health Statistics</publisher-name><year>2021</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dowell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ragan</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>CDC Clinical Practice Guideline for Prescribing Opioids for Pain - United States, 2022</article-title><source>MMWR Recomm Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.rr7103a1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9639433</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36327391</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brummett</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waljee</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goesling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>New Persistent Opioid Use After Minor and Major Surgical Procedures in US Adults</article-title><source>JAMA Surg</source><year>2017</year><volume>152</volume><elocation-id>e170504</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2017.0504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28403427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7050825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thao</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helfinstine</surname><given-names>DA</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sangaralingham</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Hospitalization, Overdose, and Mortality After Opioid Prescriptions Tied to Ophthalmic Surgery</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2024</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>943</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ophtha.2024.01.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38280654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Biskup</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dzioba</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sowerby</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Opioid prescribing practices following elective surgery in Otolaryngology-Head &amp; Neck Surgery</article-title><source>J Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source><year>2019</year><volume>48</volume><elocation-id>29</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40463-019-0352-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31234932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6591868</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mira</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Postoperative surgical trainee opioid prescribing practices (POST-OPP): A national survey</article-title><source>J Opioid Manag</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5055/jom.2019.0516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31637683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huynh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colborn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christian</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Resident Opioid Prescribing Habits Do Not Reflect Best Practices in Post-Operative Pain Management: An Assessment of the Knowledge and Education Gap</article-title><source>J Surg Educ</source><year>2021</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>1286</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsurg.2020.12.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33386285</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prigoff</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Titan</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>The Effect of Surgical Trainee Education on Opioid Prescribing: An International Evaluation</article-title><source>J Surg Educ</source><year>2020</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>1490</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsurg.2020.04.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32446768</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Starr</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartley</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Impact of Standardized Prescribing Guidelines on Postoperative Opioid Prescriptions after Ophthalmic Surgery</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2020</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>1454</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ophtha.2020.04.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32654758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Starr</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schnabel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartley</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>American Board of Ophthalmology Certifying Examination Performance and Opioid Prescription Patterns</article-title><source>J Med Regul</source><year>2023</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.30770/2572-1852-109.3.12</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiels</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ubl</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yost</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Results of a Prospective, Multicenter Initiative Aimed at Developing Opioid-prescribing Guidelines After Surgery</article-title><source>Ann Surg</source><year>2018</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SLA.0000000000002919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30004924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomaszewski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valente</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Use of Topical Anesthetics in the Management of Patients With Simple Corneal Abrasions: Consensus Guidelines From the American College of Emergency Physicians</article-title><source>Ann Emerg Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annemergmed.2024.01.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38323950</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Corneal Innervation and Sensation: The Eye and Beyond</article-title><source>Yale J Biol Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29599653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5872636</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolomeyer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>VanderBeek</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of Opioids With Incisional Ocular Surgery</article-title><source>JAMA Ophthalmol</source><year>2019</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>1283</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaophthalmol.2019.3694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31536096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6753650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goyal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamrah</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding Neuropathic Corneal Pain--Gaps and Current Therapeutic Approaches</article-title><source>Semin Ophthalmol</source><year>2016</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/08820538.2015.1114853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26959131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5607443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tannen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Association of Limiting Opioid Prescriptions With Use of Opioids After Corneal Surgery</article-title><source>JAMA Ophthalmol</source><year>2020</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaophthalmol.2019.4432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31670751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6824224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gudmundsdottir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ubl</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yost</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Finding the Balance Between Reduced Opioid Prescribing and Patient-reported Pain Management Among General Surgery Patients</article-title><source>Ann Surg</source><year>2023</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SLA.0000000000005680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35993582</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sternberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Association Between Opioid Prescribing Patterns and Abuse in Ophthalmology</article-title><source>JAMA Ophthalmol</source><year>2017</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>1216</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaophthalmol.2017.4055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28983558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5710378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolomeyer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>VanderBeek</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Curtailing Opioid Overprescribing in Ophthalmology</article-title><source>JAMA Ophthalmol</source><year>2021</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaophthalmol.2020.5435</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33300979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ung</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yonekawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waljee</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Persistent Opioid Use after Ophthalmic Surgery in Opioid-Naive Patients and Associated Risk Factors</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2021</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>1266</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ophtha.2021.04.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33895223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8384648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlson</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Opioid Prescribing Patterns Among American Society of Ophthalmic Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery Members in the Medicare Part D Database</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Ophthalmic Plast Reconstr Surg</italic></source><year>2019</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>360</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/IOP.0000000000001266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30439721</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ung</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ung</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yonekawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Opioid Prescribing Patterns among Retina Specialists in the United States</article-title><source>Ophthalmol Retina</source><year>2021</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>696</fpage><lpage>701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.oret.2020.10.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33130002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudy</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Change in Postoperative Opioid Prescribing Patterns for Oculoplastic and Orbital Procedures Associated With State Opioid Legislation</article-title><source>JAMA Ophthalmol</source><year>2021</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaophthalmol.2020.5446</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33300973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7729578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Long-term analgesic use after low-risk surgery: a retrospective cohort study</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>425</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinternmed.2011.1827</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22412106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wladis</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of postoperative pain in ophthalmic plastic surgery: a major review</article-title><source>Orbit</source><year>2021</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01676830.2020.1793373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32669009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bengani</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janbatian</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Tetracaine-eluting contact lens for corneal pain</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><year>2024</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>2690</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Characterization of ophthalmic presentations to emergency departments in the United States: 2010&#8211;2018</article-title><source>Am J Emerg Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajem.2022.02.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35227958</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayakta</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sceats</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merrell</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>&#8220;It&#8217;s Like Learning by the Seat of Your Pants&#8221;: Surgeons Lack Formal Training in Opioid Prescribing</article-title><source>J Surg Educ</source><year>2021</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsurg.2020.07.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32917541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breslin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cultural and regulatory factors influencing opioid prescribing patterns: Lessons from Australia and Europe</article-title><source>Pain Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e704</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PR9.0000000000000704</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30801044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6370140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamba</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pain management in low-resource settings: Challenges and opportunities</article-title><source>Lancet Glob Health</source><year>2019</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e1170</fpage><lpage>1</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(19)30309-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eccleston</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Psychological interventions for chronic pain in adults: an evidence map</article-title><source>Lancet Psychiatry</source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>73</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kr&#269;evski &#352;kvar&#269;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morlion</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vowles</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>European clinical practice recommendations on opioids for chronic noncancer pain - Part 2: Special situations</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Pain</italic></source><year>2021</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>969</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ejp.1744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33655678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manchikanti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Responsible, Safe, and Effective Prescription of Opioids for Chronic Non-Cancer Pain: American Society of Interventional Pain Physicians (ASIPP) Guidelines</article-title><source>Pain Physician</source><year>2022</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>S1</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28226332</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>Data are available upon reasonable request. All data relevant to the study are included in the article or uploaded as supplementary information.</p></sec></back></article></pmc-articleset>