<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur J Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">733</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">eurpub</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eurpub</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The European Journal of Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1101-1262</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1464-360X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10066478</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10066478.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10066478</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10066478</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36622179</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurpub/ckac191</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ckac191</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Health Services Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00860</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SOC01210</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SOC02610</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Emergency department outcomes for patients experiencing homelessness in England: retrospective cross-sectional study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4694-378X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Moss</surname><given-names initials="C">Charlie</given-names></name><xref rid="ckac191-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><aff>
<institution>Health Organisation, Policy and Economics (HOPE), Centre for Primary Care and Health Services Research, The University of Manchester</institution>, Manchester, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anselmi</surname><given-names initials="L">Laura</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Health Organisation, Policy and Economics (HOPE), Centre for Primary Care and Health Services Research, The University of Manchester</institution>, Manchester, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names initials="M">Matt</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Health Organisation, Policy and Economics (HOPE), Centre for Primary Care and Health Services Research, The University of Manchester</institution>, Manchester, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="ckac191-cor1"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Charlie Moss, Health Organisation, Policy and Economics (HOPE), Centre for Primary Care and Health Services Research, Williamson Building, Oxford Road, The University of Manchester, M13 9PL Manchester, UK, e-mail: <email>charlie.moss@manchester.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-01-09"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>33</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">432512</issue-id><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>09</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>02</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-04-03 04:10:48.447"><day>03</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2023. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the European Public Health Association.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="ckac191.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ckac191.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="s1"><title>Background</title><p>Emergency departments (EDs) are an important point of access to health care for people experiencing homelessness. Evidence suggests that ED attendances by homeless people are more likely to result in leaving the ED without treatment, or dying in the ED. We investigate which diagnoses and patterns of health care use are associated with these (and other) discharge destinations and re-attendance within 7 days among homeless patients.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Methods</title><p>We used national hospital data to analyze attendances of all 109&#160;254 people experiencing homelessness who presented at any Type 1 ED in England over 2013&#8211;18. We used logistic regression to estimate the association of each outcome with primary diagnosis and patterns of healthcare use.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>Compared with patients with no past ED use, patients with a high frequency of past ED use were more likely to leave without treatment and re-attend within 7 days. Patients not registered at a general practice were likelier to leave without treatment or die in the ED and had lower odds of unplanned re-attendance. A primary diagnosis of &#8216;social problems&#8217; was associated with being discharged without follow-up. Patients with a psychiatric primary diagnosis were disproportionately likely to be referred to another health care professional/provider or an outpatient clinic.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Further research is needed to understand why some homeless patients leave the ED without treatment and whether their healthcare needs are being met. Some patients may be attending the ED frequently due to poor access to other services, such as primary care and social welfare.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>National Institute for Health and Care Research</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100000272</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Applied Research Collaboration Greater Manchester</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NIHR200174</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>NIHR Senior Investigator</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Department of Health and Social Care</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100000276</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>UKRI-MRC</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>MR/S022554/1</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The European Typology of Homelessness and Housing Exclusion (ETHOS) sets out a framework for describing different types of homelessness.<xref rid="ckac191-B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> They include rooflessness, houselessness, living in insecure housing and living in inadequate housing. A cross-national survey of eight European nations in 2019 found that 4.96% of respondents had experienced rooflessness at some point in their lifetime.<xref rid="ckac191-B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref></p><p>The legal definition of homelessness in England is that a household has no home in the UK or anywhere else in the world available and reasonable to occupy.<xref rid="ckac191-B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> This includes several different circumstances, such as sleeping rough, living in a hostel, living in insecure or inadequate housing and sofa surfing. Between April 2020 and March 21, 282&#8201;000 single people, couples and families were judged as homeless or threatened with homelessness by local authorities in England.<xref rid="ckac191-B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref></p><p>People experiencing homelessness (PEH) commonly suffer poor physical and/or mental health.<xref rid="ckac191-B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5&#8211;8</sup></xref> Comorbid physical, mental and substance abuse problems are common.<xref rid="ckac191-B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> Studies have tended to find a standardized mortality ratio of 2&#8211;5 times that of the age-standardized general population.<xref rid="ckac191-B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> Deaths of PEH are often from causes amenable to timely and effective health care.<xref rid="ckac191-B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref></p><p>Studies from several high-income countries suggest that, on average, PEH are frequent emergency department (ED) users.<xref rid="ckac191-B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ckac191-B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11&#8211;17</sup></xref> This could be due partly to problems in accessing primary health care.<xref rid="ckac191-B18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ckac191-B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> A study of PEH in England found that only 66% of rough sleepers, 83% of single homeless people in accommodation and 89% of hidden homeless people (e.g. sofa surfers) were registered with a general practice, compared with 98% of the English general population.<xref rid="ckac191-B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> The way in which EDs operate may be more acceptable to some PEH than the shorter opening hours and rigid appointment schedules at most primary healthcare providers. A substantial portion of this use of emergency health care is warranted by urgent medical need.<xref rid="ckac191-B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20&#8211;22</sup></xref></p><p>Much attention has been given to the frequency with which PEH attend the ED.<xref rid="ckac191-B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ckac191-B23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> There has been scant investigation of the outcomes of ED attendances by PEH, particularly outside the USA, even though this may be related to frequent ED attendance by some PEH. A recent study of 3271 ED attendances by PEH at one hospital in England found that 18.4% of patients left the ED before receiving treatment, and 1.2% of patients died in the ED.<xref rid="ckac191-B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> Both percentages are significantly higher than for the general population.<xref rid="ckac191-B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> A comparative study of ED attendances at a hospital in Dublin, Ireland, found that 40% of attendances by PEH resulted in leaving the ED before assessment, compared with 15% of attendances by housed persons.<xref rid="ckac191-B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref></p><p>We use national hospital data to investigate which diagnoses and patterns of healthcare use are associated with outcomes of the ED attendances of 109&#8201;254 homeless patients in England. We examine discharge destinations and unplanned ED re-attendance within 7 days.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>EDs in England</title><p>In England, health care provided by National Health Service (NHS) EDs is free at the point of use, including to overseas visitors.<xref rid="ckac191-B26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> It can be routinely accessed without an appointment.</p><p>There are four types of ED that patients can choose to attend.<xref rid="ckac191-B27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ckac191-B28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> Type 1 are major NHS consultant-led 24-h departments with full facilities for resuscitating patients. They comprise the majority of ED attendances in England. We analyze attendances at Type 1 EDs only.</p></sec><sec><title>Hospital records</title><p>Hospital Episode Statistics is an administrative dataset containing information on NHS hospital service use for all ED attendances, admissions and outpatient appointments.<xref rid="ckac191-B29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> Each patient has a unique anonymized identifier allowing individuals&#8217; records to be linked when they visit different hospital settings and over time. The ED data contain information on diagnoses and treatment, where patients are referred or admitted, discharge destination and some provider and patient characteristics.<xref rid="ckac191-B28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref></p></sec><sec><title>Sample definition</title><p>Within the hospital records there are fields derived from the patient&#8217;s postcode that assign patients to different administrative geographies. One such field is &#8216;local authority district of residence&#8217; where patients can be recorded as having &#8216;no fixed abode&#8217;. This is an indicator of homelessness.<xref rid="ckac191-B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ckac191-B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ckac191-B30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref></p><p>We included individuals recorded as having &#8216;no fixed abode&#8217; at an ED attendance between 1 April 2013 and 31 March 2018. We limited the sample to patients aged 16&#8211;75.<xref rid="ckac191-B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref></p><p>For patients with multiple attendances, we kept only their earliest attendance where they were recorded as having no fixed abode to avoid giving greater weight to patients who attended more frequently. We removed 278 records with the same date and arrival time, but conflicting information in other fields. We removed 20 patients who were dead on arrival at the ED. This resulted in a sample of 109&#8201;254 PEH (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary figure S1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Outcomes</title><sec><title>Discharge destination</title><p>We created binary indicators for each of the following seven possible mutually exclusive outcomes: (i) admitted to hospital; (ii) discharged with no follow-up; (iii) discharged with GP follow-up; (iv) referred to outpatient clinic; (v) referred to other health care professional or provider; (vi) left without treatment (including patients who either left the department before treatment or refused treatment); and (vii) died in the department.</p></sec><sec><title>Re-attendance within 7 days</title><p>Unplanned ED re-attendance within 7 days is an indicator of poor quality care.<xref rid="ckac191-B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> We created a binary indicator for whether there was an unplanned follow-up attendance within 7 days of the initial attendance.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Patient characteristics</title><p>We created indicators for 5-year age bands.</p><p>We dropped a small number of observations with missing data for sex (1083; 1% of sample).</p><p>We grouped ethnic categories into six groups: White British or Irish, any other White background, Mixed, Asian, Black, or other (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary table S1</xref> for original categories). We retained &#8216;White from any other background&#8217; as a separate group from White British or Irish to investigate differences. We retained observations for patients with missing ethnicity information, 24% of the sample, and categorized them as &#8216;missing&#8217;.</p></sec><sec><title>Diagnoses</title><p>Where present, diagnosis codes are a mixture of NHS Accident and Emergency (A&amp;E) diagnosis condition codes (71&#8201;774 attendances; 66% of total)<xref rid="ckac191-B31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> and ICD-10 codes (4243 attendances; 4% of total).<xref rid="ckac191-B32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> The first two characters of A&amp;E diagnosis codes correspond to 39 broad diagnosis groups reflecting the conditions at presentation, such as &#8216;head injury&#8217;, &#8216;cardiac conditions&#8217; and &#8216;respiratory conditions&#8217; (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary table S2</xref>). There were 70&#8201;708 attendances (65% of total attendances) that had a valid A&amp;E diagnosis code. For 1066 attendances (1% of total), the first two characters of the A&amp;E diagnosis code were ambiguous. In most cases, this is because they were not in the valid range of 01&#8211;39. Thirty percent of the sample (33 237 attendances) did not have a primary diagnosis recorded. We retained observations with an ambiguous or absent code and categorized them as missing. We also categorized the few ICD-10 diagnosis codes as missing, limiting analysis of diagnosis codes to NHS ED codes.</p><p>We mapped valid A&amp;E diagnosis codes into one of the following categories: traumatic injury; physical conditions/diseases; poisoning (incl. overdose); psychiatric conditions; social problems; diagnosis not classifiable; and nothing abnormal detected (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary table S2</xref>). We classified poisoning as a separate category because drug use is prevalent amongst PEH and poisoning is one of the most common primary diagnoses received by this population at the ED.<xref rid="ckac191-B21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref></p></sec><sec><title>General practice registration</title><p>We used general practice registration status as an indicator of access to primary care.</p><p>The ED data contain information on which general practice the patient is registered with. There are three codes which indicate that a patient does not have a registered general practice to record.<xref rid="ckac191-B33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> We used these codes to identify patients not registered at a general practice. We created an indicator equal to one if any of these codes were present (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary table S3</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Past healthcare utilization</title><p>We used the unique person identifiers to extract data on all hospital interactions across all settings (inpatient, outpatient and ED) for the 5 years prior to each patient&#8217;s attendance. From total counts of ED attendances, inpatient spells, and outpatient appointments during the 5 years prior to each patient&#8217;s ED attendance, we created 12 binary indicators: zero use; low use (between one and the 40th percentile); moderate use (between 40th and 80th percentile); or high use (above 80th percentile) of ED, inpatient and outpatient care. See <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary tables S4 and S5</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Analyses</title><p>We used logistic regression to estimate the association between each outcome and the set of independent variables of interest (diagnosis category; general practice registration status; and frequency of past ED attendances, inpatient spells and outpatient appointments). We additionally included the following binary indicators as control variables in all models: 5-year age bands; sex; ethnic group; and whether the attendance was a first attendance or a follow-up.</p><p>We used Huber&#8211;White robust standard errors.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Descriptive statistics</title><p>Twenty-two percent of the sample were female (<xref rid="ckac191-T1" ref-type="table">table&#160;1</xref>). The age distribution was skewed to the right; 72% of the sample were in the bottom half of the age range (aged 16&#8211;45).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="ckac191-T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Descriptive statistics: patient characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;16&#8211;20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;21&#8211;25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;26&#8211;30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;31&#8211;35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;36&#8211;40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;41&#8211;45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;46&#8211;50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;51&#8211;55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;56&#8211;60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;61&#8211;65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;66&#8211;70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;71&#8211;75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;White British or Irish</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Any other white background</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Mixed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Asian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Black</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Missing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109&#160;254</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Data source</italic>: Hospital Episode Statistics Accident and Emergency (A&amp;E), Type 1 A&amp;E attendances by patients with no fixed abode aged 16&#8211;75 between 1 April 2013 and 31 March 2018.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Forty-five percent of the sample were White British or Irish. &#8216;Any other White background&#8217; was the second largest non-missing group (13.5%).</p><p>Diagnosis of physical trauma (14.1%) was the most frequent category after missing (35.3%; <xref rid="ckac191-T2" ref-type="table">table&#160;2</xref>); 14.7% of valid primary diagnoses were for poisoning, and 9.2% were for psychiatric conditions (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary table S2</xref>). Where a diagnosis was recorded, the vast majority were clinical codes; only 3.3% of valid primary diagnoses were for &#8216;social problems&#8217;, which includes homelessness.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="ckac191-T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Descriptive statistics: key independent variables</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnoses</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Nothing abnormal detected</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Physical trauma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Physical condition/disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Poisoning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Psychiatric conditions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Social problems</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Not classifiable</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Missing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">General practice registration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Not registered</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency of past ED attendances<xref rid="tblfn3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Low (1&#8211;4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Moderate (5&#8211;15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;High (&gt;15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency of past inpatient spells<xref rid="tblfn3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Low (1&#8211;2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Moderate (3&#8211;7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;High (&gt;7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency of past outpatient appointments<xref rid="tblfn3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Low (1&#8211;5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Moderate (6&#8211;20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;High (&gt;20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109&#160;254</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn2"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Data source</italic>: Hospital Episode Statistics Accident and Emergency (A&amp;E), Type 1 A&amp;E attendances by patients with no fixed abode aged 16&#8211;75 between 1 April 2013 and 31 March 2018.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn3"><label>a</label><p>&#8216;Past&#8217; refers to hospital care contact during the 5 years prior to the patient&#8217;s attendance.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="ckac191-T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Descriptive statistics: outcomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discharge destination</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Admitted</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.38</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Discharged with no follow-up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Discharged with GP follow-up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.99</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Referred to outpatient clinic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Referred to other professional or provider</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Left without treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.59</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Died in the department</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Re-attendance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Unplanned within 7&#8201;days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109&#160;254</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn4"><p>SD, standard deviation; GP, general practitioner.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn5"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Data source</italic>: Hospital Episode Statistics Accident and Emergency attendances by patients with no fixed abode aged 16&#8211;75 between 1 April 2013 and 31 March 2018.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn6"><p>Statistics are based on the estimation samples used for each outcome. Further details on how the estimation samples are derived are provided as <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref>. Discharge destination outcomes are calculated from attendances at Type 1 Accident and EDs only.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="ckac191-T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Regression results: discharge destinations and re-attendance within 7 days</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Admitted</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discharged with no follow-up</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discharged with GP follow-up</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Referred to outpatient clinic</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Referred to other professional or provider</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left without treatment</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Died in the department</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unplanned re-attendance within 7 days</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(8)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnoses</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Nothing abnormal detected</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Traumatic injury</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.45<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.56; 2.02]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.00; 1.16]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.43; 1.78]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[3.44; 8.63]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.90; 1.71]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.09; 0.12]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.71; 1.37]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Physical conditions/diseases</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.33<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.83<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[3.82; 4.90]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.56; 0.66]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.75; 2.17]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[4.31; 10.81]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.81; 1.54]</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">[0.10; 0.13]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.68; 1.32]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Poisoning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.45<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64<xref rid="tblfn14" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68<xref rid="tblfn14" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[3.92; 5.06]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.93; 1.09]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.87; 1.10]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.59; 1.67]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.44; 0.91]</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">[0.21; 0.26]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.48; 0.98]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Psychiatric conditions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.40<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[2.43; 3.17]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.54; 0.64]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.20; 1.52]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[2.31; 6.03]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[6.19; 11.40]</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">[0.18; 0.24]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.98; 1.93]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Social problems</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.79<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.96<xref rid="tblfn14" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[2.39; 3.26]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.18; 1.46]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.96; 1.31]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.08; 3.58]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.34; 1.01]</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">[0.19; 0.27]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.75; 1.84]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Diagnosis not classifiable</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.62<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19<xref rid="tblfn15" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.02<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50<xref rid="tblfn14" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[2.31; 2.96]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.53; 0.61]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.07; 1.32]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.90; 4.80]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.62; 2.98]</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">[0.84; 1.00]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.09; 2.05]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Missing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.07<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17<xref rid="tblfn15" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.40<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.91<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39<xref rid="tblfn14" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[2.72; 3.47]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.46; 0.53]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.05; 1.30]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[2.79; 6.93]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[2.16; 3.93]</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">[0.75; 0.89]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.02; 1.89]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">General practice registration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Not registered</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68<xref rid="tblfn14" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.92; 1.00]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.07; 1.15]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.81; 0.89]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.69; 0.87]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.89; 1.09]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.12; 1.24]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.09; 2.57]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.31; 0.53]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency of past ED attendances<xref rid="tblfn13" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.03<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.10; 1.24]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.93; 1.03]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.94; 1.07]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.85; 1.16]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.78; 1.03]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.81; 0.93]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.64; 2.02]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[4.45; 8.16]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Moderate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.97<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.91; 1.05]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.95; 1.08]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.91; 1.06]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.78; 1.13]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.74; 1.03]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.07; 1.27]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.20; 1.09]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[5.05; 9.60]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;High</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21<xref rid="tblfn15" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.79<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.65; 0.78]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.07; 1.27]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.99; 1.22]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.48; 0.81]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.49; 0.78]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.45; 1.82]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.07; 0.65]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[7.68; 15.16]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency of past inpatient spells<xref rid="tblfn13" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93<xref rid="tblfn14" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.18; 1.32]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.85; 0.94]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.87; 0.99]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.84; 1.11]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.99; 1.30]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.92; 1.07]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.72; 2.53]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.90; 1.21]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Moderate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.36<xref rid="tblfn14" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.66; 1.90]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.73; 0.83]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.74; 0.86]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.71; 1.01]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.99; 1.39]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.84; 1.00]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.08; 5.14]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.91; 1.27]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;High</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.51<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30<xref rid="tblfn14" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[2.29; 2.75]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.61; 0.73]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.58; 0.73]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.81; 1.35]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.03; 1.65]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.72; 0.92]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.86; 6.38]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.88; 1.34]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency of past outpatient appointments<xref rid="tblfn13" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09<xref rid="tblfn15" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19<xref rid="tblfn14" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.03; 1.16]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.93; 1.03]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.93; 1.06]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.02; 1.38]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.85; 1.13]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.80; 0.92]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.33; 1.21]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.86; 1.20]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Moderate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08<xref rid="tblfn14" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94<xref rid="tblfn14" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30<xref rid="tblfn15" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.02; 1.15]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.89; 1.00]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.93; 1.07]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.11; 1.53]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.94; 1.27]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.75; 0.88]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.35; 1.44]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.88; 1.24]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;High</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12<xref rid="tblfn15" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29<xref rid="tblfn14" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21<xref rid="tblfn14" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77<xref rid="tblfn16" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.03; 1.21]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.89; 1.03]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.87; 1.04]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.05; 1.58]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[1.00; 1.45]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.69; 0.85]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.69; 2.98]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.76; 1.15]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109&#160;254</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109&#160;254</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109&#160;254</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109&#160;254</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109&#160;254</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109&#160;254</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105&#160;855</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109&#160;027</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn7"><p>95% confidence intervals in brackets.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn8"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Data source</italic>: Hospital Episode Statistics Accident and Emergency, Type 1 A&amp;E attendances by patients with no fixed abode aged 16&#8211;75 between 1 April 2013 and 31 March 2018.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn9"><p>Estimated using logistic regression. Coefficients show odds ratios.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn10"><p>Models additionally include binary indicators for sex, 5-year age band, ethnicity and whether the attendance is categorized as a first attendance, planned follow-up, unplanned follow-up or unknown.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn11"><p>Due to small number of patients who died in the department, diagnosis indicators were not included in Model 7 due to perfect prediction. Also includes first attendances only due to perfect prediction.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn12"><p>Model 8 does not include attendances with attendance type or department type &#8216;unknown&#8217; due to perfect prediction.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn13"><label>a</label><p>Past refers to hospital care contact in the 5 years prior to the attendance.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn14"><label>*</label><p>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05,</p></fn><fn id="tblfn15"><label>**</label><p>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01,</p></fn><fn id="tblfn16"><label>***</label><p>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>For 49% of patients, their general practice code indicated that they were not registered with a general practice (<xref rid="ckac191-T2" ref-type="table">table&#160;2</xref>).</p><p>Twenty-two percent of attendances concluded with admission to hospital, 33% with discharge without follow-up and 15% with the patient leaving without treatment (<xref rid="ckac191-T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>); 0.2% of patients died in the ED.</p><p>Fifty-six percent of patients arrived by ambulance (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary table S6</xref>). Around half of patients were self-referred; 19% were referred by emergency services; and 7% were referred by the police.</p></sec><sec><title>Regression results</title><p>Compared with the reference category of nothing abnormal detected, all other diagnosis categories had lower odds of leaving without treatment (<xref rid="ckac191-T4" ref-type="table">table 4</xref>). The diagnoses with the largest odds ratios were &#8216;diagnosis not classifiable&#8217; (OR&#8201;=&#8201;0.92; 95% CI [0.84&#8211;1.00]) and missing primary diagnosis (OR&#8201;=&#8201;0.82; 95% CI [0.75&#8211;0.89]). Patients with a primary diagnosis of social problems were much less likely to leave without treatment (OR&#8201;=&#8201;0.23; 95% CI [0.19&#8211;0.27]).</p><p>Compared with the reference diagnosis of nothing abnormal detected, patients with poisoning (OR&#8201;=&#8201;4.45; 95% CI [3.92&#8211;5.06]) or a physical condition/disease (OR&#8201;=&#8201;4.33; 95% CI [3.82&#8211;4.90]) were most likely to be admitted to hospital. Social problems was the only diagnosis where the patient was more likely to be discharged with no follow-up, compared with a diagnosis of nothing abnormal detected (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.31; 95% CI [1.18&#8211;1.46]). Being diagnosed with a psychiatric condition was associated with a greater probability of being referred to another professional/provider (OR&#8201;=&#8201;8.40; 95% CI [6.19&#8211;11.40]).</p><p>Patients with a primary diagnosis that was not classifiable (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.50; 95% CI [1.09&#8211;2.05]) or missing primary diagnosis (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.39; 95% CI [1.02&#8211;1.89]) were more likely to have an unplanned re-attendance within 7 days.</p><p>Patients who were not registered with a general practice were more likely to be discharged with no follow-up (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.11; 95% CI [1.07&#8211;1.15]), leave without treatment (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.18; 95% CI [1.12&#8211;1.24]), or die in the ED (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.68; 95% CI [1.09&#8211;2.57]) compared with patients with a registered general practice recorded. They were less likely to be discharged with GP follow-up (OR&#8201;=&#8201;0.85; 95% CI [0.81&#8211;0.89]), be referred to an outpatient clinic (OR&#8201;=&#8201;0.78; 95% CI [0.69&#8211;0.87]), or have a re-attendance within 7 days (OR&#8201;=&#8201;0.41; 95% CI [0.31&#8211;0.53]).</p><p>Patients with high frequency of past ED attendances were more likely to be discharged with no follow-up (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.16; 95% CI [1.07&#8211;1.27]), leave without treatment (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.62; 95% CI [1.45&#8211;1.82]), or have a re-attendance within 7 days (OR&#8201;=&#8201;10.79; 95% CI [7.68&#8211;15.16]), compared with patients without prior ED use. They were also less likely to be admitted to hospital (OR&#8201;=&#8201;0.72; 95% CI [0.65&#8211;0.78]) or referred to another provider (OR&#8201;=&#8201;0.62; 95% CI [0.49&#8211;0.78]) or outpatient clinic (OR&#8201;=&#8201;0.62; 95% CI [0.48&#8211;0.81]).</p><p>Patients with high frequency of past admission spells were more likely to be admitted to hospital (OR&#8201;=&#8201;2.51; 95% CI [2.29&#8211;2.75]) and less likely to leave without treatment (OR&#8201;=&#8201;0.81; 95% CI [0.72&#8211;0.92]) than patients with no past admission spells. They were also less likely to be discharged with no follow-up (OR&#8201;=&#8201;0.67; 95% CI [0.61&#8211;0.73]) or with GP follow-up (OR&#8201;=&#8201;0.65; 95% CI [0.58&#8211;0.73]).</p><p>Similarly, patients with high frequency of past outpatient appointments were more likely to be admitted to hospital (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.12; 95% CI [1.03&#8211;1.21]) and less likely to leave without treatment (OR&#8201;=&#8201;0.77; 95% CI [0.69&#8211;0.85]), compared with patients with no past outpatient appointments.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>We aimed to investigate which diagnoses and patterns of health care use are associated with different ED discharge destinations and probability of re-attendance within 7 days in a sample of 109&#8201;254 homeless patients. We found that the outcomes were associated with certain diagnoses and patterns of healthcare use.</p><p>Frequent past use of the ED and not being registered with a general practice were factors associated with leaving the ED without treatment. This may be indicative that some patients who were recorded as leaving without treatment use the ED regularly as a way of accessing routine healthcare not otherwise accessible. It is unclear whether these patients received all necessary treatment, or whether their healthcare needs were met during their ED attendance.</p><p>The diagnosis that was most strongly associated with leaving without treatment was &#8216;nothing abnormal detected&#8217;. For these patients (3% of our sample), being recorded as leaving the ED without treatment may not be a concern as they may not have needed further treatment. However, patients with a primary diagnosis recorded as &#8216;not classifiable&#8217; (17% of our sample), or with no diagnosis recorded (35%), were also relatively likely to leave without treatment. These patients may have left the ED without receiving potentially beneficial additional investigation or treatment.</p><p>Forty-nine percent of the study sample was recorded as not being registered with a general practice. We found that these patients had slightly greater odds of dying in the ED compared with patients recorded with a registered practice. This could be driven by poor access to routine healthcare or another factor correlated with general practice registration. For example, the homeless people in the poorest health may be the least likely to be registered with a general practice.<xref rid="ckac191-B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref></p><p>Patients who received a psychiatric primary diagnosis (6% of our study sample) were more likely to be referred to another health care professional/provider than patients who received other diagnoses. This suggests that the ED is an important point of contact for PEH suffering from psychiatric conditions, enabling access to more specialized services. Some patients are likely to be suffering from acute psychiatric problems, in which case attending the ED is an appropriate way of gaining access to a specialized psychiatric service in an emergency. However, some PEH may use the ED as a point of contact for less urgent mental health issues. They may benefit from increased continuity of care through access to mental healthcare via other means, such as GP referral. Evidence suggests that often EDs are not well-equipped to deal with patients with long-term mental health problems.<xref rid="ckac191-B34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref></p><p>Patients who received a diagnosis of &#8216;social problems&#8217; were highly likely to be discharged without follow-up. For these patients, the ED may be fulfilling a need that could be met more effectively and efficiently by other welfare services.</p><p>Descriptive features of the Type 1 ED attendances in this study are different to patients in the general population. Compared with a large sample of ED attendances in 2016/17,<xref rid="ckac191-B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> a greater percentage of patients in our study left before treatment (15% vs. 4%), and arrived by ambulance (56% vs. 30%). A lower percentage of attendances in this study resulted in admission to hospital (22% vs. 28%). A similar number of referrals were from emergency services (16% vs. 17% in our study), whereas a greater percentage of patients in our study were referred by the police (6% vs. 0.5%).</p><p>Compared to a study of 3271 attendances by PEH at a Type 1 ED in England,<xref rid="ckac191-B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> we found that a similar percentage of patients left without treatment (18% vs. 15% in our study). However, we found that a much lower percentage of patients died in the ED (1.2% vs. 0.2% in our study). The population served by that particular Type 1 ED may be in particularly poor health compared with the national average for PEH.</p><sec><title>Strengths and limitations</title><p>There are several strengths of this study. We used national hospital data for a long time period. This made it possible to have a large sample size with representation of patients from different groups, such as ethnic minorities and older patients who may not be well represented in smaller studies. The individual identifier also enabled us to access information relating to previous health care use during the 5 years before their ED attendance. The ED data we have used is administratively recorded so largely complete and consistent, and we do not rely on self-reported information regarding healthcare use.</p><p>There is no study of the validity of the no fixed abode flag used for this study. However, characteristics of the patients identified as PEH using this indicator and included in this study (mean age 38; 78% male; 13.5% of patients from ethnic group &#8216;White from any background other than British or Irish&#8217;, which is a large departure from the general population<xref rid="ckac191-B35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref>) are similar to those reported in other studies of PEH in England.<xref rid="ckac191-B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ckac191-B36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ckac191-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref></p><p>There are likely to be many ED attendances by PEH who provided a past address, or the address of a family member or a friend.<xref rid="ckac191-B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> We were unable to capture these attendances as they are indistinguishable from attendances by people who are genuinely housed. Homeless patients who are recorded with &#8216;no fixed abode&#8217; may be more isolated than those who have an address to give. Patients also may be less likely to have residence coded as &#8216;no fixed abode&#8217; if an address is seen to be relevant to their care, e.g. if they are admitted to hospital. These factors may affect generalizability if the no fixed abode flag systematically misses some homeless patients.</p><p>We were only able to analyze one diagnosis code related to substance misuse (&#8216;poisoning&#8217;, which includes overdose). Given the high prevalence of substance use disorder in this population,<xref rid="ckac191-B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ckac191-B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> we would have liked to include a diagnosis category for other (non-overdose) attendances relating to substance misuse. However, we were unable to identify these attendances from the diagnosis coding system used in the EDs included in this study.</p></sec><sec><title>Implications for policy and research</title><p>Some PEH may use the ED as a point of access for routine health care and welfare support. This may be indicative of issues in accessing primary care and welfare services through other routes. This warrants further investigation.</p><p>Further research with PEH and health care providers is needed to investigate some of the findings in this study, e.g. the reasons why some patients are especially likely to leave without treatment. Further research is needed to understand care pathways for PEH and how they may be improved.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>ckac191_Supplementary_Data</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ckac191_supplementary_data.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec><title>Supplementary data</title><p>
<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary data</xref> are available at <italic toggle="yes">EURPUB</italic> online.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>This research was supported by the National Institute for Health and Care Research (NIHR) Applied Research Collaboration Greater Manchester [NIHR200174]. M.S. is an NIHR Senior Investigator. The views expressed in this publication are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the NIHR or the Department of Health and Social Care. L.A. was funded by UKRI-MRC grant [MR/S022554/1].</p></sec><sec><title>Disclaimer</title><p>The funders were not involved in the design of the study, analyses, interpretation of the data, or the decision to submit results for publication.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Conflicts of interest</italic>: None declared.</p><p>
<boxed-text id="ckac191-BOX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Key points</label><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>We analyzed the emergency department attendances of a large sample of people experiencing homelessness in England.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Forty-nine percent of patients in the sample were recorded as not registered with a general practice.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A high percentage of homeless patients leaving the ED without treatment may exacerbate unmet healthcare need in this population.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Designing appropriate routes to access care and welfare services for people experiencing homelessness should be a priority.</p></list-item></list></boxed-text>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The Hospital Episode Statistics data that support the findings of this study are available from NHS Digital. Restrictions apply to the availability of these data. They were used under licence for this study, and so are not publicly available.</p></sec><ref-list id="ref1"><title>References</title><ref id="ckac191-B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ETHOS Typology on Homelessness and Housing Exclusion. Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.feantsa.org/en/toolkit/2005/04/01/ethos-typology-on-homelessness-and-housing-exclusion" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.feantsa.org/en/toolkit/2005/04/01/ethos-typology-on-homelessness-and-housing-exclusion</ext-link> (23 May 2022, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Loubiere</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tinland</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>; <collab>Members of the HOME_EU (Horizon 2020 GA/726997) Consortium Study Group</collab>. <article-title>Lifetime, 5-year and past-year prevalence of homelessness in Europe: a cross-national survey in eight European nations</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e033237</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2019-033237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6924844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31791966</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Public Health England</collab>. Homelessness: Applying All Our Health. <year>2019</year>. Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/homelessness-applying-all-our-health/homelessness-applying-all-our-health#:~:text=The%20legal%20definition%20of%20homelessness,London%20and%20the%20South%20East" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/homelessness-applying-all-our-health/homelessness-applying-all-our-health#:~:text=The%20legal%20definition%20of%20homelessness,London%20and%20the%20South%20East</ext-link> (9 May 2022, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Crisis</collab>. The Homelessness Monitor: England 2022. Crisis. Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.crisis.org.uk/ending-homelessness/homelessness-knowledge-hub/homelessness-monitor/england/the-homelessness-monitor-england-2022" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.crisis.org.uk/ending-homelessness/homelessness-knowledge-hub/homelessness-monitor/england/the-homelessness-monitor-england-2022</ext-link> (28 April 2022, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lewer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aldridge</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Health-related quality of life and prevalence of six chronic diseases in homeless and housed people: a cross-sectional study in London and Birmingham, England</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e025192</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2018-025192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6501971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31023754</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aldridge</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Story</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Morbidity and mortality in homeless individuals, prisoners, sex workers, and individuals with substance use disorders in high-income countries: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>391</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29137869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(17)31869-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5803132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Office of the Chief Analyst</collab>. Healthcare for Single Homeless People. <year>2010</year>. Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.housinglin.org.uk/_assets/Resources/Housing/Support_materials/Other_reports_and_guidance/Healthcare_for_single_homeless_people.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.housinglin.org.uk/_assets/Resources/Housing/Support_materials/Other_reports_and_guidance/Healthcare_for_single_homeless_people.pdf</ext-link> (29 December 2022, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fazel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Geddes</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kushel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The health of homeless people in high-income countries: descriptive epidemiology, health consequences, and clinical and policy recommendations</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>384</volume>:<fpage>1529</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25390578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(14)61132-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4520328</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Pathway</collab>. Homeless and Inclusion Health Standards for Commissioners and Service Providers. <year>2018</year>. Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.pathway.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/Version-3.1-Standards-2018-Final.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.pathway.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/Version-3.1-Standards-2018-Final.pdf</ext-link> (29 December 2022, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aldridge</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lewer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Causes of death among homeless people: a population-based cross-sectional study of linked hospitalisation and mortality data in England</article-title>. <source>Wellcome Open Res</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30984881</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.12688/wellcomeopenres.15151.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6449792</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marwick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Multimorbidity and emergency department visits by a homeless population: a database study in specialist general practice</article-title>. <source>Br J Gen Pract</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>e515</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>25</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31262848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3399/bjgp19X704609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6607834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moulin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Melnikow</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Substance use, homelessness, mental illness and medicaid coverage: a set-up for high emergency department utilization</article-title>. <source>West J Emerg Med</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>902</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30429919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5811/westjem.2018.9.38954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6225935</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jamani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Hard-to-reach populations and administrative health data: a serial cross-sectional study and application of data to improve interventions for people experiencing homelessness</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>S139</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33710086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MLR.0000000000001481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cheallaigh</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cullivan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Usage of unscheduled hospital care by homeless individuals in Dublin, Ireland: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e016420</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2017-016420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5719262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29196477</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Katic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>High utilizers of emergency health services in a population-based cohort of homeless adults</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>S302</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24148033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2105/AJPH.2013.301397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3969147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lewer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cornes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Hospital readmission among people experiencing homelessness in England: a cohort study of 2772 matched homeless and housed inpatients</article-title>. <source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>681</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33402395</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/jech-2020-215204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8223662</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Newnham</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Homeless status documentation at a metropolitan hospital emergency department</article-title>. <source>Emerg Med Australas</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>639</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30920164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/1742-6723.13256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gunner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chandan</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marwick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Provision and accessibility of primary healthcare services for people who are homeless: a qualitative study of patient perspectives in the UK</article-title>. <source>Br J Gen Pract</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>e526</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31307999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3399/bjgp19X704633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6650120</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rae</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The perceptions of homeless people regarding their healthcare needs and experiences of receiving health care</article-title>. <source>J Adv Nurs</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>2096</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>107</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25916241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jan.12675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Elwell-Sutton</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fok</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Albanese</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Factors associated with access to care and healthcare utilization in the homeless population of England</article-title>. <source>J Public Health (Oxf)</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>26</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26896508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/pubmed/fdw008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cheraghi-Sohi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Comparative 4-year risk and type of hospital admission among homeless and housed emergency department attendees: longitudinal study of hospital records in England 2013&#8211;2018</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e049811</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2021-049811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8314693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34312208</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reilly</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hassanally</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Budd</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Accident and emergency department attendance rates of people experiencing homelessness by GP registration: a retrospective analysis</article-title>. <source>BJGP Open</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>bjgpopen20X101089</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3399/bjgpopen20X101089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7880188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33144361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pourat</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Essien</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Differential associations of homelessness with emergency department visits and hospitalizations by race, ethnicity, and gender</article-title>. <source>Health Serv Res</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>249</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35593107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/1475-6773.14009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9660436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Paudyal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ghani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shafi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Clinical characteristics, attendance outcomes and deaths of homeless persons in the emergency department: implications for primary health care and community prevention programmes</article-title>. <source>Public Health</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>196</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34182257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.puhe.2021.05.007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Anselmi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>Y-S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The effects of unexpected changes in demand on the performance of emergency departments</article-title>. <source>Health Econ</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>1744</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32978879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hec.4167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>NHS</collab>. About NHS Hospital Services. <year>2019</year>. Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.nhs.uk/nhs-services/hospitals/about-nhs-hospital-services/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nhs.uk/nhs-services/hospitals/about-nhs-hospital-services/</ext-link> (24 May 2022, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>The King&#8217;s Fund</collab>. What&#8217;s Going on with A&amp;E Waiting Times? <year>2020</year>. Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.kingsfund.org.uk/projects/urgent-emergency-care/urgent-and-emergency-care-mythbusters" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.kingsfund.org.uk/projects/urgent-emergency-care/urgent-and-emergency-care-mythbusters</ext-link> (12 May 2022, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>NHS Digital</collab>. HES Data Dictionary: Accident and Emergency. <year>2020</year>: <fpage>47</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>NHS Digital</collab>. Hospital Episode Statistics (HES). <year>2021</year>. Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://digital.nhs.uk/data-and-information/data-tools-and-services/data-services/hospital-episode-statistics" ext-link-type="uri">https://digital.nhs.uk/data-and-information/data-tools-and-services/data-services/hospital-episode-statistics</ext-link> (1 June 2021, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Hospital care and costs for homeless people</article-title>. <source>Clin Med (Lond)</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>506</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27927812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7861/clinmedicine.16-6-506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6297335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>NHS</collab>. Accident and Emergency Diagnosis Tables. Data Dictionary. <year>2020</year>. Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.datadictionary.nhs.uk/web_site_content/supporting_information/clinical_coding/accident_and_emergency_diagnosis_tables.asp?shownav=1" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.datadictionary.nhs.uk/web_site_content/supporting_information/clinical_coding/accident_and_emergency_diagnosis_tables.asp?shownav=1</ext-link> (19 June 2020, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>World Health Organisation</collab>. International classification of diseases and related health problems: 10th revision. <year>2016</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>NHS Digital</collab>. NHS Data Model and Dictionary: General Medical Practice Code (Patient Registration). <year>2022</year>. Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.datadictionary.nhs.uk/data_elements/general_medical_practice_code__patient_registration_.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.datadictionary.nhs.uk/data_elements/general_medical_practice_code__patient_registration_.html</ext-link> (29 December 2022, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Stigmatisation of those with mental health conditions in the acute general hospital setting. A qualitative framework synthesis</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>255</volume>:<fpage>112974</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32388323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.socscimed.2020.112974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>UK Government</collab>. UK Population by Ethnicity: Population of England and Wales. <year>2018</year>. Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ethnicity-facts-figures.service.gov.uk/uk-population-by-ethnicity/national-and-regional-populations/population-of-england-and-wales/latest" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ethnicity-facts-figures.service.gov.uk/uk-population-by-ethnicity/national-and-regional-populations/population-of-england-and-wales/latest</ext-link> (25 November 2021, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Greater London Authority</collab>. CHAIN Annual Report: Greater London April 2017 - March 2018. London, <year>2018</year>. Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://data.london.gov.uk/dataset/chain-reports" ext-link-type="uri">https://data.london.gov.uk/dataset/chain-reports</ext-link> (25 November 2021, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ckac191-B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Office for National Statistics</collab>. UK Homelessness: 2005 to 2018. <year>2019</year>. Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/housing/articles/ukhomelessness/2005to2018" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/housing/articles/ukhomelessness/2005to2018</ext-link> (1 June 2021, date last accessed).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>