<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3211</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jamasd</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JAMA Network Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2574-3805</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>JAMA Network</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11362859</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11362859.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11362859</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11362859</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39207758</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.27236</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zoi240841</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Investigation</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="online-only"><subject>Online Only</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="subject-area"><subject>Substance Use and Addiction</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pharmacy Naloxone Standing Order and Community Opioid Fatality Rates Over Time</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="headline">Pharmacy Naloxone Standing Order and Community Opioid Fatality Rates Over Time</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Pharmacy Naloxone Standing Order and Community Opioid Fatality Rates Over Time</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names initials="Z">Ziming</given-names></name><degrees>ScD</degrees><degrees>SM</degrees><xref rid="zoi240841aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="zoi240841aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walley</surname><given-names initials="AY">Alexander Y.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref rid="zoi240841aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names initials="S">Shapei</given-names></name><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="zoi240841aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names initials="A">Avik</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi240841aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names initials="TG">Traci G.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref rid="zoi240841aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pollini</surname><given-names initials="RA">Robin A.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="zoi240841aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="zoi240841aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="zoi240841aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Community Health Sciences, Boston University School of Public Health, Boston, Massachusetts</aff><aff id="zoi240841aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Epidemiology, Boston University School of Public Health, Boston, Massachusetts</aff><aff id="zoi240841aff3"><label>3</label>Grayken Center for Addiction, Clinical Addiction Research and Education Unit, Section of General Internal Medicine, Department of Medicine, Boston Medical Center and Boston University School of Medicine, Boston, Massachusetts</aff><aff id="zoi240841aff4"><label>4</label>Institute for Behavioral Health, The Heller School for Social Policy and Management at Brandeis University, Waltham, Massachusetts</aff><aff id="zoi240841aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, West Virginia University School of Medicine, Morgantown</aff><aff id="zoi240841aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, West Virginia University School of Public Health, Morgantown </aff><author-notes><title>Article Information</title><p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> June 13, 2024.</p><p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published:</bold> August 29, 2024. doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.27236</uri></p><p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-license-permissions" ext-link-type="uri">CC-BY License</ext-link>. &#169; 2024 Xuan Z et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic>.</p><corresp id="zoi240841cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Ziming Xuan, ScD, SM, Boston University School of Public Health, Department of Community Health Sciences, Crosstown Building &#8211; CT 454, 801 Massachusetts Ave, 4th Floor, Boston, MA 02118 (<email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="zxuan@bu.edu">zxuan@bu.edu</email>).</corresp><p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Dr Xuan had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Concept and design:</italic> Xuan, Walley, Green, Pollini.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> All authors.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Xuan.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> All authors.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Statistical analysis:</italic> Xuan, Yan, Green.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Obtained funding:</italic> Pollini.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Walley.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Supervision:</italic> Xuan, Pollini.</p><p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr Walley reported receiving grants from the National Institutes of Health during the conduct of the study and salary support from Massachusetts Department of Public Health outside the submitted work. No other disclosures were reported.</p><p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> This study was funded by the United States National Institute on Drug Abuse (grant No. R01DA040807; principal investigator: Dr Pollini). Dr Xuan received support from the Centers of Disease Control and Prevention (grant No. R01CE003622). Dr Green received support from the National Institute of Drug Abuse (grant No. R01DA045745) and the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (grant No. R18HS024021).</p><p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The funders had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p><p content-type="data-sharing-statement"><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> See <xref rid="note-ZOI240841-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>.</p><p><bold>Additional Contributions:</bold> Katherine Waye, MPH (Boston Medical Center), assisted with the data collection efforts. She was not compensated for this work outside of her usual salary.</p></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2024-08-29T10:00"><day>29</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>8</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">469688</issue-id><elocation-id>e2427236</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>29</day><month>08</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>31</day><month>08</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-09-01 13:25:13.907"><day>01</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright 2024 Xuan Z et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic>.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2427236.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2427236.pdf">jamanetwopen-e2427236.pdf</self-uri><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.27236"/><abstract abstract-type="key-points"><title>Key Points</title><sec id="ab-zoi240841-1"><title>Question</title><p>Was community implementation of pharmacy standing-order naloxone dispensing associated with municipal opioid fatality rates across municipalities in Massachusetts?</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi240841-2"><title>Findings</title><p>In this study with interrupted time series analysis of all 351 Massachusetts municipalities, communities with pharmacies implementing standing-order naloxone dispensing was associated with reduced opioid fatality rates over time compared with municipalities that did not implement standing-order naloxone dispensing.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi240841-3"><title>Meaning</title><p>These findings of reduced opioid fatality rates associated with standing-order naloxone dispensing support the expansion of community naloxone access, including over-the-counter naloxone, as part of a multifaceted approach to address opioid overdose.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" specific-use="electronic"><p>This cross-sectional study examines whether implementation of pharmacy naloxone standing order dispensing was associated with lower community-level opioid fatality rates in Massachusetts.</p></abstract><abstract><sec id="ab-zoi240841-4"><title>Importance</title><p>Despite the proliferation of pharmacy standing-order naloxone dispensing across many US states before the change to over-the-counter status, few policy analyses have evaluated the implementation of pharmacy naloxone standing orders in addressing opioid overdose fatality among communities.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi240841-5"><title>Objective</title><p>To determine whether the implementation of pharmacy standing-order naloxone was associated with lower opioid fatality rates compared with communities without pharmacies with standing-order naloxone.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi240841-6"><title>Design, Setting, and Participants</title><p>This retrospective multisite study was conducted with an interrupted time series analysis across 351 municipalities in Massachusetts over 24 quarters (from January 1, 2013, through December 31, 2018). Standing-order naloxone dispensing data were collected from 2 sources for all major chain pharmacies and many independent pharmacies, covering 70% of retail pharmacies in Massachusetts. Municipalities had various standing-order naloxone implementation inceptions during the study period. Data were analyzed from December 2021 to November 2023.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi240841-7"><title>Exposure</title><p>The main exposure was measured by the first quarter with standing-order naloxone dispensation as the actual implementation inception.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi240841-8"><title>Main Outcomes and Measures</title><p>The primary study outcome was municipal opioid fatality rate per 100&#8201;000 population obtained from the Massachusetts Registry of Vital Records and Statistics.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi240841-9"><title>Results</title><p>The median (IQR) population size across 351 municipalities was 10&#8201;314 (3635 to 21&#8201;781) people, with mean (SD) proportion of female individuals was 51.1% (2.8 percentage points). Pharmacies from 214 municipalities (60.9%) reported dispensing standing-order naloxone over the study period. At the baseline of the first quarter of 2013, municipalities that eventually had standing-order naloxone had greater quarterly opioid fatality rates compared with those that never implemented standing-order naloxone (3.51 vs 1.03 deaths per 100&#8201;000 population; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). After adjusting for municipal-level sociodemographic and opioid prevention factors, there was significant slope decrease of opioid fatality rates (annualized rate ratio, 0.84; 95% CI, 0.78-0.91; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) following standing-order naloxone dispensing, compared with the municipalities that did not implement standing-order naloxone. There were no significant level changes of opioid fatality rates in the adjusted models. Sensitivity analyses yielded similar and significant findings.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi240841-10"><title>Conclusions and Relevance</title><p>These findings suggest that community pharmacy dispensing of naloxone with standing orders was associated with a relative, gradual, and significant decrease in opioid fatality rates compared with communities that did not implement the standing-order naloxone program. These findings support the expansion of naloxone access, including over-the-counter naloxone as part of a multifaceted approach to address opioid overdose.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="H1-1-ZOI240841"><title>Introduction</title><p>In the US, opioid overdose caused more than 80&#8201;000 deaths in the 12 months ending in April 2023.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Providing access to naloxone is a core strategy for reducing opioid fatality in the US Department of Health and Human Services&#8217; overdose prevention strategy,<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> the President&#8217;s national drug control strategy,<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention&#8217;s 2022 clinical practice guidelines for prescribing opioids for pain.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Legislative efforts to expand naloxone access have been pursued to enable community pharmacists to have the authority to dispense naloxone through a standing order. By July 2020, almost every state and the District of Columbia had established a mechanism allowing naloxone dispensing via standing order or similar mechanism.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> There is evidence that these programs significantly increase naloxone access.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> In March of 2023, the US Food and Drug Administration approved the first naloxone formulation for over-the-counter, nonprescription use.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></p><p>Despite their proliferation, there is scarce evidence on the effect of pharmacy naloxone standing orders on opioid overdose in community settings. Most evidence focused on expanded access to naloxone, such as community, pharmacy, and coprescribing overdose education and naloxone distribution (OEND) programs.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> Multiple studies on state naloxone access laws across US found reduced opioid mortality,<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> but there was evidence that the association was driven by early adopters that passed legislation before 2011.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> However, a single-site interrupted time series analysis from 2012 to 2018 in Ontario, Canada, found that pharmacy-based naloxone dispensing under Ontario&#8217;s naloxone program for pharmacies was not inversely associated with overdose fatality rates.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> These mixed results reflect differences in study design, analytic approach, and emergence of fentanyl in the supply; yet, importantly, none focused on community-level fatality rates. Because community pharmacies can be key venues for distributing naloxone, it will be useful to not only understand the associations of these standing-order naloxone with community-level fatality rates but also infer the potential associations of over-the-counter naloxone dispensing.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup></p><p>Massachusetts declared a public health emergency in response to increasing opioid overdoses in March of 2014.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> This declaration enabled all pharmacies in Massachusetts to voluntarily obtain a standing order to dispense naloxone kits in December 2014.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> The policy was strengthened on December 1, 2017, when pharmacies were mandated to obtain a standing order permitting them to distribute naloxone without prescription. In August 2018, Massachusetts General Laws, Chapter 94C, Section 19B<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> further strengthened the policy via a single statewide standing order that authorized licensed pharmacists to dispense naloxone kits to any person at risk of experiencing an opioid-related overdose.</p><p>The standing-order naloxone policy in Massachusetts provided the opportunity to investigate its association with community-level opioid overdose. Although the rapid policy development presents challenges in identifying a single critical interruption point, pharmacy dispensing data can be used to define the inception of standing-order naloxone implementation for municipalities across Massachusetts. We hypothesized that municipalities with pharmacies dispensing standing-order naloxone would have reduced opioid fatality rates compared with municipalities that did not implement standing-order naloxone programs.</p></sec><sec id="H1-2-ZOI240841"><title>Methods</title><sec id="H2-1-ZOI240841"><title>Study Design and Setting</title><p>This repeated cross-sectional study was reviewed and designated as not human participant research by the institutional review boards of the West Virginia University and the Boston University Medical Campus. We conducted a multisite interrupted time series analysis of quarterly opioid fatality rates comparing municipalities where community pharmacies dispensed standing-order naloxone with those did not dispense standing-order naloxone. We included data from all 351 municipalities in Massachusetts. The analysis was conducted across 24 quarters from first quarter of 2013 to fourth quarter of 2018. This study is reported following the Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/strobe/" ext-link-type="uri">STROBE</ext-link>) reporting guideline for observational studies.</p></sec><sec id="H2-2-ZOI240841"><title>Outcome Variable</title><p>The primary outcome was the opioid fatality rate per quarter at the municipal level. We calculated rates of opioid-related drug poisonings by community of residence using in-state deaths from the electronic database maintained by the Massachusetts Registry of Vital Records and Statistics, Massachusetts Department of Public Health. Opioid-related deaths were defined by <italic toggle="yes">International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems, Tenth Revision </italic>(<italic toggle="yes">ICD-10</italic>) codes indicating unintentional or undetermined intentional poisoning (code X40-X44, Y10-Y14) in the underlying cause of death field and an opioid-specific T code of T40.0-T40.4 and/or the narcotic T code T40.6 in any of the multiple cause-of-death fields.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="H2-3-ZOI240841"><title>Main Exposure Variable</title><p>We used 2 sources for retail pharmacy data of standing-order naloxone distributed between 2013 and 2018. One of the authors (A.Y.W.), was the standing-order prescriber for all major chain pharmacies, except for 1, and many independent pharmacies in Massachusetts. These standing orders required pharmacies to maintain a record of each naloxone kit dispensed and report the dates and quantities to the standing order prescriber on a monthly basis. One major chain of pharmacies used their own standing-order writer during the study period. Data from this large retail chain on standing-order naloxone dispensing have been described in prior studies.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> We merged data from both sources, which in aggregate covered 70% of retail pharmacies in Massachusetts.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup></p><p>For the interrupted time series analysis, we used the first quarter in which standing-order naloxone was dispensed as a municipality-specific inception variable. The use of the quarter for the first standing-order naloxone dispensed captured the actual implementation inception for a given municipality. Once the pharmacies in a municipality dispensed standing-order naloxone, the municipality was coded in the exposure group and remained exposed for the duration of the study. As a result, 214 of 351 municipalities had various inceptions during the study period. The cumulative number of communities with actual standing order naloxone dispensing in each year were: 0 by 2013, 17 by 2014, 140 by 2015, 196 by 2016, 209 by 2017, and 214 by 2018. The remaining 137 municipalities did not dispense standing-order naloxone through their community pharmacies during the study period.</p></sec><sec id="H2-4-ZOI240841"><title>Covariates</title><p>We obtained community demographics to adjust for potential municipal-level confounding. We obtained data from the American Community Survey 5-year estimates (2013-2018), including number of municipal residents, age group proportions (&lt;25, 25-44, 45-54, 55-64, and &#8805;65 years), sex, race and ethnicity (African American or Black, American Indian or Alaska Native, Asian, Hispanic or Latinx, Pacific Islander, White, and other, which included multiracial and other group), high school education or less, and vacancy rate.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Race and ethnicity were included because opioid use patterns differ by race and ethnicity. Vacancy rate was measured by vacant housing units per 1000 population, and vacancy rate was shown to be a marker of neighborhood distress associated with opioid overdose.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> To adjust for the proliferation of naloxone kits from certain other sources, we obtained the number of naloxone kits distributed to the communities by OEND programs funded by the Massachusetts Department of Public Health. We also obtained the number of naloxone kits dispensed through pharmacies that were not under a standing order (ie, with a prescription). Although these prescribed naloxone kits data were collected for the study period, the data since the second half of 2017 were incomplete. We conducted a sensitivity analysis to further adjust for prescribed naloxone kits rates. To adjust for the level of opioid treatment in the community, we obtained methadone treatment admissions rates and residential treatment admissions rates from the Massachusetts Bureau of Substance Addiction Services. In addition, the Prescription Monitoring Program provided patient rates of buprenorphine prescriptions, indicative of an opioid use disorder. These covariates were assessed in prior studies on opioid use.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Given overdose risk is elevated at release from incarceration,<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> we also obtained data on community release rates from the Massachusetts Department of Correction. Finally, because fentanyl in the illicit drug supply is the major driver of surging overdose deaths, we used the community-specific proportion of fentanyl-related deaths over all opioid deaths from Massachusetts Registry of Vital Records and Statistics as a proxy measure to control for fentanyl-related burden among these municipalities.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="H2-5-ZOI240841"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>We used 2-sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> tests to compare the municipalities that did not have standing-order naloxone vs those dispensing standing-order naloxone. For the interrupted time series, we used the quarterly municipality-specific opioid fatality counts as the units of analysis. The total units of analysis included 28&#8201;424 town-quarters (ie, 24 quarterly measures per municipality). The municipal population based on US Census estimates was used in the log scale as a population offset. We used Poisson regression models with overdispersion adjustment to model rates with a log-linear statistical model accounting for community level covariates.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> We used the segmented regression analysis approach<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> and included multiple time series with a generalized estimation equations approach<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> to examine the population-mean changes of level and slope of fatality rate outcome after the implementation of pharmacy standing-order naloxone dispensing. We used the equation log(Y<sub>it</sub>)&#8201;=&#8201;&#946;<sub>0</sub>&#8201;+&#8201;&#946;<sub>1</sub>Time<sub>it</sub>&#8201;+&#8201;&#946;<sub>2</sub>Program<sub>it</sub>&#8201;+&#8201;&#946;<sub>3</sub>Time after program<sub>it</sub>&#8201;+&#8201;BX<sub>it</sub>&#8201;+&#8201;e<sub>it</sub>, where <italic toggle="yes">Y<sub>it</sub>
</italic>represents the quarterly rate outcome at municipality <italic toggle="yes">i</italic> and time point <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Time<sub>it</sub></italic> represents the time in quarter since the start of the study period, <italic toggle="yes">Program<sub>it</sub>
</italic>is an indicator (dummy) variable representing the pharmacy standing-order naloxone dispensing program, and <italic toggle="yes">Time after program<sub>it</sub></italic> represents the time in quarters after the dispensing inception date. &#946;<sub>0</sub> represents the intercept of the preprogram trend line at the index time, and B represents the coefficient vector of the municipal-level covariates set. We evaluated program outcomes based on the regression coefficients (&#946;<sub>2</sub> and &#946;<sub>3</sub>) assuming the preimplementation trend remained unchanged. We examined quasilikelihood information criteria to assess goodness of fit and determine the covariance structure of the repeated quarterly measures within municipalities and the overdispersion of the Poisson distribution.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> We annualized &#946;<sub>3</sub> to represent the change of rate per year after implementation of pharmacy standing-order naloxone programs.</p><p>To ascertain robustness of our findings, we conducted 5 sensitivity analyses. First, instead of using the concurrent quarter as the first dispensing quarter, we applied 1-quarter lag by using the subsequent quarter as the starting quarter, because the date of the first standing-order naloxone dispensed may not fall at the beginning of a quarter. Second, we removed substance use disorder treatment variables (eg, methadone admission rate, residential admission rate, and patient rate of buprenorphine prescription for opioid use disorder) that could be potential mediators. Third, we further controlled for prescribed pharmacy-based naloxone kit distribution rates that could partially affect opioid overdose rates in these municipalities. Fourth, to account for potential unmeasured health system effects, we followed a prior method<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> and refit the adjusted Poisson fatal overdose models replacing fatal death rates with opioid death to cancer death rate ratios for each municipality-quarter unit using data from the Massachusetts Registry of Vital Records and Statistics. We used <italic toggle="yes">ICD-10</italic> codes representing malignant neoplasms (codes C000-C979) to define cancer deaths. Cancer death rate served as a potential control of the underlying health system change over the study period; thus, a significant association with the opioid-to-cancer&#8211;death rate ratio outcome would indicate that opioid deaths were associated with the standing-order naloxone program after accounting for the underlying health system changes. Fifth, because the Massachusetts state mandate for standing-order naloxone dispensing took effect in August 2018, we restricted the final sensitivity analysis to a shortened study period from the first quarter of 2013 to the second quarter of 2018 (ie, 22 quarters).</p><p>All tests used a significance level of P&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;.05, and all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values were 2-sided. All analyses were conducted using SAS software version 9.4 (SAS Institute). Data were analyzed from December 2021 to November 2023.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-3-ZOI240841"><title>Results</title><p>The mean (SD) population size across 351 municipalities was 18&#8201;818 (39&#8201;368; median [IQR], 10&#8201;314 [3635 to 21&#8201;781]), the mean (SD) proportion of female individuals was 51.1% (2.8 percentage points), and the mean (SD) age proportions were 29.2% (5.7 percentage points) younger than 25 years, 22.7% (4.8 percentage points) aged 25 to 44 years, 17.2% (3.0 percentage points) aged 45 to 54 years, 15.3% (3.9 percentage points) aged 55 to 64 years, and 15.7% (5.1 percentage points) aged 65 years or older. Pharmacies from 214 municipalities (60.9%) reported ever dispensing standing-order naloxone over the study period. The implementation of standing-order naloxone programs was mapped with the opioid fatality rates (eFigure in <xref rid="note-ZOI240841-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).</p><p>At the baseline of the first quarter of 2013, municipalities that eventually had standing-order naloxone dispensed in their pharmacies had greater proportions of younger, female, African American, Asian, Hispanic, or other race residents and greater rates of residential admissions compared with municipalities without standing-order naloxone dispensed in their pharmacies (<xref rid="zoi240841t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Municipalities that eventually had standing-order naloxone dispensed had larger population size and lower vacancy rate (<xref rid="zoi240841t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) and a higher quarterly opioid fatality rate at baseline compared with municipalities that did not have standing-order naloxone dispensing (3.51 vs 1.03 per 100&#8201;000 population; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) (<xref rid="zoi240841t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi240841t1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1. </label><caption><title>Comparison of Characteristics of 351 Municipalities in Massachusetts in the First Quarter of 2013 and the Fourth Quarter of 2018</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="19.12%" span="1"/><col width="15.03%" span="1"/><col width="15.52%" span="1"/><col width="9.24%" span="1"/><col width="15.59%" span="1"/><col width="15.52%" span="1"/><col width="9.78%" span="1"/><col width="0.2%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th colspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">First quarter of 2013</th><th colspan="4" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Fourth quarter of 2018</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Municipalities, mean (SD)</th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">t </italic>test (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value)</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Municipalities, mean (SD)</th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value)</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">No NSO (n&#8201;=&#8201;137)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eventual NSO (n&#8201;=&#8201;214)<xref rid="zoi240841t1n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">No NSO (n&#8201;=&#8201;137)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">With NSO (n&#8201;=&#8201;214)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quarterly opioid fatality rate, No. per 100 000 population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (4.46)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.51 (6.30)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;4.01 (&lt;.001)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.17 (10.56)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.66 (6.90)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.61 (.11)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, y, %</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;25</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.49 (6.30)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.23 (4.99)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;4.52 (&lt;.001)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.15 (6.39)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.08 (5.38)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;4.61 (&lt;.001)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 25-44</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.61 (4.31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.99 (4.70)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;6.79 (&lt;.001)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.53 (4.45)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.44 (4.96)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;7.50 (&lt;.001)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 45-54</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.15 (3.17)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.52 (2.72)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.13 (&lt;.001)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.68 (3.46)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.04 (2.38)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06 (.04)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 55-64</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.36 (4.42)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.91 (2.70)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.07 (&lt;.001)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.12 (4.08)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.71 (2.75)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.32 (&lt;.001)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &#8805;65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.39 (5.88)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.35 (4.54)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87 (.06)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.52 (6.45)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.73 (5.38)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.38 (&lt;.001)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex, %</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.59 (3.16)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.35 (2.45)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;2.53 (.01)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.39 (3.50)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.35 (2.36)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;3.07 (.002)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.41 (3.16)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.65 (2.45)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53 (.01)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.61 (3.50)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.65 (2.37)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.07 (.002)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Race and ethnicity, %</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> African American or Black</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (1.68)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.06 (5.04)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;4.57 (&lt;.001)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41 (2.13)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.54 (5.17)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;4.59 (&lt;.001)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> American Indian or Alaska Native</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 (3.58)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 (0.22)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49 (0.14)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 (1.79)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16 (0.37)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 (.22)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Asian</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46 (2.16)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.90 (4.63)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;5.79 (&lt;.001)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.74 (2.99)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.57 (5.51)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;5.51 (&lt;.001)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hispanic or Latinx</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92 (1.93)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.64 (8.87)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;4.85 (&lt;.001)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60 (2.07)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.67 (9.88)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;4.75 (&lt;.001)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pacific Islander</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 (0.07)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.57 (.12)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 (0.19)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 (0.07)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60 (.11)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.87 (5.92)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.73 (10.63)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.17 (&lt;.001)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.92 (5.70)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.03 (10.93)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.81 (&lt;.001)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other<xref rid="zoi240841t1n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14 (2.14)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.15 (5.49)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;4.09 (&lt;.001)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56 (2.15)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.68 (2.15)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;4.58 (&lt;.001)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Educational level, %</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &#8804;High school</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.01 (11.38)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.11 (12.77)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.82 (.41)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.14 (11.22)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.58 (12.41)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.34 (.74)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &#8805;College</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.99 (11.38)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.89 (12.77)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (.41)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.86 (11.22)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.42 (12.41)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 (.74)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vacancy units, No. per 1000 population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142.3 (262.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.22 (128.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00 (&lt;.001)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">173.4 (447.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.08 (137.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43 (&lt;.001)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Naloxone kits distributed by OEND program, No. per 1000 population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 (0.20)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 (0.21)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;4.51 (&lt;.001)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42 (0.64)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 (1.20)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;3.66 (&lt;.001)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Releases from incarceration, No. per 1000 population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 (0.10)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09 (0.11)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;5.06 (&lt;.001)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 (0.11)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07 (0.09)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;3.49 (&lt;.001)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BSAS methadone admissions, No. per 1000 population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 (0.43)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 (0.44)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.88 (.38)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18 (0.38)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 (0.36)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;2.36 (.02)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BSAS residential admissions, No. per 1000 population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.93)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57 (1.07)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;5.63 (&lt;.001)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 (0.78)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57 (1.32)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;6.42 (&lt;.001)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buprenorphine prescription for OUD, No. per 1000 population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.06 (3.86)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.10 (6.02)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.80 (.07)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.28 (5.95)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.56 (8.23)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.58 (.12)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fentanyl-related deaths among opioid-related deaths, %</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19 (14.69)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.01 (20.01)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.42 (.16)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.06 (36.35)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.06 (48.44)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;7.46 (&lt;.001)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer-related death rate, No. per 100&#8201;000 population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.65 (47.80)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.88 (21.22)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.40 (.16)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.98 (44.82)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.19 (23.90)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.41 (.16)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Municipal population, No.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mean</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4117 (3342)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28&#8201;230 (48&#8201;136)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;5.85 (&lt;.001)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4239 (3515)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29&#8201;204 (51&#8201;373)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;5.68 (&lt;.001)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Median</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3245 (1376-6211)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#8201;646 (10&#8201;857-29&#8201;968)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3292 (1380-6551)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8201;099 (11&#8201;301-31&#8201;177)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviations: BSAS, Massachusetts Bureau of Substance Addiction Services; NA, not applicable; NSO, naloxone standing order; OEND, opioid education and naloxone distribution; OUD, opioid use disorder.</p><fn id="zoi240841t1n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Massachusetts has 351 municipalities. During the period from 2013 to 2018, pharmacies from 214 municipalities used NSO to dispense naloxone kits, while 137 municipalities did not. The 214 municipalities had various inception of actual standing-order naloxone dispensing during the study period. The cumulative number of communities with actual standing-order naloxone dispensing in each year were: 1 by 2013, 17 by 2014, 140 by 2015, 196 by 2016, 209 by 2017, and 214 by 2018.</p></fn><fn id="zoi240841t1n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Other race category included multiracial and other race groups.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p><xref rid="zoi240841t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> summarizes the changes in municipal opioid fatality rates after the implementation of standing-order naloxone dispensing from 2013 to 2018. Adjusting for municipality-level covariates and the trend of opioid fatality prior to standing-order naloxone dispensing, we did not detect a statistically significant level change in the opioid fatality rate (adjusted rate ratio [aRR], 1.09; 95% CI, 0.99 to 1.20; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.08) after naloxone dispensing under the standing-order naloxone commenced; however, there was a significant slope decrease (annualized aRR, 0.84; 95% CI, 0.78 to 0.91; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). The decrease of slope corresponded to an annual relative decrease of 16.0% of the opioid fatality rate per 100&#8201;000 population. No differential trends were detected (&#946;&#8201;=&#8201;&#8722;0.010; 95% CI, &#8722;0.028 to 0.008; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.26), thus meeting the assumption of parallel baseline trends in municipalities with and without standing-order naloxone.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> Municipalities with greater proportions of residents with only high school education or less, greater rates of inpatient residential admissions, more patients with buprenorphine prescriptions per population, and a greater proportion of fentanyl-involved opioid deaths had increased opioid fatality rates (<xref rid="zoi240841t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi240841t2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2. </label><caption><title>Changes in Level and Slope of Opioid Fatality Rates After Implementation<xref rid="zoi240841t2n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref> of Naloxone Standing Order Across 351 Municipalities in Massachusetts From the First Quarter of 2013 to the Fourth Quarter of 2018</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="34.64%" span="1"/><col width="21.43%" span="1"/><col width="10.72%" span="1"/><col width="22.45%" span="1"/><col width="10.76%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Opioid fatality rate</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Unadjusted model</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Main adjusted model</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Rate ratio (95% CI)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjusted rate ratio (95% CI)<xref rid="zoi240841t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level change</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 (1.22-1.41)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.99-1.20)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.08</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slope change (annualized per year)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.85-0.96)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.002</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.78-0.91)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="zoi240841t2n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>The exposure of the policy implementation was based on the actual starting quarter when the municipality had their first standing-order naloxone dispensed. Therefore, the actual starting quarter varied across the 214 municipalities that had standing-order naloxone dispensed in their pharmacies. Once the pharmacies in a municipality dispensed standing-order naloxone, the municipality was coded in the exposure condition. This analysis also included the 137 municipalities that did not dispense standing-order naloxone as comparative series.</p></fn><fn id="zoi240841t2n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>The adjusted model accounted for municipal-level factors of age groups, male sex, race and ethnicity, education level, vacancy units, naloxone kits distributed by Massachusetts&#8217; opioid education and naloxone distribution program, releases from incarceration, Massachusetts Bureau of Substance Addiction Services methadone treatment admissions and residential admissions, Massachusetts Prescription Monitoring Program patient rate of buprenorphine prescriptions indicated for opioid use disorder, and proportion of fentanyl-related death.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi240841t3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3. </label><caption><title>Interrupted Time Series Poisson Regression Model of the Associations of Implementing Standing Order Naloxone Dispensing With Opioid Fatality Rate Across 351 Municipalities in Massachusetts From the First Quarter of 2013 to the Fourth Quarter of 2018</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="54.62%" span="1"/><col width="30.82%" span="1"/><col width="14.56%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Opioid fatality rate<xref rid="zoi240841t3n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Main adjusted model<xref rid="zoi240841t3n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">&#946; (95% CI)<xref rid="zoi240841t3n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exposure variables</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intercept</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;11.45 (&#8722;13.28 to &#8722;9.621)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Change in the outcome level after implementation</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085 (&#8722;0.011 to 0.182)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.08</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Change in trend per quarter after implementation</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.044 (&#8722;0.064 to &#8722;0.024)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Trend per quarter before implementation</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012 (0.003 to 0.021)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Age, y, %</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 25-44</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001 (&#8722;0.014 to 0.014)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.96</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 45-54</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.003 (&#8722;0.034 to 0.029)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.09</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 55-64</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013 (&#8722;0.009 to 0.034)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.25</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &#8805;65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001 (&#8722;0.012 to 0.012)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.99</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female sex, %</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.006 (&#8722;0.025 to 0.013)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.53</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Race and ethnicity, %</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> African American or Black</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.003 (&#8722;0.016 to 0.010)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.66</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> American Indian or Alaska Native</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022 (&#8722;0.023 to 0.066)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.34</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Asian</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001 (&#8722;0.014 to 0.016)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.92</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hispanic or Latinx</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.006 (&#8722;0.013 to 0.002)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.16</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pacific Islander</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.003 (&#8722;0.352 to 0.346)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.99</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.003 (&#8722;0.014 to 0.009)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.67</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &#8804;High school education, %</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018 (0.013 to 0.023)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Vacancy units, per 1000 population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0004 (&#8722;0.001 to 0.001)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.12</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Naloxone kits distributed by OEND program, per 1000 population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.036 (&#8722;0.109 to 0.038)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.34</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Releases from incarceration, per 1000 population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.008 (&#8722;0.226 to 0.209)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.94</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> BSAS methadone admissions, per 1000 population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.040 (&#8722;0.158 to 0.079)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.51</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> BSAS residential admissions, per 1000 population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.104 (0.055 to 0.154)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Patients with buprenorphine prescription for OUD, per 1000 population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015 (0.005 to 0.025)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.003</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fentanyl-related deaths among opioid-related deaths, %</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011 (0.009 to 0.013)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviations: BSAS, Massachusetts Bureau of Substance Addiction Services; OEND, opioid education and naloxone distribution; OUD, opioid use disorder.</p><fn id="zoi240841t3n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>The exposure of the policy implementation was based on the actual starting quarter when the municipality had their first standing order naloxone dispensed. Therefore, the actual starting quarter varied across the 214 municipalities that had standing order naloxone dispensed in their pharmacies. Once the pharmacies in a municipality dispensed standing order naloxone, the municipality was coded in the exposure condition. This analysis also included the 137 municipalities without standing-order naloxone as comparative series.</p></fn><fn id="zoi240841t3n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Municipality quarter data of opioid fatality rate per 100&#8201;000 population were available from the first quarter of 2013 to the fourth quarter of 2018.</p></fn><fn id="zoi240841t3n3"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>The adjusted model accounted for municipal-level factors of age groups, male sex, race and ethnicity, education, vacancy units, naloxone kits distributed by Massachusetts&#8217; OEND program, releases from incarceration, BSAS methadone treatment admissions and residential admissions, Massachusetts Prescription Monitoring Program patient rate of buprenorphine prescriptions indicated for opioid use disorder, and proportion of fentanyl-related death among opioid-related deaths.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>All sensitivity analyses yielded consistent results with respect to no statistically significant level changes yet significant slope changes of opioid fatality rates (<xref rid="zoi240841t4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). First, lag-1 analysis also detected slope change (annualized aRR, 0.84; 95% CI, 0.77 to 0.91; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). Statistically significant slope changes were also detected in models when removing municipal substance use disorder treatment utilization (aRR, 0.85; 95% CI, 0.78 to 0.92; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) and additionally controlling for prescribed pharmacy-based naloxone kit rates (aRR, 0.84; 95% CI, 0.78 to 0.91; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). In the fourth sensitivity analysis, the opioid-related overdose fatality outcomes were substituted for the ratio of opioid death rates over the cancer-related death rates. Slope change was also detected (aRR, 0.85; 95% CI, 0.81 to 0.90; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). Thus, the decrease of slope in opioid fatality rates after standing-order naloxone programs was independent of underlying health system change over the study period. Finally, excluding the last 2 quarters of 2018 still resulted in a significant slope change for the opioid fatality rate (aRR, 0.87; 95% CI, 0.80 to 0.94; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi240841t4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4. </label><caption><title>Post Hoc Sensitivity Analyses of the Associations of Implementing Standing-Order Naloxone Dispensing With Opioid Fatality Rate Across 351 Municipalities in Massachusetts From the First Quarter of 2013 to the Fourth Quarter of 2018</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="64.55%" span="1"/><col width="24.76%" span="1"/><col width="10.69%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Opioid fatality rate<xref rid="zoi240841t4n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Main adjusted model<xref rid="zoi240841t4n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Adjusted rate ratio (95% CI)<xref rid="zoi240841t4n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">
<bold>Lag-1 approach using the following quarter as the starting quarter</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level change</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.98-1.18)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.13</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slope change (annualized per year)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.77-0.91)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">
<bold>Remove potential mediators (eg, substance use disorder treatment variables)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level change</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.99-1.17)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.07</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slope change (annualized per year)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 (0.78-0.92)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">
<bold>Include pharmacy-based non&#8211;standing order prescribed naloxone kits rate as additional covariate</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level change</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.99-1.20)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.08</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slope change (annualized per year)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.78-0.91)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">
<bold>Based on the rate ratio of opioid death rate over cancer death rate</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level change</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.85-1.10)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.57</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slope change (annualized per year)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 (0.81-0.90)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">
<bold>Restrict study period from first quarter 2013 to second quarter 2018</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level change</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.97-1.17)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.15</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slope change (annualized per year)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.80-0.94)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="zoi240841t4n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>The exposure of the policy implementation was based on the first standing order naloxone dispensed quarter. Therefore, the actual starting quarter varied across the 214 municipalities that had standing order naloxone dispensed in their pharmacies. This analysis also included the 137 municipalities without standing-order naloxone dispensing as comparative series.</p></fn><fn id="zoi240841t4n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Municipality quarter data of opioid fatality rate per 100&#8201;000 population were available from the first quarter of 2013 to the fourth quarter of 2018.</p></fn><fn id="zoi240841t4n3"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>The adjusted model accounted for municipal-level factors of age groups, male sex, race and ethnicity, education, vacancy units, naloxone kits distributed by Massachusetts&#8217; opioid education and naloxone distribution program, releases from incarceration, Massachusetts Bureau of Substance Addiction Services methadone treatment admissions and residential admissions, Massachusetts Prescription Monitoring Program patient rate of buprenorphine prescriptions indicated for opioid use disorder, and proportion of fentanyl-related death among opioid-related deaths.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="H1-4-ZOI240841"><title>Discussion</title><p>This repeated cross-sectional study with interrupted time series analysis found that despite an uptrend of opioid fatality rate across Massachusetts, standing-order naloxone dispensing was associated with a relative, gradual, and significant decrease in opioid fatality rates in the municipalities with standing-order naloxone dispensing compared with the municipalities where pharmacies did not dispense standing-order naloxone. Our main analysis and several sensitivity analyses confirmed the association with reduced community-level opioid fatality rates.</p><p>Although we observed a reduction in the slope of opioid fatality rates over time, we did not detect an immediate change of opioid fatality rates in the adjusted models. This was true whether we anchored the policy implementation on the first standing-order naloxone dispensing event or lagged it by 1 quarter. It is possible that community pharmacies started dispensing naloxone in response to heightened opioid overdose in the communities. The lack of immediate level change was also expected, given the gradual process to make community residents aware of the standing-order prescribing of naloxone in their community pharmacies. Detecting an immediate policy impact can be challenging when policy implementation is shaped by contextual factors and time-delayed effects in a fluid and complex ecological system.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> Policy-, chain- and pharmacy-level interventions that occurred during the period of study are worth considering. For example, a multicomponent study examined barriers experienced by patients, caregivers, and pharmacists<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup>; developed educational intervention materials tailored to these barriers for the pharmacy and staff<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup>; and then implemented the materials through academic detailing visits.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> Such efforts may have boosted the standing-order naloxone outcomes through systemic dissemination and implementation in community pharmacies.</p><p>Municipalities with greater proportions of residents with lower education had higher opioid fatality rates. A 2020 study found that individuals with only high school education or less were more likely to die of opioid overdose compared with individuals with a graduate degree.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> This association of overdose fatality with lower education likely reflects the health impacts from structural inequities in social resources, like education.</p><p>This study conducted a multisite interrupted time series using standing-order naloxone dispensing as a natural experiment. The use of a community&#8217;s actual quarter of their first standing order naloxone dispensing also departs from prior approaches that relied on between-state naloxone access law pre-post comparison,<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> thus yielding new evidence for the association of pharmacy naloxone dispensing with opioid fatality at the community level.</p><sec id="H2-6-ZOI240841"><title>Limitations</title><p>The study has several limitations. First, our study is susceptible to residual confounding, particularly other unmeasured community-level factors. We tried to mitigate confounding by including a large set of community-level covariates. Second, although our data covered 70% of retail pharmacies in Massachusetts and should have correctly identified all pharmacies dispensing standing-order naloxone prior to state mandate in October 2018, it is possible that some pharmacies dispensed standing-order naloxone under standing orders not covered by our data. If this happened, it was likely a small proportion. A 2023 study comparing a national commercial pharmacy naloxone dataset with the same pharmacy naloxone data sources in Massachusetts used in this study found that the overall (standing order and non&#8211;standing order combined) dispensing counts were similar with the commercial dataset, though the commercial dataset counted more overall naloxone dispensed in the later quarters.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> However, the commercial dataset had no indicator for standing-order naloxone, so it is not possible to test our hypothesis with the commercial dataset. Third, we were not able to measure or include in our model coprescribing of naloxone with prescription opioids, which has been shown in multiple states to drive pharmacy naloxone dispensing,<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup> because it was not a policy mandate in Massachusetts during this time. Fourth, we only used the first standing-order naloxone dispensing quarter as the start of the intervention, and we did not capture the actual volume of standing-order naloxone per quarter during the study period. Fifth, this study also did not directly measure over-the-counter naloxone, as it was not available. However, standing-order naloxone dispensing is a close approximation of over-the-counter naloxone. We did not investigate price of naloxone as a factor in this study, as we did not have price information. A prior study showed that insurance coverage for naloxone during this period was common.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup></p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-5-ZOI240841"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The findings of this study with interrupted time series analysis provide support for implementation of standing-order naloxone dispensing and expansion of access to naloxone to address opioid overdose crisis. Our findings are also consistent with previous literature refuting the idea of naloxone as a moral hazard&#8212;that naloxone provision would lead to increased opioid use or overdose.<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="zoi240841r48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup> With the US Food and Drug Administration&#8217;s approval of certain over-the-counter naloxone products,<sup><xref rid="zoi240841r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> it is important to examine their diffusion across communities over time, augmentation of other formulations through existing standing-order mandates, and ultimately their impact on reducing opioid fatalities. Future research could ascertain how communities of color (eg, African American or Black, American Indian or Alaska Native, Asian, Hispanic or Latinx, Pacific Islander) or other vulnerability characteristics, such as low economic resources, could benefit from proactive, broader access to naloxone that comes from policies like standing orders or over-the-counter to overcome other barriers, including willingness to engage with first responders and readiness to administer naloxone. It would also be valuable to examine how standing-order naloxone dispensing may interact with other strategies, such as medications for opioid use disorder and referrals to recovery support services, in reducing opioid overdose.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="REF-ZOI240841"><title>References</title><ref id="zoi240841r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cisewski</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rossen</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. Provisional drug overdose death counts. National Center for Health Statistics. <year>2023</year>. Accessed September 17, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nvss/vsrr/drug-overdose-data.htm" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nvss/vsrr/drug-overdose-data.htm</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>US Department of Health &amp; Human Services</collab></person-group>. Overdose prevention strategy. Accessed January 10, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.hhs.gov/overdose-prevention/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.hhs.gov/overdose-prevention/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>The White House</collab></person-group>. National drug control strategy. Accessed January 10, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/National-Drug-Control-2022Strategy.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.whitehouse.gov/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/National-Drug-Control-2022Strategy.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dowell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ragan</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>CDC clinical practice guideline for prescribing opioids for pain&#8212;United States, 2022</article-title>. <source>MMWR Recomm Rep</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>95</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.rr7103a1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36327391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9639433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>The Network for Public Health Law</collab></person-group>. Opioid misuse and overdose prevention: 50-state survey. Accessed April 9, 2021. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.networkforphl.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/50-State-Survey-Legal-Interventions-to-Reduce-Overdose-Mortality-Naloxone-Access-Laws.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.networkforphl.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/50-State-Survey-Legal-Interventions-to-Reduce-Overdose-Mortality-Naloxone-Access-Laws.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gangal</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hincapie</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jandarov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Frede</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boone</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heaton</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Physician-approved protocols increase naloxone dispensing rates</article-title>. <source>J Addict Med</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>317</fpage>-<lpage>323</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ADM.0000000000000899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34380983</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gangal</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hincapie</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jandarov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between a state law allowing pharmacists to dispense naloxone without a prescription and naloxone dispensing rates</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<elocation-id>e1920310</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.20310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32003819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7042867</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>GP</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khushalani</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sims</surname><given-names>RSC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Arifkhanova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Trends in state-level pharmacy-based naloxone dispensing rates, 2012-2019</article-title>. <source>Am J Prev Med</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e289</fpage>-<lpage>e295</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2021.05.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34801208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9732744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>US Food and Drug Administration</collab></person-group>. FDA approves first over-the-counter naloxone nasal spray: agency continues to take critical steps to reduce drug overdose deaths being driven primarily by illicit opioids. News release. March 29, 2023. Accessed April 9, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/news-events/press-announcements/fda-approves-first-over-counter-naloxone-nasal-spray" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.fda.gov/news-events/press-announcements/fda-approves-first-over-counter-naloxone-nasal-spray</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Walley</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hackman</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Opioid overdose rates and implementation of overdose education and nasal naloxone distribution in Massachusetts: interrupted time series analysis</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>346</volume>:<fpage>f174</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.f174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23372174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4688551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pollini</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Joyce</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ozga-Hess</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Walley</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessing pharmacy-based naloxone access using an innovative purchase trial methodology</article-title>. <source>J Am Pharm Assoc (2003)</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>853</fpage>-<lpage>860</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.japh.2020.05.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32651116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7655699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Razaghizad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Windle</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Filion</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of overdose education and naloxone distribution: an umbrella review of systematic reviews</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e1</fpage>-<lpage>e12</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2021.306306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34214412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8489614</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Coffin</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Behar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nonrandomized intervention study of naloxone coprescription for primary care patients receiving long-term opioid therapy for pain</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>165</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>245</fpage>-<lpage>252</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M15-2771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27366987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5783639</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sabia</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Argys</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Latshaw</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dave</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>With a Little Help From My Friends: The Effects of naloxone Access and Good Samaritan Laws on Opioid-Related Deaths</source>. <publisher-name>National Bureau of Economic Research</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3386/w23171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McClellan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lambdin</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Opioid-overdose laws association with opioid use and overdose mortality</article-title>. <source>Addict Behav</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>90</fpage>-<lpage>95</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.addbeh.2018.03.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29610001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abouk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pacula</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Association between state laws facilitating pharmacy distribution of naloxone and risk of fatal overdose</article-title>. <source>JAMA Intern Med</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>179</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>805</fpage>-<lpage>811</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2019.0272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31058922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6503576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Antoniou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Men</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tadrous</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leece</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Munro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of a publicly funded pharmacy-dispensed naloxone program on fatal opioid overdose rates: a population-based study</article-title>. <source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>236</volume>:<elocation-id>109473</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2022.109473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35523113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sanfilippo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dietze</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Community pharmacy naloxone supply, before and after rescheduling as an over-the-counter drug: sales and prescriptions data, 2014-2018</article-title>. <source>Med J Aust</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>212</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>314</fpage>-<lpage>320</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5694/mja2.50524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32124984</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>Commonwealth of Massachusetts Executive Department Office of Governor Deval L. Patrick</collab></person-group>. Governor Patrick declares public health emergency, announces actions to address opioid addiction epidemic. News release. March 27, 2014. Accessed April 9, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://archives.lib.state.ma.us/bitstream/handle/2452/207588/ocn795183245-2014-03-27b.pdf?sequence=1&amp;isAllowed=y" ext-link-type="uri">https://archives.lib.state.ma.us/bitstream/handle/2452/207588/ocn795183245-2014-03-27b.pdf?sequence=1&amp;isAllowed=y</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pollini</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Slocum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ozga</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacy naloxone codispensing: A mixed methods study of practices and perspectives under a statewide standing order program</article-title>. <source>J Am Pharm Assoc (2003)</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1546</fpage>-<lpage>1554</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.japh.2022.03.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35450833</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9464657</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>The Commonwealth of Massachusetts Executive Office of Health and Human Services</collab></person-group>. Policy No. 2018-04: naloxone dispensing via standing order. Accessed December 10, 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.mass.gov/doc/policy-2018-04-naloxone-dispensing-via-standing-order/download" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.mass.gov/doc/policy-2018-04-naloxone-dispensing-via-standing-order/download</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bratberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baird</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rurality and differences in pharmacy characteristics and community factors associated with provision of naloxone in the pharmacy</article-title>. <source>Int J Drug Policy</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>85</volume>:<elocation-id>102602</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugpo.2019.11.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31740174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Walley</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bratberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Laws mandating coprescription of naloxone and their impact on naloxone prescription in five US states, 2014-2018</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>110</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>881</fpage>-<lpage>887</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2020.305620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32298179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7204438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Broadening access to naloxone: Community predictors of standing order naloxone distribution in Massachusetts</article-title>. <source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>230</volume>:<elocation-id>109190</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2021.109190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34864356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8714703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>US Census Bureau</collab></person-group>. American Community Survey 5-year data (2009-2021). Accessed November 1, 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.census.gov/data/developers/data-sets/acs-5year.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.census.gov/data/developers/data-sets/acs-5year.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hyder</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Southerland</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Porr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>311 Service requests as indicators of neighborhood distress and opioid use disorder</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>19579</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-76685-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33177583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7658248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Binswanger</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Deyo</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Release from prison&#8212;a high risk of death for former inmates</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>356</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>157</fpage>-<lpage>165</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMsa064115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17215533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2836121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gladden</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Donnell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seth</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in opioid-involved overdose deaths by opioid type and presence of benzodiazepines, cocaine, and methamphetamine&#8212;25 states, July-December 2017 to January-June 2018</article-title>. <source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>34</issue>):<fpage>737</fpage>-<lpage>744</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6834a2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31465320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6715260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soumerai</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ross-Degnan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gortmaker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Avorn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Withdrawing payment for nonscientific drug therapy. Intended and unexpected effects of a large-scale natural experiment</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>263</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>831</fpage>-<lpage>839</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.1990.03440060077036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2404151</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soumerai</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ross-Degnan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Segmented regression analysis of interrupted time series studies in medication use research</article-title>. <source>J Clin Pharm Ther</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>299</fpage>-<lpage>309</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2710.2002.00430.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12174032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Durkin</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Use of Poisson regression and time series analysis for detecting changes over time in rates of child injury following a prevention program</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>140</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>943</fpage>-<lpage>955</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.aje.a117183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7977282</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Akaike&#8217;s information criterion in generalized estimating equations</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>120</fpage>-<lpage>125</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0006-341X.2001.00120.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11252586</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dimick</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Methods for evaluating changes in health care policy: the difference-in-differences approach</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>312</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<fpage>2401</fpage>-<lpage>2402</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2014.16153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25490331</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tarpey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Are wicked problems really so wicked: perceptions of policy problems</article-title>. <source>Policy Soc</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>218</fpage>-<lpage>236</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14494035.2019.1626595</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Case</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fiske</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Perpetuating stigma or reducing risk? Perspectives from naloxone consumers and pharmacists on pharmacy-based naloxone in 2 states</article-title>. <source>J Am Pharm Assoc (2003)</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>2S</issue>):<fpage>S19</fpage>-<lpage>S27, 27.e4</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.japh.2017.01.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28214219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baird</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bratberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacist attitudes toward pharmacy-based naloxone: a cross-sectional survey study</article-title>. <source>J Am Pharm Assoc (2003)</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>304</fpage>-<lpage>310</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.japh.2019.11.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31870862</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bratberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baird</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacy leaders&#8217; beliefs about how pharmacies can support a sustainable approach to providing naloxone to the community</article-title>. <source>Res Social Adm Pharm</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1493</fpage>-<lpage>1497</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sapharm.2020.01.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31983625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Case</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bratberg</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Beliefs associated with pharmacy-based naloxone: a qualitative study of pharmacy-based naloxone purchasers and people at risk for opioid overdose</article-title>. <source>J Urban Health</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>367</fpage>-<lpage>378</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11524-019-00349-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30747371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6565759</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Klug</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Revisiting pharmacy-based naloxone with pharmacists and naloxone consumers in 2 states: 2017 perspectives and evolving approaches</article-title>. <source>J Am Pharm Assoc (2003)</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>740</fpage>-<lpage>749</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.japh.2020.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32334964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10948012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soipe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baloy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacy on-site overdose protocols and prevention of overdose</article-title>. <source>Subst Abus</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>64</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08897077.2020.1736236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32186478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10937094</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bratberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Study protocol for the Respond to Prevent Study: a multi-state randomized controlled trial to improve provision of naloxone, buprenorphine and nonprescription syringes in community pharmacies</article-title>. <source>Subst Abus</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>901</fpage>-<lpage>905</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08897077.2021.2010162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35213293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9720900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Altekruse</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Altekruse</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Socioeconomic risk factors for fatal opioid overdoses in the United States: findings from the Mortality Disparities in American Communities Study (MDAC)</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<elocation-id>e0227966</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0227966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31951640</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6968850</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of a national commercial pharmacy naloxone data source to state and city pharmacy naloxone data sources&#8212;Rhode Island, Massachusetts, and New York City, 2013-2019</article-title>. <source>Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1141</fpage>-<lpage>1150</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1475-6773.14200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37408299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10480090</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heiman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lanh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Steck</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Electronic Advisories Increase Naloxone Prescribing Across Health Care Settings</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1402</fpage>-<lpage>1409</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-022-07876-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36376626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9663180</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sohn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Talbert</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lofwall</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Association of naloxone coprescription laws with naloxone prescription dispensing in the United States</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<elocation-id>e196215</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.6215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31225895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6593960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Doe-Simkins</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Overdose rescues by trained and untrained participants and change in opioid use among substance-using participants in overdose education and naloxone distribution programs: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-14-297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24684801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4004504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Metz</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Comer</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>No evidence of compensatory drug use risk behavior among heroin users after receiving take-home naloxone</article-title>. <source>Addict Behav</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>104</fpage>-<lpage>106</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.addbeh.2017.03.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28325710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5449215</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi240841r48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Djordjevic</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Borja</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Does naloxone provision lead to increased substance use: a systematic review to assess if there is evidence of a &#8216;moral hazard&#8217; associated with naloxone supply</article-title>. <source>Int J Drug Policy</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<elocation-id>103513</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugpo.2021.103513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34798434</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><notes notes-type="supplementary-material" id="note-ZOI240841-1"><supplementary-material id="note-ZOI240841-1-s" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplement 1.</label><caption><p><bold>eFigure.</bold> Change of Opioid Fatality Rate and Uptake of Pharmacy Naloxone Standing Order Implementation Across 351 Municipalities in Massachusetts From the First Quarter of 2013 to the Fourth Quarter of 2018</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2427236-s001.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplement 2.</label><caption><p>
Data Sharing Statement
</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2427236-s002.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></notes></back></article></pmc-articleset>