<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Dermatol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Dermatol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3211</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jamasd</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JAMA Dermatology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2168-6068</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2168-6084</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>JAMA Network</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10248813</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10248813.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10248813</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10248813</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37285130</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamadermatol.2023.1400</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">doi230020</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="domain" specific-use="print"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Investigation</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="online-first"><subject>Online First</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="allowCommenting"><subject>Comments</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Fertility Trends and Adverse Pregnancy Outcomes in Female Patients With Psoriasis in the UK</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="headline">Fertility Trends and Adverse Pregnancy Outcomes in Female Patients With Psoriasis in the UK</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Fertility Trends and Adverse Pregnancy Outcomes in Female Patients With Psoriasis in the UK</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="TC">Teng-Chou</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="doi230020aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iskandar</surname><given-names initials="IYK">Ireny Y. K.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="doi230020aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names initials="R">Rosa</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="doi230020aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names initials="M">Matthias</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="doi230020aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tower</surname><given-names initials="C">Clare</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="doi230020aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleyn</surname><given-names initials="CE">C. Elise</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="doi230020aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names initials="CEM">Christopher E. M.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="doi230020aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashcroft</surname><given-names initials="DM">Darren M.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="doi230020aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="doi230020aff7" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref></contrib><on-behalf-of>for the Global Psoriasis Atlas</on-behalf-of></contrib-group><aff id="doi230020aff1"><label>1</label>Centre for Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety, Division of Pharmacy and Optometry, School of Health Sciences, Faculty of Biology, Medicine and Health, The University of Manchester, Manchester, England, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="doi230020aff2"><label>2</label>Centre for Occupational and Environmental Health, Division of Population Health, Health Services Research and Primary Care, School of Health Sciences, Faculty of Biology, Medicine and Health, The University of Manchester, Manchester, England, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="doi230020aff3"><label>3</label>Division of Informatics, Imaging and Data Sciences, Manchester Academic Health Sciences Centre, School of Health Sciences, Faculty of Biology, Medicine and Health, The University of Manchester, Manchester, England, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="doi230020aff4"><label>4</label>Centre for Women&#8217;s Mental Health, Division of Psychology and Mental Health, School of Health Sciences, Faculty of Biology, Medicine and Health, The University of Manchester, Manchester, England, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="doi230020aff5"><label>5</label>Division of Obstetrics, St Mary&#8217;s Hospital, Manchester University NHS Foundation Trust, Manchester Academic Health Science Centre, Manchester, England, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="doi230020aff6"><label>6</label>Centre for Dermatology Research, Salford Royal NHS Foundation Trust, The University of Manchester, Manchester Academic Health Science Centre, National Institute for Health and Care Research (NIHR) Manchester Biomedical Research Centre, Manchester, England, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="doi230020aff7"><label>7</label>National Institute for Health and Care Research (NIHR) Greater Manchester Patient Safety Translational Research Centre, Manchester Academic Health Science Centre, The University of Manchester, Manchester, England, United Kingdom</aff><author-notes><title>Article Information</title><p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> April 10, 2023.</p><p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published Online:</bold> June 7, 2023. doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamadermatol.2023.1400</uri></p><p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-license-permissions" ext-link-type="uri">CC-BY License</ext-link>. &#169; 2023 Chen TC et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Dermatology</italic>.</p><corresp id="doi230020cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Teng-Chou Chen, PhD, Centre for Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety, Division of Pharmacy and Optometry, School of Health Sciences, Faculty of Biology, Medicine and Health, The University of Manchester, Oxford Road, Stopford Building, 1st Floor, Room 1.134, Manchester M13 9PT, United Kingdom (<email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="teng-chou.chen@manchester.ac.uk">teng-chou.chen@manchester.ac.uk</email>).</corresp><p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Dr Chen had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Concept and design:</italic> Chen, Iskandar, Parisi, Pierce, Griffiths, Ashcroft.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> Chen, Pierce, Tower, Kleyn, Griffiths, Ashcroft.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Chen, Griffiths.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Critical revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> All authors.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Statistical analysis:</italic> Chen, Pierce.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Obtained funding:</italic> Griffiths, Ashcroft.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Chen, Iskandar, Parisi, Tower, Kleyn.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Supervision:</italic> Griffiths, Ashcroft.</p><p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr Kleyn reported personal fees from AbbVie, Almirall, Celgene, Eli Lilly, Galderma, GSK, Leo Pharma, Janssen, Novartis, Pfizer, and UCB Pharma; grants from Almirall, Amgen, Celgene, Eli Lilly, Janssen, Novartis, Pfizer, and UCB Pharma; and nonfinancial support from Eli Lilly, Leo Pharma, Janssen, and UCB Pharma outside the submitted work. Prof Griffiths reported grants from the LEO Foundation and the International League of Dermatological Societies during the conduct of the study, as well as grants from Almirall and UCB Pharma and personal fees from AbbVie, Boehringer Ingelheim, Evelo Bioscience, Inmagene, Eli Lilly, Janssen, Novartis, GSK, Ono Pharmaceutical, and Bristol Myers Squibb outside the submitted work. Prof Ashcroft reported grants from Abbvie, Almirall, Celgene, Eli Lilly, Janssen, Novartis, UCB Pharma and the LEO Foundation during the conduct of the study. No other disclosures were reported.</p><p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> This study was funded by the International League of Dermatological Societies on behalf of the Global Psoriasis Atlas. Dr Kleyn and Profs Griffiths and Ashcroft were funded in part by the National Institute for Health and Care Research Manchester Biomedical Research Centre.</p><p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The funders had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p><p><bold>Group Information:</bold> The Global Psoriasis Atlas.</p><p><bold>Disclaimer:</bold> The interpretation and conclusions contained in this study are those of the authors alone and not necessarily those of the Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency.</p><p content-type="data-sharing-statement"><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> See <xref rid="note-DOI230020-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>.</p><p><bold>Additional Contributions:</bold> We thank all of the data providers and general practices that make anonymized data available for research. We would also like to thank the substantial contribution of the Global Psoriasis Atlas project teams at The University of Manchester for administration of the project and the key roles of the Global Psoriasis Atlas collaborating organizations: the International Psoriasis Council, the International Federation of Psoriasis Associations, and the International League of Dermatological Societies.</p><p><bold>Additional Information:</bold> This study is based on data from the Clinical Practice Research Datalink obtained under license from the UK Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency. The data are provided by patients and collected by the National Health Service as part of their care and support. Hospital Episode Statistics are subject to Crown copyright (2021) protection, reused with the permission of the Health and Social Care Information Centre, all rights reserved.</p></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-06-07T10:00"><day>7</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>159</volume><issue>7</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">437725</issue-id><fpage>736</fpage><lpage>744</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>07</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>09</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-07-21 00:25:09.467"><day>21</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright 2023 Chen TC et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Dermatology</italic>.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jamadermatol-e231400.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamadermatol-e231400.pdf">jamadermatol-e231400.pdf</self-uri><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/archderm/fullarticle/10.1001/jamadermatol.2023.1400"/><abstract abstract-type="teaser" specific-use="electronic"><p>This cohort study investigates fertility rates and obstetric outcomes of pregnancies in female patients with psoriasis compared with age- and general practice&#8211;matched comparators without psoriasis.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="key-points"><title>Key Points</title><sec id="ab-doi230020-1"><title>Question</title><p>What are the fertility rates and birth outcomes in female patients with psoriasis when compared with age- and practice-matched patients without psoriasis?</p></sec><sec id="ab-doi230020-2"><title>Findings</title><p>This cohort study included 63&#8201;681 patients with psoriasis and 318&#8201;405 matched comparators of common reproductive ages from the UK Clinical Practice Research Datalink from 1998 to 2019. Patients with moderate to severe psoriasis had lower fertility rates, and there was a slightly higher risk of pregnancy loss in patients with psoriasis.</p></sec><sec id="ab-doi230020-3"><title>Meaning</title><p>Because of the increased risk of pregnancy loss in patients with psoriasis, particularly occurring during the first trimester, future research should identify the mechanism of pregnancy loss in patients with psoriasis.</p></sec></abstract><abstract><sec id="ab-doi230020-4"><title>Importance</title><p>Evidence regarding fertility trends and obstetric outcomes among patients with psoriasis is limited by studies of small sample sizes, noninclusion of comparators, and the lack of accurate pregnancy records.</p></sec><sec id="ab-doi230020-5"><title>Objective</title><p>To investigate fertility rates and obstetric outcomes of pregnancies in female patients with psoriasis compared with age- and general practice&#8211;matched comparators without psoriasis.</p></sec><sec id="ab-doi230020-6"><title>Design, Setting, and Participants</title><p>This population-based cohort study used data from 887 primary care practices that contributed to the UK Clinical Practice Research Datalink GOLD database between 1998 and 2019, linked to a pregnancy register and Hospital Episode Statistics. There were 6&#8201;223&#8201;298 patients of common childbearing ages (15-44 years), and 63&#8201;681 patients with psoriasis had at least 1 year of follow-up data prior to the diagnosis of psoriasis. For each patient with psoriasis, 5 patients were matched by age from the same general practice. The median follow-up duration was 4.1 years. Data analysis was performed in 2021.</p></sec><sec id="ab-doi230020-7"><title>Exposures</title><p>Patients with psoriasis were identified using clinical diagnostic codes from consultations.</p></sec><sec id="ab-doi230020-8"><title>Main Outcomes and Measures</title><p>Fertility rates were calculated as the number of pregnancies per 100 patient-years. The outcomes of each pregnancy recorded in the pregnancy register or Hospital Episode Statistics were screened to identify obstetric outcomes. A negative binomial model was used to examine the association between psoriasis and the fertility rate. Logistic regression was applied to compare the association between psoriasis and obstetric outcomes.</p></sec><sec id="ab-doi230020-9"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 63&#8201;681 patients with psoriasis and 318&#8201;405 matched comparators were included in the analysis (median [IQR] age, 30 [22-37] years). Lower fertility rates (rate ratio, 0.75; 95% CI, 0.69-0.83) were found in patients with moderate to severe psoriasis. Compared with matched comparators without psoriasis, pregnancies in patients with psoriasis had a higher risk of loss (odds ratio, 1.06; 95% CI, 1.03-1.10); however, there was no increase in the risks of antenatal hemorrhage, preeclampsia, or gestational diabetes.</p></sec><sec id="ab-doi230020-10"><title>Conclusion and Relevance</title><p>In this cohort study, patients with moderate to severe psoriasis had a lower fertility rate, and the risk of pregnancy loss was higher than in matched comparators without psoriasis. Future research should identify the mechanism of increased risk of pregnancy loss among patients with psoriasis.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="H1-1-DOI230020"><title>Introduction</title><p>Psoriasis is an immune-mediated, inflammatory skin condition that has been recognized by the World Health Organization as a noncommunicable disease.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Half of patients with psoriasis are women in whom the age of diagnosis is often before 40 years.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> When coinciding with the peak reproductive period, a diagnosis of psoriasis could affect childbearing potential.</p><p>Inflammatory and autoimmune diseases have been associated with negative pregnancy outcomes.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> It has been hypothesized that proinflammatory cytokines affect endothelial cells and result in systemic and placental vasculopathy.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Psoriasis and its management could lead to a lower fertility rate and negative pregnancy outcomes, such as miscarriage, for several reasons. First, psoriasis can cause an alteration in body image and is often associated with low self-esteem and stigmatization, and may adversely affect social functioning.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Patients with moderate to severe psoriasis may be treated with systemic therapies and need appropriate counselling regarding contraception.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Moreover, unhealthy lifestyle behaviors, such as smoking, and multimorbidity, such as depression and metabolic syndrome, are more common among patients with psoriasis and are also linked to adverse pregnancy outcomes.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup></p><p>Studies that have examined fertility and pregnancy outcomes in women with psoriasis have reported conflicting findings.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> Most studies had small sample sizes (&lt;100 women) and are thus likely underpowered to detect a difference in pregnancy outcomes.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> The majority of those studies used disease registry data or lacked a matched comparison group and hence were unable to estimate the association of fertility and adverse pregnancy outcomes in women with psoriasis when compared with the general population.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup></p><p>Therefore, in this cohort study we aimed to investigate fertility and obstetric outcomes in patients with psoriasis when compared with the age- and practice-matched population using population-based electronic health records (EHRs). The objectives were to (1) explore the annual trends in fertility rates in female patients with psoriasis, (2) investigate the association between psoriasis and birth outcomes when compared with matched comparators without psoriasis, and (3) identify the association between psoriasis and adverse pregnancy outcomes.</p></sec><sec id="H1-2-DOI230020"><title>Methods</title><sec id="H2-1-DOI230020"><title>Study Design and Data Sources</title><p>This population-based cohort study used EHR data from a large UK primary care database, the Clinical Practice Research Datalink (CPRD) GOLD, from 1998 to 2019, linking to the pregnancy register, Hospital Episode Statistics (HES), and an area-level measure of deprivation.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> The pregnancy register was generated by using Read codes to screen any primary care record in CPRD GOLD; this approach has been validated using linked HES data. The study protocol was approved by the Independent Scientific Advisory Committee of the Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency, which waived need for patient informed consent owing to use of deidentified data. The study was reported according to the Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/strobe/" ext-link-type="uri">STROBE</ext-link>) reporting guideline.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="H2-2-DOI230020"><title>Study Population for Different Analytical Purposes</title><p>We identified all female patients aged 15 to 44 years during January 1998 through December 2019 to include patients of common reproductive ages. Patients with psoriasis were identified by screening relevant Read codes from clinical consultations in the EHRs. We followed patients from the latest date of receiving a diagnosis of psoriasis, age 15 years or January 1, 1998 (index date). For each patient with psoriasis, 5 comparators without psoriasis from the same primary care practice were selected and matched on year of birth. Matched comparators were assigned the same index date as the patient with psoriasis. Both patients with psoriasis and matched comparators were followed from the index date to (1) age 45 years, (2) date of death, (3) transfer out of practice, (4) last date of data collection, or (5) end of the study period (December 31, 2019), whichever occurred first. Patients were excluded from the study if they did not have at least 1 year of registration records before the index date.</p><p>All pregnancy records from patients with psoriasis and matched comparators were extracted. Pregnancy records resulting in more than 1 live-born infant (ie, multiple pregnancy, such as twins or triplets) were excluded because there was increasing risk of severe maternal outcomes.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> Based on published methods of generating pregnancy registers, conflicting pregnancy records were also excluded.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> Pregnancy records with linkage eligibility to HES were selected to identify the association between psoriasis and adverse pregnancy outcomes (<xref rid="doi230020f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="doi230020f1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1. </label><caption><title>Flowchart for Selection of Female Patients With Psoriasis and Matched Comparators and Their Pregnancy Episodes</title><p>CPRD indicates Clinical Practice Research Datalink; HES, Hospital Episode Statistics.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jamadermatol-e231400-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="H2-3-DOI230020"><title>Outcome Measures</title><p>Any pregnancy episode with a start date within the follow-up period was counted to calculate fertility rate, which also included pregnancies with an outcome of stillbirth. We screened the pregnancy outcomes in the pregnancy register to categorize birth outcomes into pregnancy loss, live birth, stillbirth, and preterm birth. Pregnancy loss was defined as pregnancies recorded as miscarriage, ectopic, molar, blighted ovum, and any unspecified loss. Live births were defined as any pregnancy episode with the outcome recorded as a live birth or delivery based on a third-trimester pregnancy record or a late pregnancy record. Pregnancies with the outcome recorded as stillbirth were defined as stillbirth. Any pregnancy episode that was not recorded as pregnancy loss or termination was categorized as delivery, and delivered pregnancy episodes with a gestation period less than 37 weeks were treated as preterm birth (eTable 1 in <xref rid="note-DOI230020-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).</p><p>For each pregnancy record, adverse pregnancy outcomes were identified using codes from the <italic toggle="yes">International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems, Tenth Revision</italic>, from HES records or Read codes from CPRD GOLD clinical files. Adverse pregnancy outcomes included venous thromboembolism, antenatal hemorrhage, preeclampsia, gestational hypertension, gestational diabetes, and cesarean delivery. Cesarean delivery was identified based on the method of delivery in the HES maternity information. Pregnancy episodes in patients with diagnosis records of hypertension or diabetes in the CPRD GOLD before the start of pregnancy were not eligible for the analysis of gestational hypertension or diabetes (eTable 1 in <xref rid="note-DOI230020-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="H2-4-DOI230020"><title>Severity of Psoriasis</title><p>Patients with psoriasis were categorized as having moderate to severe psoriasis when systemic treatments (methotrexate, apremilast, acitretin, etretinate, ciclosporin, fumaric acid esters, or hydroxycarbamide), phototherapy, or biologic therapies (adalimumab, brodalumab, certolizumab, efalizumab, etanercept, guselkumab, infliximab, ixekizumab, secukinumab, tildrakizumab, and ustekinumab) were prescribed. The severity of psoriasis was a time-dependent variable, and hence the date when patients were designated with moderate to severe psoriasis was also assigned to their matched comparators. A graphical depiction of this study is presented in eFigure 1 in <xref rid="note-DOI230020-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="H2-5-DOI230020"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>To compare characteristics between the 2 groups and adjust the association on obstetric outcomes, patients&#8217; demographic characteristics, lifestyle factors, and comorbidities before the index date and each pregnancy were identified. Demographic characteristics included age and quintile of practice-level deprivation. Lifestyle factors included body mass index, alcohol intake, and smoking status, and were determined using existing algorithms.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> Alcohol intake was categorized into nondrinker, occasional/light drinker, former drinker, moderate drinker, and heavy drinker based on UK guidance. Comorbidities that might be associated with fertility and pregnancy outcomes were identified according to published criteria.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup></p><p>During the entire follow-up period and each calendar year, fertility rates, defined as the number of pregnancies per 100 patient-years, were calculated. The annual fertility rate in each age category (&lt;20, 20-24, 25-29, 30-34, 35-39, and &#8805;40 years) was also calculated. A negative binomial model and an offset term of follow-up time was used to identify the association between psoriasis and the fertility rate. The results are presented as rate ratios (RRs) and 95% CIs.</p><p>Logistic regression was used to assess the association of birth outcomes and adverse pregnancy outcomes between patients with psoriasis and matched comparators after adjusting for potential confounding factors. The parsimonious models that contained psoriasis and potential confounding factors were presented after eliminating nonsignificant terms based on the likelihood ratio test. The results are presented as adjusted odds ratios (aORs) and 95% CIs. We conducted several sensitivity analyses to assess the robustness of the findings (eMethods in <xref rid="note-DOI230020-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).</p><p>The threshold for statistical significance was a 2-sided <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.05. All statistical analyses were conducted using Stata, version 16 (StataCorp).</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-3-DOI230020"><title>Results</title><sec id="H2-6-DOI230020"><title>Baseline Characteristics of the Study Cohort</title><p>Overall, there were 4&#8201;224&#8201;536 female patients aged 15 to 44 years in the CPRD GOLD during 1998 through 2019, and 63&#8201;681 patients with psoriasis and 318&#8201;405 comparators were included in this study. The median (IQR) age on the index date was 30 (22-37) years, and the median (IQR) follow-up duration was 4.1 (1.7-7.9) years. There were 3252 patients (5.1%) with moderate to severe psoriasis in the follow-up period, and 561 were assigned as having moderate to severe psoriasis on the index date.</p><p>Compared with matched comparators, patients with psoriasis were more likely to be current smokers, overweight, or current alcohol drinkers on the index date. Higher proportions of patients with psoriasis were diagnosed with alcohol use disorders and psychological diseases, such as depression and anxiety; in addition, patients with psoriasis were more often diagnosed with diabetes, hypertension, inflammatory bowel disease, thyroid disorders, inflammatory polyarthropathies, systemic connective tissue disorders, and respiratory diseases, such as asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (<xref rid="doi230020t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="doi230020t1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1. </label><caption><title>Baseline Characteristics of Patients With Psoriasis and Matched Comparators Without Psoriasis</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="37.59%" span="1"/><col width="20.6%" span="1"/><col width="32.08%" span="1"/><col width="9.73%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">No. (%)</th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Psoriasis (n&#8201;=&#8201;63&#8201;681)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matched comparators (n&#8201;=&#8201;318&#8201;405)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, median (IQR), y</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (22-37)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (22-37)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA<xref rid="doi230020t1n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age category, y</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;20</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#8201;787 (18.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58&#8201;932 (18.5)</td><td rowspan="6" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">NA<xref rid="doi230020t1n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 20-24</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8955 (14.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44&#8201;776 (14.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 25-29</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8201;707 (16.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53&#8201;538 (16.8)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 30-34</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#8201;696 (18.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58&#8201;483 (18.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 35-39</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8201;938 (17.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54&#8201;683 (17.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &#8805;40</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9598 (15.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47&#8201;993 (15.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quintile of index of multiple deprivation</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1 (Least deprived)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8201;340 (16.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51&#8201;700 (16.2)</td><td rowspan="5" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">NA<xref rid="doi230020t1n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8201;711 (16.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53&#8201;555 (16.8)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#8201;855 (18.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59&#8201;275 (18.6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#8201;805 (20.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64&#8201;025 (20.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5 (Most deprived)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#8201;970 (28.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89&#8201;850 (28.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body mass index</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Normal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16&#8201;406 (25.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79&#8201;671 (25.0)</td><td rowspan="5" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Overweight</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#8201;185 (17.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49&#8201;371 (15.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Obesity</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#8201;100 (17.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#8201;734 (12.8)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Underweight</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3748 (5.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8201;775 (5.9)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Missing</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#8201;242 (33.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129&#8201;854 (40.8)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking status</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Never smoked</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22&#8201;993 (36.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131&#8201;301 (41.2)</td><td rowspan="4" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Former smoker</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9297 (14.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#8201;110 (12.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Current smoker</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22&#8201;211 (34.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89&#8201;305 (28.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Missing</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9180 (14.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58&#8201;689 (18.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol intake</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Nondrinker</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5583 (8.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28&#8201;143 (8.8)</td><td rowspan="6" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Occasional/light drinker</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8898 (14.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43&#8201;634 (13.7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Former drinker</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4196 (6.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8201;438 (5.8)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Moderate drinker</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19&#8201;766 (31.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95&#8201;464 (30.0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Heavy drinker</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2974 (4.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8201;818 (3.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Missing</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22&#8201;264 (35.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121&#8201;908 (38.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychological disease or substance use issue</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Depression</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8460 (13.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29&#8201;142 (9.2)</td><td rowspan="5" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Anxiety<xref rid="doi230020t1n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2490 (3.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8265 (2.6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Psychoactive substance misuse</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">882 (1.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2855 (0.9)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Alcohol use disorder</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">578 (0.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1910 (0.6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Schizophrenia or bipolar disorder</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">419 (0.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1468 (0.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiovascular disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diabetes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">717 (1.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2701 (0.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hypertension</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1134 (1.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4796 (1.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Coronary heart disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (0.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">377 (0.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.009</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastroenterology disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Inflammatory bowel disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">478 (0.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1576 (0.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Irritable bowel syndrome</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4593 (7.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#8201;637 (6.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Peptic ulcer disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200 (0.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">921 (0.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.29</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Asthma</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4873 (7.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#8201;518 (6.8)</td><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (0.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">236 (0.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other conditions</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Rheumatoid arthritis<xref rid="doi230020t1n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1591 (2.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1850 (0.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Thyroid disorders</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1624 (2.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6482 (2.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Epilepsy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">470 (0.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2255 (0.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.04</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Chronic liver disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">119 (0.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">564 (0.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.60</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hearing loss</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2767 (4.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13&#8201;088 (4.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.007</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Migraine</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">252 (0.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1105 (0.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.06</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Systemic lupus erythematosus</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84 (0.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">340 (0.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.08</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviation: NA, not applicable.</p><fn id="doi230020t1n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>These factors were matched during comparators selection.</p></fn><fn id="doi230020t1n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Including other neurotic, stress-related, and somatoform disorders.</p></fn><fn id="doi230020t1n3"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>Including polyarthritis and other inflammatory systemic connective tissue disorders.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="H2-7-DOI230020"><title>Trends of Annual Rates of Fertility</title><p>Over the study period, patients with psoriasis had higher rates of fertility (RR, 1.30; 95% CI, 1.27-1.33; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) compared with age- and practice-matched patients without psoriasis. Following stratification according to the severity of psoriasis, patients with moderate to severe psoriasis had lower rates of fertility (RR, 0.75; 95% CI, 0.69-0.83; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001).</p><p>The annual fertility rate of patients with psoriasis increased from 8.5 per 100 patient-years in 1998 to 9.8 per 100 patient-years in 2011 and decreased to 6.5 per 100 patient-years in 2019 (eFigure 2 in <xref rid="note-DOI230020-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). Examining the annual fertility rates of patients in different age groups identified a higher annual fertility rate in some calendar years for patients with psoriasis who were 29 years or younger. Compared with matched comparators, patients with psoriasis who were older than 29 years had a similar annual fertility rate (<xref rid="doi230020f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="doi230020f2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2. </label><caption><title>Annual Fertility Rates for Female Patients With Psoriasis and Matched Comparators by Age</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jamadermatol-e231400-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="H2-8-DOI230020"><title>Risk of Adverse Birth Outcomes</title><p>Overall, 29&#8201;657 and 122&#8201;115 pregnancies in patients with psoriasis and matched comparators, respectively, between 1998 and 2019 were included. Pregnancies in patients with psoriasis were less likely to end in live birth (OR, 0.91; 95% CI, 0.88-0.93; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). In addition, the odds of pregnancy loss were statistically significantly higher in patients with psoriasis (OR, 1.06; 95% CI, 1.03-1.10; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001), and more than 95% of these (5596 of 5860) were at a gestation period shorter than 91 days. The number needed to harm for pregnancy loss was approximately 107 when comparing patients with psoriasis with age-matched comparators without psoriasis. In addition to psoriasis, patients younger than 20 years (OR, 2.04; 95% CI, 1.94-2.15; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) and between the ages of 20 and 24 years (OR, 1.35; 95% CI, 1.31-1.40; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) had a higher risk of pregnancy loss compared with patients between the ages of 25 and 34 years. There was no statistically significant difference in stillbirth (OR, 0.96; 95% CI, 0.74-1.26; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.78) and preterm birth (OR, 1.03; 95% CI, 0.96-1.09; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.43) among pregnancies in the 2 groups. The results were consistent after adjusting for demographic characteristics, lifestyle factors, socioeconomic status, and comorbidities (<xref rid="doi230020t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="doi230020t2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2. </label><caption><title>Birth Outcomes in Patients With Psoriasis and Matched Comparators Without Psoriasis</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="14.36%" span="1"/><col width="25.14%" span="1"/><col width="23.97%" span="1"/><col width="18.35%" span="1"/><col width="18.18%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Outcome</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">No. (%)</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Odds ratio (95% CI)</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Pregnancies in patients with psoriasis (n&#8201;=&#8201;29&#8201;657)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pregnancies in matched comparators (n&#8201;=&#8201;122&#8201;115)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjusted<xref rid="doi230020t2n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Live birth</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16&#8201;078 (54.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69&#8201;120 (56.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.88-0.93)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.88-0.93)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pregnancy loss</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5860 (19.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22&#8201;998 (18.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (1.03-1.10)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (1.01-1.08)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stillbirth</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (0.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286 (0.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.74-1.26)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.73-1.25)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preterm birth<xref rid="doi230020t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1350 (8.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5668 (8.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (0.96-1.09)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.95-1.08)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Outcome</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Pregnancies in patients with moderate to severe psoriasis (n&#8201;=&#8201;839)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Pregnancies in matched comparators (n&#8201;=&#8201;1588)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Crude</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Adjusted<xref rid="doi230020t2n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Live birth</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">433 (51.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">902 (56.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.69-0.96)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (0.70-0.97)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pregnancy loss</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174 (20.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">293 (18.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 (0.94-1.43)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 (0.95-1.46)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stillbirth<xref rid="doi230020t2n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preterm birth<xref rid="doi230020t2n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (8.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (8.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.67-1.54)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.67-1.54)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviation: NA, not available.</p><fn id="doi230020t2n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Adjusted by demographic characteristics, lifestyle factors, and comorbidities before the start of pregnancy. Only results from the parsimonious model that contained psoriasis and potential confounding factors were presented after eliminating nonsignificant terms.</p></fn><fn id="doi230020t2n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>The analysis included only pregnancies with delivery records (16&#8201;223 among those with psoriasis and 69&#8201;681 among matched comparators).</p></fn><fn id="doi230020t2n3"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>Due to the low number of stillbirths, the results were not reported, in line with data governance requirements to minimize potential patient disclosure.</p></fn><fn id="doi230020t2n4"><label>
<sup>d</sup>
</label><p>The analysis included only pregnancies with delivery records (436 among those with moderate to severe psoriasis and 908 among matched comparators).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Pregnancies in patients with moderate to severe psoriasis were less likely to end in live birth compared with matched comparators without psoriasis after adjusting for potential confounding factors (aOR, 0.82; 95% CI, 0.70-0.97; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.02). There were no statistically significant differences in the risks of pregnancy loss, stillbirth, and preterm birth between patients with moderate to severe psoriasis and matched comparators (<xref rid="doi230020t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The risks of adverse birth outcomes in patients with mild psoriasis were similar to these results, including among pregnancies in all patients with psoriasis (eTable 2 in <xref rid="note-DOI230020-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="H2-9-DOI230020"><title>Risk of Adverse Pregnancy Outcomes</title><p>Overall, 13&#8201;247 and 52&#8201;773 pregnancies in patients with psoriasis and matched comparators, respectively, were able to be linked to HES records. There was an increased risk of venous thromboembolism in pregnant patients with psoriasis (OR, 1.31; 95% CI, 1.07-1.59; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.008). However, there were no statistically significant differences in the risks of antenatal hemorrhage, preeclampsia, gestational hypertension, gestational diabetes, and cesarean delivery between 2 groups. After adjustment for potential confounding factors, there was no statistically significant difference in the odds of venous thromboembolism (aOR, 1.12; 95% CI, 0.91-1.37; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.28; <xref rid="doi230020t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Due to the limited number of adverse pregnancy outcomes in patients with moderate to severe psoriasis and matched comparators, the results are not presented, in line with data governance requirements to minimize potential patient disclosure. The results from the sensitivity analysis were consistent with the primary analysis (eTables 3 and 4 in <xref rid="note-DOI230020-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="doi230020t3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3. </label><caption><title>Adverse Pregnancy Outcomes in Patients With Psoriasis and Matched Comparators Without Psoriasis</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="21.23%" span="1"/><col width="23.05%" span="1"/><col width="23.19%" span="1"/><col width="14.61%" span="1"/><col width="17.92%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Outcome</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">No. (%)</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Odds ratio (95% CI)</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Pregnancies in patients with psoriasis (n&#8201;=&#8201;13&#8201;247)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pregnancies in matched comparators (n&#8201;=&#8201;52&#8201;773)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjusted<xref rid="doi230020t3n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Venous thromboembolism</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134 (1.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">410 (0.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 (1.07-1.59)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12 (0.91-1.37)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antenatal hemorrhage</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1682 (12.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6689 (12.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.95-1.06)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.92-1.03)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preeclampsia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">187 (1.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">803 (1.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 (0.79-1.09)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.78-1.07)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gestational hypertension<xref rid="doi230020t3n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">614 (4.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2505 (4.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.89-1.07)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.86-1.03)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gestational diabetes<xref rid="doi230020t3n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">319 (2.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1215 (4.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.93-1.19)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.87-1.13)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cesarean delivery<xref rid="doi230020t3n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1200 (18.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4734 (18.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (0.96-1.10)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.95-1.10)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="doi230020t3n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Adjusted by demographic characteristics, lifestyle factors, and comorbidities before the start of pregnancy. Only results from the parsimonious model that contained psoriasis and potential confounding factors were presented after eliminating nonsignificant terms.</p></fn><fn id="doi230020t3n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>The analysis included only pregnancies in which the patient was not diagnosed with hypertension before the start of pregnancy (13&#8201;119 among those with psoriasis and 52&#8201;241 among matched comparators).</p></fn><fn id="doi230020t3n3"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>The analysis included only pregnancies in which the patient was not diagnosed with diabetes before the start of pregnancy (13&#8201;145 among those with psoriasis and 52&#8201;447 among matched comparators).</p></fn><fn id="doi230020t3n4"><label>
<sup>d</sup>
</label><p>The analysis included only pregnancies with delivery records and linkage eligibility to Hospital Episode Statistics maternity data (6362 among those with psoriasis and 25&#8201;647 among matched comparators).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="H1-4-DOI230020"><title>Discussion</title><p>Higher fertility rates were found in patients with psoriasis, especially among those aged between 15 and 29 years, but lower fertility rates were found in patients who had moderate to severe psoriasis. Overall, the fertility rates of patients with psoriasis followed the national fertility trends.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> However, live birth was less likely to occur in patients with psoriasis. In addition, the risk of pregnancy loss was higher when compared with the matched population, and most of these losses occurred in the first trimester. A higher proportion of pregnant patients with psoriasis were diagnosed with venous thromboembolism, but no statistically significant difference was found after adjustment for potential confounding factors.</p><p>A US study that used a claims database showed a small increase in fertility rate (RR, 1.1; 95% CI, 1.0-1.2) in women with psoriasis.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> The present study found a higher fertility rate (RR, 1.30; 95% CI, 1.27-1.33) when using a pregnancy registry that systematically identified pregnancies.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> Underrecording fertility in a claims database would lead to a nondifferential misclassification error.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> Regarding birth outcomes, Lima et al<sup><xref rid="doi230020r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> included 122 women with psoriasis and 290 comparators in their study and reported a nonsignificant association between psoriasis and pregnancy loss due to the limited sample size. By comparing more than 63&#8201;000 patients with psoriasis with 318&#8201;000 comparators, the present study found a statistically significant association between psoriasis and pregnancy loss, and the results are similar to a case-control study.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> Consistent with studies from the US, Denmark, Sweden, and Taiwan,<sup><xref rid="doi230020r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> we also showed no difference in preterm birth.</p><p>A meta-analysis showed a higher risk of preeclampsia, gestational hypertension, and gestational diabetes in women with psoriasis<sup><xref rid="doi230020r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>; this differs from the present findings. However, due to the variation in study design, marked heterogeneity existed even though subgroup analyses were performed. Previous published studies reported no statistically significant increases in the risk of gestational hypertension and preeclampsia in patients with psoriasis, which might be related to the small sample sizes.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> However, the present study echoes their results when using a much larger UK primary care database. Although cardiovascular diseases were common in patients with psoriasis, we only included female patients of common reproductive ages, and this might explain the nonsignificant association with gestational hypertension and gestational diabetes.</p><p>Of particular note, we observed an increased risk of pregnancy loss in patients with psoriasis. The mechanism to link the higher risk of pregnancy loss in patients with psoriasis is not clear, but there might be potential explanations. Psoriasis is characterized by the increased activity of IL-17, IL-23, and tumor necrosis factor &#945;.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> Those proinflammatory cytokines may negatively affect the placenta and cause impaired fetal growth.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup></p><p>Pregnancy loss has been linked with adverse consequences, such as depression,<sup><xref rid="doi230020r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> and the annual national economic cost of pregnancy loss is around &#163;471 million in the UK.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> We found that pregnancy loss occurred in about 1 in 5 pregnancies in patients with psoriasis, and approximately 95% of these occurred in the first trimester, which was probably unavoidable due to chromosomal errors. A Danish study indicated a higher risk of ectopic pregnancy in women with psoriasis,<sup><xref rid="doi230020r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> which often complicates pregnancies in the first trimester and might explain the higher risk of loss in the present study. Due to the small effect size of pregnancy loss (19.8% vs 18.8%), it is unclear if better management of psoriasis and close monitoring could balance maternal benefit and risk. There is a need for studies exploring the mechanism of pregnancy loss in patients with psoriasis. In addition, general practitioners in primary care, where the diagnosis of psoriasis may be missed and hence the treatment may be delayed, should be aware of the increased risk of early pregnancy loss, especially for younger patients with psoriasis.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup></p><p>This study used a large EHR database that is representative in terms of age and gender distribution, and hence the results could be generalized to the population.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> To the best of our knowledge, this is one of the largest studies investigating fertility and obstetric outcomes in psoriasis.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> Linkage with pregnancy registry and HES data provides more accurate records regarding timing and outcomes of pregnancies, minimizing misclassification of study outcomes.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> Compared with administrative birth records, which include only pregnancies that end in live births or stillbirths, the use of a pregnancy registry enables the risk of pregnancy loss to be quantified.</p><sec id="H2-10-DOI230020"><title>Limitations</title><p>There are some limitations. Due to the lack of direct measures of psoriasis severity, we used surrogates for moderate to severe psoriasis, which are commonly used in published studies using EHR databases.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="doi230020r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> Although we applied a large EHR database, due to the lower fertility rate, there were a limited number of adverse pregnancy outcomes in patients with moderate to severe psoriasis. In addition, we could only adjust the influence of ethnicity on adverse pregnancy outcomes that were identified in patients with linkage eligibility to HES records because only a small proportion of all patients in the CPRD GOLD have ethnicity recorded.<sup><xref rid="doi230020r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> Although the majority of patients report their pregnancies to primary care in the UK,<sup><xref rid="doi230020r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> for patients who are not aware of the pregnancy or who did not contact their general practitioner and experienced a miscarriage, they will not be included in the pregnancy register.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-5-DOI230020"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In this cohort study, patients with psoriasis had higher rates of fertility when compared with those without psoriasis, but lower fertility rates were found when patients developed moderate to severe psoriasis. Of particular note, pregnancy loss was more common in patients with psoriasis. To avoid miscarriage and its adverse consequences, further studies should evaluate the effects of better management of psoriasis and close monitoring during pregnancy on pregnancy loss. In particular, patients with psoriasis were more likely to have comorbidities that may be related to poor pregnancy outcomes, and hence increased emphasis of managing comorbidities as part of the routine management plan is also warranted.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="REF-DOI230020"><title>References</title><ref id="doi230020r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">Global report on psoriasis. <person-group><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>. October 26, <year>2016</year>. Accessed April 24, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789241565189" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789241565189</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Springate</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kontopantelis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ashcroft</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Incidence, prevalence and mortality of patients with psoriasis: a U.K. population-based cohort study</article-title>. <source>Br J Dermatol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>176</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>650</fpage>-<lpage>658</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bjd.15021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27579733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5363241</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Iskandar</surname><given-names>IYK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>CEM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ashcroft</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>; <collab>Global Psoriasis Atlas</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Systematic review examining changes over time and variation in the incidence and prevalence of psoriasis by age and gender</article-title>. <source>Br J Dermatol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>184</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>243</fpage>-<lpage>258</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bjd.19169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32358790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fallow</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Silman</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Women with inflammatory polyarthritis have babies of lower birth weight</article-title>. <source>J Rheumatol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>355</fpage>-<lpage>359</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11246676</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Molina-Leyva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jim&#233;nez-Mole&#243;n</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Naranjo-Sintes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz-Carrascosa</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Sexual dysfunction in psoriasis: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>649</fpage>-<lpage>655</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jdv.12845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25424331</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sumpton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tunnicliffe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Patients&#8217; perspectives and experience of psoriasis and psoriatic arthritis: a systematic review and thematic synthesis of qualitative studies</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken)</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>711</fpage>-<lpage>722</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/acr.23896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30927508</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rademaker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Agnew</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>The Australasian Psoriasis Collaboration</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Psoriasis in those planning a family, pregnant or breast-feeding</article-title>. <source>Australas J Dermatol</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>86</fpage>-<lpage>100</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ajd.12641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28543445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vena</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cassano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bellia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Psoriasis in pregnancy: challenges and solutions</article-title>. <source>Psoriasis (Auckl)</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>83</fpage>-<lpage>95</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29387585</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/PTT.S82975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5683115</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gelfand</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Neimann</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Margolis</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Troxel</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of myocardial infarction in patients with psoriasis</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>296</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1735</fpage>-<lpage>1741</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.296.14.1735</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17032986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Increased risk of acute myocardial infarction in patients with psoriasis: a 5-year population-based study in Taiwan</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>495</fpage>-<lpage>501</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2010.01.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21216492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Psoriasis and increased risk of ischemic stroke in Taiwan: a nationwide study</article-title>. <source>J Dermatol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>279</fpage>-<lpage>281</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1346-8138.2011.01401.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22035230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ellervik</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yazdanyar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jemec</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Meta-analysis of psoriasis, cardiovascular disease, and associated risk factors</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1014</fpage>-<lpage>1024</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2013.06.053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24238156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harskamp</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Psoriasis and metabolic syndrome: a systematic review and meta-analysis of observational studies</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>654</fpage>-<lpage>662</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2012.08.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23360868</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bobotsis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gulliver</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Monaghan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lynde</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Psoriasis and adverse pregnancy outcomes: a systematic review of observational studies</article-title>. <source>Br J Dermatol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>175</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>464</fpage>-<lpage>472</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bjd.14547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26991866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Maternal and neonatal outcomes in pregnant women with psoriasis and psoriatic arthritis: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Rheumatology (Oxford)</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>4018</fpage>-<lpage>4028</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/rheumatology/keab357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33878171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen-Barak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nachum</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rozenman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ziv</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Pregnancy outcomes in women with moderate-to-severe psoriasis</article-title>. <source>J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1041</fpage>-<lpage>1047</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1468-3083.2010.03917.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21108670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kimball</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guenther</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kalia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pregnancy outcomes in women with moderate-to-severe psoriasis from the Psoriasis Longitudinal Assessment and Registry (PSOLAR)</article-title>. <source>JAMA Dermatol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>157</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>301</fpage>-<lpage>306</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamadermatol.2020.5595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33533924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7859871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Minassian</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Meeraus</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smeeth</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>OMR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Methods to generate and validate a Pregnancy Register in the UK Clinical Practice Research Datalink primary care database</article-title>. <source>Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>923</fpage>-<lpage>933</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pds.4811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31197928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6618019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">The Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) Statement: guidelines for reporting observational studies. <person-group><collab>EQUATOR Network</collab></person-group>. Updated March 6, 2023. Accessed April 24, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/strobe/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/strobe/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cheong-See</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schuit</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Arroyo-Manzano</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>Global Obstetrics Network (GONet) Collaboration</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Prospective risk of stillbirth and neonatal complications in twin pregnancies: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>354</volume>:<fpage>i4353</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.i4353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27599496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5013231</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kontopantelis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Springate</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Longitudinal multiple imputation approaches for body mass index or other variables with very low individual-level variability: the mibmi command in Stata</article-title>. <source>BMC Res Notes</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>41</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13104-016-2365-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28086961</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5234260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Alcohol-related mortality in patients with psoriasis: a population-based cohort study</article-title>. <source>JAMA Dermatol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>153</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1256</fpage>-<lpage>1262</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamadermatol.2017.3225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28914955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5817445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lunt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>Identification and Management of Psoriasis Associated ComorbidiTy (IMPACT) project team</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Psoriasis and the risk of major cardiovascular events: cohort study using the Clinical Practice Research Datalink</article-title>. <source>J Invest Dermatol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>135</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2189</fpage>-<lpage>2197</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jid.2015.87</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25742120</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mendonca</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Development and validation of the Cambridge Multimorbidity Score</article-title>. <source>CMAJ</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>192</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>E107</fpage>-<lpage>E114</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1503/cmaj.190757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32015079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7004217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">Conceptions in England and Wales: 2018. <person-group><collab>Office for National Statistics</collab></person-group>. Accessed April 24, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/birthsdeathsandmarriages/conceptionandfertilityrates/bulletins/conceptionstatistics/2018" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/birthsdeathsandmarriages/conceptionandfertilityrates/bulletins/conceptionstatistics/2018</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seeger</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lanza</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rivero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Pregnancy and pregnancy outcome among women with inflammatory skin diseases</article-title>. <source>Dermatology</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>214</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>32</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000096910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17191045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Margulis</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Palmsten</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Beginning and duration of pregnancy in automated health care databases: review of estimation methods and validation results</article-title>. <source>Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>335</fpage>-<lpage>342</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pds.3743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25627986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jurek</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Greenland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maldonado</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Church</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Proper interpretation of non-differential misclassification effects: expectations vs observations</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>680</fpage>-<lpage>687</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyi060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15802377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>XT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Janakiraman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kimball</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of psoriasis on pregnancy outcomes</article-title>. <source>J Invest Dermatol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>132</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>85</fpage>-<lpage>91</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jid.2011.271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21918537</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Egeberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jimenez-Solem</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Skov</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thomsen</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Psoriasis and adverse pregnancy outcomes: a nationwide case-control study in 491,274 women in Denmark</article-title>. <source>JAAD Int</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>146</fpage>-<lpage>155</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdin.2022.03.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35497641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9043664</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Psoriasis and pregnancy outcomes: a nationwide population-based study</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>71</fpage>-<lpage>77</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2010.02.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20970879</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Br&#246;ms</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haerskjold</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Granath</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kieler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Berglind</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of maternal psoriasis on pregnancy and birth outcomes: a population-based cohort study from Denmark and Sweden</article-title>. <source>Acta Derm Venereol</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>98</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>728</fpage>-<lpage>734</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2340/00015555-2923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29542809</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>CEM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gudjonsson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>JNWN</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Psoriasis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>397</volume>(<issue>10281</issue>):<fpage>1301</fpage>-<lpage>1315</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)32549-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33812489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guven</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Coskun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ertas</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aral</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zencirci</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Oksuz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Association of maternal serum CRP, IL-6, TNF-alpha, homocysteine, folic acid and vitamin B12 levels with the severity of preeclampsia and fetal birth weight</article-title>. <source>Hypertens Pregnancy</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>190</fpage>-<lpage>200</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10641950802601179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19437229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fried</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Muga</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Misore</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Malaria elicits type 1 cytokines in the human placenta: IFN-gamma and TNF-alpha associated with pregnancy outcomes</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>160</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>2523</fpage>-<lpage>2530</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.160.5.2523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9498798</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nynas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Narang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kolikonda</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lippmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Depression and anxiety following early pregnancy loss: recommendations for primary care providers</article-title>. <source>Prim Care Companion CNS Disord</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4088/PCC.14r01721</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26137360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4468887</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Farren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell-Jones</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Verbakel</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Timmerman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jalmbrant</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bourne</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The psychological impact of early pregnancy loss</article-title>. <source>Hum Reprod Update</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>731</fpage>-<lpage>749</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humupd/dmy025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30204882</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Quenby</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gallos</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dhillon-Smith</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Miscarriage matters: the epidemiological, physical, psychological, and economic costs of early pregnancy loss</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>397</volume>(<issue>10285</issue>):<fpage>1658</fpage>-<lpage>1667</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)00682-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33915094</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abo-Tabik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ashcroft</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>; <collab>Global Psoriasis Atlas</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Mapping opportunities for the earlier diagnosis of psoriasis in primary care settings in the UK: results from two matched case-control studies</article-title>. <source>Br J Gen Pract</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>724</issue>):<fpage>e834</fpage>-<lpage>e841</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3399/BJGP.2022.0137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36192358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9550319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Herrett</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bhaskaran</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Data resource profile: Clinical Practice Research Datalink (CPRD)</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>827</fpage>-<lpage>836</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyv098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26050254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4521131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>van Staa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Puri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Recent advances in the utility and use of the General Practice Research Database as an example of a UK Primary Care Data resource</article-title>. <source>Ther Adv Drug Saf</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>89</fpage>-<lpage>99</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2042098611435911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25083228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4110844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mathur</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bhaskaran</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chaturvedi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Completeness and usability of ethnicity data in UK-based primary care and hospital databases</article-title>. <source>J Public Health (Oxf)</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>684</fpage>-<lpage>692</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pubmed/fdt116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24323951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4245896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="doi230020r43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Redshaw</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brocklehurst</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hockley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. National survey of women&#8217;s experience of maternity care <year>2006</year>. Accessed May 4, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.npeu.ox.ac.uk/research/projects/26-nms-2006" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.npeu.ox.ac.uk/research/projects/26-nms-2006</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><notes notes-type="supplementary-material" id="note-DOI230020-1"><supplementary-material id="note-DOI230020-1-s" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplement 1.</label><caption><p><bold>eTable 1.</bold> Definitions of adverse birth outcomes and pregnancy outcomes and the data sources</p><p><bold>eTable 2.</bold> Birth outcomes in women with or without mild psoriasis</p><p><bold>eTable 3.</bold> The results of sensitivity analysis on fertility and birth outcomes</p><p><bold>eTable 4.</bold> The results of sensitivity analysis on pregnancy outcomes</p><p><bold>eFigure 1.</bold> Graphical depiction of study design and follow-up</p><p><bold>eFigure 2.</bold> Annual rate of fertility of women with psoriasis when compared to matched comparator</p><p><bold>eMethods.</bold> Explanation of sensitivity analysis</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jamadermatol-e231400-s001.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplement 2.</label><caption><p>Data Sharing Statement</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jamadermatol-e231400-s002.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></notes></back></article></pmc-articleset>