<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">CMAJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">CMAJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">77</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cmaj</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">9711805</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>CMAJ : Canadian Medical Association Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0820-3946</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1488-2329</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Canadian Medical Association</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11810442</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11810442.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11810442</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11810442</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39929491</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1503/cmaj.241542</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">197e122</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effect of emergency department opioid prescribing on health outcomes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names initials="J">Jake</given-names></name><degrees>MD MPH</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosychuk</surname><given-names initials="RJ">Rhonda J.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McRae</surname><given-names initials="AD">Andrew D.</given-names></name><degrees>MD PhD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinnarajah</surname><given-names initials="A">Aynharan</given-names></name><degrees>MD MPH</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names initials="K">Kathryn</given-names></name><degrees>MD MSc</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanguay</surname><given-names initials="R">Robert</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names initials="L">Lori</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names initials="A">Andrew</given-names></name><degrees>MA MSc</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Innes</surname><given-names initials="G">Grant</given-names></name><degrees>MD MHSc</degrees></contrib><aff id="af1-197e122">Department of Emergency Medicine (Hayward), University of Alberta; Department of Pediatrics (Rosychuk), University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alta.; Departments of Emergency Medicine and Community Health Sciences (McRae, Innes), University of Calgary, Calgary, Alta.; Department of Medicine (Sinnarajah), Queen&#8217;s University, Kingston, Ont.; Department of Emergency Medicine, Faculty of Medicine &amp; Dentistry (Dong), University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alta.; Hotchkiss Brain Institute of Psychiatry, Psychology and Neuroscience (Tanguay), University of Calgary; Department of Family Medicine (Montgomery), University of Calgary, Calgary, Alta.; Alberta Health Services (Huang), Edmonton, Alta.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1-197e122">Correspondence to: Grant Innes, <email>grant.innes@ahs.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>10</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>197</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">481825</issue-id><fpage>E122</fpage><lpage>E130</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>10</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-04-19 00:25:27.313"><day>19</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2025 CMA Impact Inc. or its licensors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0) licence, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided that the original publication is properly cited, the use is noncommercial (i.e., research or educational use), and no modifications or adaptations are made. See: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="197e122.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="alt-language" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="article-commentary" vol="197" page="E133" journal-id="CMAJ" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11810449"><article-title>Preventing harms from first prescriptions of opioids</article-title><volume>197</volume><issue>5</issue><date><day>10</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date><fpage>E133</fpage><lpage>E134</lpage><source>CMAJ : Canadian Medical Association Journal</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11810449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39929493</pub-id></related-article><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="companion" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="article-commentary" journal-id="CMAJ" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11810449"><article-title>Preventing harms from first prescriptions of opioids</article-title><volume>197</volume><issue>5</issue><date><day>10</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date><fpage>E133</fpage><lpage>E134</lpage><source>CMAJ : Canadian Medical Association Journal</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11810449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39929493</pub-id></related-article><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="companion" xml:lang="fr" xlink:title="article-commentary" journal-id="CMAJ" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC12007950"><article-title>Pr&#233;vention des m&#233;faits d&#232;s la premi&#232;re prescription d&#8217;opio&#239;des</article-title><volume>197</volume><issue>14</issue><date><day>14</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><fpage>E400</fpage><lpage>E402</lpage><source>CMAJ : Canadian Medical Association Journal</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12007950</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40228841</pub-id></related-article><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>The relation between emergency department opioid prescribing and subsequent harm is complex and poorly studied. We sought to quantify adverse outcomes, incremental risk, and rates of prolonged opioid use among emergency department patients receiving an opioid prescription and propensity-matched controls.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>We used administrative data to sample all Alberta emergency department visits over 10 years, excluding patients with cancer, palliative care, or concurrent opioid use. Treated patients filled an opioid prescription within 72 hours after their index visit; untreated patients did not. We generated propensity scores to identify matched controls among untreated patients. The 1-year primary composite outcome included opioid-related emergency visits (e.g., overdoses), new opioid agonist therapy, all-cause hospital admission, or death. The secondary outcome was prolonged opioid use.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>After 13 028 575 eligible visits, 689 074 patients (5.3%) filled an opioid prescription. The mean age was 43.9 years, and 49.8% of patients were female. Most were high-acuity patients with traumatic, gastrointestinal&#8211;genitourinary, or musculoskeletal complaints. Patients who received opioids experienced 1.4% more primary outcome events (17.1% v. 15.7%), driven by all-cause hospital admissions (16.4% v. 15.1%; number needed to harm [NNH] = 53) and prolonged opioid use (4.5% v. 3.3%; NNH = 59). Opioid-related visits, new opioid agonist treatment, and mortality were unaffected. Incremental risk was low for patients with documented mental health conditions or substance use, and was highest for opioid-naive patients, older patients, and males.</p></sec><sec><title>Interpretation:</title><p>Emergency department opioid prescriptions were associated with small increases in subsequent opioid prescription use and hospital admission, particularly in older and opioid-naive patients, and males; they were not associated with overdoses, new opioid agonist therapy, or mortality. Physicians should understand patient-specific incremental risks when prescribing opioids for acute pain.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="CS1">The Canadian Institutes of Health Research</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><p>
<related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="alt-language" id="RA1" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="article-commentary" vol="197" page="E133" journal-id="CMAJ" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11810449">See related article at www.cmaj.ca/lookup/doi/10.1503/cmaj.250094</related-article>
</p></notes></front><body><p>Opioid prescriptions are a factor in some overdose-related deaths,<xref rid="b1-197e122" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="b4-197e122" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> and this awareness has driven substantial reductions in prescribing.<xref rid="b5-197e122" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="b7-197e122" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Despite these reductions, mortality has increased, with more than 500 000 opioid-related deaths in North America since 2016.<xref rid="b8-197e122" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="b10-197e122" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> In Alberta, Canada, the proportion of people who filled an opioid prescription dropped 35% between 2016 and 2021, but opioid-related deaths tripled, from 554 to 1510 per year, largely because of potent opioids in the illegal market.<xref rid="b7-197e122" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></p><p>The relation between emergency department opioid prescribing and harm is complex.<xref rid="b11-197e122" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Emergency physicians face growing pressure to curtail opioid prescribing<xref rid="b12-197e122" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> but must manage severe pain and treat opioid-tolerant patients who can no longer access opioids from their physicians.<xref rid="b13-197e122" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> There is little research to guide them.<xref rid="b14-197e122" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> The few guidelines that address opioids for acute pain provide generic advice to avoid replacement opioids, potent or sustained-release opioids, high daily doses, and prolonged prescription durations.<xref rid="b15-197e122" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="b18-197e122" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> None discuss risk stratification or modified approaches for different patients.</p><p>Previous studies of opioid prescribing in the emergency department involved mostly older opioid-naive American Medicare populations and assessed a primary outcome of prolonged prescription opioid use, with estimates of number needed to harm (NNH) from 7 to 300 prescriptions to cause an episode of prolonged use.<xref rid="b1-197e122" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="b2-197e122" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="b19-197e122" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="b20-197e122" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Prolonged use is important but not synonymous with adverse health consequences. Therefore, we chose to study additional outcomes.</p><p>We sought to quantify, for emergency department patients filling an opioid prescription, the likelihood of adverse outcomes, the incremental risk to opioid-treated patients compared with propensity-matched controls, and rates of prolonged opioid use for these groups.</p><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Setting</title><p>We performed a population-based observational cohort study using linked administrative data to sample all patients discharged from an emergency department in the province of Alberta, Canada, over a 10-year period. We adhered to the Reporting of Studies Conducted Using Observational Routinely-Collected Health Data statement.<xref rid="b21-197e122" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></p></sec><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Patients</title><p>Patients older than 12 years who were discharged from an Alberta emergency department between January 2010 and June 2020 were eligible. We excluded patients with opioid use disorder or prolonged opioid use (defined below) during the year preceding their index visit. We excluded patients with a cancer diagnosis or who received palliative care in the 6 months before or after their index visit. A patient was deemed to have cancer if data recorded them as having a cancer-related visit, taking chemotherapy, or having active cancer other than nonmelanoma skin cancer in the provincial cancer registry. Patients were deemed as palliative if data recorded an <italic toggle="yes">International Classification of Diseases, 10th Revision</italic> (ICD-10) code Z51.5. We excluded patients who left against medical advice or were admitted to hospital during their index visit, because they did not have the opportunity to receive prescriptions from the emergency department when they left. Our unit of analysis was the emergency department visit. Patients who had no outcome event during a 1-year washout period were eligible for re-enrolment.</p></sec><sec><title>Comparator groups</title><p>Treated patients filled an opioid prescription (codeine, morphine, hydrocodone, hydromorphone, tramadol, meperidine, fentanyl, or oxycodone) within 72 hours after their index visit. Untreated patients did not. We generated propensity scores to identify matched controls among untreated patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Outcomes</title><p>The 1-year primary composite outcome included opioid-specific events (opioid-related emergency department visits [ICD-10: F11, T40.0&#8211;T40.4 or T40.6], or new opioid agonist therapy), all-cause hospital admission, or death. Opioid-related emergency department visits and new opioid agonist treatment are proxies for progression to opioid use disorder. All-cause hospital admissions reflect major health events, and mortality is the measure most relevant to the opioid epidemic. We included all-cause outcomes because opioids generate diverse harms through gastrointestinal dysfunction, immune suppression, injury, mental illness, and other mechanisms that may not be identified as specific to opioids.<xref rid="b22-197e122" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> If no indication was present in the health record that an encounter was related to opioids, we considered it an all-cause event. Secondary outcomes included prolonged opioid use (&gt; 120 days of prescribed opioids), the measure preferred by previous researchers, and cumulative morphine milligram equivalents (MMEs) dispensed 30&#8211;365 days after the emergency department visit.<xref rid="b19-197e122" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="b23-197e122" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> We excluded dispensations between 0 and 30 days to avoid correlation with the index prescription.<xref rid="b19-197e122" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Data collection</title><p>Alberta Health Services (AHS) operates all hospitals and compiles health information for all Alberta residents. The AHS Pharmaceutical Information Network records agent, dose, and amount dispensed for all prescriptions. The AHS data warehouse collates patient demographic characteristics and health information, including ICD-10 diagnoses, Canadian Institute for Health Information health conditions, and health profile groups. Health conditions are based on ICD diagnostic codes from the Discharge Abstract Database, the National Ambulatory Care Reporting System, Continuing Care Reporting System, and patient-level billing data. Patients may have several health conditions, so their health status is categorized by mapping these to 239 health profile groups, each based on the most complex conditions. Alberta Health Services analysts linked these data sources and prepared study databases.</p></sec><sec><title>Covariates</title><p>We categorized patients by opioid status in the preceding year. Patients with opioid use disorder had an opioid-related ICD-10 code (F11 [mental and behavioural disorders due to opioids], T40.0&#8211;T40.4, T40.6 [opioid poisoning]);<xref rid="b24-197e122" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="b25-197e122" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> a positive opioid toxicology screen; or opioid agonist therapy with methadone, Kadian, or buprenorphine. Patients with prior opioid exposure had 1 or more opioid prescriptions but no opioid use disorder criteria. Opioid-naive patients had no opioid prescriptions and no opioid use disorder criteria. We documented visit time, arrival mode, and acuity, based on the 5-level Canadian Triage and Acuity Score. We captured ICD-10 discharge diagnoses to categorize complaint type, documented length of stay as a visit complexity marker, and recorded the number of emergency department visits in the prior year to determine utilization patterns. We measured demographic characteristics, including age, sex, and socioeconomic status based on Pampalon deprivation quintiles.<xref rid="b26-197e122" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> The Pampalon deprivation index is a proxy for socioeconomic status in administrative databases, representing inequality in material resources and social supports. We identified comorbid conditions, including mental health and substance use disorders, at the time of the index visit using health profile groupings. We used Pharmaceutical Information Network data to identify active medications at the time of the emergency department visit, opioid prescriptions at discharge, opioid prescriptions, and cumulative MMEs dispensed after discharge.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>We prepared descriptive summaries of patient characteristics. We developed logistic regression models to generate propensity scores representing the conditional probability of opioid treatment for each eligible visit, using the following covariates: age, sex, complaint type, visit year, visit time (day, evening, night), arrival mode (ambulance v. ambulatory), triage acuity, number of prior emergency department visits, deprivation category, number of documented health conditions, mental health or substance use disorders, psychotropic or analgesic prescriptions within a year, prior opioid exposure status, and index visit length of stay. We used standardized mean differences to assess covariate balance, with discrepancies greater than 0.10 suggesting imbalance.<xref rid="b27-197e122" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Because of the large data set, we randomly partitioned the data into 10 subsets. We used the MatchIt package in R to perform 1-to-1 nearest neighbour matching without replacement within each subset, then combined subset results.<xref rid="b28-197e122" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="b29-197e122" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Propensity models were assessed by comparing residual covariate balance, standardized mean differences, and propensity score distributions.<xref rid="b30-197e122" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="b32-197e122" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></p><p>After comparing treated and control groups, we performed a second-level regression using the above variables to adjust for residual covariate imbalance, then estimated the causal effect of an opioid prescription for defined outcomes.<xref rid="b33-197e122" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="b34-197e122" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> For our primary outcome we calculated adjusted odds ratios (ORs) with 95% confidence intervals (CIs) and determined NNH using adjusted ORs rather than crude risk differences.<xref rid="b35-197e122" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="b36-197e122" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Because data on cumulative MME were skewed, we performed a natural log transformation before regression analysis so that the coefficient for treatment would represent a multiplicative effect.</p><p>We evaluated subgroups defined by age, sex, previous opioid status, mental health diagnosis, and substance use disorder. We repeated analyses within each subgroup, then used multivariable logistic regression to identify factors associated with adverse outcomes in patients receiving opioids. As with earlier analyses, subgroup evaluations compared treated patients with matched controls.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethics approval</title><p>The University of Calgary Research Ethics Board approved this study.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>During the 10-year study, 18 133 370 visits to the emergency department occurred (<xref rid="f1-197e122" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>), including 13 028 575 eligible visits. Of these, 689 074 patients (5.3%) filled an opioid prescription. Opioid-treated patients were more likely than untreated patients to have previous opioid prescriptions, high triage acuity, and trauma or musculoskeletal pain. They were less likely to have mental health diagnoses or multiple prior visits. After propensity matching, opioid-treated patients were similar to controls on all measured parameters. The mean age was 43.9 years, and 49.8% of patients were female (<xref rid="t1-197e122" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Most had high triage acuity with traumatic, gastrointestinal&#8211;genitourinary, or musculoskeletal complaints. A total of 15.6% had 3 or more emergency visits the previous year, and 4.8% and 3.8%, respectively, had documented mental health or non-opioid substance use disorders.</p><fig position="float" id="f1-197e122" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1:</label><caption><p>Flowchart of the participant selection process. <sup>*</sup>Previously enrolled and within the 1-year outcome assessment period (i.e., the visit was considered an outcome event rather than an index encounter). See Related Content tab for accessible version.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="197e122f1.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t1-197e122" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1:</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of eligible patients who visited the emergency department (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 13 028 575)</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="2" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th colspan="3" valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1">% of patients<xref rid="tfn2-197e122" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="2" align="center" scope="col" colspan="1">SMD<xref rid="tfn3-197e122" ref-type="table-fn">&#8224;</xref></th></tr><tr><th valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Untreated (all)<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12 339 501</th><th valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treated<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 689 074</th><th valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matched control<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 689 074</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, yr, mean &#177; SD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.8 &#177; 20.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.7 &#177; 17.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.0 &#177; 19.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex, female</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMS arrival</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1">CTAS acuity level<xref rid="tfn4-197e122" ref-type="table-fn">&#8225;</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Index complaint type</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;CNS or neurologic</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Trauma</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Gastrointestinal&#8211;genitourinary</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Cardiovascular&#8211;respiratory</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Musculoskeletal</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Eyes or ears, nose, and throat</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Mental health</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1">Visit time</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Day</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Evening</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">372</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Night</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1">Emergency visits in prior year</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1&#8211;2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8805; 3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1">Social deprivation quintile<xref rid="tfn5-197e122" ref-type="table-fn">&#167;</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1 (least deprivation)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;5 (most deprivation)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1">Material deprivation quintile<xref rid="tfn5-197e122" ref-type="table-fn">&#167;</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1 (least deprivation)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;5 (most deprivation)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbidity count, median (IQR)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (4&#8211;0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (4&#8211;10)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (4&#8211;10)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Affective disorder</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychotic disorder</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Personality disorder</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other substance use disorder</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prior opioid exposure</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychoactive medication</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Index emergency department LOS, mean &#177; SD, min</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">172 &#177; 181</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197 &#177; 183</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202 &#177; 210</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1-197e122"><p>Note: CNS = central nervous system, CTAS = Canadian Triage and Acuity Scale, EMS = emergency medical service, IQR = interquartile range, LOS = length of stay, SD = standard deviation, SMD = standardized mean difference.</p></fn><fn id="tfn2-197e122"><label>*</label><p>Unless stated otherwise.</p></fn><fn id="tfn3-197e122"><label>&#8224;</label><p>Standardized mean difference refers to comparisons between treated patients and matched controls.</p></fn><fn id="tfn4-197e122"><label>&#8225;</label><p>Canadian Triage and Acuity Scale levels 1&#8211;5 refer to patients in the resuscitation, emergent, urgent, less urgent, and nonurgent categories, respectively.</p></fn><fn id="tfn5-197e122"><label>&#167;</label><p>About 10% of study patients had missing Pampalon deprivation data.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Opioid-treated patients had worse outcomes than controls (<xref rid="t2-197e122" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), with a 1.4% increase of absolute risk in the primary composite outcome (17.1% v. 15.7%). After adjustment for residual covariate imbalance, the adjusted OR was 1.15 (95% CI 1.14&#8211;1.16), and the number of opioid prescriptions needed to cause 1 primary outcome (NNH) was 52. Composite outcome differences were driven by all-cause hospital admission (16.4% v. 15.1%; adjusted OR 1.15, 95% CI 1.14&#8211;1.16; NNH = 53), not by opioid-specific events or mortality.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="t2-197e122" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2:</label><caption><p>One-year outcomes for all eligible patients</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="2" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Outcome</th><th colspan="3" valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1">% of patients<xref rid="tfn7-197e122" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="2" align="center" scope="col" colspan="1">Adjusted OR<xref rid="tfn8-197e122" ref-type="table-fn">&#8224;</xref> (95% CI)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="2" align="center" scope="col" colspan="1">NNH</th></tr><tr><th valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Untreated (all)<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12 339 501</th><th valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treated<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 689 074</th><th valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matched control<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 689 074</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary composite outcome</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 (1.14&#8211;1.16)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Opioid-related emergency visit<xref rid="tfn9-197e122" ref-type="table-fn">&#8225;</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 (1.18&#8211;1.32)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1047</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">New opioid agonist therapy<xref rid="tfn9-197e122" ref-type="table-fn">&#8225;</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 (0.98&#8211;1.40)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1968</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All-cause death</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (1.00&#8211;1.09)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3038</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All-cause hospital admission</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 (1.14&#8211;1.16)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prolonged opioid use<xref rid="tfn10-197e122" ref-type="table-fn">&#167;</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54 (1.51&#8211;1.57)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total MME dispensed, mean &#177; SD<xref rid="tfn10-197e122" ref-type="table-fn">&#167;</xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">887 &#177; 5783</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1444 &#177; 6126</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1190 &#177; 7750</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18<xref rid="tfn11-197e122" ref-type="table-fn">&#182;</xref> (1.17&#8211;1.19)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn6-197e122"><p>Note: CI = confidence interval, MME = morphine milligram equivalent, NA = not applicable, NNH = number needed to harm, OR = odds ratio, SD = standard deviation.</p></fn><fn id="tfn7-197e122"><label>*</label><p>Unless stated otherwise.</p></fn><fn id="tfn8-197e122"><label>&#8224;</label><p>Adjustment variables included age, sex, complaint type, visit year, visit time (day, evening, night), arrival mode (ambulance v. ambulatory), triage acuity, number of prior emergency visits, deprivation category, number of documented health conditions, mental health or substance use disorders, psychotropic or analgesic prescriptions within a year, prior opioid exposure status, and index visit length of stay.</p></fn><fn id="tfn9-197e122"><label>&#8225;</label><p>Opioid-specific outcomes are specific but lack sensitivity.</p></fn><fn id="tfn10-197e122"><label>&#167;</label><p>Prolonged opioid use is &gt; 120 days of prescribed opioids within 30&#8211;365 days after index visit. Total MME is the mean total opioid dispensed within 30&#8211;365 days.</p></fn><fn id="tfn11-197e122"><label>&#182;</label><p>Adjusted difference (&#946;-coefficient) after natural log-transformation and multiple linear regression. The exponentiated coefficient (1.18) should be interpreted as a multiplicative factor.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Prolonged prescription opioid use occurred more often in opioid recipients (4.5% v. 3.3%; adjusted OR 1.54; 95% CI 1.51&#8211;1.57; NNH = 59). During the follow-up year, opioid-treated patients received 254 mg more total MMEs (1444 mg v. 1190 mg). Multivariable regression of the natural log-transformed outcome provided an estimate of 1.18, meaning treated patients received 1.18 times as much opioid as controls at 1 year. <xref rid="f2-197e122" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> shows that, among opioid recipients, composite outcomes were most likely in patients with psychotic disorders, substance use disorders, older patients, patients with greater illness burden, and frequent emergency department users. <xref rid="f3-197e122" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref> shows that incremental risk, the outcome difference between treated patients and matched controls, was highest for opioid-naive patients, older patients, and males. Patients with documented mental health conditions or substance use had high event rates with or without an opioid prescription; therefore, they experienced minimal incremental risk after opioid prescriptions. Even in the high-risk opioid-naive subgroup, composite outcome differences were driven by all-cause hospital admission and prolonged prescription opioid use, not by opioid-specific events (<xref rid="s1-197e122" ref-type="supplementary-material">Appendix 1, Table 2a</xref>, available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.cmaj.ca/lookup/doi/10.1503/cmaj.241542/tab-related-content" ext-link-type="uri">www.cmaj.ca/lookup/doi/10.1503/cmaj.241542/tab-related-content</ext-link>).</p><fig position="float" id="f2-197e122" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2:</label><caption><p>Factors associated with the primary composite outcome in opioid-treated patients. This figure summarizes outcomes for opioid-treated patients only. <sup>*</sup>Adjustment variables included age, sex, complaint type, visit year, visit time (day, evening, night), arrival mode (ambulance v. ambulatory), triage acuity, number of prior emergency visits, deprivation category, number of documented health conditions, mental health or substance use disorders, psychotropic or analgesic prescriptions within a year, prior opioid exposure status, and index visit length of stay. &#8224;High acuity = CTAS 1&#8211;2 (resuscitation, emergent), medium acuity = CTAS 3 (urgent), low acuity = CTAS 4&#8211;5 (less urgent, non-urgent). Note: CI = confidence interval, CTAS = Canadian Triage and Acuity Scale, ED = emergency department, EMS = emergency medical services, OR = odds ratio, SUD = substance use disorder. See Related Content tab for accessible version.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="197e122f2.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="f3-197e122" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3:</label><caption><p>Risk of primary composite outcome by subgroups. <sup>*</sup>Adjustment variables included age, sex, complaint type, visit year, visit time (day, evening, night), arrival mode (ambulance v. ambulatory), triage acuity, number of prior emergency visits, deprivation category, number of documented health conditions, mental health or substance use disorders, psychotropic or analgesic prescriptions within a year, prior opioid exposure status, and index visit length of stay. Note: CI = confidence interval, MHD = mental health diagnosis, NNH = number needed to harm, OR = odds ratio, SUD = substance use disorder. See Related Content tab for accessible version.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="197e122f3.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Interpretation</title><p>Patients who received opioids experienced more composite outcomes than matched controls (NNH = 52); however, opioid-specific emergency department visits (e.g., overdoses), new opioid agonist treatment, and mortality were similar between groups. Outcome differences were driven by higher rates of all-cause hospital admission (NNH = 53) and prolonged opioid use (NNH = 59).</p><p>These results have practice implications. They provide precise population and subgroup risk estimates. They confirm that single opioid prescriptions are not risk-free but that the likelihood of harm is low and unlikely to outweigh the benefit of treating severe pain. Our findings also show that patient characteristics influence risk and that the outcomes were associated with opioid-naive status, older age, frequent emergency department use, and high illness burden.</p><p>The relative effects of opioid prescriptions, intentional misuse, diversion, societal factors, and other opioid exposures on the opioid epidemic are unclear. These knowledge gaps are most pronounced for acute pain management and unscheduled care settings. <xref rid="b14-197e122" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Composite events occurred in 17.1% of treated patients and 15.7% of controls. This relatively small difference suggests that societal factors and other opioid sources likely play a larger causal role than emergency department prescriptions. To isolate the iatrogenic potential of an emergency department prescription, we estimated incremental risks &#8212; differences between treated patients and matched controls. We found that the risk after an opioid prescription did not always correlate with the incremental risk (iatrogenic potential) attributable to that prescription. To illustrate, patients with mental health and substance use disorders had high rates of composite outcomes after opioid prescription but similarly high rates without opioid prescription; therefore, they experienced small incremental risk (NNH = 101 and 649, respectively; <xref rid="f3-197e122" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). Conversely, opioid-naive patients had lower rates of composite outcomes after prescription but high incremental risk (NNH = 21) and had the greatest potential for harm after a prescription. Prescribers should understand the likelihood of adverse outcomes, but also the incremental risk associated with opioid treatment.</p><p>Previous emergency department studies were limited to opioid-naive patients and reported estimates from 7 to 300 prescriptions to cause 1 episode of prolonged prescription opioid use.<xref rid="b1-197e122" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="b2-197e122" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="b19-197e122" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="b20-197e122" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="b37-197e122" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="b39-197e122" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Shah and colleagues found that 6% of opioid recipients continued using opioids beyond a year, but the study was uncontrolled.<xref rid="b1-197e122" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Delgado and colleagues identified a correlation between the amount of opioid prescribed and prolonged use in patients with ankle sprains.<xref rid="b40-197e122" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> Hoppe and colleagues reported that an opioid prescription increased the likelihood of subsequent prescriptions (17% v. 10%) but did not adjust for baseline patient differences that might predispose to subsequent prescriptions.<xref rid="b20-197e122" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Friedman and colleagues found that 1% of patients who received opioids in the emergency department exhibited persistent use, and Meisel and colleagues reported that 13.7% developed high-risk use.<xref rid="b41-197e122" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="b42-197e122" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> Barnett and colleagues found that opioid-naive Medicare patients exposed to high-intensity opioid prescribers had increased rates of prolonged opioid use (NNH = 48)<xref rid="b19-197e122" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> but could not replicate this finding in another population.<xref rid="b37-197e122" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> Studies of military personnel and adolescents found no association between high-intensity opioid prescribers and subsequent opioid use.<xref rid="b38-197e122" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="b39-197e122" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></p><p>Prolonged opioid use, the outcome used most frequently in previous studies,<xref rid="b1-197e122" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="b2-197e122" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="b19-197e122" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="b20-197e122" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="b40-197e122" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="b42-197e122" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> is important but is not the same as misuse, opioid use disorder, overdose, or adverse health consequences; therefore, we also studied opioid-specific and all-cause outcome events. Our finding that opioid prescriptions were not associated with overdoses, new opioid use disorder treatment, or mortality suggests that these more severe outcomes are unlikely to be caused by prescriptions in the emergency department. However, our finding that prescriptions were associated with subsequent all-cause hospital admission suggests that opioids may cause health events that are not recognized as opioid related.</p><p>Future research should evaluate longer-term outcomes and explore the relation between prolonged opioid use and health outcomes. Researchers should investigate agent-specific effects, as all opioids may not be the same, and identify pain syndromes for which opioid risk may be greater or less than treatment benefit. Robust randomized controlled trials (RCTs) are unlikely to be conducted because of ethical concerns (randomly assigning patients with severe pain to non-opioid analgesia), selection bias (patients of greatest interest selecting out), loss to follow-up, and the large samples required to detect small outcome differences. The single RCT evaluating emergency opioid prescription illustrated these problems. Jones and colleagues randomly assigned 350 patients with neck or back pain to oxycodone or placebo during a 6-year enrolment at 157 sites.<xref rid="b43-197e122" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Problems included slow accrual, averaging less than 1 patient per site per year, poor compliance with the study regimen, missing outcome data, and a sample size insufficient to address health events or subgroups. Observational and quasiexperimental studies in large populations are more feasible and, if well done, can yield clinically important results.</p><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>We did not capture social or functional outcomes. We assessed outcomes at 1 year, which may be insufficient to identify all opioid-related sequelae. Because we analyzed emergency department visits, some patients were enrolled multiple times. This breaches the assumption of independent observations; however, adjusting for within-patient correlation is highly unlikely to decrease the precision of the effect estimates or change our conclusions. Although we reliably identified opioid-treated patients, matched controls, and main outcomes, some subgroups were susceptible to misclassification. For example, our definition of opioid use disorder would miss opioid users who had no opioid prescriptions or opioid-related health encounters.</p><p>Administrative data may lack important matching variables. We could not ascertain pain severity and instead matched on diagnosis, which is a strong predictor of opioid administration.<xref rid="b44-197e122" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> We also matched on sex, visit year, triage acuity, ambulance arrival, and length of stay. To address illness burden, we matched on age, comorbidity, deprivation status, medication use, and prior emergency department use. This rich variable set provided a multidimensional picture of patients and allowed us to generate highly comparable treated and control cohorts. We believe the range of matching variables provided partial coverage for unmeasured covariates; however, confounding by intention (which arises from systematic differences in treatment allocation based on clinicians&#8217; intentions or decisions, influenced by patient characteristics or context) remains a possible source of bias. If our opioid-treated group had more severe pain or other features that prompted physicians to prescribe opioids, this group would be expected to have a worse prognosis and receive more subsequent opioid prescriptions. Confounding by intention would therefore bias our study against opioid treatment, and the actual risk associated with opioid prescription might be less than reported. Our finding of harm with opioid prescription is plausible, and the low level of harm estimated suggests that confounding by intention did not substantially influence our results.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Emergency opioid prescriptions were associated with small increases in subsequent opioid prescription use and hospital admission, particularly in older and opioid-naive patients. They were not associated with opioid-related emergency department visits (e.g., overdoses), new opioid agonist therapy, or mortality. Physicians should understand the concept of patient-specific incremental risks when prescribing opioids for acute pain and prescribe cautiously within high-risk groups.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><supplementary-material id="s1-197e122" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="241542-res-1-at.pdf" id="d100e1081" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="s2-197e122" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="241542-res-f1-longdesc.pdf" id="d100e1083" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="fn1-197e122" fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> Jake Hayward reports funding from the Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR) and the Canadian Association of Emergency Physicians. Rhonda Rosychuk declares a project grant from CIHR. Andrew McRae reports project grants from CIHR and unrestricted research funding from Roche Diagnostics Canada for unrelated research work. Aynharan Sinnarajah reports grant funding from CIHR and logistical support from Alberta Health Services (AHS). Robert Tanguay is director of the Canadian Academy for Addiction Psychiatry and co-chair of the Alberta Pain Strategy; he also declares roles with the Canadian Addiction Council, Calgary Police Comission, Alberta Association of Police Governance, Alberta Clinical Code Review Board, Queen&#8217;s University Ignite Conference, Canadian Society of Addiction Medicine Policy Committee, and Pain Society of Alberta. He has received lecture honoraria from the Master Clinician Alliance and Indivior Canada, and declares travel honoraria from International Foundation of Employee Benefit Plans. Dr. Tanguay declares stock with Newly Institute; Telus; Apple; Becton, Dickinson and Company; Numinus Wellness; and Mind Medicine. Kathryn Dong has received lecture honoraria from the Alberta Society for Human Toxicology and travel support from the Royal College of Physicians and Surgeons of Canada to attend meetings in her role as the chair of the Area of Focused Competence Committee in Addiction Medicine. As Alberta Health Services Chair in Emergency Medicine Research, Dr. Dong reports salary support, paid via the University of Alberta. Lori Montgomery reports funding for a pilot clinical trial of a medication for opioid withdrawal from Hotchkiss Brain Institute (University of Calgary), Alberta Innovates, and teaching honoraria from Alberta College of Family Physicians, University of Calgary, and University of British Columbia. Grant Innes reports support from AHS and CIHR. No other competing interests were declared.</p></fn><fn id="fn2-197e122"><p>This article has been peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn id="fn3-197e122"><p><bold>Contributors:</bold> Grant Innes and Jake Hayward envisioned the study, wrote the original study design, prepared and submitted the CIHR research grant, enlisted the support of Alberta Health Services to assure data access, collaborated with analysts in building study databases, collaborated with biostatisticians in the design and conduct of the analysis, verified the study data, and wrote the primary manuscript draft. Andrew McRae, Aynharan Sinnarajah, Kathryn Dong, Robert Tanguay, and Lori Montgomery sat on the original research grant committee, collaborated in study design, grant development and revision, interpretation of data, and participated in multiple revisions of the manuscript. Andrew Huang helped devise the statistical analysis, accessed and linked primary databases, performed many of the study analyses, and reviewed and contributed to revisions of the final manuscript. Rhonda Rosychuk was a co&#8211;principal investigator on the initial research grant, helped design the study, was primarily responsible for the statistical analysis plan, oversaw all data analyses, performed many of the analyses, and participated in review and revision of the final manuscript. All authors gave final approval of the version to be published and agreed to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p></fn><fn id="fn4-197e122"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The Canadian Institutes of Health Research provided peer-reviewed grant funding for this work. Alberta Health Services provided in-kind support in the form of secure data access, analyst time, and database preparation. Neither entity participated in study conduct, analysis, interpretation or manuscript preparation. No other agency, pharmaceutical company, or commercial entity was involved with any aspect of the study.</p></fn><fn id="fn5-197e122"><p><bold>Disclaimer:</bold> Andrew McRae is an associate editor for <italic toggle="yes">CMAJ</italic> and was not involved in the editorial decision-making process for this article.</p></fn><fn id="fn6-197e122"><p><bold>Data sharing:</bold> The study data are the property of Alberta Health Services (AHS) and housed behind a firewall in the AHS enterprise data warehouse. Our analyst (Andrew Huang) and biostatistician (Rhonda Rosychuk) accessed study databases using secure servers at the University of Alberta. The authors would support requests from other qualified investigators in an application to AHS to access the necessary data if required.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-197e122"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characteristics of initial prescription episodes and likelihood of long-term opioid use &#8212; United States, 2006&#8211;2015</article-title>. <source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>265</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28301454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.15585/mmwr.mm6610a1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5657867</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2-197e122"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ancona</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beauchamp</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Emergency department prescription opioids as an initial exposure preceding addiction</article-title>. <source>Ann Emerg Med</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>202</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26875061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.annemergmed.2015.11.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4958587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b3-197e122"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deyo</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallvik</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hildebran</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between initial opioid prescribing patterns and subsequent long-term use among opioid-naive patients: a statewide retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27484682</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-016-3810-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5215151</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b4-197e122"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brummett</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waljee</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goesling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>New persistent opioid use after minor and major surgical procedures in US adults</article-title>. <source>JAMA Surg</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>152</volume>:<fpage>e170504</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2017.0504</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28403427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7050825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5-197e122"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schappert</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Opioids prescribed to adults at discharge from emergency departments: United States, 2017&#8211;2020</article-title>. <source>NCHS Data Brief, no 461</source>. <publisher-loc>Hyattsville (MD)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Center for Health Statistics</publisher-name>; <year>2022</year>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15620/cdc:122879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36693206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6-197e122"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaoser</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudoler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Trends in dispensing of individual prescription opioid formulations, Canada 2005&#8211;2020</article-title>. <source>J Pharm Policy Pract</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>27</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40545-022-00423-1</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35351208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8966300</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b7-197e122"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellehoj</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eurich</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <source>Tracked prescription drug monitoring program</source>. <publisher-loc>Edmonton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The College of Physicians &amp; Surgeons of Alberta</publisher-name>; <year>2022</year>. <comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.tppalberta.ca/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.tppalberta.ca/</ext-link></comment> (<date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2023 Dec. 1</date-in-citation>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b8-197e122"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cisewski</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossen</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <source>Provisional drug overdose death counts</source>. <publisher-name>National Center for Health Statistics</publisher-name>. <year>2025</year>. <comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nvss/vsrr/drug-overdose-data.htm#citation" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nvss/vsrr/drug-overdose-data.htm#citation</ext-link></comment> (<date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2025 Jan. 22</date-in-citation>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b9-197e122"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><source>Modelling opioid-related deaths during the overdose crisis</source>. <publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Public Health Agency of Canada</publisher-name>; <year>2023</year>. <comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.canada.ca/en/health-canada/services/opioids/data-surveillance-research/modelling.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.canada.ca/en/health-canada/services/opioids/data-surveillance-research/modelling.html</ext-link></comment> (<date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2025 Jan. 22</date-in-citation>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b10-197e122"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><source>Opioid harms in Canada</source>. <publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Government of Canada</publisher-name>; <year>2019</year>. <comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cihi.ca/sites/default/files/document/opioid-related-harms-report-2018-en-web.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cihi.ca/sites/default/files/document/opioid-related-harms-report-2018-en-web.pdf</ext-link></comment> (<date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2023 Sept. 27</date-in-citation>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b11-197e122"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyndall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The crucial opioid interventions Canada needs now</article-title>. <source>The Globe and Mail [Toronto]</source>. <year>2017</year><month>Aug</month>. <day>18</day>. <comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/opinion/the-crucial-opioid-interventions-canada-needs-now/article36034061/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.theglobeandmail.com/opinion/the-crucial-opioid-interventions-canada-needs-now/article36034061/</ext-link></comment> (<date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2023 Sept. 27</date-in-citation>). [subscription required to access].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b12-197e122"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Motov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strayer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The treatment of acute pain in the emergency department: a white paper position statement prepared for the American Academy of Emergency Medicine</article-title>. <source>J Emerg Med</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>731</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29523420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jemermed.2018.01.020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b13-197e122"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>No chronic pain patient will be abandoned</article-title>. <source>Edmonton Journal</source><year>2019</year><month>July</month><day>12</day>. Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://edmontonjournal.com/opinion/columnists/college-registrar-no-chronic-pain-patient-should-be-abandoned" ext-link-type="uri">edmontonjournal.com/opinion/columnists/college-registrar-no-chronic-pain-patient-should-be-abandoned</ext-link> (<date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2023 Sept. 27</date-in-citation>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b14-197e122"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beauchamp</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winstanley</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Moving beyond misuse and diversion: the urgent need to consider the role of iatrogenic addiction in the current opioid epidemic</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>2023</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25211712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2105/AJPH.2014.302147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4202970</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b15-197e122"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lew</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buttemer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>First do no harm: advocating for opioid prescribing guidelines in Canadian emergency departments</article-title>. <source>CJEM</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>324</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28318458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/cem.2017.8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b16-197e122"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantrill</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlisle</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>.; <collab>American College of Emergency Physicians Opioid Guideline Writing Panel</collab>. <article-title>Clinical policy: critical issues in the prescribing of opioids for adult patients in the emergency department</article-title>. <source>Ann Emerg Med</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>499</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>525</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23010181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.annemergmed.2012.06.013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b17-197e122"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><source>Opioid prescribing for acute pain: care for people 15 years of age and older</source>. <publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Health Quality Ontario</publisher-name>; <year>2018</year>. <comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.hqontario.ca/portals/0/documents/evidence/quality-standards/qs-opioid-acute-pain-clinician-guide-en.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.hqontario.ca/portals/0/documents/evidence/quality-standards/qs-opioid-acute-pain-clinician-guide-en.pdf</ext-link></comment> (<date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2025 Jan. 22</date-in-citation>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b18-197e122"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Ohio Governor&#8217;s Cabinet Opiate Action Team</collab>. <source>Ohio guidelines for emergency and acute care facility opioid and other controlled substances (OOCS) prescribing</source>. <publisher-loc>Columbus (OH)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ohio Department of Health</publisher-name>; <year>2014</year>. <comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://dam.assets.ohio.gov/image/upload/mha.ohio.gov/Portals/0/assets/ResearchersAndMedia/Combating%20Opiate%20Abuse/OPG/Guidelines-ED-Acute-Care.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://dam.assets.ohio.gov/image/upload/mha.ohio.gov/Portals/0/assets/ResearchersAndMedia/Combating%20Opiate%20Abuse/OPG/Guidelines-ED-Acute-Care.pdf</ext-link></comment> (<date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2025 Jan. 22</date-in-citation>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b19-197e122"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olenski</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jena</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Opioid-prescribing patterns of emergency physicians and risk of long-term use</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>376</volume>:<fpage>663</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28199807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMsa1610524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5428548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b20-197e122"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoppe</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heard</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of emergency department opioid initiation with recurrent opioid use</article-title>. <source>Ann Emerg Med</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>493</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>499.e4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25534654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.annemergmed.2014.11.015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b21-197e122"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benchimol</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smeeth</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guttmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The REporting of studies Conducted using Observational Routinely-collected health Data (RECORD) Statement</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e1001885</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26440803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4595218</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b22-197e122"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larney</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>All-cause and cause-specific mortality among people using extramedical opioids: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>JAMA Psychiatry</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>493</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>502</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31876906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2019.4170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6990804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b23-197e122"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Von Korff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas Ray</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Defacto long-term opioid therapy for non-cancer pain. [published erratum in <italic toggle="yes">Clin J Pain</italic> 2014;30:830]</article-title><source>Clin J Pain</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>521</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18574361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/AJP.0b013e318169d03b</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3286630</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b24-197e122"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><source>Characteristics of patients with repeat emergency department visits for opioid-related harms in Alberta, Ontario and the Yukon</source>. <publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Public Health Agency of Canada</publisher-name>; <year>2024</year>. <comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.canada.ca/en/health-canada/services/opioids/data-surveillance-research/characteristics-patients-repeat-emergency-department-visits-opioid-related-harms-alberta-ontario-yukon.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.canada.ca/en/health-canada/services/opioids/data-surveillance-research/characteristics-patients-repeat-emergency-department-visits-opioid-related-harms-alberta-ontario-yukon.html</ext-link></comment> (<date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2025 Jan. 22</date-in-citation>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b25-197e122"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chartash</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paek</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dziura</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Identifying opioid use disorder in the emergency department: multi-system electronic health record-based computable phenotype derivation and validation study</article-title>. <source>JMIR Med Inform</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e15794</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31674913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2196/15794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6913746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b26-197e122"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pampalon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Denis Hamel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathieu</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>An area-based material and social deprivation index for public health in Qu&#233;bec and Canada</article-title>. <source>Can J Public Health</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>103</volume>(<issue>8 Suppl 2</issue>):<fpage>S17</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23618066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF03403824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6973787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b27-197e122"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Balance diagnostics for comparing the distribution of baseline covariates between treatment groups in propensity-score matched samples</article-title>. <source>Stat Med</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>3083</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>107</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19757444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/sim.3697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3472075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b28-197e122"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kosuke</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>MatchIt: nonparametric preprocessing for parametric causal inference</article-title>. <source>J Stat Softw</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b29-197e122"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>R: A language and environment for statistical computing</article-title>. <source>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</source>. <publisher-loc>Vienna (Austria)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>R Core Team</publisher-name>; <year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b30-197e122"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sekhon</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Multivariate and propensity score matching</article-title>. <source>J Stat Softw</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b31-197e122"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A critical appraisal of propensity-score matching in the medical literature between 1996 and 2003</article-title>. <source>Stat Med</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>2037</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>49</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18038446</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/sim.3150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b32-197e122"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The performance of different propensity-score methods for estimating relative risks</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>537</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18471657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2007.07.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b33-197e122"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laupacis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A tutorial on methods to estimating clinically and policy-meaningful measures of treatment effects in prospective observational studies: a review</article-title>. <source>Int J Biostat</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2202/1557-4679.1285</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22848188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3404554</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b34-197e122"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Double propensity-score adjustment: a solution to design bias or bias due to incomplete matching</article-title>. <source>Stat Methods Med Res</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>201</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25038071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0962280214543508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5302082</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b35-197e122"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blettner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Calculating the &#8220;number needed to be exposed&#8221; with adjustment for confounding variables in epidemiological studies</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>525</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12007557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0895-4356(01)00510-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b36-197e122"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><source>Odds Ratio to NNT Converter</source>. <publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Knowledge Translation Program</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>. <comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ebm-tools.knowledgetranslation.net/calculator/converter/" ext-link-type="uri">https://ebm-tools.knowledgetranslation.net/calculator/converter/</ext-link></comment> (<date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2023 Nov. 29</date-in-citation>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b37-197e122"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fine</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Emergency physician opioid prescribing and risk of long-term use in the Veterans Health Administration: an observational analysis</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>1522</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31144281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-019-05023-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6667564</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b38-197e122"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Winkle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghobadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Opioid prescribing patterns in emergency departments and future opioid use in adolescent patients</article-title>. <source>Am J Emerg Med</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>2297</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2302</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31784388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajem.2019.10.020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b39-197e122"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moresco</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between 1-year patient outcomes and opioid-prescribing group of emergency department clinicians: a cohort study with Army active-duty soldiers</article-title>. <source>Acad Emerg Med</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>1251</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34245641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/acem.14331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10393064</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b40-197e122"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meisel</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>National variation in opioid prescribing and risk of prolonged use for opioid-naive patients treated in emergency department for ankle sprains</article-title>. <source>Ann Emerg Med</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>389</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>400.e1</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30054152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.annemergmed.2018.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6319263</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b41-197e122"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dym</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davitt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Naproxen with cyclobenzaprine, oxycodone-acetaminophen, or placebo for treating acute low back pain: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>314</volume>:<fpage>1572</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26501533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2015.13043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b42-197e122"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meisel</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lupulescu-Mann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Conversion to persistent or high-risk opioid use after a new prescription from the emergency department: evidence from Washington Medicaid beneficiaries</article-title>. <source>Ann Emerg Med</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>611</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31229392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.annemergmed.2019.04.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6864746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b43-197e122"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CMO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koes</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Opioid analgesia for acute low back pain and neck pain: a randomised placebo-controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><year>2023</year>; <volume>402</volume>:<fpage>304</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37392748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(23)00404-X</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b44-197e122"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vatanpour</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Sex-related differences in opioid administration in the emergency department: a population-based study</article-title>. <source>Emerg Med J</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>467</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33853938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/emermed-2020-210215</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>