<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biol Trace Elem Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biol Trace Elem Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">365</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">springeropen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Biological Trace Element Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0163-4984</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1559-0720</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Springer</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10954846</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10954846.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10954846</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10954846</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37608129</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12011-023-03801-1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3801</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Circulating Copper Is Associated with Inflammatory Biomarkers in Greek Older Adults with Osteoarthritis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amerikanou</surname><given-names initials="C">Charalampia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valsamidou</surname><given-names initials="E">Evdokia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karavoltsos</surname><given-names initials="S">Sotirios</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tagkouli</surname><given-names initials="D">Dimitra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakellari</surname><given-names initials="A">Aikaterini</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kontou</surname><given-names initials="M">Maria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Houhoula</surname><given-names initials="D">Dimitra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalogeropoulos</surname><given-names initials="N">Nick</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zoumpoulakis</surname><given-names initials="P">Panagiotis</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaliora</surname><given-names initials="AC">Andriana C.</given-names></name><address><email>akaliora@hua.gr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02k5gp281</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.15823.3d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0622 2843</institution-id><institution>Department of Nutrition and Dietetics, School of Health Science and Education, </institution><institution>Harokopio University of Athens, </institution></institution-wrap>70 El. Venizelou Ave, 17676 Athens, Greece </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04gnjpq42</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5216.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2155 0800</institution-id><institution>Department of Chemistry, </institution><institution>National and Kapodistrian University of Athens, </institution></institution-wrap>Panepistimiopolis Zografou, 15784 Athens, Greece </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>TheraCell Advanced Biotechnologies, 14564 Kifissia, Greece </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00r2r5k05</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.499377.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 7222 9074</institution-id><institution>Department of Food Science and Technology, </institution><institution>University of West Attica, </institution></institution-wrap>Ag. Spyridonos, 12243 Egaleo, Athens, Greece </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>202</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">458318</issue-id><fpage>1866</fpage><lpage>1877</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>22</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>22</day><month>03</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-03-22 00:25:14.460"><day>22</day><month>03</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12011_2023_Article_3801.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Osteoarthritis (OA) is the most common form of arthritis, that causes a significant decrease in the quality of life of the afflicted and constitutes a great burden for the socioeconomic system. Trace elements and heavy metals are implicated in the pathophysiology of OA, exacerbating inflammatory and oxidative stress responses. The aim of this cross-sectional study was to quantify metals in plasma samples of Greek OA patients and explore their link with disease related parameters, health status or quality of life, as well as epigenetic OA markers. This is the first study on plasma metal levels in Greek knee&#160;OA patients. To achieve precision in plasma metal and miRNA measurements, high-quality samples were selected from a subset of 34 participants (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT04783792">NCT04783792</ext-link>). Demographic, quality of life, clinical, biochemical, inflammation, oxidative stress, and anthropometric parameters, as well as microRNA levels were assessed. Significant correlations were found between circulating metals with OA related parameters or with measured microRNAs. Also, significant positive associations between plasma copper (Cu) levels and CRP (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.033) or IL-6 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.001) occurred when adjusting for age, gender, BMI, physical activity level, smoking, disease severity, total arthroplasty, and dietary intake of the respective metal. Cu&#8217;s role in OA is bidirectional, and this study confirms the findings that in OA, Cu is positively associated with inflammation. Such relationships between lifestyle, environment and OA enhance our understanding and encourage further study on metals related to OA inflammation.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Osteoarthritis</kwd><kwd>Circulating metals/metalloids</kwd><kwd>MicroRNAs</kwd><kwd>Inflammat&#959;ry markers</kwd><kwd>Copper</kwd><kwd>Lifestyle</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Harokopio University</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open access funding provided by HEAL-Link Greece.</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Osteoarthritis (OA) is a non-communicable, degenerative disease of the articular cartilage of the joints. It is a heterogeneous and multifaceted malady with genetic, mechanical, and environmental factors contributing to the deterioration of the consistency of the articular cartilage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The onset of the disease can occur as early as the 30s; however, its prevalence increases exponentially with age, particularly in the female gender [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. OA is the most common form of arthritis globally with serious person-level repercussions such as pain and decrease in functionality and in quality of life (QoL) of the afflicted, and society-level burdens in the socioeconomic realm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Treatments can only offer palliative relief and chronic pharmacological approaches have serious side effects. Non-pharmacological options include physical therapy, weight management, incorporation of appropriate physical activities, education of patients and supplements to reinforce health and manage symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], as well as the use of nutraceuticals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The pathophysiology of OA is complex, and it affects all the tissues of the joint, leading to inflammation of the synovium, the formation of bone spurs and the degradation of the articular cartilage; sustained chronic low-grade inflammation and oxidative stress (OS) generate metabolites that further aggravate the progression of the disease through positive feedback loops [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par3">Metals have been found to be implicated in biological processes such as inflammation and OS. They can be either beneficial or harmful depending on the tissue, duration of exposure, type and levels of metals. Several metals and metalloids (i.e., aluminum (Al), mercury (Hg), arsenic (As), cadmium (Cd), chromium (Cr), copper (Cu)) occur naturally in Earth&#8217;s crust [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Toxic metals/metalloids such as Hg, Cr, Cd, As, and lead (Pb) may provoke deleterious effects on human metabolism and mechanistically their toxicity can be attributed to induction of OS and depletion of antioxidant capacities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. On the contrary, trace or essential metals (i.e., sodium (Na), potassium (K), magnesium (Mg), and calcium (Ca)) are necessary for human body at specific concentrations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Their biological roles include among others catalytic actions, stabilization of oxidation states, and structural functions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], with their ligand binding strengths and mobilities being the most significant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Given that metals play a pivotal role in metabolic functions which are altered in OA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], the interplay between circulating metals and OA including the inflammatory mediators of the disease is of particular interest.</p><p id="Par4">MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are endogenous single-stranded, noncoding sequences of 20&#8211;25 nucleotides with their biological role being highlighted as negative regulators of gene expression at post-transcriptional level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Due to their regulatory role, miRNAs have recently gained considerable attention regarding their involvement in OA pathophysiology. In OA they participate in the homeostasis of chondrocytes and cartilage and in vivo modulation of them has been shown to affect the progression of the disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. What is more, several studies have investigated the associations between metals and miRNAs in signaling pathways and in disease development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. However, none of them has addressed whether miRNA regulation mediates the role of metals in OA or whether metal exposure influences OA through epigenetic miRNA alterations.</p><p id="Par5">On that aspect, the aim of our study was to quantify plasma metals in Greek OA patients and explore their associations with disease related parameters. Additionally, because it has been hypothesized that specific miRNAs are dysregulated in OA, their quantification herein was conducted to provide evidence of a potential mediating role. Exploring such relationships among lifestyle, environment and development of the disease broadens our understanding in disease pathophysiology, management and/or prevention.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Ethics</title><p id="Par6">This is a cross-sectional study that used baseline data from a subset of patients from a randomized controlled trial (RCT) that evaluated a standardized nutraceutical supplement in pain, quality of life, inflammation and OS in OA (manuscript in peern review process). The RCT was approved by Harokopio University Ethics Committee (13/21&#8211;2-2020) and Evgenidio Hospital Scientific Board (29/19&#8211;02-2019) and was registered in the ClinicalTrials.gov database with the identifier <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT04783792">NCT04783792</ext-link>. The protocol followed all the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki 2013 and the Data Protection Act 2018 and all patients gave their informed consent before entering the study. More details on the clinical trial study design and sample size calculation are given elsewhere (manuscript in peer review process).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Participants</title><p id="Par7">Individuals above the age of 35 with unilateral or bilateral OA of the knee confirmed by radiography (stage II, III, or IV according to Kellgren and Lawrence classification, K&amp;L) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] and by the American College of Rheumatology (ACR) clinical and radiographic criteria for OA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] were enrolled. To confirm that radiographic findings correlated with the symptoms, patients had to have at least moderate symptoms of pain in the target knee depicted as intermittent (pain during the last 7 days) or constant pain above 4 in the Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteroarthritis (WOMAC) pain subscale and in visual analogue scale (VAS). In bilateral OA, the target knee was determined by the highest VAS pain score. Volunteers had to be able to walk without support devices such as a walking stick, crutches, or a kneecap. Main exclusion criteria were patients with OA who were having physical therapy or transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation prior the trial, rheumatoid arthritis, fibromyalgia, spinal disorders or any other musculoskeletal disorders that according to the physician were a bias (i.e., chronic low back pain), a scheduled knee surgery or any other programmed surgery during the trial, those using injected or per-os corticosteroids within 2 months prior to randomization and during the trial or those with adaptations to diet/food supplements 1 month prior or during the recruitment and throughout the trial. Patients were advised to adhere to their lifestyle habits prior the randomization to the trial, and upon discomfort due to pain they were allowed to use rescue medication (paracetamol and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Baseline Assessments</title><p id="Par8">At baseline the medical history of the patients was recorded along with information regarding the progress of OA and related surgeries such as total knee arthroplasty (TKA), demographics, and smoking. Furthermore, anthropometric measurements were taken that included height (cm) and body weight (kg) to compute body mass index (BMI) as weight (kg)/height (m)<sup>2</sup>, as well as waist circumference (cm) and hip circumference (cm) to compute the waist-hip ratio (WHR). Finally, validated questionnaires for OA that evaluate core symptoms of the disease and physical function were filled out. Those included (1) VAS for pain that is a numeric continuum from 0 (no pain) to 100 mm (worst pain) and recorded the worst feeling of pain patients had on the target knee during the last 7 days, (2) WOMAC that consists of 24 items that are divided into 3 subscales; the subscale of pain (5 items): during walking, using stairs, in bed, sitting or lying, and standing upright, the subscale of stiffness (2 items): after first waking and later in the day and the subscale of physical function (17 items): using stairs, rising from sitting, standing, bending, walking, getting in/out of a car, shopping, putting on/taking off socks, rising from bed, lying in bed, getting in/out of bath, sitting, getting on/off toilet, heavy domestic duties, light domestic duties The 24 test questions are scored on a scale of 0&#8211;4, which correspond to the following: none (0), mild (1), moderate (2), severe (3), and extreme (4). The scores for each subscale are summed up; with a possible score range of 0&#8211;20 for pain, 0&#8211;8 for stiffness, and 0&#8211;68 for physical function that together compute a percentage of the WOMAC score. Higher scores indicate worse pain, stiffness, and functional limitations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">Regarding QoL, ShortForm36 (SF-36) was used. This is a health-related questionnaire with 36 questions about physical functioning, role limitations due to physical health, due to emotional problems, energy/fatigue, emotional well-being, social functioning, bodily pain, and general health. All eight dimensions of the questionnaire were computed via an online tool [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] and higher scores indicated a better health status. Physical activity was assessed via the International Physical Activity Questionnaire Short Form (IPAQ-SF)&#160;and expressed as metabolic equivalent task in minutes per week (MET-min/week) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Adherence to the Mediterranean diet was evaluated using the Mediterranean Diet score (MedDiet score) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. The total score of MedDiet ranges from 0 to 55 with higher values indicating greater adherence to the Mediterranean diet. Also, 24-h recalls were used to assess metals dietary intake using Nutritionist Pro&#8482; software package (Axxya Systems, Stafford, TX, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Blood Collection</title><p id="Par10">Blood sample collection (20 mL) was performed in the subjects after overnight fasting. For plasma and serum isolation whole blood was collected in blood tubes. The vacutainers were centrifuged for 10 min at a speed of 3000 rpm in order to receive the supernatant. Plasma and serum were stored in Eppendorf tubes in&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;80 &#176;C until further analysis.</p><p id="Par11">For accuracy in miRNA and metals quantification, samples used were not hemolyzed and were of adequate volume for the Inductively Coupled Plasma Mass Spectometry (ICP-MS) analysis or of high purity extracted RNA for the miRNA quantification. These characteristics were met in 34 out of 60 samples&#160;of the RCT.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Analysis of Serum Biomarkers</title><p id="Par12">Biochemical analysis was performed in serum with an automatic biochemical analyzer (Cobas 8000 analyzer, Roche Diagnostics GmbH, Mannheim, Germany) and included vitamin D, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL), triglycerides (TG), glucose, urea, C-reactive protein (CRP), albumin, creatinine, serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT), and serum glutamic pyruvic transaminase (SGPT). Inflammation and OS markers that were measured in duplicate in serum through sandwich enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) included: interleukin-6 (IL-6) (R&amp;D Systems, Inc. Minneapolis, MN, USA), tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-&#945;) (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., Waltham, MA, USA), myeloperoxidase (MPO) (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., Waltham, MA, USA) and oxidized low-density lipoprotein (oxLDL) (Mercodia, AB, Uppsala, Sweden).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>MicroRNA Quantification in Plasma</title><p id="Par13">Four miRNAs (mir21-5p, mir126-3p, mir146a-5p, mir155-5p) were quantified in plasma of patients with knee&#160;OA through reverse transcription quantitative real-time PCR (RT-qPCR) analysis. The above miRNAs were selected after thorough bibliographic search as they have been reported to mediate the development, pathogenesis and progression of OA. MagMAX&#8482; mirVana&#8482; Total RNA Isolation Kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., Waltham, MA, USA) was used for the extraction of total RNA (enriched in miRNAs) from plasma according to the manufacturer&#8217;s protocol. RNA quality and quantity was assessed using an Implen P330 nanophotometer (Implen GmbH). cDNA was produced using TaqMan&#174; Advanced miRNA cDNA Synthesis Kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., Waltham, MA, USA). MiRNA expression was determined in StepOnePlus&#8482; Real-Time PCR System (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., Waltham, MA, USA) in duplicates using TaqMan&#174; Advanced miRNA Assays (for I-miR-21-5p (assay ID #477975_mir) fIhsa-miR-126-3p (assay ID #477887_mir)Ior hsa-miR-146a-5p (assay ID #478399_mir)Id for hsa-miR-155-5p (assay ID #477927_mir). ExpressionSuite&#8482; Software was used to calculate relative expression using the comparative Ct (&#916;&#916;Ct) method and an exogenous control (Caenorhabditis elegans miRNA Cel-miR-39-3p (assay ID #478293_mir)) was used for normalization. Relative levels of miRNAs were compared to a reference sample, and results are presented as fold change using the 2<sup>&#8722;&#916;&#916;Ct</sup> formula, where &#916;&#916;Ct&#8201;=&#8201;[(Ct gene of interest-Ct control) sample] &#8211; [(Ct gene of interest-Ct control) reference sample].</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Inductively Coupled Plasma Mass Spectrometry for Metal Quantification</title><p id="Par14">Plastic materials contacting blood samples were thoroughly washed, subsequently soaked in dilute HNO<sub>3</sub> (Merck, Darmstadt, Germany), and finally rinsed with ultrapure water of 18.2 M&#937; cm (Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA). Samples dilution was performed with micropipettes subject to regular calibration. Class A volumetric glassware was used in order to prepare all required solutions. For samples digestion a mixture of HNO<sub>3</sub> (suprapur 65%) (Merck) and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (suprapur 30%) (Merck) was used and the procedure followed is described by Jin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] and Bat&#225;riov&#225; et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], modified to a small extent. Analysis of the digested samples was carried out employing an ICP-MS (Thermo Scientific ICAP Qc, Waltham, MA USA), with measurements performed in a single collision cell mode, with kinetic energy discrimination (KED) using pure He. Internal standards (<sup>45</sup>Sc, <sup>103</sup>Rh) were used for the correction of matrix induced signal suppressions and instrumental drift. Each sample was analyzed twice, with the average of the two measurements being used for the statistical treatment of data. The limits of detection (LOD), calculated according to US EPA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], varied from 0.03 &#956;g L<sup>&#8722;1</sup> for Cs and Tl to 0.8 for Fe. For statistical calculations, values below the LOD were assigned the method detection limit divided by &#8730;2.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p id="Par15">The Shapiro&#8211;Wilk test was used to assess normal distribution. Continuous variables are presented as medians (interquartile range, IQR) or as mean&#8201;&#177;&#8201;standard deviation (SD). Categorical data are presented as counts and percentages. Student&#8217;s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test (normally distributed data) and Mann&#8211;Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> test (non-normally distributed data) were used for the comparisons of means between two independent groups. Correlations between two variables were investigated using Spearman&#8217;s correlation test. Linear models were used to test the associations of metals with study parameters that showed a significant bivariate correlation. Not normally distributed parameters were log transformed where needed. Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS 21.0 (IBM, SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Results</title><p id="Par16">Since accurate plasma metal and miRNA measurements require high-quality samples, a subset of 34 participants (out of 60 participants) were selected to be included in this study. The descriptive characteristics of the study population are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. OA patients had a mean age of 60.2&#8201;&#177;&#8201;10.1, and a mean BMI over 30 (30.1&#8201;&#177;&#8201;5.0). They were mostly females, married or divorced, with moderate to severe OA.<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Descriptive characteristics of the sample</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OA patients (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;34)<break/>Mean&#8201;&#177;&#8201;SD or median (IQR)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Demographic/anthropometric characteristics</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Age (years)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.2&#8201;&#177;&#8201;10.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sex</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Females, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (61.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Males, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (38.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.1&#8201;&#177;&#8201;5.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">WC (cm)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103.9&#8201;&#177;&#8201;10.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">WHR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (20.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (79.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Marital status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Married/divorced, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (82.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unmarried, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (17.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Education</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1&#8211;9 years, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (20.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10&#8211;12 years, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (17.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&gt;&#8201;12 years, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (61.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Disease indices</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Kelgren and Lawrence</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (17.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,<italic toggle="yes"> N</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (58.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (23.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">VAS</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.0&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">WOMAC pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.0&#8201;&#177;&#8201;3.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">WOMAC stiffness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0 (2.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">WOMAC function</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.0 (17.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">WOMAC total score (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.9 (24.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Biochemical parameters</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Vitamin D (ng/mL)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.2&#8201;&#177;&#8201;12.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;TC (mg/dL)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200.0&#8201;&#177;&#8201;37.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;LDL (mg/dL)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">118.4&#8201;&#177;&#8201;34.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;HDL (mg/dL)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.2&#8201;&#177;&#8201;12.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;TG (mg/dL)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">123.0 (74.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Glucose (mg/dL)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95.0 (13.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Creatinine (mg/dL)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7 (0.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Urea (mg/dL)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.5&#8201;&#177;&#8201;11.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Albumin (g/dL)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.4&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;SGOT (U/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.0 (5.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;SGPT (U/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.0 (14.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Inflammatory/oxidative stress biomarkers</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;CRP (mg/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8 (2.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;IL-6 (pg/mL)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.9 (1.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;TNFa (pg/mL)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9 (0.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;OxLDL (U/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.7 (40.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;MPO (ng/mL)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.4 (61.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Relative expression of OA-related miRNAs (RQ)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;miR-21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.752 (1.480)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;miR-126</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.360 (0.730)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;miR-146a</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.640 (1.670)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;mir-155</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.922 (7.100)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">QoL indices</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;SF-36 (physical functioning)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.3&#8201;&#177;&#8201;24.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;SF-36 (bodily pain)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.9&#8201;&#177;&#8201;45.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;SF-36 (energy/fatigue)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.5&#8201;&#177;&#8201;21.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;SF-36 (role limitations due to emotional problems)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100.0 (66.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;SF-36 (Role limitations due to physical health)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.0 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;SF-36 (emotional well-being)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.8&#8201;&#177;&#8201;18.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;SF-36 (social functioning)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75.0 (62.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;SF-36 (general health)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.5 (20.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;PAL (MET-min/week)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1267.0 (1596.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;MedDiet score</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.2&#8201;&#177;&#8201;3.9</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Continuous variables are presented as medians (interquartile range) or as mean&#8201;&#177;&#8201;standard deviation (SD). Categorical data are presented as counts and percentages</p><p><italic toggle="yes">OA</italic> osteoarthritis, <italic toggle="yes">BMI</italic> body mass index, <italic toggle="yes">WC</italic> waist circumference, <italic toggle="yes">WHR</italic> waist to hip ratio, <italic toggle="yes">VAS</italic> visual analogue scale, <italic toggle="yes">WOMAC</italic> Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index, <italic toggle="yes">TC</italic> total cholesterol, <italic toggle="yes">LDL</italic> low density lipoprotein, <italic toggle="yes">HDL</italic> high density lipoprotein, <italic toggle="yes">TG</italic> triglycerides, <italic toggle="yes">SGOT</italic> serum glutamic-oxaloacetic transaminase, <italic toggle="yes">SGPT</italic> serum glutamic-pyruvic transaminase, <italic toggle="yes">CRP</italic> C-reactive protein,, <italic toggle="yes">IL-6</italic> interleukin-6, <italic toggle="yes">TNF-&#945;</italic> tumor necrosis factor-alpha, <italic toggle="yes">oxLDL</italic> oxidized low-density lipoprotein, <italic toggle="yes">MPO</italic> myeloperoxidase, <italic toggle="yes">RQ</italic> relative quantification, <italic toggle="yes">QoL</italic> quality of life, <italic toggle="yes">SF-36</italic> short form-36, <italic toggle="yes">PAL</italic> physical activity level as assessed by International Physical Activity Questionnaire Short Form</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par17">In Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, plasma levels of metals in all participants and in males or females are presented. Distribution between sexes was similar in all metals examined.<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Plasma metals in all participants (total), males and females</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;34)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Males (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;13)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Females (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;21)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V (&#956;g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.36 (1.17)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.35 (1.27)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.26 (1.23)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.753</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cr (&#956;g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.59 (4.72)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.07 (5.02)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.64 (4.57)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.753</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mn (&#956;g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.85 (5.68)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.98 (9.98)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.22 (4.4)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.181</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fe (&#956;g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1348 (413)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1371 (594)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1332 (492)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.727</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Co (&#956;g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.35 (0.72)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.24 (1.07)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.49 (0.61)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.529</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ni (&#956;g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.65 (2.54)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.69 (6.54)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.53 (2.81)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.889</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cu (&#956;g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1119&#8201;&#177;&#8201;186</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1057&#8201;&#177;&#8201;155</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1157&#8201;&#177;&#8201;197</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.131</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Zn (&#956;g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">966 (422)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">972 (435)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">869 (353)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.624</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">As (&#956;g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (2.11)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.21 (2.32)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.30 (1.83)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.193</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Se (&#956;g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.4&#8201;&#177;&#8201;20.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.7&#8201;&#177;&#8201;21.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.8&#8201;&#177;&#8201;20.4</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.887</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rb (&#956;g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">387&#8201;&#177;&#8201;80</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">414&#8201;&#177;&#8201;72</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">371&#8201;&#177;&#8201;83</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.130</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sr (&#956;g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.1&#8201;&#177;&#8201;9.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.8&#8201;&#177;&#8201;8.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.1&#8201;&#177;&#8201;10.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.433</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cd (&#956;g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06 (0.20)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03 (0.21)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02 (0.08)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.400</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cs (&#956;g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.78 (0.36)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.80 (0.44)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.75 (0.32)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.309</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ba (&#956;g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.67 (8.87)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.20 (8.97)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.14 (7.15)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.807</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tl (&#956;g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05 (0.11)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06 (0.35)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05 (0.08)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.529</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cu/Zn ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2 (0.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2 (0.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2 (0.5)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.441</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Continuous variables are presented as medians (interquartile range) or as mean&#8201;&#177;&#8201;standard deviation (SD). Categorical data are presented as counts and percentages. Student&#8217;s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test (normally distributed data) and Mann&#8211;Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> test (non-normally distributed data) were used for the comparisons of means between two independent groups</p><p><italic toggle="yes">V</italic> vanadium, <italic toggle="yes">Cr</italic> chromium, <italic toggle="yes">Mn</italic> manganese, <italic toggle="yes">Fe</italic> iron, <italic toggle="yes">Co</italic> cobalt, <italic toggle="yes">Ni</italic> nickel, <italic toggle="yes">Cu</italic> copper, <italic toggle="yes">Zn</italic> zinc, <italic toggle="yes">As</italic> arsenic, <italic toggle="yes">Se</italic> selenium, <italic toggle="yes">Rb</italic> rubidium, <italic toggle="yes">Sr</italic> strontium, <italic toggle="yes">Cd</italic> cadmium, <italic toggle="yes">Cs</italic> caesium, <italic toggle="yes">Ba</italic> barium, <italic toggle="yes">Tl</italic> thallium</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par18">In Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, significant correlations between plasma metals, and all parameters tested related to the disease are presented. Mn was negatively correlated with HDL, Fe with urea, As with VitD and Co/Zn ratio with WHR. Co correlated with miR-21 and mir-146a, Ni with oxLDL, Ba with WOMAC total score, Cu correlated positively with WOMAC stiffness, CRP, IL-6&#160;and TNF-&#945;. A negative correlation was found between Zn and HDL and mir-155. Rb correlated positively with creatinine and inversely with glucose. Some interesting correlations were observed between SF-36 questionnaire dimensions and metals. More specifically, SF-36 (role limitations due to emotional problems) correlated with Cd and Cs, SF-36 (role limitations due to physical health) with Ba and SF-36 (social functioning) with Cs. Finally, SF-36 (emotional well-being) was positively corellated with Cd, Cs and Tl&#160;and SF-36 (general health) was positively correlated with Cd, Cs and Cu/Zn.<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Significant correlations among metals/metalloids and parameters reflecting the disease</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Correlations</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rho</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WHR with Cu/Zn</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;0.384</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.033</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WOMAC stiffness with Cu</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.365</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.034</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WOMAC total score (%) with Ba</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.343</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.047</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vit D with As</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;0.378</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.033</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HDL (mg/dL) with Mn</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;0.361</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.036</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HDL (mg/dL) with Zn</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;0.470</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Glucose (mg/dL) with Rb</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;0.427</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Creatinine (mg/dL) with Rb</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.390</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.022</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Urea (mg/dL) with Fe</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;0.341</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.049</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CRP (mg/L) with Cu</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.455</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IL-6 (pg/mL) with Cu</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.606</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TNF-a (pg/mL) with Cu</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.364</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.035</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OxLDL (U/L) with Ni</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.410</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.016</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">miR-21 with Co</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.398</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.036</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">miR-146a with Co</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.442</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.021</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mir-155 with Zn</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;0.513</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.030</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SF-36 (role limitations due to emotional problems) with Cd</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.361</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.039</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SF-36 (role limitations due to emotional problems) with Cs</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.405</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.019</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SF-36 (role limitations due to physical health) with Ba</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.360</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.040</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SF-36 (emotional well-being) with Cd</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.357</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.041</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SF-36 (emotional well-being) with Cs</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.345</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.050</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SF-36 (emotional well-being) with TI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.496</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SF-36 (social functioning) with Cs</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.441</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.010</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SF-36 (general health) with Cd</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.482</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SF-36 (general health) with Cs</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.471</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SF-36 (general health) with Cu/Zn</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.523</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Correlation analysis was performed with Spearman&#8217;s rank correlation. Level of significance was set as 0.05</p><p><italic toggle="yes">WHR</italic> waist to hip ratio, <italic toggle="yes">HDL</italic> high-density lipoprotein, <italic toggle="yes">CRP</italic> C-reactive protein, <italic toggle="yes">IL-6</italic> interleukin-6, <italic toggle="yes">TNF-&#945;</italic> tumor necrosis factor-alpha, <italic toggle="yes">oxLDL</italic> oxidized low-density lipoprotein, <italic toggle="yes">SF-36</italic> short form-36. <italic toggle="yes">Mn</italic> manganese, <italic toggle="yes">Fe</italic> iron, <italic toggle="yes">Co</italic> cobalt, <italic toggle="yes">Ni</italic> nickel, <italic toggle="yes">Cu</italic> copper, <italic toggle="yes">Zn</italic> zinc, <italic toggle="yes">As</italic> arsenic, <italic toggle="yes">Se</italic> selenium, <italic toggle="yes">Rb</italic> rubidium, <italic toggle="yes">Cd</italic> cadmium, <italic toggle="yes">Cs</italic> caesium, <italic toggle="yes">Ba</italic> barium, <italic toggle="yes">Tl</italic> thallium</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par19">Linear regression models were applied to examine the associations of the above studied parameters showing significant correlations (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The first model applied was adjusted for disease severity (as assessed by K&amp;L), the second one for disease severity, age, gender, and BMI while the third one for disease severity, age, gender, BMI, physical activity level, smoking, TKA and dietary intake of the respective metal. Only significant associations in all three models are presented. CRP and IL-6 exhibited a significant positive association with Cu (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.033 and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.001 respectively in the third model), and WHR was negatively associated with Cu/Zn (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.022 in the third model).<table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Significant associations between OA-related parameters and metals</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Model 1</th><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Model 2</th><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Model 3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="12" rowspan="1">CRP</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beta&#8201;&#177;&#8201;SE</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">R</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adj. <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beta&#8201;&#177;&#8201;SE</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">R</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adj. <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beta&#8201;&#177;&#8201;SE</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">R</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adj. <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sup>2</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cu (&#956;g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.002&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">0.402</td><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">0.108</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.002&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">0.494</td><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">0.109</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.002&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.033</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">0.523</td><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Disease activity<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.161&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.256</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.512</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.169&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.268</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.517</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.135&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.312</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.646</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (years)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.995&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.755</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.984&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.496</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex (males vs females)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.767&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.409</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.445</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.851&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.476</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.685</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.993&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.033</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.861</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.991&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.040</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.807</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAL (MET-min/week)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.728</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking status<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.247&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.559</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.624</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TKA (no vs yes)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.291&#8201;&#177;&#8201;2.460</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.728</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cu dietary intake (mg)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.832&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.380</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.573</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="12" rowspan="1">IL-6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beta&#8201;&#177;&#8201;SE</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">R</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adj. <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beta&#8201;&#177;&#8201;SE</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">R</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adj. <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beta&#8201;&#177;&#8201;SE</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">R</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adj. <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sup>2</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cu (&#956;g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.002&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">0.614</td><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">0.336</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.002&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">0.711</td><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">0.417</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.002&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">0.806</td><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">0.518</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Disease activity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.977&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.122</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.845</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.951&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.117</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.646</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.845&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.114</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.131</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (years)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.009&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.007</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.263</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.002&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.009</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.845</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex (males vs females)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.734&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.169</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.061</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.782&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.167</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.121</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.033&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.036</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.019&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.257</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAL (MET-min/week)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.937&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.107</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.675&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.191</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.007</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TKA (no vs yes)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.227&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.425</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.571</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cu dietary intake (mg)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.869&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.135</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.281</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="12" rowspan="1">WHR*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beta&#8201;&#177;&#8201;SE</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">R</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adj. <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beta&#8201;&#177;&#8201;SE</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">R</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adj. <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beta&#8201;&#177;&#8201;SE</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">R</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adj. <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sup>2</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cu/Zn</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;0.024&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.010</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.021</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">0.499</td><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">0.195</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;0.020&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.008</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.023</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">0.728</td><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">0.457</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;0.021&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.009</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.022</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">0.781</td><td align="left" rowspan="9" colspan="1">0.442</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Disease activity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.026&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.135</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.025&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.014</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.092</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.017&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.280</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (years)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.041</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.309</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex (males vs females)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;0.077&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.020</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;0.071&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAL (MET-min/week)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;1.020&#8201;&#215;&#8201;10<sup>&#8722;5</sup>&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.061</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.008&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.741</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TKA (no vs yes)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.050</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.980</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cu dietary intake (mg)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;0.006&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.784</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Zn dietary intake (mg)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.002</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.847</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Model 1: adj. for disease activity (as assessed by Kelgren and Lawrence); model 2: adj. for disease activity, age, gender, and BMI; model 3: adj. for disease activity, age, gender, BMI, PAL, smoking, TKA, and dietary intake of the respective metal. CRP and IL-6 were logarithmically transformed during the analysis; therefore, the results (beta&#8201;&#177;&#8201;SE) are presented as exponential, meaning that for every 1-unit increase in the independent variable, the dependent variable changes by the beta coefficient as a percentage. WHR was not logarithmically transformed, meaning that for every 1-unit increase in the independent variable, the dependent variable will change (increase or decrease) by the beta coefficient value</p><p><italic toggle="yes">BMI</italic> body mass index, <italic toggle="yes">CRP</italic> C-reactive protein, <italic toggle="yes">Cu</italic> copper, <italic toggle="yes">IL-6</italic> interleukin-6, <italic toggle="yes">PAL</italic> physical activity level as assessed by International Physical Activity Questionnaire Short Form, <italic toggle="yes">TKA</italic> total knee arthroplasty, <italic toggle="yes">Zn</italic> zinc, <italic toggle="yes">SE</italic> standard error, <italic toggle="yes">Adj. R</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">2</italic></sup> adjusted <italic toggle="yes">R</italic>.<sup>2</sup></p><p><sup>a</sup>Disease activity was assessed by Kelgren and Lawrence</p><p><sup>b</sup>Smoking status as non-smokers vs smokers</p><p>*BMI adjustment was not used in these models. Values resulted from linear regression models. Level of significance was set as 0.05. Significant <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> is in bold</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par20">The role of metals in human health and development, and progress of diseases is well documented. During the last decades, human exposure to heavy metals has increased due to industrial and everyday life and has been associated with several acute and chronic toxic effects contributing to gastrointestinal, nervous, immune system dysfunction, cancers, and other disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. On the contrary, trace elements are essential for several biological functions, serving as catalysts in enzyme systems, oxidation reactions, and oxygen transport, whereas their insufficient or excessive concentrations are associated with several diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Although the role of metals in inflammation and inflammation associated diseases, such as OA, is well established, the exact epigenetic mechanisms that underlie their activities are not fully explored. This is the first study to report a full profile of plasma metals in a Greek OA population. No differences were observed between males and females. Compared to other studies in non-Greek OA patients, we report similar levels in circulating Se and Cu [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], but higher levels of Fe and Zn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] and lower of Cd and Mn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p><p id="Par21">Herein, the sampling strategy selected assured a qualitative data collection. Thus, the thirty-four OA patients had moderate to severe symptoms according to K&amp;L, VAS, and WOMAC, and were mostly non-smokers. The descriptive characteristics of our population coincided with those of the Greek epidemiological study on OA (ESORDIG) reporting higher prevalence of OA in females, aged&#8201;&gt;&#8201;50 years, in obese and non-smokers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p><p id="Par22">Several significant correlations of plasma metals with anthropometrics, disease severity, biochemical, inflammatory/OS markers, QoL and miRNAs were found in our study population.</p><p id="Par23">WOMAC stiffness was positively correlated with Cu and WOMAC total score with Ba. Disease severity has been previously reported to correlate with Cu [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], but, so far, no data exist for its potential relation with Ba levels. Cd, Cs, Ba, and Tl were positively correlated with various dimensions of SF-36 that reflect QoL in OA, although previous studies have shown that exposure to Cd, Cs, and Tl increases OA risk, possibly mediated by biological aging [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. This paradox finding in our study may in part be explained by the fact that the observed positive correlation between these metals and QoL was not confirmed when adjusting for possible confounders, such as age. Regarding correlations with biochemical and OS markers, our findings confirm already known relations between trace elements and biochemical profile, however, most of them are shown herewith for the first time in Greek OA patients.</p><p id="Par24">Similar to our finding, it has been previously demonstrated that Mn is negatively correlated with HDL in aging men with metabolic syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. As expected, Fe, which is beneficial for kidney function was negatively correlated with urea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] and Rb which is considered nephrotoxic was positively correlated with creatinine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Also, a positive correlation was found between Ni and oxLDL confirming the existing knowledge that Ni exposure is associated with increased OS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. In our study Zn was negatively correlated with HDL. Zn supplementation is known to increase HDL levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Additionally, As was negatively correlated with vitamin D in accordance with recent literature that reports that the effect of As exposure on Th17 function is modified by vitamin D status [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], supporting the negative correlation of As with vitamin D herein. Finally, some studies show that Rb is positively associated with diabetes risk or glucose levels, while others demonstrate the opposite [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>].</p><p id="Par25">Furthermore, we exhibited some noteworthy correlations of plasma metals with miRNA levels that help explain the complex relationships between lifestyle, environment, and molecular traits of OA. Co correlated positively with miR-21 and mir-146a and Zn inversely with mir-155. These three miRNAs contribute to the pathogenesis of OA and are usually upregulated in the tissues of OA patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. They are already known to regulate inflammatory responses, apoptosis, chondrogenesis and cartilage homeostasis and target key signaling mediators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. For example, miR-21 downregulates programmed cell death 4 protein and growth differentiation factor 5 (GDF-5) impairing osteoclastogenesis and chondrogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>], miR-146a upregulates Vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) and downregulates Smad4 expression increasing apoptosis rate in chondrocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>] and miR-155 inhibits gene expression of autophagy regulators such as Unc-51-like kinase 1 (Ulk1) and Forkhead transcription factor (FoxO3) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].</p><p id="Par26">Upregulation of miR-21 by Co has been described previously when treatment of human renal epithelial cells with cobalt chloride increased miR-21 levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. A direct association of Co with miR-146a levels has not been shown before, but miR-146a is known to be implicated in the detrimental effects of several metals, such as Cd and Pb and its dysregulation mediates disease progression attributed to heavy metals toxicity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Finally zinc finger proteins are known as direct targets of miR-155 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>], which may explain the negative correlation we found between plasma Zn and miR-155 levels.</p><p id="Par27">After controlling disease activity, age, and gender, a relationship between BMI and IL-6 was present. IL-6 is produced by adipose tissue and the mean values for WC and WHR herewith are indicative of abdominal obesity. According to previous study, obesity increases the crosstalk between chondrocytes and synovial fibroblasts by elevating levels of the pro-inflammatory adipokine leptin, which causes OA patients to produce more IL-6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Yet, the aforementioned association did not survive when applying the regression model 3. On the contrary, the association between smoking status, as non-smokers vs smokers, and IL-6 survived all three regression models in our study. Knee OA has been shown to have an inverse relationship with smoking [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Given that BMI is a key risk factor for OA, there is some evidence to suggest that non-smokers often have higher BMIs than smokers, which results in a high prevalence of OA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. However, this needs to be further investigated as a recent observation in the US NHANES 1999&#8211;2018 study supports that there is a positive association between smoking and OA prevalence, yet with the major limitations of no physical examination to determine whether participants had OA and the absence of covariates, such as physical activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>].</p><p id="Par28">When adjusting for disease severity, age, gender, BMI, physical activity level, smoking, TKA and dietary intake of the respective metal (regression model 3), Cu was associated positively with inflammatory markers (CRP, IL-6, and Cu/Zn negatively with WHR. Although weak, the associations of Cu with inflammatory markers herein can be considered as preliminary evidence of a potential in-between link that needs to be further investigated. The role of Cu in OA is well established, being essential for bone health. It promotes regeneration of articular cartilage, enhances chondrogenesis differentiation and regulates cellular and humoral immunity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. However, its role may be considered bidirectional; in OA patients, serum Cu levels are higher compared with healthy controls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>] and Cu accumulation in Wilson's disease is related to early-onset of OA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>], probably due to the copper-mediated oxidations and collagen degradation when free Cu occurs in excess [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. Contradictory findings have been found in the literature about changes in circulation levels with aging; unaltered levels with aging were seen in patients aged 75 to 85 as well as younger subjects (55 to 64 years) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. The concentration of blood Cu was higher in healthy older people sampled in Italy than in younger individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. In our study, plasma Cu levels in patients with moderate to severe OA were comparable with Cu levels in Greek healthy and not-OA adults when assessed applying the exact same methodology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Hereby, in our cohort of OA older-adults, Cu levels were associated with several inflammatory markers (CRP, IL-6) even after adjusting for possible confounders (including Cu dietary intake and TKA) enhancing the robustness of our results. Although Cu&#8217;s role may be very important in early stages of life, as it is essential for iron metabolism, immune function, energy production, and neurological system, during aging, when all metabolic functions change, its role may be connected to several diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. Interestingly, Zhou et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>] showed that genetically predicted higher Cu levels are associated with increased risk for OA.</p><p id="Par29">Additionally, we calculated the&#160;Cu/Zn ratio, which is suggested as a better biomarker of inflammatory or nutritional changes than Cu and has been associated with several diseases and mortality in elderly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>] and correlates with OA severity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Cu/Zn was negatively associated with WHR in our OA patients, independently of their disease severity, age, gender, smoking status, TKA, physical activity and nutritional intakes of Cu and Zn. Cu, Zn or Cu/Zn have been independently associated with BMI and obesity, with Cu and Cu/Zn showing a positive and Zn a negative association [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. The study of Kerkadi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>] showed the same paradox in a general population, where Zn/Cu ratio positively correlated with waist circumference, although it negatively correlated with BMI and Cu levels positively with BMI.</p><p id="Par30">This is the first study that, to the best of our knowledge, analyzed the whole profile of plasma metals in Greek knee OA patients and assessed how they are connected to several disease-associated variables of the population, including miRNAs. Yet, it displays both strengths and limitations. All questionnaires and tools used in this study (disease severity, QoL, nutritional analysis) are validated and methodologies for metals, miRNAs and biomarkers assessment are well established offering high sensitivity and specificity. However, the small sample size, and the lack of a control sample do not allow us to extrapolate our findings.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par31">A positive association between plasma Cu levels and inflammatory biomarkers in OA was demonstrated for the first time in the present study. Correlations were pointed between circulating metals and both disease related parameters and miRNAs, partly explaining the role of metals in OA progression. Although not all correlations were confirmed when adjusting for potential confounders, several are reported for the first time in OA patients. Our findings encourage further research on metals related to OA in bigger samples, which will enable us to validate the above correlations and explain the absence of others.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>Charalampia Amerikanou and Evdokia Valsamidou have equally contributed to this work.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contribution</title><p>ACK designed the study. CA and EV wrote the manuscript. CA, EV, SK, DT, AS, MK conducted the experiments. CA analyzed the data. All authors have read and approved the final version.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by HEAL-Link Greece. The implementation of the doctoral thesis of E.V. was co-financed by Greece and the European Union (European Social Fund-ESF) through the Operational Programme &#171;Human Resources Development, Education and Lifelong Learning&#187; in the context of the Act &#8220;Enhancing Human Resources Research Potential by undertaking a Doctoral Research&#8221; Sub-action 2: IKY Scholarship Programme for PhD candidates in the Greek Universities.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p>Upon reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval</title><p id="Par32">This study was performed in line with the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki. Approval was granted by Harokopio University Ethics Committee (13/21&#8211;2-2020) and Evgenidio Hospital Scientific Board (29/19&#8211;02-2019).</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent to Participate</title><p id="Par33">All authors have given their consent for publication.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Consent for Publication</title><p id="Par34">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar4" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par35">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Branco</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Osteoarthritis</article-title><source>Acta Med Port</source><year>2015</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2034/amp.5477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25817486</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McBeth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Update on the epidemiology, risk factors and disease outcomes of osteoarthritis</article-title><source>Best Pract Res Clin Rheumatol</source><year>2018</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>312</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.berh.2018.10.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30527434</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martel-Pelletier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cicuttini</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conaghan</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldring</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldring</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teichtahl</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><source>Osteoarthritis Nat Rev Dis Primers</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>16072</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrdp.2016.72</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27734845</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abramoff</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caldera</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Osteoarthritis: pathology, diagnosis, and treatment options</article-title><source>Med Clin North Am</source><year>2020</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcna.2019.10.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32035570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Far&#236;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Megna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scacco</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ranieri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hemp seed oil in association with &#946;-caryophyllene, myrcene and ginger extract as a nutraceutical integration in knee osteoarthritis: a double-blind prospective case-control study</article-title><source>Medicina (Kaunas)</source><year>2023</year><volume>59</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>191</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/medicina59020191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36837393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9960141</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodell-May</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sommerfeld</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of Inflammation and the Immune System in the Progression of Osteoarthritis</article-title><source>J Orthop Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jor.24457</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31469192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Samman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of heavy metal impurities in secondary Mg alloys on the microstructure and mechanical properties during deformation</article-title><source>Mater Des</source><year>2015</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>983</fpage><lpage>988</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.matdes.2014.10.025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of heavy metals on human metabolism</article-title><source>Toxicol Mech Methods</source><year>2020</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15376516.2019.1701594</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31818169</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zoroddu</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aaseth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crisponi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Medici</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nurchi</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The essential metals for humans: a brief overview</article-title><source>J Inorg Biochem</source><year>2019</year><volume>195</volume><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinorgbio.2019.03.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30939379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jomova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Makova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alomar</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alwasel</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nepovimova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuca</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential metals in health and disease</article-title><source>Chem Biol Interact</source><year>2022</year><volume>367</volume><fpage>110173</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cbi.2022.110173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36152810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mobasheri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of metabolism in chondrocyte dysfunction and the progression of osteoarthritis</article-title><source>Ageing Res Rev</source><year>2021</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>101249</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arr.2020.101249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33383189</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>TX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothenberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2018</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>1202</fpage><lpage>1207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2017.08.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29074454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5889965</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swingler</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paddy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barter</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joung</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The function of microRNAs in cartilage and osteoarthritis</article-title><source>Clin Exp Rheumatol</source><year>2019</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31621575</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Associations of blood levels of trace elements and heavy metals with metabolic syndrome in Chinese male adults with microRNA as mediators involved</article-title><source>Environ Pollut</source><year>2019</year><volume>248</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2019.02.015Li2022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30771749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Circulating metals, leukocyte microRNAs and microRNA networks: A profiling and functional analysis in Chinese adults</article-title><source>Environ Int</source><year>2022</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>107511</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2022.107511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36095929</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Associations between microRNA (miR-21, 126, 155 and 221), albuminuria and heavy metals in Hong Kong Chinese adolescents</article-title><source>Clin Chim Acta; Int J Clin Chem</source><year>2012</year><volume>413</volume><issue>13&#8211;14</issue><fpage>1053</fpage><lpage>1057</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cca.2012.02.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22405870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taalab</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Toxic-metal-induced alteration in miRNA expression profile as a proposed mechanism for disease development</article-title><source>Cells</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>901</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cells9040901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32272672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7226740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kellgren</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Radiological assessment of osteo-arthrosis</article-title><source>Ann Rheum Dis</source><year>1957</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>494</fpage><lpage>502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ard.16.4.494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13498604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1006995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alarc&#243;n</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Appelrouth</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bloch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borenstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The American College of Rheumatology criteria for the classification and reporting of osteoarthritis of the hip</article-title><source>Arthritis Rheum</source><year>1991</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>514</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.1780340502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2025304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellamy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stitt</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validation study of WOMAC: a health status instrument for measuring clinically important patient-relevant outcomes following total hip or knee arthroplasty in osteoarthritis</article-title><source>J Orthop Rheumatol</source><year>1988</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3068365</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Free online SF-36 score calculator &#8211; OrthoToolKit. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orthotoolkit.com/sf-36/">https://orthotoolkit.com/sf-36/</ext-link>. Accessed 20 May 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sj&#246;str&#246;m</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauman</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ainsworth</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekelund</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yngve</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sallis</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oja</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>International physical activity questionnaire: 12-country reliability and validity</article-title><source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source><year>2003</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1381</fpage><lpage>1395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/01.MSS.0000078924.61453.FB</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12900694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Panagiotakos</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pitsavos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stefanadis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dietary patterns: a Mediterranean diet score and its relation to clinical and biological markers of cardiovascular disease risk</article-title><source>Nutr Metab Cardiovasc Dis</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>559</fpage><lpage>568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.numecd.2005.08.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17126772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Concentrations of selected heavy metals in maternal blood and associated factors in rural areas in Shanxi Province, China</article-title><source>Environ Int</source><year>2014</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2014.01.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24584080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bat&#225;riov&#225;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spev&#225;ckov&#225;</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benes</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cejchanov&#225;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sm&#237;d</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cern&#225;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blood and urine levels of Pb, Cd and Hg in the general population of the Czech Republic and proposed reference values</article-title><source>Int J Hyg Environ Health</source><year>2006</year><volume>209</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijheh.2006.02.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16740414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">United States Environmental Protection Agency (1997) Definition and procedures for the determination of the method detection limit, App B, Part 136, 343&#8211;345, 40 CFR Ch (7&#8211;1&#8211;12 edition)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Balali-Mood</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naseri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tahergorabi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khazdair</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadeghi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxic mechanisms of five heavy metals: mercury, lead, chromium, cadmium, and arsenic</article-title><source>Front Pharmacol</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>643972</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2021.643972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33927623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8078867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Konikowska K, Mandecka A (2018) Trace elements in human nutrition. In: Chojnacka K, Saeid A (ed) Recent Advances in Trace Elements Wiley: 339&#8211;372</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between serum levels of some trace elements, disease duration and severity in patients with knee osteoarthritis</article-title><source>Pharmacol Pharm</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>495</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4236/pp.2015.611051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yazar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarban</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kocyigit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isikan</surname><given-names>UE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synovial fluid and plasma selenium, copper, zinc, and iron concentrations in patients with rheumatoid arthritis and osteoarthritis</article-title><source>Biol Trace Elem Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>106</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1385/BTER:106:2:123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16116244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification for heavy metals exposure on osteoarthritis among aging people and Machine learning for prediction: a study based on NHANES 2011&#8211;2020</article-title><source>Front Public Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>906774</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.906774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35979456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9376265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrianakos</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kontelis</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karamitsos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aslanidis</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Georgountzos</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaziolas</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pantelidou</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vafiadou</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dantis</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><collab>ESORDIG Study Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of symptomatic knee, hand, and hip osteoarthritis in Greece The ESORDIG study</article-title><source>J Rheumatol</source><year>2006</year><volume>33</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2507</fpage><lpage>2513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17143985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological aging mediates the associations between urinary metals and osteoarthritis among U. S. adults</article-title><source>BMC Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>207</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12916-022-02403-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35710548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9205020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rotter</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kosik-Bogacka</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Do&#322;&#281;gowska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Safranow</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lubkowska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laszczy&#324;ska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between the concentrations of heavy metals and bioelements in aging men with metabolic syndrome</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2015</year><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>3944</fpage><lpage>3961</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph120403944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25867198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4410226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Swelm</surname><given-names>RPL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wetzels</surname><given-names>JFM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swinkels</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The multifaceted role of iron in renal health and disease</article-title><source>Nat Rev Nephrol</source><year>2020</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41581-019-0197-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31554933</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Associations of plasma metal concentrations with the decline in kidney function: A longitudinal study of Chinese adults</article-title><source>Ecotoxicol Environ Saf</source><year>2020</year><volume>189</volume><fpage>110006</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2019.110006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31812020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chadchan</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biradar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nickel and oxidative stress: cell signaling mechanisms and protective role of vitamin C</article-title><source>Endocr Metab Immune Disord Drug Targets</source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1024</fpage><lpage>1031</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1871530319666191205122249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31804169</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Partida-Hern&#225;ndez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arreola</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fenton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cabeza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rom&#225;n-Ramos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Revilla-Monsalve</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of zinc replacement on lipids and lipoproteins in type 2-diabetic patients</article-title><source>Biomed Pharmacother</source><year>2006</year><volume>60</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2006.02.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16632297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parvez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lauer</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Factor-Litvak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eunus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horayara</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarwar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahsan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graziano</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burchiel</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exposure to arsenic and level of Vitamin D influence the number of Th17 cells and production of IL-17A in human peripheral blood mononuclear cells in adults</article-title><source>PloS One</source><year>2022</year><volume>17</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e0266168</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0266168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35404942</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9000092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of urinary metal profiles with altered glucose levels and diabetes risk: a population-based study in China</article-title><source>PloS One</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e0123742</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25874871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4395404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Associations of plasma metal levels with type 2 diabetes and the mediating effects of microRNAs</article-title><source>Environ Pollut</source><year>2022</year><volume>292</volume><issue>Pt B</issue><fpage>118452</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2021.118452</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34737026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snijders</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribution of trace element exposure to gestational diabetes mellitus through disturbing the gut microbiome</article-title><source>Environ Int</source><year>2021</year><volume>153</volume><fpage>106520</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2021.106520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33774496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8638703</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lao</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le</surname><given-names>TAH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Data integration reveals the potential biomarkers of circulating microRNAs in osteoarthritis</article-title><source>Diagnostics (Basel, Switzerland)</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>412</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/diagnostics11030412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33670901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7997238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-21 controls the development of osteoarthritis by targeting GDF-5 in chondrocytes</article-title><source>Exp Mol Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>46</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e79</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emm.2013.152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24577233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3944443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Noncoding RNAs in subchondral bone osteoclast function and their therapeutic potential for osteoarthritis</article-title><source>Arthritis Res Ther</source><year>2020</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>279</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13075-020-02374-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33239099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7690185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sondag</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haqqi</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of microRNAs and their targets in osteoarthritis</article-title><source>Curr Rheumatol Rep</source><year>2016</year><volume>18</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>56</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11926-016-0604-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27402113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5294969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugatani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vacher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hruska</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A microRNA expression signature of osteoclastogenesis</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2011</year><volume>117</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>3648</fpage><lpage>3657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2010-10-311415</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21273303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3072882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>miR-146a, an IL-1&#946; responsive miRNA, induces vascular endothelial growth factor and chondrocyte apoptosis by targeting Smad4</article-title><source>Arthritis Res Ther</source><year>2012</year><volume>14</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>R75</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/ar3798</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22507670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3446449</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Adamo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez-Garcia</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muramatsu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flamigni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lotz</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-155 suppresses autophagy in chondrocytes by modulating expression of autophagy proteins</article-title><source>Osteoarthr Cartil</source><year>2016</year><volume>24</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1082</fpage><lpage>1091</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joca.2016.01.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4875787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26805019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kriegel</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Usa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mladinov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Delayed ischemic preconditioning contributes to renal protection by upregulation of miR-21</article-title><source>Kidney Int</source><year>2012</year><volume>82</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1167</fpage><lpage>1175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ki.2012.241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22785173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3777822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapral</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wawszczyk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>W&#281;glarz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of microRNA-155 and its related genes expression by inositol hexaphosphate in colon cancer cells</article-title><source>Molecules (Basel, Switzerland)</source><year>2019</year><volume>24</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>4153</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules24224153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31744065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6891702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herndler-Brandstetter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tariq</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Philp</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IL-6 secretion in osteoarthritis patients is mediated by chondrocyte-synovial fibroblast cross-talk and is enhanced by obesity</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3451</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-03759-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28615667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5471184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between smoking and risk of knee osteoarthritis: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Osteoarthr Cartil</source><year>2017</year><volume>25</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>809</fpage><lpage>816</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joca.2016.12.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28011100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>UDT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does smoking cessation increase risk of knee replacement? a general population-based cohort study</article-title><source>Osteoarthr Cartil</source><year>2021</year><volume>29</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>697</fpage><lpage>706</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joca.2021.02.382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33621706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of smoking and osteoarthritis in US (NHANES 1999&#8211;2018)</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3911</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-30644-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36890196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9995311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of trace elements on osteoarthritis</article-title><source>Front Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>771297</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2021.771297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8732765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35004740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The daily intake levels of copper, selenium, and zinc are associated with osteoarthritis but not with rheumatoid arthritis in a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Biol Trace Elem Res</source><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12011-023-03636-w.10.1007/s12011-023-03636-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36943549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genotype and clinical course in 2 Chinese Han siblings with Wilson disease presenting with isolated disabling premature osteoarthritis: a case report</article-title><source>Medicine</source><year>2017</year><volume>96</volume><issue>47</issue><fpage>e8641</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000008641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29381936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5708935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiku</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Narla</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yalamanchili</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glucosamine prevents in vitro collagen degradation in chondrocytes by inhibiting advanced lipoxidation reactions and protein oxidation</article-title><source>Arthritis Res Ther</source><year>2007</year><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>R76</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/ar2274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17686167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2206377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sfar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Heni</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laporte</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Braham</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jawed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sfar</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerkeni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trace element status and fatty acids metabolism during healthy ageing: an example of a population from the Tunisian eastern coast</article-title><source>Exp Gerontol</source><year>2012</year><volume>47</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exger.2011.12.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22222317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Corso</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pastine</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Protti</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romanelli</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moruzzo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruocco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pentimone</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blood zinc, copper and magnesium in aging. A study in healthy home-living elderly</article-title><source>Panminerva Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>42</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11294091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asprouli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalafati</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakellari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karavoltsos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vlachogiannakos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Revenas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kokkinos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dassenakis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dedoussis</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalogeropoulos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of plasma trace elements in different stages of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease</article-title><source>Biol Trace Elem Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>188</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12011-018-1432-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30014284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risks of copper and iron toxicity during aging in humans</article-title><source>Chem Res Toxicol</source><year>2010</year><volume>23</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/tx900338d</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19968254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grider</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetically predicted circulating levels of copper and zinc are associated with osteoarthritis but not with rheumatoid arthritis</article-title><source>Osteoarthr Cartil</source><year>2021</year><volume>29</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1029</fpage><lpage>1035</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joca.2021.02.564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33640581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malavolta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giacconi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piacenza</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santarelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cipriano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costarelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tesei</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierpaoli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galeazzi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lattanzio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mocchegiani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plasma copper/zinc ratio: an inflammatory/nutritional biomarker as predictor of all-cause mortality in elderly population</article-title><source>Biogerontology</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10522-009-9251-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19821050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Escobedo-Monge</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrado</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parodi-Rom&#225;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Escobedo-Monge</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres-Hinojal</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marug&#225;n-Miguelsanz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Copper/zinc ratio in childhood and adolescence: a review</article-title><source>Metabolites</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>82</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/metabo13010082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36677007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9862945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olechnowicz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tinkov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skalny</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suliburska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zinc status is associated with inflammation, oxidative stress, lipid, and glucose metabolism</article-title><source>J Physiol Sci: JPS</source><year>2018</year><volume>68</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12576-017-0571-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28965330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5754376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torkanlou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bibak</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbaspour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reduced serum levels of zinc and superoxide dismutase in obese individuals</article-title><source>Ann Nutr Metab</source><year>2016</year><volume>69</volume><issue>3&#8211;4</issue><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000454894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28002829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerkadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alkudsi</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alkeldi</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salih</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agouni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>the association between zinc and copper circulating levels and cardiometabolic risk factors in adults: a study of Qatar Biobank Data</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><year>2021</year><volume>13</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2729</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu13082729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34444889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8398315</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>