<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.--><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Reg Anesth Pain Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Reg Anesth Pain Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">319</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">nihpa</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Regional anesthesia and pain medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1098-7339</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-8651</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>NIHPA Author Manuscripts</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10370290</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10370290.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10370290</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10370290</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id">NIHMS1911318</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37001888</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/rapm-2022-104097</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHMS1911318</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHPA1911318</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evidence-based consensus guidelines on patient selection and trial stimulation for spinal cord stimulation therapy for chronic non-cancer pain</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4105-4465</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Shanthanna</surname><given-names initials="H">Harsha</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eldabe</surname><given-names initials="S">Sam</given-names></name><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2147-3523</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Provenzano</surname><given-names initials="DA">David Anthony</given-names></name><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouche</surname><given-names initials="B">Benedicte</given-names></name><xref rid="A4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchser</surname><given-names initials="E">Eric</given-names></name><xref rid="A5" ref-type="aff">5</xref><xref rid="A6" ref-type="aff">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chadwick</surname><given-names initials="R">Raymond</given-names></name><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5011-3298</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Doshi</surname><given-names initials="TL">Tina L</given-names></name><xref rid="A7" ref-type="aff">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6485-7415</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names initials="R">Rui</given-names></name><xref rid="A8" ref-type="aff">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0507-7889</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names initials="C">Christine</given-names></name><xref rid="A9" ref-type="aff">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huygen</surname><given-names initials="FJPM">Frank J P M</given-names></name><xref rid="A10" ref-type="aff">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names initials="J">Judy</given-names></name><xref rid="A11" ref-type="aff">11</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohan</surname><given-names initials="L">Lynn</given-names></name><xref rid="A12" ref-type="aff">12</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>North</surname><given-names initials="R">Richard</given-names></name><xref rid="A13" ref-type="aff">13</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenow</surname><given-names initials="J">Joshua</given-names></name><xref rid="A14" ref-type="aff">14</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winfree</surname><given-names initials="CJ">Christopher J</given-names></name><xref rid="A15" ref-type="aff">15</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1849-1402</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Narouze</surname><given-names initials="S">Samer</given-names></name><xref rid="A16" ref-type="aff">16</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Anesthesia, McMaster University, Hamilton, Ontario, Canada</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>James Cook University Hospital, Middlesbrough, UK</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Pain Diagnostics and Interventional Care, Sewickley, Pennsylvania, USA</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>CHU Poitiers, Poitiers, France</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Pain Management and Neuromodulation Centre, EHC, Morges, Switzerland</aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Pain, EHC, Morges, Switzerland</aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Anesthesiology and Critical Care Medicine, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland, USA</aff><aff id="A8"><label>8</label>Department of Health Data Science, University of Liverpool, Liverpool, UK</aff><aff id="A9"><label>9</label>Anesthesiology - Pain Medicine, Mayo Clinic in Florida, Jacksonville, Florida, USA</aff><aff id="A10"><label>10</label>Erasmus MC, Rotterdam, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="A11"><label>11</label>Summa Western Reserve Hospital, Cuyahoga Falls, Ohio, USA</aff><aff id="A12"><label>12</label>Department of Anesthesiology, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Virginia, USA</aff><aff id="A13"><label>13</label>Neurosurgery, Anesthesiology and Critical Care Medicine (ret.), Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland, USA</aff><aff id="A14"><label>14</label>Department of Neurological Surgery, Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine, Chicago, Illinois, USA</aff><aff id="A15"><label>15</label>Columbia University Irving Medical Center, New York City, New York, USA</aff><aff id="A16"><label>16</label>Center for Pain Medicine, Summa Western Reserve Hospital, Cuyahoga Falls, Ohio, USA</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="con" id="FN1"><p id="P1"><bold>Contributors</bold> HS: Guidelines Chair and Steering Committee member. Conduct and reporting of guidelines. Anesthesiologist and Pain Physician. ASRA pain medicine regulatory committee member. Guarantor. SE: Anesthesiologist and Pain physician. Steering committee member; directions on the guidelines; ensuring liaison and representation from appropriate stakeholders from Europe and UK. ESRA Member DAP: Steering committee member; directions on the guidelines; ensuring liaison and representation from appropriate stakeholders. ASRA pain medicine member. BB: Anesthesiologist and Pain Physician. Guidelines committee member. ESRA member EB: Anesthesiologist and Pain Physician. Guidelines committee member. ESRA member RC: Clinical psychologist with expertise in chronic pain management. Guidelines committee member. TLD: Anesthesiologist and Pain Physician. Guidelines committee member. ASRA pain medicine member RD: Clinical and Health Economic Specialist. Guidelines committee member CH: Physiatrist and Pain physician. Guidelines committee member. ASRA pain medicine member. FJPMH: Anesthesiologist and Pain Physician. Guidelines committee member. ESRA member JK: Patient representative with lived experience with SCS. Guidelines committee participation. LK: Anesthesiologist and Pain Physician. Guidelines committee participation. ASRA pain medicine member. RN: Neurosurgeon and expertise in neuromodulation. Representation and reviewer from NANS and IoN. JR: Neurosurgeon and expertise in neuromodulation. Guidelines committee member. NANS member. CJW: Neurosurgeon and expertise in neuromodulation. Guidelines committee member. SN: Steering committee lead; directions on the guidelines; ensuring liaison and representation from appropriate stakeholders. ASRA pain medicine president.</p></fn><corresp id="CR1"><bold>Correspondence to</bold> Dr Harsha Shanthanna, Anesthesia, McMaster, University, Hamilton, ON L8S 4L8, Canada; <email>shanthh@mcmaster.ca</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN4"><p id="P113"><bold>Competing interests</bold> HS, RC, JK, JR, CJW: None. SE: Received consultancy fees from Medtronic, Mainstay Medical, Boston Scientific Corp, and Saluda Medical. He has received department research funding from the National Institute of Health Research, Medtronic Ltd, and Boston Scientific. DAP: Editor for Reg Anesth Pain Med. Consulted for Avanos, Boston Scientific, Medtronic, Nevro, and SI BONE. Pain Diagnostics and Interventioal Care has received research support from Avanos, Medtronic, Nevro, Stimgenics, and Abbott. BB: Consultancy agreement with Medtronic Switzerland. Department has received unrestricted research grants from Medtronic Switzerland. EB: Consultancy agreement with Medtronic Switzerland. Department has received unrestricted research grants from Medtronic Switzerland. TD: Biohaven Pharmaceuticals (coinvestigator in clinical trial of rimegepant for trigeminal neuralgia). RD: Consultancy fees from Boston Scientific Corp, Mainstay Medical, Medtronic and Saluda Medical for work unrelated with the role and conduct of trial stimulation on spinal cord stimulation (SCS) therapy for chronic pain patients. CH: Institutional research grants from Nevro. FH: Consultancy fees from Abbott, Saluda, Salvia, Pfizer; Research grants from Zonmw, STW, VWS, Abbott, Medtronic, Saluda, Boston Scientific (Investigator initiated studies). LK: Consulting from Avanos, Institutional Funding from Avanos and FUS Mobile. RN: Dr North&#8217;s previous employers, including Johns Hopkins University, and the charitable nonprofit Neuromodulation Foundation, of which he is an unpaid officer, have received grant support and income from industry, including Abbott, Boston Scientific, Medtronic, Nevro, Algostim/Nuvectra, and Stimwave. He holds over 30 patents in the field of neuromodulation, and currently receives royalties from Abbott. SN: Editor for Reg Anesth Pain Med.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>48</volume><issue>6</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">441534</issue-id><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="nihms-submitted"><date><day>21</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>06</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>06</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-04-20 16:25:23.090"><day>20</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="nihms-1911318.pdf"/><abstract id="ABS1"><p id="P2">Spinal cord stimulation (SCS) has demonstrated effectiveness for neuropathic pain. Unfortunately, some patients report inadequate long-term pain relief. Patient selection is emphasized for this therapy; however, the prognostic capabilities and deployment strategies of existing selection techniques, including an SCS trial, have been questioned. After approval by the Board of Directors of the American Society of Regional Anesthesia and Pain Medicine, a steering committee was formed to develop evidence-based guidelines for patient selection and the role of an SCS trial. Representatives of professional organizations with clinical expertize were invited to participate as committee members. A comprehensive literature review was carried out by the steering committee, and the results organized into narrative reports, which were circulated to all the committee members. Individual statements and recommendations within each of seven sections were formulated by the steering committee and circulated to members for voting. We used a modified Delphi method wherein drafts were circulated to each member in a blinded fashion for voting. Comments were incorporated in the subsequent revisions, which were recirculated for voting to achieve consensus. Seven sections with a total of 39 recommendations were approved with 100% consensus from all the members. Sections included definitions and terminology of SCS trial; benefits of SCS trial; screening for psychosocial characteristics; patient perceptions on SCS therapy and the use of trial; other patient predictors of SCS therapy; conduct of SCS trials; and evaluation of SCS trials including minimum criteria for success. Recommendations included that SCS trial should be performed before a definitive SCS implant except in anginal pain (grade B). All patients must be screened with an objective validated instrument for psychosocial factors, and this must include depression (grade B). Despite some limitations, a trial helps patient selection and provides patients with an opportunity to experience the therapy. These recommendations are expected to guide practicing physicians and other stakeholders and should not be mistaken as practice standards. Physicians should continue to make their best judgment based on individual patient considerations and preferences.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front></article></pmc-articleset>