<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Med (Lausanne)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Med (Lausanne)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2657</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">frontmedicine</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Med.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2296-858X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10050706</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10050706.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10050706</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10050706</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37007797</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2023.1079637</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Serum triglyceride levels are associated with recurrence in patients with acute hypertriglyceridemic pancreatitis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names initials="L">Langyi</given-names></name><xref rid="fn0003" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names initials="L">Ling</given-names></name><xref rid="fn0003" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names initials="J">Jianhua</given-names></name><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1587170/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names initials="L">Liang</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names initials="W">Wenhua</given-names></name><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1454077/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names initials="H">Huifang</given-names></name><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1590202/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names initials="L">Lingyu</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names initials="N">Nonghua</given-names></name><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/288366/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yin</given-names></name><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/544674/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff><institution>Department of Gastroenterology, Digestive Disease Hospital, The First Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University</institution>, <addr-line>Nanchang, Jiangxi Province</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn id="fn0001" fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Hao Sun, Nanjing Medical University, China</p></fn><fn id="fn0002" fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Kshaunish Das, Institute of Postgraduate Medical Education and Research, India; Jakob Gubensek, University Medical Centre Ljubljana, Slovenia</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Yin Zhu, <email>zhuyin27@sina.com</email>; <email>ndyfy01977@ncu.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn id="fn0003" fn-type="equal"><p><sup>&#8224;</sup>These authors share first authorship</p></fn><fn id="fn0004" fn-type="other"><p>This article was submitted to Gastroenterology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Medicine</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">427505</issue-id><elocation-id>1079637</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>15</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>30</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-04-03 12:10:11.213"><day>03</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 Guan, Ding, Wan, Xia, He, Xiong, Luo, Lu and Zhu.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Guan, Ding, Wan, Xia, He, Xiong, Luo, Lu and Zhu</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fmed-10-1079637.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Aim</title><p>To analyze the clinical profile of patients with acute hypertriglyceridemic pancreatitis (HTGP) and explore risk factors for recurrence.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>A retrospective observational study was conducted in patients who experienced an attack of HTGP for the first time. Patients were followed until the recurrence of acute pancreatitis (AP) or 1&#8201;year. The detailed clinical profile was compared between patients with or without recurrence. Multivariate logistic regression analysis was conducted to explore independent risk factors for recurrence.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>A total of 108 HTGP patients were included in this study with 73.1% being male, and the median age being 37 (interquartile range, IQR, 30.3&#8211;44.8) years. Recurrence occurred in 70 patients (64.8%). Compared with the nonrecurrent group, serum triglyceride (TG) levels before discharge [4.1 (2.8,6.3) mmol/L vs. 2.9 (2.2,4.2) mmol/L; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.002], at 1&#8201;month [3.7 (2.3,9.7) mmol/L vs. 2.0 (1.4,2.7) mmol/L; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.001], at 6&#8201;months [6.1 (3.1,13.1) mmol/L vs. 2.5 (1.1,3.5) mmol/L; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.003] and 12&#8201;months [9.6 (3.5,20.0) mmol/L vs. 2.7 (1.6,5.5) mmol/L; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.001] after discharge were higher in the recurrent group. Poor control of TG levels (TG&#8201;&gt;&#8201;3.1&#8201;mmol/l) at the 1-month follow-up after discharge and a high Charlson&#8217;s Comorbidity Index score (&#8805;&#8201;2 points) increased the risk of recurrence of HTGP.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>High TG levels during follow-up and Charlson&#8217;s Comorbidity Index score were independently associated with recurrence in patients with HTGP.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>acute pancreatitis</kwd><kwd>recurrence</kwd><kwd>risk factor</kwd><kwd>hypertriglyceridemia</kwd><kwd>follow-up</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn1">Double-Thousand Plan of Jiangxi Province</funding-source><award-id award-type="contract" rid="cn1">jxsq2019201028</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="7"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="41"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="6324"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec5"><title>Introduction</title><p>Acute pancreatitis (AP), an inflammatory condition of the pancreas, has become one of the most common acute gastrointestinal disorders in recent years. The overall incidence of AP has increased by 3.07% per year (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), leading to an increasing burden on healthcare services. Overall AP-related mortality is approximately 5% (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Severe acute pancreatitis (SAP) attacks develop in 20% of patients, with a substantial mortality risk up to 20&#8211;40% (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). The etiology of AP is diverse, including biliary disease, hypertriglyceridemia (HTG), alcohol consumption, hyperparathyroidism, steroid use and other rare etiologies (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). There are obvious differences in the etiology of AP due to differences in races, regions, and economic and health conditions (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). The incidence of hypertriglyceridemic pancreatitis (HTGP) has been increasing for a number of years (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), accounting for 0.36&#8211;25.6% of all AP cases (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). In some regions of China, HTG is currently the second most common cause of AP (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p><p>Generally, AP is a self-limiting process, and a small number of patients will have repeated attacks, known as recurrent acute pancreatitis (RAP). The pooled incidence of RAP can reach 10&#8211;30% (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). RAP can further lead to chronic pancreatitis (CP), causing endocrine and exocrine dysfunction of the pancreas and affecting peoples work and even normal life activities (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). It is crucial to accurately identify the cause of RAP and etiological treatment. Recent studies have shown that the recurrence rate of HTGP is high, reaching 30.1&#8211;32% (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). This phenomenon may be related to the persistence of certain factors (such as drinking, diabetes, obesity and other factors) that cause to secondary dyslipidemia, poor TG control or genetic susceptibility (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Prior studies mostly focused on the risk factors for recurrence of alcoholic and biliary pancreatitis (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Studies have revealed that reducing alcohol consumption and cholecystectomy can be a way to diminish the risk of recurrent AP. Other studies mainly assessed the severity of AP and the characteristics of hospitalization (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Few studies have focused on recurrence of HTGP. Wu et al. (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) found that elevated TG levels in the ambulatory setting were associated with an increased risk of recurrent HTGP, but the study lacked TG measurements of inpatients during hospitalization for AP. The objective of this study was to analyze the clinical features of HTGP and develop a nomogram to determine the risk factors for recurrent pancreatitis in patients with HTGP.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec6"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec7"><title>Study design and participants</title><p>This was a retrospective, observational study of patients hospitalized for a first attack of HTGP admitted to the Department of Gastroenterology, First Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University, a tertiary care referral center in China, from January 2017 to December 2019. The exclusion criteria were as follows: (a) a history of HTGP, (b) death or abandonment of treatment during the index hospitalization and incomplete hospitalization data, (c) age&#8201;&lt;&#8201;18&#8201;years, (d) chronic pancreatitis or pancreatic cancer or (e) not fulfilling 1&#8201;year follow-up. All patients were followed up with for at least 1&#8201;year after discharge, and patients who were lost to follow-up were excluded. We extracted data from a prospectively maintained database, and the use of AP data was approved by the Ethics Committee of the First Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University (No: 2011001). Written informed consent was waived due to the retrospective nature of the study.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Definitions</title><p>The criteria for AP diagnosis were as follows: (1) abdominal pain suggestive of AP, (2) a serum amylase and/or lipase level 3 times higher than the upper limit of normal, and (3) abdominal ultrasound, computed tomography (CT) and magnetic resonance features of AP (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). All patients met at least two of three diagnostic criteria for AP (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). HTGP was diagnosed when (1) the serum TG level was &gt;&#8201;11.3&#8201;mmol/l or (2) the serum TG level was between 5.65 and 11.3&#8201;mmol/l without other etiologies, such as biliary or alcoholic AP (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). RAP referred to 2 or more episodes of documented AP with an interval of at least 3&#8201;months (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><title>Data collection</title><p>General baseline information, including sex, age, body mass index (BMI), history of fatty liver diseases, Charlson&#8217;s Comorbidity Index score, drinking status or smoking status, history of use for lipid-lowering medicine, time from AP attack to hospitalization and recorded data, was collected. Clinical features including the severity of pancreatitis, types of AP, hospital stay, intensive care unit (ICU) admission rate and hospitalization expense during the first hospitalization were also assessed.</p><p>Charlson&#8217;s Comorbidity Index score was used as a measure of patient comorbidity. Severity and types of pancreatitis were defined according to the revised Atlanta Classification criteria (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>).</p><p>Furthermore, serum TG levels and total cholesterol (TC) levels within 24&#8201;h after an AP attack, 24 and 72&#8201;h after admission, and before discharge and high-density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol levels and low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol levels within 24&#8201;h after admission and before discharge were recorded. All serum tests were executed and interpreted by trained and experienced staff who were blinded to the patients&#8217; clinical information. Serum TG, TC, HDL cholesterol, and LDL cholesterol levels were measured on an automatic biomedical analyzer (Hitachi High-Tech, 7,600&#8211;120, Japan) within 24&#8201;h. The normal reference range for TG is 0&#8211;1.7&#8201;mmol/l, TC is 0&#8211;5.7&#8201;mmol/l, HDL cholesterol is 1.29&#8211;1.55&#8201;mmol/l, and LDL cholesterol is 0&#8211;3.62&#8201;mmol/l in human serum.</p><p>Patients were followed after discharge. We collected blood lipid indexes, including serum TG, TC, HDL and LDL cholesterol levels, at 1, 6, and 12&#8201;months after discharge. The relevant follow-up time was at least 1&#8201;year; or until December 2020. A detailed clinical profile was recorded and compared between patients with or without recurrence.</p></sec><sec id="sec10"><title>Data analysis</title><p>Categorical variables are expressed as absolute numbers and proportions, and continuous variables are described as medians and interquartile ranges (IQRs). The differences in continuous variables were analyzed by using the Kruskal&#8211;Wallis test, and the Chi-square test or Fisher&#8217;s exact test was used to compare categorical variables. Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve analysis was used to determine the optimal cutoff values for continuous variables. Multivariable logistic regression (a forward stepwise regression with typicality dependent variable) was further used to analyze independent risk factors for HTGP recurrence. The indicators with <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.1 in the univariate analysis were incorporated into multivariable analysis. All results are presented as odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs). Statistical significance was considered at a <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value of &lt;&#8201;0.05. Statistical evaluation was performed by using SPSS software (v26.0; SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, United States) or R software (version 4.0.5, R Development Core Team).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec11"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec12"><title>Baseline characteristics and clinical profiles during index hospitalization</title><p>A total of 108 eligible HTGP patients were included (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Among these patients, 73.1% were male, the median age was 37 (30.344.8) years, and the mean BMI was 26.2 (24.4, 28.2) kg/m<sup>2</sup>. Thirty-eight patients had only one episode of AP during the observation period (nonrecurrent group), and 70 patients had at least 2 episodes of AP (recurrent group). The differences in the baseline and clinical characteristics during the index hospitalization between the two groups are summarized in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. No significant difference between the two groups for baseline characteristics was observed. During the first hospitalization, milder illness was observed in patients with recurrence than in those without recurrence, as indicated by a lower proportion of necrotizing pancreatitis (11.4 vs. 31.6%; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.010), severe acute pancreatitis (14.3 vs. 34.2%; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.047), shorter hospital stay [8.0 (5.0, 13.5) days vs. 13 (6.5, 21.0) days; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.040], and lower hospital costs [16,126 (8,801,36,284) RMB vs. 43,630 (10,781,111,400) RMB; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.006].</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flow-diagram for selection process of the study group of hypertriglyceridemic pancreatitis (HTGP).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fmed-10-1079637-g001.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics and clinical profile during index hospitalization of patients with HTGP.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> =&#8201;108)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recurrent group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> =&#8201;70)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-recurrent group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> =&#8201;38)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Baseline characteristics</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.584</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (73.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (71.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (76.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (26.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (28.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (23.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.0 (30.3,44.8)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.0 (27.8,44.3)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.5 (32.0,45.3)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.129</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.2 (24.4,28.2)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.6 (24.8,28.4)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.9 (23.6,26.8)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.082</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Charlson&#8217;s Comorbidity Index score, points</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0,1)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1,1)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0,1)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.116</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">History of fatty liver disease</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (72.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (72.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (71.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.842</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">History of diabetes</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (14.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (17.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (10.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.355</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">History of use for lipid-lowering medicine</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (27.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (27.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (28.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.842</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking status</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (38.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (40.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (36.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.748</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinking status</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (41.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (35.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (52.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time from AP attack to admission</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0 (2.0,4.0)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (2.0,4.0)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 (2.0,5.0)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.079</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Clinical profile during index hospitalization</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory failure</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (39.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (32.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (52.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.045</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Renal failure</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (7.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.3%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (13.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.126</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiovascular failure</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (6.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (13.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.094</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><sup>*</sup>Types of AP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.010</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interstitial oedematous pancreatitis</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88 (81.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (88.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (68.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Necrotizing pancreatitis</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (18.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (11.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (31.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>*</sup>Severity of AP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.047</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (22.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (25.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (15.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSAP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (56.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (60.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (50.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (21.3%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (14.3%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (34.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital stay, day</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 (6,17)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0(5.0,13.5)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (6.5,21.0)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.040</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU admission</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (40.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (35.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (50.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.149</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital costs, RMB</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,953 (9,778,57,783)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,126 (8,801,36,284)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43,630 (10,781,111,400)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.006</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Date are median (interquartile ranges) or absolute numbers (proportions). HTGP, hypertriglyceridemic pancreatitis; BMI, body mass index; AP, acute pancreatitis; MAP, mild acute pancreatitis; MSAP, moderately severe acute pancreatitis; SAP, severe acute pancreatitis; ICU: intensive care unit. <sup>*</sup>Types and severity of AP were assessed according to 2012 Atlanta Classification of AP. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05 was bolded.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec13"><title>Serum lipid levels and lipid-lowering treatment in patients with HTGP during the index hospitalization</title><p>The levels of serum TG, TC, HDL, and LDL cholesterol at different time points during hospitalization were compared between the two groups. <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows the lipid indexes and rate of lipid-lowering treatment in patients with HTGP during the first hospitalization. As the time from the onset of AP increased, the levels of serum TG and TC gradually decreased (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). The serum TG level before discharge was much lower than the serum TG level within 24&#8201;h of onset (3.7 (2.6&#8211;5.7) mmol/L vs. 16.2 (10.6&#8211;24.4) mmol/L), and the TC level followed a similar trend [9.3 (6.1&#8211;12.3) mmol/L vs. 5.1 (3.9&#8211;6.5) mmol/L], see in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. In the recurrent group, serum TG levels [4.1 (2.8&#8211;6.3) mmol/L vs. 2.9 (2.2&#8211;4.2) mmol/L, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.002] and TC levels [5.5 (4.1&#8211;6.8) mmol/L vs. 4.4 (3.7&#8211;7.0) mmol/L, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.031] before discharge were higher than those in the nonrecurrent group. No significant differences in the HDL and LDL cholesterol levels were found between the two groups at different time points. The majority of patients received lipid-lowering therapy. Over half of the patients were treated with oral lipid-lowering drugs, intravenous insulin, or low weight molecular heparin. Only 5.6% of the patients received hemofiltration or plasmapheresis therapy.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Serum lipid levels and lipid-lowering treatments of patients with HTGP during index hospitalization.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recurrent group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> =&#8201;70)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-recurrent group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> =&#8201;38)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Serum lipid levels of patients during index hospitalization</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG (within 24&#8201;h of onset), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6 (8.7,23.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5 (12.6,24.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.356</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG (within 24&#8201;h of admission), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8 (5.4,14.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1 (5.9,16.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.687</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG (within 72&#8201;h of admission), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1 (3.1,8.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3 (3.5,7.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.862</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG (before discharge), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1 (2.8,6.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9 (2.2,4.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.002</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC (within 24&#8201;h of onset), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 (5.5,11.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3 (6.9,16.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC (within 24&#8201;h of admission), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 (4.8,8.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5 (5.7,11.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.150</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC (within 72&#8201;h of admission), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 (4.7,7.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4 (4.3,7.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.599</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC (before discharge), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5 (4.1,6.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4 (3.7,6.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.031</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL cholesterol (within 24&#8201;h of admission), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (0.5,1.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (0.5,0.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.716</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL cholesterol (before discharge), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (0.5,0.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.5,0.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.340</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL cholesterol (within 24&#8201;h of admission), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0.6,3.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 (0.6,2.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.786</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL cholesterol (before discharge), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4 (1.2,3.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 (1.3,3.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.825</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Lipid-lowering treatments of patients during index hospitalization</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any lipid-lowering treatments</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (92.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (97.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.309</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral lipid-lowering drugs</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (68.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (76.3%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.396</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intravenous insulin</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (80.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (86.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.372</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low molecular weight heparin</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (57.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (52.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.652</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemofiltration or plasmapheresis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.3%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (7.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.663</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Date are median (interquartile ranges) or absolute numbers (proportions). HTGP, hypertriglyceridemic pancreatitis; TG, triglyceride; TC, total cholesterol; HDL cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol; LDL cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol. Normal ranges: TG (0&#8211;1.7&#8201;mmol/l), TC (0&#8211;5.7&#8201;mmol/l), HDL cholesterol (1.29&#8211;1.55&#8201;mmol/l), VDL cholesterol (0&#8211;3.62&#8201;mmol/l). <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05 was bolded.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Dynamic change of serum lipid levels of patients with HTGP during index hospitalization, <bold>(A)</bold> the serum TG levels, <bold>(B)</bold> the serum TC levels.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fmed-10-1079637-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec14"><title>Serum lipid levels of patients with HTGP during follow-up</title><p><xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> lists the blood lipid profiles of the two groups at different time points during the one-year follow-up. Serum TG levels and TC levels gradually increased in all two groups. Serum TG level in the recurrent group at 1&#8201;month [3.7 (2.3&#8211;9.7) vs. 2.0(1.4&#8211;2.7), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.001], 6&#8201;months [6.1(3.1&#8211;13.1) vs. 2.5(1.1&#8211;3.5), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.003] and 12&#8201;months [9.6(3.5&#8211;20.0) vs. (2.7(1.6&#8211;5.5), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.001] of follow-up were higher than those in the nonrecurrent group. Similarly, the TC levels at 1&#8201;month [5.3 (4.2&#8211;6.2) vs. 4.4(4.0&#8211;4.8), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.005], 6&#8201;months [5.4 (4.7&#8211;7.8) vs. 4.7(4.3&#8211;5.4), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.003], and 12&#8201;months [6.6 (5.4&#8211;10.7) vs. 4.7(4.3&#8211;5.4), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.001] of follow-up were higher than those in the nonrecurrent group.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Serum lipid levels of patients with HTGP during follow-up.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After discharge</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recurrent group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> =&#8201;70)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-recurrent group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> =&#8201;38)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#8201;month</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7 (2.3,9.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 (1.4,2.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3 (4.2,6.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4 (4.0,4.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.005</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL cholesterol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0.8,1.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0.9,1.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.856</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VDL cholesterol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 (1.7,3.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 (2.1,2.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.371</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#8201;months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (3.1,13.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (1.1,3.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.003</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4 (4.7,7.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 (4.3,5.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.019</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL cholesterol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (0.8,1.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (1.0,1.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.189</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL cholesterol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (1.5,2.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (2.1,2.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.177</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#8201;months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6 (3.5,20.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 (1.6,5.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6 (5.4,10.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 (4.3,5.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL cholesterol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (0.7,1.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (1.0,1.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.009</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL cholesterol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.8,2.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (2.1,3.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.004</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Date are median (interquartile ranges) or absolute numbers (proportions). HTGP, hypertriglyceridemic pancreatitis; TG, triglyceride; TC, total cholesterol; HDL cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol; LDL cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol. Normal ranges: TG (0&#8211;1.7&#8201;mmol/l), TC (0&#8211;5.7&#8201;mmol/l), HDL cholesterol (1.29&#8211;1.55&#8201;mmol/l), LDL cholesterol (0&#8211;3.62&#8201;mmol/l). <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05 was bolded.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>There was no significant difference between the two groups in HDL cholesterol levels and LDL cholesterol levels at 1&#8201;month and 6&#8201;months of follow-up. At the 12-month follow-up, the levels of HDL [1.1(1.0&#8211;1.5) vs. 0.9(0.7&#8211;1.1), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.009] and LDL [2.5(2.1&#8211;3.0) vs. 1.3(0.8&#8211;2.6), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.004] cholesterol in the nonrecurrent group were higher than those in the recurrent group. The HDL cholesterol level was a protective factor against cardiovascular diseases, and it may also play an important role in pancreatitis, which can explain the change in the nonrecurrent group. LDL cholesterol levels were all in the normal range in both groups at different time points of follow-up, so it was not clinically meaningful. <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref> describes the changing trends of the levels of serum TG, TC, HDL and LDL cholesterol at different follow-up times in two groups.</p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Dynamic change of serum lipid levels of patients with HTGP during follow-up, <bold>(A)</bold> the serum TG levels, <bold>(B)</bold> the serum TC levels, <bold>(C)</bold> the serum HDL cholesterol levels, <bold>(D)</bold> the serum LDL cholesterol levels. <sup>*</sup> indicates statistically significant difference.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fmed-10-1079637-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec15"><title>Risk factors for recurrence of HTGP</title><p>We performed ROC analysis to determine the optimal cutoff values of continuous numerical variables for predicting recurrent episodes of HTGP. Univariate (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>) and multivariate (<xref rid="tab5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>) logistic regression analyses were conducted to determine the independent risk factors for recurrence of HTGP. A serum TG level&#8201;&gt;&#8201;3.1&#8201;mmol/l at 1&#8201;month of follow-up was associated with a substantially increased risk, with an adjusted rate ratio of 10.3 (95% confidence limit, 95% CI, 2.5&#8211;34.1), for recurrent episodes in patients with HTGP. Compared with individuals with a Charlson&#8217;s Comorbidity Index score less than 2 points, the multivariable adjusted OR for recurrence of HTGP was 9.0 (95% CI, 1.1&#8211;96.9) in individuals with a Charlson&#8217;s Comorbidity Index score greater than or equal to 2 points. See in <xref rid="tab6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Univariable logistic regression analysis for recurrence in patients with HTGP.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unadjusted OR,95%CI</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex (Ref: male)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.5&#8211;3.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.585</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (Ref: &#8804;&#8201;34&#8201;years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;&#8201;34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.2&#8211;1.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.048</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (Ref: &lt;&#8201;26.8&#8201;kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;&#8201;26.8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7 (1.3&#8211;10.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.015</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Charlson&#8217;s Comorbidity Index score (Ref: &lt;&#8201;2 points)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;&#8201;2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5 (0.9&#8211;12.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">History of fatty liver disease (Ref: no)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.5&#8211;2.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.842</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">History of use for lipid-lowering medicine (Ref: no)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (0.4&#8211;2.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.842</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking status (Ref: no)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.5&#8211;2.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.748</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinking status (Ref: no)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.2&#8211;1.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.091</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG before discharge (Ref: TG&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;3.2&#8201;mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;&#8201;3.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 (1.7&#8211;9.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC before discharge (Ref: TC&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;5.4&#8201;mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;&#8201;5.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2 (1.3&#8211;7.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.009</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL cholesterol before discharge (Ref: HDL HDL&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.7&#8201;mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;&#8201;0.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 (0.8&#8211;4.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.123</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL cholesterol before discharge (Ref: VDL&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;3.3&#8201;mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;&#8201;3.3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 (1.0&#8211;7.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG at 1&#8201;month of follow-up (Ref: TG&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;3.1&#8201;mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;&#8201;3.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9 (3.5&#8211;39.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC at 1&#8201;month of follow-up (Ref: TC&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;5.4&#8201;mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;&#8201;5.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2 (3.2&#8211;71.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL cholesterol at 1&#8201;month of follow-up (Ref: &#8804;&#8201;0.9&#8201;mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;&#8201;0.9</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.1&#8211;1.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.091</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL cholesterol at 1&#8201;month of follow-up (Ref: &#8804;&#8201;2.1&#8201;mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;&#8201;2.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.1&#8211;1.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>HTGP, hypertriglyceridemic pancreatitis; OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval; BMI, body mass index; TG, triglyceride; TC, total cholesterol; HDL cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol; LDL cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05 was bolded.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Multivariate logistic regression analysis for recurrence in patients with HTGP.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR,95%CI</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (Ref: &#8804;&#8201;34&#8201;years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;&#8201;34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (0.1&#8211;3.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.596</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (Ref: &lt;&#8201;26.8&#8201;kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;&#8201;26.8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 (0.6&#8211;12.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.188</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Charlson&#8217; Comorbidity Index score (Ref: &lt;&#8201;2 points)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;&#8201;2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0 (1.1&#8212;96.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.041</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinking status (Ref: no)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (0.2&#8211;3.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.790</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG at 1&#8201;month of follow-up (Ref: &#8804;&#8201;3.1&#8201;mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;&#8201;3.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3 (2.5&#8211;34.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.001</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Only results with <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05 in the multivariate regression were listed above. HTGP, hypertriglyceridemic pancreatitis; aOR, adjusted odds ratio; CI, confidence interval; TG, triglyceride. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05 was bolded.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Variables included in risk-score model and probability for recurrence of HTGP.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;3.1&#8201;mmol/l</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG&#8201;&gt;&#8201;3.1&#8201;mmol/l</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCI&#8201;&lt;&#8201;2 points</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCI&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;2 points</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>&#8220;CCI&#8221; refers to Charlson&#8217; Comorbidity Index score. &#8220;TG&#8221; refers to TG at 1&#8201;month of follow-up.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec16"><title>Clinical characteristics of the recurrent group</title><p>During the follow-up period, 70 patients (64.8%) had recurrent pancreatitis, and 37% of the patients with HTGP experienced 2 or more attacks of recurrent pancreatitis. We performed a subgroup analysis in patients with recurrence, and the clinical profile was compared between index hospitalization and rehospitalization in those patients. There was a significantly higher incidence of ICU admission (35.7 vs. 17.1%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.009) and more severe disease (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.044) during the index hospitalization than during rehospitalization. In addition, the length of hospitalization (8.0(5.0&#8211;13.5) vs. 6.0(4.0&#8211;9.0), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.001) was longer and the hospital costs [16,126 (8801&#8211;36,284) vs. 11,319 (6,243,23,111), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.029] were higher during the index hospitalization than during rehospitalization. Comparisons of blood lipid indexes, treatments and clinical outcomes in the recurrent group in terms of first admission and readmission are detailed in <xref rid="tab7" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab7" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Clinical profile compared between index and recurrent hospitalization in patients with recurrence.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Index hospitalization (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> =&#8201;70)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recurrent hospitalization (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> =&#8201;70)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Serum lipid levels</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG (within 24&#8201;h of onset), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6 (8.7,23.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.1 (12.1,36.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.510</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG (within 24&#8201;h of admission), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8 (5.4,14.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3 (4.5,22.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.227</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG (within 72&#8201;h of admission), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1 (3.1,8.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 (3.7,9.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.221</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG (before discharge), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1 (2.8,6.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9 (3.2,6.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.232</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC (within 24&#8201;h of onset), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 (5.5,11.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4 (6.8,15.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.878</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC (within 24&#8201;h of admission), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 (4.8,8.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 (4.9,11.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC (within 72&#8201;h of admission), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 (4.6,7.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 (4.7,7.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.782</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC (before discharge), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5 (4.1,6.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4 (4.5,7.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.840</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL cholesterol (within 24&#8201;h of admission), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (0.5,1.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (0.6,1.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL cholesterol (before discharge), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (0.5,0.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (0.6,0.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.315</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL cholesterol (within 24&#8201;h of admission), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0.6,3.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (0.6,2.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.383</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL cholesterol (before discharge), mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4 (1.2,3.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 (1.7,3.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.777</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Clinical treatment and outcome</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time from AP attack to admission</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (2.0,4.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 (2.0,3.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.209</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any lipid-lowering treatment</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (92.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (90.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral lipid-lowering drugs</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (68.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (61.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.369</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intravenous insulin</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (80.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (72.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.297</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low molecular weight heparin</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (57.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (55.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.869</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemofiltration or plasmapheresis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.3%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.317</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>*</sup>Severity of AP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.044</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAP</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (25.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (38.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSAP</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (60.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (54.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAP</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (14.3%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (7.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital day, day</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 (5.0,13.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 (4.0,9.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU admission</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (35.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (17.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.009</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital costs, RMB</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,126 (8,801,36,284)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,319 (6,243,23,111)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.029</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Date are median (interquartile ranges) or absolute numbers (proportions). HTGP, hypertriglyceridemic pancreatitis; TG, triglyceride; TC, total cholesterol; HDL cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol; LDL cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol. Normal ranges: TG (0&#8211;1.7&#8201;mmol/l), TC (0&#8211;5.7&#8201;mmol/l), HDL cholesterol (1.29&#8211;1.55&#8201;mmol/l), LDL cholesterol (0&#8211;3.62&#8201;mmol/l). AP, acute pancreatitis; MAP, mild acute pancreatitis; MSAP, moderately severe acute pancreatitis; SAP, severe acute pancreatitis. <sup>*</sup>Severity of AP were assessed according to 2012 Atlanta Classification of AP. ICU: intensive care unit. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05 was bolded.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussions" id="sec17"><title>Discussion</title><p>We retrospectively studied the baseline clinical features and lipid levels of patients with HTGP and assessed the dynamic change in serum TG levels within 1&#8201;year after the first attack of HTGP. Analysis of these data showed that a high Charlson&#8217;s Comorbidity Index score was related to recurrent episodes of HTGP. Charlson&#8217;s Comorbidity Index score is an extensively used comorbidity index. To date, few studies have reported that the Charlson&#8217;s Comorbidity Index score is a risk factor for recurrence of HTGP. Of our study&#8217;s findings, a high Charlson&#8217;s Comorbidity Index score was associated with an increased risk of recurrence in patients with HTGP, which may suggest that we should focus on patients with more comorbidities.</p><p>One finding of our study on the risk factors for recurrent HTGP is consistent with those of previous studies. The serum TG level at 1&#8201;month of follow-up was closely associated with HTGP recurrence. Some reports have suggested that serum TG levels after hospital discharge higher than 5.65&#8201;mmol/l are independently associated with recurrent pancreatitis (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Even moderately elevated baseline serum TG levels (2.25&#8201;mmol/l-5.65&#8201;mmol/l) within 12&#8201;months postdischarge were associated with a significant increase in the risk of disease recurrence (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). In this study, we found that a serum TG level &gt;&#8201;3.1&#8201;mmol/l at 1&#8201;month of follow-up was strongly related to the recurrence of HTGP, with an adjusted OR of 10.3, consistent with previous studies. In addition, a high Charlson&#8217;s Comorbidity Index score (&#8805;&#8201;2 points) was also related to an increased risk of recurrent attacks, with an adjusted OR of 9.0. On the basis of previous studies, it is usually considered that serum TG levels should be controlled below 5.65&#8201;mmol/l to prevent the recurrence of HTGP (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). However, mild elevation of serum TG levels also increase the risk of HTGP (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). The compliance of patients may also play a major role in the control of serum TG levels. More consensus is needed on serum TG level required for control.</p><p>Hypertriglyceridemia (HTG) is a well-established cause of AP (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Zheng et al. (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) reported that the incidence of HTGP has surpassed that of alcoholic pancreatitis as the second leading cause of AP. In recent years, the incidence of HTGP has shown an increasing trend (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Other studies have revealed that the recurrence rate of HTGP was also high and could reach up to 30.1&#8211;32% (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). In this retrospective study, the recurrence rate of HTGP was 64.8%, which was much higher than the recurrence rate in previous related studies. The possible reasons may be that the follow-up period was 1&#8201;year, which caused considerable enrollment bias because some patients did not attend our hospital for regular follow-up. The recurrence rate may be overestimated.</p><p>Increased production and/or decreased catabolism of serum TG can lead to HTG. Primary HTG is usually caused by genetic abnormalities, while secondary HTG is often caused by environmental and external factors, such as diabetes, obesity, and the use of certain drugs (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). The mechanism by which HTG causes HTGP to occur is not yet clear. It may be related to fatty acid toxicity, microcirculation disturbance, oxidative stress, Ca<sup>2+</sup> overload and gene polymorphisms (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). Qi et al. (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>) confirmed that the interaction between genes and the environment is extremely significant in the occurrence and development of HTGP. It is vitally important to actively control serum TG levels to reduce the occurrence of HTG and even the occurrence and recurrence of HTGP.</p><p>In the recurrent group, there was no significant difference in the blood lipid profile or lipid-lowering treatment during the two hospitalizations. As previous studies have shown no superiority in any lipid-lowering treatments of severe hypertriglyceridemia among patients hospitalized for pancreatitis (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). From the data analysis, it can be seen that the proportions of MSAP and SAP in patients in the first hospitalization were higher than those at readmission. More serious disease may lead to higher compliance of patients, thus reducing the rate of rehospitalization. However, this finding does not suggest that the severity of index hospitalization of patients with recurrence is more severe than that of rehospitalization. We did not include patients who died, which accounts for a large proportion of the severity of HTGP. In addition, according to clinical experience, the severity of HTGP in patients with relapse is increased when they are readmitted to the hospital. Thus far, there are insufficient data to support this idea. More studies are needed to explore the severity of HTGP in patients with relapse.</p><p>Our article is a retrospective study with several limitations. One is that we retrospectively collected data subject to selection bias and overrepresentation of patients to some extent. Second, these data lacked information about the time of lipid-lowering treatment, the timing of lipid-lowering drug discontinuation and other medication use during the follow-up period, which may affect the research results. In addition, as mentioned above, we did not calculate mortality, which may lead to underestimation of the severity of the disease during hospitalization and an inability to assess the impact of severity on recurrence.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec18"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The present study focused on the risk factors for recurrence of HTGP. It was found that poorly controlled serum TG level at 1&#8201;month of follow-up and a high Charlson&#8217;s Comorbidity Index score (&#8805;&#8201;2 points) were associated with higher recurrence rates. The results of the study indicate that it is extremely important to prevent and treat underlying diseases and to control serum TG levels in patients with HTGP during follow-up.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec19"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation.</p></sec><sec id="sec20"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The studies involving human participants were reviewed and approved by The institutional review boards of the First Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University (No: 2011001). The patients/participants provided their written informed consent to participate in this study.</p></sec><sec id="sec21"><title>Author contributions</title><p>LG collected the data, analyzed formal information, and wrote the manuscript. LD designed this study and revised the draft. JW, LX, WH, HX, LL, and NL provided guidance and amendments. YZ revised the draft and approved the final submission. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="sec22"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the Double-Thousand Plan of Jiangxi Province (No. jxsq2019201028).</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec100"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors thank the Jiangxi Clinical Research Center for Digestive Disease (No. 20201ZDG020007) for their support and all participants involved in this study.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iannuzzi</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leong</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Windsor</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanyingoh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global incidence of acute pancreatitis is increasing over time: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>162</volume>:<fpage>122</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2021.09.043</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34571026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrov</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Global epidemiology and holistic prevention of pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>175</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41575-018-0087-5</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30482911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6597260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gapp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jahann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kassim</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddymasu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Trends and outcomes of hospitalizations related to acute pancreatitis: epidemiology from 2001 to 2014 in the United States</article-title>. <source>Pancreas</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>548</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MPA.0000000000001275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30946239</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wadhwa</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patwardhan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jobanputra</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanaka</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Health care utilization and costs associated with acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Pancreas</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>410</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MPA.0000000000000755</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28099261</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Acute Pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>174</volume>:<fpage>Itc17</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>itc32</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/AITC202102160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33556276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrov</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shanbhag</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>ARJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Windsor</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Organ failure and infection of pancreatic necrosis as determinants of mortality in patients with acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>139</volume>:<fpage>813</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2010.06.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20540942</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schepers</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Besselink</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bollen</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gooszen</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dutch pancreatitis study group, impact of characteristics of organ failure and infected necrosis on mortality in necrotising pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Gut</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>1044</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2017-314657</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29950344</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tenner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baillie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeWitt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vege</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>American College of Gastroenterology guideline: management of acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>108</volume>:<fpage>1400</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>; <comment>1416</comment>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ajg.2013.218</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23896955</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McNabb-Baltar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hypertriglyceridemia and acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Pancreatology</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>795</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>800</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pan.2020.06.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32571534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matta</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gougol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Talukdar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kochhar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Worldwide variations in demographics, management, and outcomes of acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1567</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1575.e2</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cgh.2019.11.017</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31712075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9198955</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A study on the etiology, severity, and mortality of 3260 patients with acute pancreatitis according to the revised Atlanta classification in Jiangxi, China over an 8-year period</article-title>. <source>Pancreas</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>504</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MPA.0000000000000776</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28196012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A multicenter study on etiology of acute pancreatitis in Beijing during 5 years</article-title>. <source>Pancreas</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>409</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>14</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MPA.0000000000000273</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25438072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Youn</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paik</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The etiologic evaluation of acute pancreatitis in a general Hospital of Seoul-Gyeonggi Province in Korea</article-title>. <source>Korean J Gastroenterol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>190</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4166/kjg.2017.70.4.190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29060957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Recurrent acute pancreatitis and its relative factors</article-title>. <source>World J Gastroenterol</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>3002</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3748/wjg.v11.i19.3002</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15902746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4305677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed Ali</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Issa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagenaars</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Goor</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nieuwenhuijs</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dutch pancreatitis study group, risk of recurrent pancreatitis and progression to chronic pancreatitis after a first episode of acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>738</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cgh.2015.12.040</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26772149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gullo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Migliori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pezzilli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farkas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>An update on recurrent acute pancreatitis: data from five European countries</article-title>. <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>97</volume>:<fpage>1959</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1572-0241.2002.05907.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12190160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>MX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Incidence and clinical features of hyperlipidemic acute pancreatitis from Guangdong, China: a retrospective multicenter study</article-title>. <source>Pancreas</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>548</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MPA.0000000000000069</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24717803</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vipperla</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Furlan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koutroumpakis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saul</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chennat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical profile and natural course in a large cohort of patients with hypertriglyceridemia and pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>J Clin Gastroenterol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>77</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>85</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MCG.0000000000000579</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27322530</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scherer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pitchumoni</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Issues in hypertriglyceridemic pancreatitis: an update</article-title>. <source>J Clin Gastroenterol</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>203</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.mcg.0000436438.60145.5a</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24172179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3939000</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>BU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Batech</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of ambulatory triglyceride levels on risk of recurrence in patients with hypertriglyceridemic pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Dig Dis Sci</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>890</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10620-018-5226-x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30094622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of a novel and heterozygous LMF1 nonsense mutation in an acute pancreatitis patient with severe hypertriglyceridemia, severe obesity and heavy smoking</article-title>. <source>Lipids Health Dis</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>68</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12944-019-1012-9</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30885219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6421687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordback</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pelli</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lappalainen Lehto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>J&#228;rvinen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>R&#228;ty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sand</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The recurrence of acute alcohol-associated pancreatitis can be reduced: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>136</volume>:<fpage>848</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2008.11.044</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19162029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pothoulakis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paragomi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Archibugi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuft</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Talukdar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kochhar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical features of hypertriglyceridemia-induced acute pancreatitis in an international, multicenter, prospective cohort (apprentice consortium)</article-title>. <source>Pancreatology</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>325</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pan.2020.02.010</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32107193</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>EX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Early predictors of hyperlipidemic acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Exp Ther Med</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>4232</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/etm.2018.6713</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30344698</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6176128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bollen</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dervenis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gooszen</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarr</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Acute pancreatitis classification working group, classification of acute pancreatitis--2012: revision of the Atlanta classification and definitions by international consensus</article-title>. <source>Gut</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>62</volume>:<fpage>102</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2012-302779</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23100216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guda</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muddana</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitcomb</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cote</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Recurrent acute pancreatitis: international state-of-the-science conference with recommendations</article-title>. <source>Pancreas</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>653</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MPA.0000000000001053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29894415</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Suboptimal management of hypertriglyceridemia in the outpatient setting is associated with the recurrent pancreatitis: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>e22887</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000022887</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33120833</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7581036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zafrir</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saliba</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jubran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hijazi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shapira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Severe hypertriglyceridemia-related pancreatitis: characteristics and predictors of recurrence</article-title>. <source>Pancreas</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>182</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MPA.0000000000001235</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30629026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Christian</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arondekar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buysman</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seeger</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical and economic benefits observed when follow-up triglyceride levels are less than 500 mg/dL in patients with severe hypertriglyceridemia</article-title>. <source>J Clin Lipidol</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>450</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacl.2012.08.007</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23009781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langsted</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordestgaard</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nonfasting mild-to-moderate hypertriglyceridemia and risk of acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>JAMA Intern Med</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>176</volume>:<fpage>1834</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2016.6875</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27820614</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valdivielso</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ram&#237;rez-Bueno</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ewald</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Current knowledge of hypertriglyceridemic pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Eur J Intern Med</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>689</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejim.2014.08.008</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25269432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Noel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Durgampudi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trivedi</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crowell</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Peripancreatic fat necrosis worsens acute pancreatitis independent of pancreatic necrosis via unsaturated fatty acids increased in human pancreatic necrosis collections</article-title>. <source>Gut</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>100</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2014-308043</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25500204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4869971</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sternfeld</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayden</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The role of free fatty acids, pancreatic lipase and ca+ signalling in injury of isolated acinar cells and pancreatitis model in lipoprotein lipase-deficient mice</article-title>. <source>Acta Physiol (Oxf)</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>195</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>28</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-1716.2008.01933.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18983441</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landahl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Severe acute pancreatitis: gut barrier failure, systemic inflammatory response, acute lung injury, and the role of the mesenteric lymph</article-title>. <source>Surg Infect</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>651</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/sur.2015.034</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26237406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Biczo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vegh</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shalbueva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mareninova</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elperin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lotshaw</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mitochondrial dysfunction, through impaired autophagy, leads to endoplasmic reticulum stress, deregulated lipid metabolism, and pancreatitis in animal models</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>154</volume>:<fpage>689</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>703</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2017.10.012</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29074451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6369139</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR) mutation/variant/haplotype and tumor necrosis factor (TNF) promoter polymorphism in hyperlipidemic pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Clin Chem</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1373/clinchem.2007.093492</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17981921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>SEJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varbo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tybj&#230;rg-Hansen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordestgaard</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic variants associated with increased plasma levels of triglycerides, via effects on the lipoprotein lipase pathway, increase risk of acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1652</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1660.e6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cgh.2020.08.016</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32801009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Role of oxidative stress in pancreatic inflammation</article-title>. <source>Antioxid Redox Signal</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>135</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/ars.2008.2109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18837654</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>MX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term high-fat diet induces pancreatic injuries via pancreatic microcirculatory disturbances and oxidative stress in rats with hyperlipidemia</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>347</volume>:<fpage>192</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2006.06.063</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16814251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Digenic inheritance and gene-environment interaction in a patient with hypertriglyceridemia and acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Front Genet</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>640859</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fgene.2021.640859</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34040631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8143378</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frankova</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whyms</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guevara Hernandez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franko</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of intravenous insulin, apheresis and oral lipid-lowering agents on non-fasting hypertriglyceridemia and associated pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Postgrad Med</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>130</volume>:<fpage>494</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>500</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00325481.2018.1470439</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29702000</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>