<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Chin J Traumatol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Chin J Traumatol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3010</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cjt</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Chinese Journal of Traumatology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1008-1275</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10388246</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10388246.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10388246</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10388246</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37062622</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cjtee.2023.03.007</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1008-1275(23)00024-X</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pressure ulcers and acute risk factors in individuals with traumatic spinal fractures with or without spinal cord injuries: A prospective analysis of the National Spinal Column/Cord Injury Registry of Iran (NSCIR-IR) data</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farahbakhsh</surname><given-names initials="F">Farzin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezaei Aliabadi</surname><given-names initials="H">Hossein</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baigi</surname><given-names initials="V">Vali</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghodsi</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zahra</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dashtkoohi</surname><given-names initials="M">Mohammad</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pour-Rashidi</surname><given-names initials="A">Ahmad</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">g</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrop</surname><given-names initials="JS">James S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">h</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahimi-Movaghar</surname><given-names initials="V">Vafa</given-names></name><email>v_rahimi@sina.tums.ac.ir</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="aff9" ref-type="aff">i</xref><xref rid="aff10" ref-type="aff">j</xref><xref rid="aff11" ref-type="aff">k</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#8727;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Sina and Trauma Surgery Research Center, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Brain and Spinal Cord Injury Research Center, Neuroscience Institute, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Shariati Hospital, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Sports Medicine Research Center, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>School of Medicine, Bam University of Medical Sciences, Bam, Iran</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>Students' Scientific Research Center (SSRC), Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>g</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Sina Hospital, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="aff8"><label>h</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Thomas Jefferson University, Philadelphia, USA</aff><aff id="aff9"><label>i</label>Universal Scientific Education and Research Network (USERN), Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="aff10"><label>j</label>Institute of Biochemistry and Biophysics, University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="aff11"><label>k</label>Spine Program, University of Toronto, Toronto, Canada</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#8727;</label>Corresponding author. Sina and Trauma Surgery Research Center, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran. <email>v_rahimi@sina.tums.ac.ir</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p id="ntpara0015">These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>26</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">441948</issue-id><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>30</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-08-01 15:25:10.120"><day>01</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2023 Chinese Medical Association. Production and hosting by Elsevier B.V.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Chinese Medical Association</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>To identify risk factors for developing pressure ulcers (PUs) in the acute care period of traumatic spinal fracture patients with or without spinal cord injuries (SCIs).</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Data were collected prospectively in participating the National Spinal column/Cord Injury Registry of Iran (NSCIR-IR) from individuals with traumatic spinal fractures with or without SCIs, inclusive of the hospital stay from admission to discharge. Trained nursing staff examined the patients for the presence of PUs every 8&#160;h during their hospital stay. The presence and grade of PUs were assessed according to the European Pressure Ulcer Advisory Panel classification. In addition to PU, following data were also extracted from the NSCIR-IR datasets during the period of 2015 &#8211; 2021: age, sex, Glasgow coma scale score at admission, having SCIs, marital status, surgery for a spinal fracture, American Spinal Injury Association impairment scale (AIS), urinary incontinence, level of education, admitted center, length of stay in the intensive care unit (ICU), hypertension, respiratory diseases, consumption of cigarettes, diabetes mellitus and length of stay in the hospital. Logistic regression models were used to estimate the unadjusted and adjusted odds ratio (<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic>) with 95% confidence intervals (<italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Altogether 2785 participants with traumatic spinal fractures were included. Among them, 87 (3.1%) developed PU during their hospital stay and 392 (14.1%) had SCIs. In the SCI population, 63 (16.1%) developed PU during hospital stay. Univariate logistic regression for the whole sample showed that marital status, having SCIs, urinary incontinence, level of education, treating center, number of days in the ICU, age, and Glasgow coma scale score were significant predictors for PUs. However, further analysis by multiple logistic regression only revealed the significant risk factors to be the treating center, marital status, having SCIs, and the number of days in the ICU. For the subgroup of individuals with SCIs, marital status, AIS, urinary incontinence, level of education, the treating center, the number of days in the ICU and the number of days in the hospital were significant predictors for PUs by univariate analysis. After adjustment in the multivariate model, the treating center, marital status (singles <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> marrieds, <italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> = 3.06, 95% <italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>: 1.55 &#8211; 6.03, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.001), and number of days in the ICU (<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> = 1.06, 95% <italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>: 1.04 &#8211; 1.09, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001) maintained significance.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>These data confirm that individuals with traumatic spinal fractures and SCIs, especially single young patients who suffer from urinary incontinence, grades A-D by AIS, prolonged ICU stay, and more extended hospitalization are at increased risk for PUs; as a result strategies to minimize PU development need further refinement.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010s"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Spinal fractures</kwd><kwd>Spinal cord injuries</kwd><kwd>Pressure ulcer</kwd><kwd>NSCIR-IR</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Traumatic spinal cord injury (SCI) is a prevalent global injury that impacts almost every aspect of the life of the affected individuals. The annual incidence ranges from 5 to 195 cases per million worldwide.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> SCI results in loss of sensation, motor and autonomic impairments; therefore, these individuals are at a high risk of developing pressure ulcers (PUs).<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> A recent meta-analysis estimated that the global incidence of PUs among individuals with SCIs is about 20%, i.e., 1/5 individuals with SCIs is affected.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref></p><p id="p0015">PU itself significantly burdens SCI patients and the health care systems. It is associated with frequent hospitalization, multiple surgeries, more complications, and extended hospital stays in acute and chronic SCI phases.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> PU also affects psychological, physical, social aspects, and the quality of life of SCI patients.<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></p><p id="p0020">PU is considered a preventable adverse effect. In the acute phase of SCIs, nursing care plays an important role in prevention.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> Although the etiology of PU is complex, there are some suggested risk factors in SCI patients, including older age, male sex, poor nutrition, other comorbidities, being depressed, less education, and singleness.<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Some characteristics of the SCI, such as level of injury, time since SCI, urinary and fecal incontinence, and dependency for daily activities can also be associated with PUs.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> While modifiable risk factors can play an essential role in preventing PUs in SCI patients, much data are from retrospective studies.<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref></p><p id="p0025">National Spinal Column/Cord Injury Registry of Iran (NSCIR-IR) is a multi-disciplinary effort that can help understand SCIs&#8217; nature and course.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> This initiative has prospectively collected data on spinal fractures with or without SCIs in Iran. In this study, using systematically collected data from NSCIR-IR, we want to identify risk factors for developing PUs in individuals with traumatic spinal fractures with or without SCIs in the acute care setting.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>Patients</title><p id="p0030">The NSCIR-IR is a hospital-based registry of traumatic spinal fractures with or without SCIs, which was initiated in 2015. At the time of this study, 9 trauma centers from 8 major cities of Iran participated in the registry. Patients that meet the inclusion and exclusion criteria<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> of the registry are collected and recorded daily during their admission, in both paper and electronic format. A quality reviewer examines the submitted electronic data, and any potential errors are returned to the initial examiner. The entered data on a patient are considered complete only when the quality reviewer has resolved any inquires. Details of the NSCIR-IR and collected data protocols can be found in previously published articles.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> In this study, all patients with traumatic spinal fractures with or without SCIs who were registered in the NSCIR-IR during the period of 2015 &#8211; 2021 were included without any exclusion criteria. The Ethics Committee of Sina Trauma and Surgery Research Center, Tehran University of Medical Sciences has approved the study (No. 96-02-38-303).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Measurements</title><p id="p0035">Hospitals that participate in the NSCIR-IR are respectively A&#160;=&#160;Imam Khomeini Urmia, B&#160;= Imam Reza Tabriz, C&#160;= Shahid Beheshti Kashan, D&#160;=&#160;Firouzgar Tehran, E&#160;=&#160;Sina Tehran, F&#160;= Rahnemon Yazd, G&#160;=&#160;Poursina Rasht, H&#160;= Imam Hasan Shahrod, I&#160;= Valiasr Arak. Once patients are enrolled, begin documenting their data at admission. Data are collected prospectively, on a daily basis during the patient's hospital admission. The data entry form covers information regarding many fields related to spinal fractures and SCIs. From this set, data pertaining to PUs are age, sex, Glasgow coma scale (GCS) score at admission, having SCIs, marital status, surgery for a spinal fracture, American Spinal Injury Association impairment scale (AIS), urinary incontinence, level of education, admitted center, length of stay in the intensive care unit (ICU), hypertension, respiratory diseases, consumption of cigarettes, diabetes mellitus and length of stay in the hospital. There is an obligatory routine program in Iran's public hospitals to assess PUs in admitted patients. Therefore, in the NSCIR-IR centers (like every other public hospital in Iran), trained nursing staff examine the patients for the presence of PUs every 8&#160;h during their stay. The presence and grade of PUs are further assessed and documented according to the European Pressure Ulcer Advisory Panel classification.<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0040">In this study, logistic regression models were used to estimate the unadjusted and adjusted odds ratio (<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic>) with 95% confidence intervals (<italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>). First, we fitted logistic regression models with 1 covariate at a time and analyzed the fits. In particular, look at the estimated coefficients, their standard errors and the likelihood ratio test for the significance of the coefficient, then in the final model only those with <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.2 were included. Since that variables which did not exceed 5% of missing values (according to scientific articles), we did not use impute methods to handle missing. As a result, we excluded missing values. However, we used correlation coefficients and variance inflation factors to diagnostic collinearity between variables. All the analyses were performed via the R-software version (3.6.2). A <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.05 was considered significant based on two-tailed tests.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Results</title><p id="p0045">In this study, 2785 participants with traumatic spinal fractures were included, 2044 male (73.4%) and 741 female (26.6%). Among them, 87 (3.1%) developed PUs during their acute hospital admission. The mean age (years) was 42.20&#160;&#177;&#160;17.20 among patients without PUs and 37.4&#160;&#177;&#160;17.6 among those with PUs. Univariate analysis of the potential risk factors for developing PUs in traumatic spinal fracture patients is presented in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#160;1</xref>. It is shown that SCI, marital status (single <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> married), AIS, urinary incontinence, level of education, hospital in which the patient received treatment, number of days in the ICU, days in the hospital, age and GCS score (all <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.05) were statistically significant predictors for developing PUs for the whole samples.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;1</label><caption><p>Univariate analysis of potential risk factors for PUs in the 2785 patients with traumatic spinal fractures.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Table&#160;1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variables</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Without PU (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#160;=&#160;2698)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">With PU <italic toggle="yes">(n</italic>&#160;=&#160;87)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Crude <italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> (95% <italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1976 (73.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">68 (78.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Female</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">722 (26.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (21.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.76 (0.46 &#8211; 1.28)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.298</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">SCI</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2336 (86.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (18.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">329 (12.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">63 (72.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.96 (15.96 &#8211; 48.98)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Missing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (1.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (9.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Marital status</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Married</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1919 (71.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45 (51.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Single</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">655 (24.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">36 (41.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.34 (1.49 &#8211; 3.66)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Divorce</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">177 (4.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (4.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.46 (0.52 &#8211; 4.12)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.471</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Missing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (0.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (2.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Hypertension</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2496 (92.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">84 (96.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">202 (7.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (3.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.44 (0.13 &#8211; 1.41)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.159</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Respiratory disease</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2652 (98.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">85 (97.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46 (1.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (2.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.35 (0.32 &#8211; 5.68)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.668</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Cigarettes</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2090 (77.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">63 (72.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">608 (22.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (27.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.31 (0.81 &#8211; 2.11)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.274</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Diabetes mellitus</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2552 (94.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">86 (98.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">146 (5.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20 (0.02 &#8211; 1.47)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.109</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">COVID_19</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2688 (99.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">86 (98.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (0.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.13 (0.40 &#8211; 24.70)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.278</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Surgical intervention</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1494 (55.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 (46.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1202 (44.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 (54.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.46 (0.95 &#8211; 2.24)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.076</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Missing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">AIS</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;E</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2296 (85.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (21.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">166 (6.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (49.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.30 (17.84 &#8211; 54.93)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;B</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (0.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (2.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.17 (4.96 &#8211; 117.79)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;C</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">57 (2.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (8.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.84 (6.0 &#8211; 36.70)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;D</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">113 (4.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (13.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.83 (6.08 &#8211; 27.08)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Missing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">56 (2.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (4.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Urinary incontinence</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2421 (89.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (26.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">234 (8.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">54 (62.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.29 (14.64 &#8211; 40.29)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Missing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (1.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (11.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Level of education</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Diploma</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">635 (23.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (13.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Illiterate</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">496 (18.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (19.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.81 (0.86 &#8211; 3.83)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.107</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Primary school</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">549 (20.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (19.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.64 (0.78 &#8211; 3.46)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.190</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Middle school</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">439 (16.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (14.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.57 (0.71 &#8211; 3.47)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.257</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;High school</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">275 (10.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (20.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.46 (1.65 &#8211; 7.29)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Academic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">289 (10.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (6.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.09 (0.40 &#8211; 2.96)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.843</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Missing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (0.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (4.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Hospitals</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">680 (25.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (19.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;B</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">404 (15.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45 (51.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.45 (2.51 &#8211; 7.88)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;C</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">206 (7.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (10.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.78 (0.76 &#8211; 3.97)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.176</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;D</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">214 (7.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (5.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.93 (0.34 &#8211; 2.56)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.892</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;E</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">158 (5.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (9.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.02 (0.85 &#8211; 4.77)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.103</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">82 (3.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (3.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.46 (0.42 &#8211; 5.10)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.556</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;G</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">437 (16.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.987</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;H</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (1.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.988</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;I</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">486 (18.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.989</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Days in the ICU</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0, 0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (0, 35)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.08 (1.07 &#8211; 1.10)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Days in the hospital</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">102 (52, 184)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">265 (189, 369)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.009 (1.006 &#8211; 1.011)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (year)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.2&#160;&#177;&#160;17.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.4&#160;&#177;&#160;17.6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.98 (0.97 &#8211; 1.00)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">GCS</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.7&#160;&#177;&#160;3.9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.7&#160;&#177;&#160;5.4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.90 (0.87 &#8211; 0.93)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tspara0015"><p>Data are expressed as <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%), mean&#160;&#177;&#160;SD or median (Q<sub>1</sub>, Q<sub>3</sub>); -: not exist.</p></fn><fn id="tspara0020"><p>PU: pressure ulcers; <italic toggle="yes">OR</italic>: odds ratio; <italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>: confidence interval; SCI: spinal cord injury; AIS: American Spinal Injury Association impairment scale; GCS: Glasgow coma scale.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0050">Of the 2785 patients with traumatic spinal fractures, 392 (14.1%) were diagnosed with SCIs. AIS distribution of the SCI cases was 207 of A, 12 of B, 64 of C, 98 of D, and 8 of E. Among the 392 SCI individuals, 63 (16.1%) developed PUs in their hospital stay. <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#160;2</xref> shows the potential risk factors for developing PUs in the subgroup of traumatic spinal fracture patients with SCIs. It was showed that marital status, AIS, urinary incontinence, level of education (high school education <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> diploma), hospital in which patient received treatment, number of days in the ICU and number of days in the hospital were statistical significant predictors for developing PUs in patients suffering from SCIs.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;2</label><caption><p>Univariate analysis of potential risk factors for developing PUs in 392 traumatic spinal fracture patients with SCIs.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Table&#160;2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variables</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Without PU (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#160;=&#160;329)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">With PU (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#160;=&#160;63)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Crude <italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> (95% <italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">265 (80.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (77.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Female</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64 (19.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (22.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.19 (0.62 &#8211; 2.27)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.612</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Marital status</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Married</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">224 (68.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (49.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Single</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">96 (29.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (44.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.11 (1.19 &#8211; 3.71)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Divorce</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (2.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (6.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.13 (1.14 &#8211; 14.92)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.033</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Missing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Hypertension</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">318 (96.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">61 (96.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (3.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95 (0.20 &#8211; 4.38)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.937</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Respiratory disease</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">324 (98.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">62 (98.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (1.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.04 (0.12 &#8211; 9.10)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.975</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Cigarettes</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">238 (72.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">44 (69.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">91 (27.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (30.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.30 (0.63 &#8211; 2.03)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.694</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Diabetes mellitus</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">309 (93.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">63 (100.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (6.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.987</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">COVID_19</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">326 (99.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">63 (100.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.986</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Surgical intervention</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">218 (66.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45 (71.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">111 (33.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (28.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.79 (0.43 &#8211; 1.42)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.419</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">AIS</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">165 (50.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (66.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;B</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (3.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.79 (0.17 &#8211; 3.72)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.758</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;C</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">57 (17.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (11.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.48 (0.21 &#8211; 1.13)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.088</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;D</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 (26.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (15.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.45 (0.21 &#8211; 0.93)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.032</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;E</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (2.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.56 (0.06 &#8211; 4.69)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.598</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Missing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Urinary incontinence</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">215 (65.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">52 (82.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">106 (32.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (15.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.40 (0.20 &#8211; 0.80)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.014</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Missing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (2.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Level of education</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Diploma</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">69 (21.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (14.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Illiterate</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">53 (16.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (22.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.02 (0.82 &#8211; 5.04)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.128</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Primary school</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">60 (18.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (12.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02 (0.37 &#8211; 2.82)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.963</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Middle school</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">60 (18.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (19.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.53 (0.60 &#8211; 3.89)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.367</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;High school</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">38 (11.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (20.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.62 (1.02 &#8211; 6.67)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.042</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Academic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">44 (13.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (7.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.87 (0.27 &#8211; 2.77)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.814</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Missing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (1.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Hospitals</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">93 (28.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (17.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">--</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;B</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">84 (25.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (46.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.92 (1.37 &#8211; 6.21)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;C</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (5.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (14.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.0 (1.46 &#8211; 10.99)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;D</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41 (12.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (7.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03 (0.33 &#8211; 3.16)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.956</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;E</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (7.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (12.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.94 (1.06 &#8211; 8.15)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.039</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (2.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94 (0.11 &#8211; 8.13)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.955</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;G</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">39 (11.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.992</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;I</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (6.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.986</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Days in the ICU</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0 &#8211; 5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (0 &#8211; 28)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.04 (1.02 &#8211; 1.06)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Days in the hospital</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">167 (87, 247)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">280 (217, 391)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.01 (1.00 &#8211; 1.01)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (year)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.9&#160;&#177;&#160;15.4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.5&#160;&#177;&#160;18.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.99 (0.98 &#8211; 1.01)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.837</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">GCS</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.0&#160;&#177;&#160;4.8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.1&#160;&#177;&#160;5.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.96 (0.92 &#8211; 1.01)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.138</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tspara0030"><p>Data are expressed as <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%), mean&#160;&#177;&#160;SD or median, (Q<sub>1</sub>, Q<sub>3</sub>); -: not exist.</p></fn><fn id="tspara0035"><p>PU: pressure ulcers; SCI: spinal cord injury; <italic toggle="yes">OR</italic>: odds ratio; <italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>: confidence interval; AIS: American Spinal Injury Association impairment scale; GCS: Glasgow coma scale.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0055">After unadjusted logistic regression, we first tested the multicollinearity and there was no multicollinearity between symptoms. Then the multiple logistic regression was conducted (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#160;3</xref>, <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table&#160;4</xref>). For the whole sample (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#160;3</xref>), B hospital (<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic>&#160;=&#160;12.37, 95% <italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>: 6.49 &#8211; 23.62, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001), C hospital (<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic>&#160;=&#160;4.16, 95% <italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>: 1.26 &#8211; 13.68, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.013), marital status (singles <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> marrieds, <italic toggle="yes">OR</italic>&#160;=&#160;2.80, 95% <italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>: 1.53 &#8211; 5.12, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.001), SCI (<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic>&#160;=&#160;12.37, 95% <italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>: 6.49 &#8211; 23.62, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001) and days in the ICU (<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic>&#160;=&#160;1.09, 95% <italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>: 1.05 &#8211; 1.11, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001) were significant risk factors for developing PU.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;3</label><caption><p>Multivariate analysis of potential risk factors for developing PUs in traumatic spinal fracture patients.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Table&#160;3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variables</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Crude <italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> (95% <italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adjusted <italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> (95% <italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">SCI</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.96 (15.96 &#8211; 48.98)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.37 (6.49 &#8211; 23.62)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Missing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Marital status</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Married</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Single</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.34 (1.5 &#8211; 3.67)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.80 (1.53 &#8211; 5.12)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Divorce</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.46 (0.52 &#8211; 4.12)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.26 (0.58 &#8211; 8.90)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.238</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Missing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Hospitals</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;B</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.20 (1.01 &#8211; 4.71)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.53 (4.75 &#8211; 33.02)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;C</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86 (0.32 &#8211; 2.28)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.16 (1.26 &#8211; 13.68)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;D</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.46 (0.14 &#8211; 1.43)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.19 (0.31 &#8211; 4.60)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.798</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;E</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.49 (0.20 &#8211; 1.16)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.09 (0.92 &#8211; 10.43)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.068</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.72 (0.18 &#8211; 2.79)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.79 (0.12 &#8211; 5.05)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.802</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;G</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.989</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;H</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.988</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;I</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.987</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Days in the ICU</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.08 (1.07 &#8211; 1.10)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.09 (1.05 &#8211; 1.11)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>PU: pressure ulcers; <italic toggle="yes">OR</italic>: odds ratio; <italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>: confidence interval; SCI: spinal cord injury; GCS: Glasgow coma scale.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;4</label><caption><p>Multivariate analysis of potential risk factors for developing PUs in traumatic spinal fracture patients with SCIs.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Table&#160;4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variables</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Crude <italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> (95% <italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adjusted <italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> (95% <italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Marital status</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Married</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Single</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.11 (1.19 &#8211; 3.71)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.06 (1.55 &#8211; 6.03)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Divorce</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.13 (1.14 &#8211; 14.92)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.73 (0.80 &#8211; 17.26)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.087</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Missing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Hospitals</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;B</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.92 (1.37 &#8211; 6.21)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.03 (3.33 &#8211; 30.20)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;C</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.0 (1.46 &#8211; 10.99)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.46 (1.80 &#8211; 23.30)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;D</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03 (0.33 &#8211; 3.16)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.55 (0.38 &#8211; 6.38)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.545</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;E</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.94 (1.06 &#8211; 8.15)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.90 (1.34 &#8211; 17.81)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.069</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94 (0.11 &#8211; 8.13)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.32 (0.02 &#8211; 4.54)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.023</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;G</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.988</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;I</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.987</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Days in the ICU</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.40 (1.02 &#8211; 1.06)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.06 (1.04 &#8211; 1.09)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>PU: pressure ulcers; SCI: spinal cord injury; <italic toggle="yes">OR</italic>: odds ratio; <italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>: confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p20060">In the subgroup of patients with SCIs (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table&#160;4</xref>), B, C and F hospitals, marital status (singles <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> marrieds) and days in the ICU were statistically significant.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0060">Traumatic SCI is a relatively common injury, particularly in developing countries, which makes patients susceptible to develop PUs. This study aims to identify the risk factors predisposing to PUs at the acute stage of injury.</p><p id="p0065">Among the included 2785 patients with traumatic spinal fractures, 392 (14.1%) were diagnosed with SCIs, in which 63 (16.1%) developed PUs during their hospital stay. The reported incidence of PUs ranges 1% &#8211; 57%. But in a recent systematic review, pooled data from 29 studies showed the incidence to be close to 20%.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> The 16.1% incidence of PU in individuals with SCIs is relatively lower than many other reports. All the centers participating in the NSCIR-IR have dedicated staff specially trained to manage SCIs, which might be a contributing factor to this lower incidence of PUs in this study. Despite this, some of the centers participating in the NSCIR-IR had higher rates of PUs and were significant risk factors for developing PUs. This underlines the importance of continuous staff training and care facility improvement in these centers. Though the occurrence of PUs was higher in males than in females, there was no association between gender and PU development. Previous studies have also shown mixed results on the association of PU and gender.<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></p><p id="p0070">PU is a complex entity, and even in the acute period after SCI, many factors can play a role in its development. Previously it has been suggested that patients' family and relative involvement in hospital care may reduce PU development and improve outcomes in individuals with SCIs.<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> Likewise, in a study by Chen et&#160;al.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> single patients were more likely to develop PUs. These findings are similar to this study, which noted that marital status plays a significant role in PU development in subjects with traumatic spinal fractures and SCIs.</p><p id="p0075">Most subjects with traumatic spinal fractures do not have neurologic injuries and are considered neurologically intact. When AIS E was considered the reference group in the univariate analysis, individuals with AIS A, B, C, and D who had higher level neurological impairment were more likely to develop PUs. In the subgroup of SCI subjects, most were categorized as having AIS A. When taking AIS A as the reference group, all other levels of neurological impairments had lower odds of developing PUs, but this was only significant for AIS D and C. The number of individuals in the AIS B and E groups in our subjects with SCIs is low, and that might be why the odds in these 2 groups are not significant. Although previous findings are inconsistent regarding the association between AIS and PU<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref>, our results are consistent with many other studies showing that individuals with complete neurological impairment have a higher chance of developing PUs.<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></p><p id="p0080">We found that urinary incontinence is a risk factor for PUs among SCI patients. Consequently, patients without a urethral catheterization, who either do clean-intermittent-catheterization or use clothing, should be checked for PU initiation or aggravation. Skin wetness and prolonged pressure can lead to skin maceration that would trigger PUs. Our results were in line with the literature regarding incontinence as a predisposing factor for PUs.<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref></p><p id="p0085">Moreover, prolonged ICU stay and longer length of hospital stay are accompanied by a higher rate of PUs, which is in concordance with the results of Kayser et&#160;al.<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> and Pacha et&#160;al.<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> Many SCI patients also have some other traumatic injuries, leading to secondary complications such as pneumonia, urinary tract infections, deep vein thrombosis, etc., making hospitalization longer. Therefore, in parallel to the Dinh et&#160;al.<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> study, an excellent multi-disciplinary approach involving all the necessary specialties is needed to treat the patients and transfer them to their homes as soon as possible.</p><p id="p0090">It is important to highlight that in this investigation there were 24 individuals who developed PUs during the study period but were not diagnosed with SCIs. Anyway they had traumatic spinal fractures. Hence, factors other than SCI such as low level of consciousness, immobilization, prolonged ICU stay, and limited movements due to other fractures or disabilities could have led to PU development.</p><p id="p0095">This study potentially has several limitations. First, not all patients with traumatic spinal fractures are referred to the NSCIR-IR centers, but the studied population can still represent these individuals. Second, many factors can play a role in PU development, but not all of them are evaluated in the NSCIR-IR forms. There were also some critical data, such as nutritional status and ulcer locations, have not been included in our analysis due to the incomplete data in the forms. Third, ideally, PU should be assessed both in the acute care setting and prolonged intervals after the first hospitalization, but our study only evaluates the acute care setting. Forth, some factors like stroke, ischemic heart disease, asthma, multiple sclerosis, unspecified respiratory disease, and other disease can also play a role in PU development, but for all of these factors there were not enough data point to assess, as a consequence we did not considerate to analyze. Finally, some patients were transferred to the NSCIR-IR centers from other less equipped centers. This might have led to prolongation in terms of the initiation of PU prevention measures.</p><p id="p0100">In conclusion, this data confirms that individuals with traumatic spinal fractures and SCI, especially in single young patients who suffer from urinary incontinence, AIS grades A to D, prolonged ICU stay, and more extended hospitalization are at increased risk for PUs and strategies to minimize development need further refinement.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Funding</title><p id="p0110">This work was funded by <funding-source id="gs1">Sina Trauma and Surgery Research Center, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Iran</funding-source> (grant number is 96-02-38-35120).</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Ethical statement</title><p id="p0105">The Ethics Committee of Sina Trauma and Surgery Research Center, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, approved the study, and the reference number is 96-02-38-303.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0120">The authors announce that there is no conflict of interests about this research.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Author contributions</title><p id="p0115">Vafa Rahimi-Movaghar: study design, supervising the findings, editing draft; Farzin Farahbakhsh: draft writing, interpretation of the results; Hossein Rezaei and Vali Baigi: analysis; Mohammad Dashtkhoohi: data collecting; Ahmad Pourrashidi: draft writing; Zahra Ghodsi: edits the draft, communication with team members. All authors provided critical feedback and discussed the results and contributed to the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Incidence of pressure injury in individuals with spinal cord injury: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>J&#160;Wound, Ostomy Cont Nurs</source><volume>47</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/1673-5374.303026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32384524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahimi-Movaghar</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saadat</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasouli</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of spinal cord injury in Tehran, Iran</article-title><source>J&#160;Spinal Cord Med</source><volume>32</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>428</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10790268.2009.11754572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19777865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2830683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jazayeri</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beygi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shokraneh</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Incidence of traumatic spinal cord injury worldwide: a systematic review</article-title><source>Eur Spine J</source><volume>24</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>905</fpage><lpage>918</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00586-014-3424-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24952008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khorasanizadeh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yousefifard</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eskian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neurological recovery following traumatic spinal cord injury: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>J&#160;Neurosurg Spine</source><volume>30</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>699</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/2018.10.SPINE18802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30771786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Javadi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hafezi-Nejad</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaccaro</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Medical complications and patient outcomes in Iranian veterans with spinal cord injury</article-title><source>Adv Clin Exp Med</source><volume>23</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>275</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17219/acem/37075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24913118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eslami</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saadat</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Habibi Arejan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with the development of pressure ulcers after spinal cord injury</article-title><source>Spinal Cord</source><volume>50</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>899</fpage><lpage>903</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sc.2012.75</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22777490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soloway</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Civil claims relating to pressure ulcers: a claimants' lawyer's perspective</article-title><source>Ostomy/Wound Manag</source><volume>44</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><comment>26</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9526418</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gottschlich</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helvig</surname><given-names>E.I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Review of evidenced-based practice for the prevention of pressure sores in burn patients</article-title><source>J&#160;Burn Care Rehabil</source><volume>25</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>388</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.bcr.0000138289.83335.f4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15353931</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coulter</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Balancing the pressure ulcer cost and quality equation</article-title><source>Nurs Econ</source><volume>10</volume><year>1992</year><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1465158</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>B.A.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dea</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Street</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The economic burden of urinary tract infection and pressure ulceration in acute traumatic spinal cord injury admissions: evidence for comparative economics and decision analytics from a matched case-control study</article-title><source>J&#160;Neurotrauma</source><volume>34</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>2892</fpage><lpage>2900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/neu.2016.4934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28791891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nanwa</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mittmann</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The average cost of pressure ulcer management in a community dwelling spinal cord injury population</article-title><source>Int Wound J</source><volume>10</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1742-481X.2012.01002.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22715990</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7950392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Consortium for Spinal Cord Medicine Clinical Practice Guidelines</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Pressure ulcer prevention and treatment following spinal cord injury: a clinical practice guideline for health-care professionals</article-title><source>J&#160;Spinal Cord Med</source><volume>24</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>S40</fpage><lpage>S101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10790268.2001.11753592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11958176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Skin sores after spinal cord injury: relationship to life adjustment</article-title><source>Spinal Cord</source><volume>36</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.sc.3100528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9471139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahimi-Movaghar</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moradi-Lakeh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasouli</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Burden of spinal cord injury in Tehran, Iran</article-title><source>Spinal Cord</source><volume>48</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>492</fpage><lpage>497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sc.2009.158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19901955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pancorbo-Hidalgo</surname><given-names>P.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Fernandez</surname><given-names>F.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Medina</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk assessment scales for pressure ulcer prevention: a systematic review</article-title><source>J&#160;Adv Nurs</source><volume>54</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2648.2006.03794.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16553695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guihan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>LaVela</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors predicting pressure ulcers in veterans with spinal cord injuries</article-title><source>Am J Phys Med Rehabil</source><volume>87</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>750</fpage><lpage>757</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PHM.0b013e3181837a50</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18716487</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Devivo</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pressure ulcer prevalence in people with spinal cord injury: age-period-duration effects</article-title><source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source><volume>86</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>1208</fpage><lpage>1213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apmr.2004.12.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15954061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Idowu</surname><given-names>O.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yinusa</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gbadegesin</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for pressure ulceration in a resource constrained spinal injury service</article-title><source>Spinal Cord</source><volume>49</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>643</fpage><lpage>647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sc.2010.175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21221118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verschueren</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Post</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Groot</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Occurrence and predictors of pressure ulcers during primary in-patient spinal cord injury rehabilitation</article-title><source>Spinal Cord</source><volume>49</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sc.2010.66</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20531357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olney</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spinal cord injury survey to determine pressure ulcer vulnerability in the outpatient population</article-title><source>Med Hypotheses</source><volume>83</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>552</fpage><lpage>558</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mehy.2014.08.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25241921</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarrias</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An analysis of the diverse factors concerned with the development of pressure sores in spinal cord injured patients</article-title><source>Paraplegia</source><volume>29</volume><year>1991</year><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sc.1991.37</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1870891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pressure sores and the spinal cord injured</article-title><source>Sci Digest</source><volume>3</volume><year>1981</year><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>17</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiyagarajan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aetiology of pressure sores in patients with spinal cord injury</article-title><source>Br Med J</source><volume>289</volume><year>1984</year><fpage>1487</fpage><lpage>1490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.289.6457.1487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6439284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1443766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Curry</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casady</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship between extended periods of immobility and decubitus ulcer formation in the acutely spinal cord-injured individual</article-title><source>J&#160;Neurosci Nurs</source><volume>24</volume><year>1992</year><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01376517-199208000-00003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1517663</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maklebust</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magnan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors associated with having a pressure ulcer: a secondary data analysis</article-title><source>Adv Wound Care</source><volume>7</volume><year>1994</year><fpage>25</fpage><comment>27-28, 31-34 passim</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7795863</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Prinzio</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Argento</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbalaco</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for the development and recurrence of pressure ulcers in patients with spinal cord injury: a systematic review</article-title><source>Rev Fac Cien Med Univ Nac Cordoba</source><volume>76</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.31053/1853.0605.v76.n4.24906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31833749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharif-Alhoseini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azadmanjir</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadeghi-Naini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>National spinal cord injury registry of Iran (NSCIR-IR) &#8211; a critical appraisal of its strengths and weaknesses</article-title><source>Chin J Traumatol</source><volume>22</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>300</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cjtee.2019.05.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31445798</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6823677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Azadmanjir</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohtasham-Amiri</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ziabari</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sustaining the national spinal cord injury registry of Iran (NSCIR-IR) in a regional center: challenges and solutions</article-title><source>Iran J Public Health</source><volume>49</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>736</fpage><lpage>743</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32548054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7283190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haesler</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>European Pressure Ulcer Advisory Panel, National Pressure Injury Advisory Panel and Pan Pacific Pressure Injury Alliance. Prevention and Treatment of Pressure Ulcers/injuries: Quick Reference Guide</part-title><edition>Cambridge Media:</edition><year>2014</year><publisher-name>Osborne Park, Australia</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ash</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An exploration of the occurrence of pressure ulcers in a British spinal injuries unit</article-title><source>J&#160;Clin Nurs</source><volume>11</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>470</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2702.2002.00603.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12100643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mawson</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biundo</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neville</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for early occurring pressure ulcers following spinal cord injury</article-title><source>Am J Phys Med Rehabil</source><volume>67</volume><year>1988</year><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00002060-198806000-00007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3377890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Irgens</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoff</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jelnes</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spinal cord injury and development of pressure injury during acute rehabilitation in Norway: a national retrospective cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Spinal Cord</source><volume>58</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>1069</fpage><lpage>1079</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41393-020-0465-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32341478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadarajah</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spinal injuries admitted to a specialist centre over a 5-year period: a study to evaluate delayed admission</article-title><source>Spinal Cord</source><volume>43</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>434</fpage><lpage>437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.sc.3101734</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15753960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kabir</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predicting pressure ulcers during initial hospitalization for acute spinal cord injury</article-title><source>Wounds</source><volume>11</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>57</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorecki</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patient risk factors for pressure ulcer development: systematic review</article-title><source>Int J Nurs Stud</source><volume>50</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>974</fpage><lpage>1003</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2012.11.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23375662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchand</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davido</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Management of established pressure ulcer infections in spinal cord injury patients</article-title><source>Med Maladies Infect</source><volume>49</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.medmal.2018.05.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29937316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kayser</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>VanGilder</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lachenbruch</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predictors of superficial and severe hospital-acquired pressure injuries: a cross-sectional study using the International Pressure Ulcer Prevalence&#8482; survey</article-title><source>Int J Nurs Stud</source><volume>89</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2018.09.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30339955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pach&#225;</surname><given-names>H.H.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>J.I.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pressure ulcer in intensive care units: a case-control study</article-title><source>Rev Bras Enferm</source><volume>71</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>3027</fpage><lpage>3034</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0034-7167-2017-0950</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30517408</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn id="d35e1787"><p id="ntpara0010">Peer review under responsibility of Chinese Medical Association.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>