<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1609</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmjo</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMJ Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2044-6055</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10314639</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10314639.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10314639</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10314639</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37385743</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2023-073391</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen-2023-073391</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Paediatrics</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1506</subject><subject>1719</subject></subj-group><series-title>Original research</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Respite care: qualitative arts-based findings on the perspectives and experiences of families of children and youth with special healthcare needs residing in Manitoba, Canada</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-48519160" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7176-2390</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodgate</surname><given-names initials="RL">Roberta L</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-56531161" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Isaak</surname><given-names initials="C">Corinne</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-106015788" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kipling</surname><given-names initials="A">Ardelle</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-36761656" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names initials="S">Sue</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-58267349" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keilty</surname><given-names initials="K">Krista</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">College of Nursing, Rady Faculty of Health Sciences</institution>, <institution specific-use="Ringgold_8664">University of Manitoba</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Winnipeg</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Manitoba</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">School of Health Sciences</institution>, <institution specific-use="Ringgold_5292">The University of Manchester</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Manchester</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="department">Connected Care</institution>, <institution specific-use="Ringgold_7979">The Hospital for Sick Children</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Toronto</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Ontario</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country></aff><author-notes><corresp><label>Correspondence to</label> Dr Roberta L Woodgate; <email>Roberta.Woodgate@umanitoba.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>6</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">437839</issue-id><elocation-id>e073391</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>29</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>02</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-07-03 04:25:09.690"><day>03</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2023. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense" start_date="2023-06-29">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See:&#160;<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-073391.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-073391.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="reviewers-comments-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-073391.reviewer_comments.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="draft-revisions-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-073391.draft_revisions.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>Respite for families of children and youth with special healthcare needs (CYSHCN) is essential for sustaining a family care environment. Lacking is an understanding of families&#8217; respite experiences who reside in Canada. We sought to understand experiences of the use of respite services by families with CYSHCN with the aim to help improve respite services. This paper reports on the qualitative arts-based findings.</p></sec><sec><title>Design</title><p>Qualitative methods including open-ended interviews combined with the arts-based methods of ecomaps and the photovoice process were used. Analysis involved delineating units of meaning from the data, clustering units of meaning to form thematic statements and extracting themes.</p><p>
<bold>Setting</bold>
</p><p>Manitoba, a western Canadian province.</p></sec><sec><title>Participants</title><p>Thirty-two families (including 38 parents and 13 siblings) of CYSHCN.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We identified six themes surrounding challenges experienced by families&#8217; in their journeys accessing, acquiring and navigating the respite care system, and sustainment of respite care for their families, leading to familial burn-out and breakdown, financial stress, unemployment and unaddressed mental health struggles. Families provided multipronged recommendations to address these challenges.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Through the lens of Canadian families of children with a range of complex care needs, the qualitative arts-based portion of the study underscores the challenges with accessing, navigating and sustaining respite care, which has implications for CYSHCN, their clinicians and the potential for long-term costs for government and society. This study identifies the state of the current Manitoba respite care system as an issue, presenting actionable recommendations from families that can assist policymakers and clinicians in advocating for and implementing a collaborative, responsive, family-centred system of respite care.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>QUALITATIVE RESEARCH</kwd><kwd>Community child health</kwd><kwd>Patient Navigation</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group specific-use="FundRef"><award-group id="funding-1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Canadian Institutes of Health Research</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Reference # PJT-162427</award-id></award-group><award-group id="funding-2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>CIHR -Canadian Research Chair - 950-231845</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>special-feature</meta-name><meta-value>unlocked</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>STRENGTHS AND LIMITATIONS OF THIS STUDY</title></caption><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>There are few Canadian studies within the past 10 years exploring the respite experiences of families with children and youth with special healthcare needs (CYSHCN) to understand current challenges with accessing respite services, along with their solutions to address these challenges.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Inclusion of questions relating to participating family characteristics, primary conditions of CYSHCN of participating families and self-reported respite hours received provides a comprehensive picture of families&#8217; situations.</p></list-item><list-item><p>We used multiple research methods, including open-ended interviews (individual and family), photo voice and ecomaps to generate our significant findings.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Limitations of sample include few newcomers and fathers.</p></list-item></list></boxed-text><disp-quote><p>While generalization of findings to populations of families of CYSHCN in other jurisdictions in Canada and beyond is not the goal of qualitative research, these findings nonetheless can be used by others in understanding the experiences of the use of respite services by families with CYSHCN.</p></disp-quote><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The Canadian Institute for Health Information states that children and youth with medical complexity, including a range of single or multiple conditions, neurological impairment or neurological impairment with other condition(s), share four characteristics: complex chronic conditions, functional limitations, high healthcare utilisation and caregiving needs.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> The unique needs of these Canadians requires extensive physical, financial and social resources to participate in daily life,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2&#8211;4</xref> and achieve optimal outcomes.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Between 2010 and 2016, there were 97&#8201;561 Canadian children and youth (aged 0&#8211;24 years) with medical complexity, an age-adjusted rate across provinces of 948 per 100&#8201;000<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> sparking increased demand for extensive medical therapies and supports.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5 6</xref> Advances in medical care, and shifts in public policy in Canada have led to increasing numbers of children and youth with medical complexity to be cared for within Canadians&#8217; homes (vs hospitals or institutions).<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> However, Canadian healthcare systems have yet to address the rising demand for and coordination of care of children and youth with special healthcare needs (CYSHCN), tasking families with the brunt of caregiving duties.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6 8</xref> Caregiving for these children and youth varies based on needs and conditions, including behavioural monitoring, mobility, ventilator or feeding support, medical therapy, and or assistive technology dependence, sometimes resulting in the need for 24-hour care.</p><p>While there is no agreed on definition, here, we use the term CYSHCN which includes infants, children and youth who have one or more chronic physical, developmental, behavioural or emotional conditions, and require special health and support services. As primary caregivers of CYSHCN, parents struggle to maintain a balance between social and work life, personal well-being and this unique context of parenting.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3 9</xref> Moreover, having CYSHCN greatly impacts the family dynamic especially for siblings who may assume caretaker roles, feel protective over their sibling with complex care needs or experience mental health challenges.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10&#8211;12</xref> Although family members of CYSHCN may share deep connections, negative outcomes such as emotional exhaustion are evident.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10 13</xref> Respite care (short-term breaks), either in-home or out-of-home can benefit parents, the CYSHCN and siblings<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4 14 15</xref> and sustain family care environments, reducing parental stress, anxiety and depression,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> while addressing needs of CYSHCN.<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> Respite care services vary across Canada both interprovincially and intraprovincially. Although respite may be for a crisis intervention, it is ideally a component of a supportive network provided for caregivers but may also be for the CYSHCN.<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> In Manitoba, Canada, for example, the provincially administered Children&#8217;s disABILITY Services programme provides respite to parents who are caring for a child under age 18 who have a diagnosis of specific conditions, for example, intellectual disability, developmental delay, autism spectrum disorder or lifelong physical disability. Depending on eligibility, assessed needs and available resources, respite may be provided in or outside the child&#8217;s home by a worker, or in-home by a nurse for complex medical needs. Some funding for certain supplies, equipment or transportation may also be available.<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></p><p>Although respite care offers many benefits, Nuri <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> identify five key themes impacting respite access: availability, accessibility, affordability, acceptability and awareness, with barriers including staff shortages, long wait times, lack of service coordination, social stigma and limited knowledge concerning service eligibility.<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Parents have also reported a lack of information and knowledge regarding available respite and support services,<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> and needing to &#8216;jump through hoops&#8217; for respite service qualification.<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20 21</xref></p><p>Reports of unmet respite needs from the literature, families and service providers have long been seen,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22 23</xref> and past research<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18 22 24</xref> has framed respite access as an undeniable problem. While the networks for change exist,<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> there has been minimal social or government action towards change. Why has lack of adequate access and receipt of respite care not been formally named as an issue&#8212;a human rights violation,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> adopted and championed?<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Perhaps, because respite care and its numerous systemic shortcomings have been deemed a non-issue, one that can be neglected without substantial consequences for policy-makers and the public.</p><p>To this end, previous research primarily with American parents or siblings of CYSHCN highlights recommendations for addressing barriers to respite services including improved communications between service providers and families,<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28 29</xref> enhanced coordination of services,<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28 29</xref> family-focused approaches,<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30 31</xref> family empowerment,<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30 31</xref> increased education about disabilities<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> and support with system navigation.<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></p><p>However, as noted by the Canadian Healthcare Association, there is a need to pursue Canadian research on respite care that will result in improvement in the services themselves.<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> Furthermore, there are few Canadian studies within the past 10 years exploring experiences with respite from the perspective of families (both parents and siblings) of CYSHCN to understand familial challenges with respite, together with their recommendations for addressing these challenges. This paper addresses these gaps, using multiple methods, reporting on the qualitative arts-based findings specific to families residing in Manitoba, Canada.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><p>The findings reported in this paper are part of a mixed-methods study gathering evidence to inform respite care that is responsive and integrative for families of CYSHCN in Manitoba. Not reported in this paper are a quantitative component using administrative data<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> and findings from interviews with respite services administrators and providers.</p><sec id="s2-1"><title>Study design and participant selection</title><p>Qualitative, arts-based methodologies were employed to elucidate the respite care experiences of families of CYSHCN along with proposed recommendations to enhance respite care. These methodologies provided a creative way for study participants to share their stories and illuminate the human dimensions of health and illness.<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33 34</xref></p><p>Manitoba (MB), Canada families (mothers, fathers and siblings) of CYSHCN who were receiving specialised healthcare services were recruited using purposive and snowball sampling from 10 local healthcare centres, family networks and community agencies that provide specialised services/supports for this population, through posters, invitation letters sent to families and via social media until theoretical saturation was achieved.<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35 36</xref> Study personnel then contacted interested families who consented, leaving the choice to families to decide which member(s), for example, mothers, fathers and/or siblings would participate. The study was further explained and scheduled for in-person or virtual interviews.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Data collection</title><p>Multiple data collection methods were used to examine families&#8217; perspectives, providing complementary insights that may otherwise be difficult to access if using a single method.<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37 38</xref> One author (AK) with direction from a second author (RLW) collected the data. Both researchers (female) were trained in qualitative interviewing and arts-based data collection methods. Data collection took place between between November 2019 and April 2022. Shortly after the start of this study, the COVID-19 pandemic emerged resulting in most data collection taking place virtually.</p><p>Family caregiver(s) (eg, mothers, fathers, siblings) completed a demographic form, and then took part in an open-ended interview using various strategies to facilitate discussion<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39 40</xref> to understand their experiences of using respite services and their recommendations for future respite care. Although taking place during the pandemic, families were asked to focus on their overall respite care experiences. An additional question was added to the interview about how the pandemic had impacted their overall respite experiences. Interviews took place either at local coffee shops or virtually, lasted between 90 and 120&#8201;min and were digitally recorded and transcribed verbatim. When multiple caregivers were present in the family, they were interviewed separately to afford privacy and adequate time (see <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental appendix 1</xref>: Interview Guides). Each family member was given an opportunity to draw an ecomap at the beginning of their first open-ended interview, a graphical portrayal of social relationships or networks, key events, places or issues.<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> After the first interview, families were given instructions about the photovoice process<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33 42</xref> previously used in research with children<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> and adults.<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> After completing the photovoice activity, families participated in a digitally recorded family-group interview (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental appendix 1</xref>: Interview Guides&#8212;see Photovoice Interview Guide), capturing interactional data or shared realities<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> and contextualising photovoice stories. Using probes and the SHOWeD<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> interview method, families were guided through each photo by asking them the why, what and how, of their photos in relation to respite care, thus allowing opportunity for participant feedback on their interviews. All participants consented to have their photos or ecomaps used, and families/family members chose which photos to submit. Field notes were recorded following each interview. Identifying information was removed to protect confidentiality.</p><supplementary-material id="SP1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2023-073391.supp1</object-id><label>Supplementary data</label><p>
<inline-supplementary-material xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="SS1" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-073391supp001.pdf" content-type="local-data"/>
</p></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Data analysis</title><p>In keeping with the qualitative paradigm, data analysis occurred concurrently with data collection. Informing the data analysis process was all the data emerging from the interviews and field notes (textual data) and photographs and ecomaps (graphical data). Participant quotes and field note data were entered manually into a Microsoft Word document and organised by themes. The inductive approach of thematic analysis which involves identifying recurrent themes across participants was applied.<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36 46 47</xref> First, the interview transcripts were read and reread to get a sense of the data and overall meaning. This was followed by searching and delineating units of meaning from the textual data. Units of meaning with similar patterns and relationships of meaning were then grouped together to create themes. These themes were then collated and discussed (RLW, CI and AK). Any discrepancies or uncertainty of themes were resolved via discussion among all three authors until consensus was achieved. Attention was given to exploring similarities and differences between participants throughout data analysis. Themes were refined after comparing data from the first set of interviews with the second set of interviews. During the second interviews, preliminary analyses were discussed with participants which helped to uncover and lend support for the identified themes. The photos and ecomaps served as visual representations of the text-based findings and informed the themes emerging from the data. By relating the visual data to the corresponding transcripts, we gained a greater understanding of families&#8217; experiences. All data were reviewed repeatedly for significant statements to fully understand participants&#8217; lived worlds and meanings of their experiences through themes (RLW, CI and AK).<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> To enhance the methodological rigour of the study, measures were applied including prolonged engagement with participants and data, careful line-by-line analysis of the interview transcripts, and detailed memo writing<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39 46</xref> was in place.</p><p>The Family Advisory Committee (FAC), made up of six members representing six different participating families, were presented with findings and reviewed the major themes on an ongoing basis. After meetings, notes were made, and assumptions checked to ensure no researcher bias.</p><p>Participant demographics were calculated using basic descriptive statistics, including means, frequencies and ranges using SAS V.9.4. (RLW and CI)<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Patient and public involvement</title><p>Patients, researchers, clinicians and decision-makers along with our FAC, composed of members of participating families of CYSHCN were part of the research team. The FAC was formed and met regularly to advise and work with the research team members, knowledge users and collaborators throughout the study to ensure findings were translated in a meaningful way.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Findings</title><sec id="s3-1"><title>Participants</title><p>Of those families approached none refused to participate, resulting in 32 families taking part in the study. Of the 32 families, participant representation was as follows: 1 parent only,<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> 2 parents only,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> 1 parent and 1 sibling,<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> 1 parent and 2 siblings,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> 2 parents and 1 sibling.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> There were no siblings who were included without parents also taking part. Six of the families did only the first interview as they could not complete all phases due to time, etc, however their data were used to inform this paper. See <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref> for participant characteristics. Although invitations were sent to families, primarily mothers responded. The pandemic did not seem to affect recruitment and may have made participating simpler as no travel was required. Further, while the intent was to include CYSHCN in the interviews, given less than five participated, their responses are not included to protect confidentiality.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of parent and sibling respondents, CYSHCN, and respite care received</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Characteristics</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Families (N=32)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Parents (N=38)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Siblings (N=13)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="2" rowspan="1">CYSHCN of participating families (N=34)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per cent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per cent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per cent</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per cent</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age at interview (years)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Range</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">31&#8211;63</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">6&#8211;24</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0&#8211;30*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Mean</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">46</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">14</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender identity</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.95</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.46</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.05</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.54</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.82</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Caucasian including Canadian English, Scottish</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.05</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.92</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Various includes black, Metis, Filipino, mixed, Japanese, Jewish, Somali, Saudi Arabian, Middle Eastern, Persian</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.95</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">s</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">s</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Educational level/attainment</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Grades 1&#8211;8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.20</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Grades 9&#8211;12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.89</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.50</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;College or vocational certificate</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.05</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">s</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">s</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;University (bachelor, masters, PhD degree)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.74</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">s</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">s</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Unknown/not disclosed</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.32</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urbanicity</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Urban</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.25</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Rural</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.75</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total # of children in home</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.50</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.25</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;3 or 4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.25</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Make up of home</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Two parent</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.75</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;One parents</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.25</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total family income ($C annual)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8804;$C60&#8201;000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.35</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="char" char="ndash" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;$C60&#8201;001&#8211;$C100&#8201;000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.65</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&gt;$C100&#8201;000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.41</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Prefer not to answer</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.59</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of respite care received by family n=32</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Overnight</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.88</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;In-home</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.75</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Provided by informal respite worker (eg, family, friends)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.75</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Out-of-home</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.25</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Daytime</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.13</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Long term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.75</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.50</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Provided by trained respite worker</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hours of respite care received (per week) (self-reported)n=34 CYSHCN</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;0</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.65</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="ndash" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1&#8211;5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.71</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="ndash" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;6&#8211;12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.06</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="ndash" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;13&#8211;35</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.59</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T1_FN1"><p>*Some CYSHCN of participating families were dependent on their parents requiring constant supervision and parents defined as a child/youth. The child&#8217;s parent reflected on respite experiences when their child was younger and up to current times.</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN2"><p>CYSHCN, children and youth with special healthcare needs.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Among CYSHCN in participating families (n=34), more than half (20; 58.82%) had a primary diagnosis of Developmental/cognitive disorder, while genetic/chromosomal abnormality and neuromuscular or seizure/pPhysical disorder diagnoses categories each represented 20.59% of these children. Additionally, 58.83% had between one and four co-occurring conditions. Participating families reported receiving from 0 up to 35 hours of respite per week, resulting in an average (mean) of 8&#8201;hours of respite care per week over the past 12 months.</p></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Themes</title><sec id="s3-2-1"><title>A: challenges</title><p>Multiple methods (ecomaps, family interviews and photovoice activity) builds on the story of families&#8217; challenges with respite care. Six themes emerged from these methods encompassing families&#8217; challenges with accessing, acquiring and navigating the respite care system, sustaining appropriate care for their CYSHCN, and COVID-19 pandemic-accentuated challenges.</p><sec id="s3-2-1-1"><title>&#8216;You don&#8217;t know what you don&#8217;t know&#8217;</title><p>This theme refers to the lack of available information about respite services resulting in families&#8217; lack of knowledge about respite and service options and how this in turn precluded them from knowing potential questions to ask that might lead to their child receiving respite care.</p><p>For example, many parents expressed not knowing what respite was, what to ask for, how it could benefit their family or where to apply for respite services. <italic toggle="yes">You are going in there</italic> (respite system) <italic toggle="yes">flying blind and you don&#8217;t know what you are entitled to. If you don&#8217;t know, you don&#8217;t know. That is the problem when you don&#8217;t know what is covered by respite</italic> [Father 07]. Other families did not learn about respite services entitlements until their child was older as shared by a mother.</p><disp-quote><p>You need someone that can intervene for you because you don&#8217;t know what you don&#8217;t know and that&#8217;s the biggest problem. We found out years later that we didn&#8217;t have to pay for certain things that we had to get for &#8216;B&#8217;. Just there was no way of knowing this. [Mother 04]</p></disp-quote><p>Further, inconsistencies and <italic toggle="yes">no real rhyme or reason to if people get accepted</italic> [Mother 28] were noted regarding eligibility, while the hours of respite care families received was explained as being <italic toggle="yes">all over the map</italic> [Mother 01]. Those who were strong advocates, comfortable navigating the system were often able to secure services for their CYSHCN, potentially leaving families lacking these skills without adequate respite.</p></sec><sec id="s3-2-1-2"><title>Always waiting</title><p>The theme, always waiting, refers to the long journey of wait times reported by families when attempting to access each stage of the respite system. The excerpt below describes one families&#8217; arduous experience of obtaining a respite-eligible diagnosis and waiting for a case worker.</p><disp-quote><p>To get respite support, what do you have to do? You as a parent have to identify that there are issues, you have to go to the doctor, you have to wait for a referral. Wait lists for [Treatment Centre] are easily a year right now, if not longer, then you have to go through the assessment process, then if you are lucky, you get a diagnosis that allows you to access [government program] and that&#8217;s not every family&#8230;Then even if you are told, yes, you qualify for a (family case) worker, what&#8217;s the wait list? [Mother 28]</p></disp-quote><p>A photovoice submission (see <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>k) visualises the onerous process required for remuneration of self-managed respite. These multiple steps and waiting often resulted in families reaching breaking points and exhaustion, as shared by a parent; <italic toggle="yes">application on application and appointments and OT, like it&#8217;s insane, it&#8217;s like managing, it&#8217;s very, very hard</italic>. [Mother 31].</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Paperwork.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-073391f01.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3-2-1-3"><title>Lost in the maze</title><p>This theme describes families&#8217; difficulties in navigating the respite care system once gaining access to the system. Often families learnt about respite services through various entry points, receiving referrals from for example, schools or clinics. Some parents took system navigation on themselves;</p><disp-quote><p>I try to get involved to understand and navigate the system because I think that&#8217;s how you do it. You learn from other people, you hear things from other people, so they give you the direction and then you start looking for yourself [Father 06].</p></disp-quote><p>Others struggled to navigate, often losing their way traversing through one or more of the various government, agency and self-managed respite service options.</p><p>Navigation of respite services also required constant vigilance to remain abreast of upcoming transitions. For example, families voiced challenges with the comprehensive assessments required for continued respite as their child aged into adulthood, describing this process as demeaning.</p><disp-quote><p>There was an assessment based to see how much care he would receive and how much funding you would receive for that care and the entire process, I was actually at that meeting. You're trying to make it look like he&#8217;s as low as possible, so you can get as much care as possible. Like he&#8217;s not an idiot, he&#8217;s pretty capable, but we have to sell it as if he is, so he gets money. That&#8217;s really messed up. [Sibling 02]</p></disp-quote><p>Families seeking day programmes for their adult special care needs children (&#8805;21 years old), did not always find a suitable option, leaving parents to fulfil multicarer roles.</p><disp-quote><p>It&#8217;s been very hard to work as a mother with a child with special needs. If the services aren&#8217;t there, I&#8217;ve got to fill that need. So, I&#8217;m now her teacher, her healthcare provider, on top of her parent, plus now you might as well say her respite care worker. [Mother 11]</p></disp-quote></sec><sec id="s3-2-1-4"><title>Undervalued caregiving</title><p>This theme describes the difficulty families experienced finding skilled and committed respite workers to provide safe, quality care to their CYSHCN. Low wages, lack of training and respite work not being viewed as a career were cited as the reason for high turnover and scarcity of qualified respite workers. Parents suggested that if respite caregiving were more valued, this role could be considered a career rather than transitional employment.</p><disp-quote><p>Caregiving in general isn't really valued. Maybe now, we're seeing the value of it, now during the pandemic, it really is important, but I find if respite work or caregiving could be seen as, could be valued more and the job be paid higher, it would be less of this kind of interim, this job one does in between while they&#8217;re a student or while they're doing, it could actually be a career. [Mother 25]</p></disp-quote><p>Given the MB respite worker wage ($C11&#8211;$C15/hour) it is challenging for families undertaking self-managed respite to attract, hire or retain respite workers, leading some to &#8216;top up&#8217; wages out of pocket. Yet, family members are only granted remuneration for respite services in special circumstances leading to significant frustration.</p><disp-quote><p>It&#8217;s unfair and it is ridiculous. And for some people, that&#8217;s the only person that they have that&#8217;s available. Like maybe they live remotely, out in the country. And they have a sibling that lives in the home, but they can&#8217;t get anybody else. Well, what are you going to do? Like so, to have our hands tied like that is ridiculous and it&#8217;s not fair&#8230; They (family members) know our kids. It&#8217;s logical to me. And why shouldn&#8217;t you compensate them like you would anybody else. [Mother 30]</p></disp-quote><p>Consequently, various family members including siblings often provide unpaid respite care.</p><disp-quote><p>I would often be left at home to watch her, so I always said I was the unpaid respite &#8230; so I have been like at times like the main carer, the only person at home with her [CYSHCN child] &#8230; And so even though like I always joke like &#8216;oh I&#8217;m like the respite worker, I&#8217;m the babysitter for &#8220;M&#8221;&#8217;, like I mean I&#8217;m there but it&#8217;s not like I&#8217;m getting paid or anything&#8230; [Sibling 04]</p></disp-quote></sec><sec id="s3-2-1-5"><title>Respite as a lifeline</title><p>The respite as a lifeline theme paints a picture of the continuum of impact on families receiving respite care or not.</p><p>Despite challenges, respite care services were identified by numerous families as a lifeline, important to their survival, as shared by a mother; <italic toggle="yes">&#8216;B&#8217;s care is so intense, respite is lifesaving. They say that it shouldn&#8217;t be the most important thing, but it&#8217;s the only thing that&#8217;s keeping my family together</italic> [Mother 13]. Siblings noted the importance of respite, granting time for parent couples and speaking to the need for constant care required by families, <italic toggle="yes">I think they like having a break when</italic> [Child with SHCN] <italic toggle="yes">is out of the house. I am sure they really enjoy it. Especially my mom. She&#8217;s my sister&#8217;s 24/7 respite worker</italic> [Sibling 19]. Respite also gave siblings time with their parents themselves, as described via this ecomap (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2</xref> &#8216;Restbite&#8217; Sibling Ecomap) [Sibling 13].</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Restbite.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-073391f02.jpg"/></fig><p>However, without adequate respite, there was little to no downtime. Feeling as if being in a constant fight added to families&#8217; stress and exhaustion, with few able to use respite to recharge.</p><disp-quote><p>We are in a constant fight, we desperately need help and there&#8217;s never enough, never enough. It is very stressful and not easy&#8230; It&#8217;s exhausting to have to prove to higher ups that you are in need of respite. I have to constantly fight and say, you know, we can't do it. That&#8217;s the worst thing for a parent to say is, I can't do it&#8230;and I think we're just a number which is really, really sad. [Mother 13]</p></disp-quote><p>Alongside caring for their CYSHCN, many families struggled with underemployment, unemployment, financial stress, sleep deprivation and mental health issues. More concerning, inadequate or no respite services and family exhaustion resulted in some feeling forced to make difficult decisions about the care of their CYSHCN, such as voluntary placement with child and family services (CFS).</p><p>For example, the quote below and ecomap (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">figure 3</xref> CFS Mother 02) by one mother tells the story of a family who were attempting to obtain adequate respite support with their child living with multiple complex conditions including severe aggression.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Child and family services.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-073391f03.jpg"/></fig><disp-quote><p>I think when &#8220;R&#8221; was about 12 they increased our respite to six hours a week with two staff being present. Um and then and that was because &#8220;R&#8221; was getting stronger, there was more aggression. But we were finding that we couldn&#8217;t manage with those six hours, we were getting completely worn down and it just wasn&#8217;t enough. So, we did some self-managed respite as well as them um having some respite workers from their agency, And it was quite stressful even then. Um about two years ago &#8220;R&#8221; severely assaulted me &#8230; And uh at that point we knew that we were really in crisis. &#8230;We took him to the, the Child and Adolescent Treatment Centre, they said that due to &#8220;R&#8221;&#8217;s disability they couldn&#8217;t admit him, and we had to take him home and we refused. &#8230; And &#8220;R&#8221; was in care for three weeks and it cost the government $30,000. &#8230; So, during that time, I was, I was able to, to further advocate saying its going to be $600,000 a year for &#8220;R&#8221; to enter care. But our [respite care] plan is at most $13,000 [a month] [Mother 02 Ecomap]</p></disp-quote><p>The ripple effect of an inadequate respite care system and costs to families, government and society was identified. As parents became overwhelmed physically, mentally and emotionally with the all-consuming care of their child, some experienced family breakdown.</p><disp-quote><p>It gets tiring. And then you see a lot of peoples&#8217; family dynamics fall apart due to stress. It&#8217;s very stressful you know. I look back at my marriage and, and I think people saw it before I did, but my partner I don&#8217;t think could, he could [not] cope with this. [Family 11 &#8211; Mother &amp; Sibling]</p></disp-quote><p>Participants further spoke of the current respite care system as, <italic toggle="yes">a system that again is crisis based, it isn&#8217;t proactive</italic> [Mother 02] highlighting the longer-term costs of insufficient respite services to both government and society.</p><disp-quote><p>If we don&#8217;t do that [acknowledge impact on caregiver health and wellbeing] as a society and, and decision-makers don&#8217;t do this, you&#8217;re going to end up paying for it anyhow. Because these people are going to have increased mental uh health issues. Uh they&#8217;re not going to be able to work and do their jobs. They&#8217;re going to have you know mental leaves, they&#8217;re going to be on stress leaves. It, it&#8217;s a ripple effect. [Father 22]</p></disp-quote></sec><sec id="s3-2-1-6"><title>COVID-19 accentuated the challenges</title><p>With the onset of the pandemic, the challenges faced by families were only intensified. The constantly changing guidelines around the pandemic and respite services were difficult for case workers, respite workers and families to interpret, making navigation of respite even more difficult. Furthermore, fear of contracting COVID-19 resulted in some families not requesting respite. Likewise, some respite workers feared entering families&#8217; homes and were not mandated to do so as respite workers were not deemed essential during the pandemic. Families felt more isolated and struggled in caring for their children with the loss of respite services as well as friends and families not being able to visit due to safety reasons.</p><disp-quote><p>Certainly, during these COVID times, it&#8217;s just sort of that we have not had any respite or anything, so the last time we had respite was probably mid-February and here it is now mid-June, so certainly the province saved some money because everything shutdown&#8230;<italic toggle="yes">&#8230;</italic>Basically for all intents and purpose everything stopped because of COVID&#8230;everybody she (daughter) saw before, whether it&#8217;s her workers, therapists that would come occasionally and all the day program staff. So, unfortunately for &#8220;M&#8221; (daughter), she lost. [Father 04]</p></disp-quote></sec></sec><sec id="s3-2-2"><title>B: families&#8217; recommendations for respite system improvement</title><p>Families recommended a multipronged approach to address their experienced challenges with the respite care system. <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> highlights the challenges themes depicting families&#8217; journeys through the respite care system and how their recommendations for improvement and actionable solutsions are linked to the various themes/phases of their journeys.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Families&#8217; recommendations to address ongoing challenges with respite care services</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Challenges identified<break/>main themes</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recommendations</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Actionable solutions for respite funders and service providers</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">You don&#8217;t Know, what you don&#8217;t know</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Develop an accessible resource hub to guide families, outlining available respite care service entitlements</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A reference guide</p></list-item><list-item><p>A database</p></list-item><list-item><p>A website or online App</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Always waiting</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Improve ease of access, navigation and coordination of respite care services</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Decrease wait times</p></list-item><list-item><p>Increase respite hours</p></list-item><list-item><p>Overhaul respite care system&#8212;is currently a crisis-based system, not proactive</p></list-item><list-item><p>Create a one stop shop with a navigator, family advocate</p></list-item><list-item><p>Parents and families are experts</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lost in the maze</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Undervalued caregiving</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Develop and designate respite care as a career</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Provide training and education for respite workers on various disability and behavioural conditions</p></list-item><list-item><p>Increase the pool of trained respite workers</p></list-item><list-item><p>Increase respite worker wages</p></list-item><list-item><p>Provide mentorship for respite workers</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respite as a lifeline</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Using multiple data collection methods, this qualitative arts-based study through the lens of MB families with CYSHCN, underscores the challenges with accessing, navigating and sustaining respite care combined with actionable recommendations for change. Along with interview data, parents&#8217; and siblings&#8217; ecomaps and photovoice submissions allowed for creativity, and visualise their perspectives, building a more complete picture of their experiences.</p><p>As some interviews included members of the same family, intrafamilial dynamics or disagreements potentially could have arisen, however, this was not experienced in our study. Also, when members of the same family were interviewed separately, there may have been differing perspectives, however, comparisons such as these are beyond the scope of this paper.</p><p>Although invitations to participate were sent to families, parental participants in our study were primarily (78.95%) mothers, which may have affected the findings. However, it is relevant to note here that mother-identifying caregivers tend to assume the majority of caregiving for their CYSHCN child,<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49 50</xref> and experiences of families with CYSHCN are predominantly expressed through maternal voices<xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">51 52</xref> leaving fewer paternal caregiver experiences to draw from.<xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></p><p>Having participants also serve on the family advisory board provided expert lived experience for guiding the study. While advisory board members did have some differing views, they were respectful of differing opinions, quite possibly because they had the shared experiences of caring for CYSHCN. Thus, findings did not change based on Family Advisory input and discussions. A positive outcome of these meetings was the opportunity for members to share with each other and feel support from within the group.</p><p>Overall our findings echo evidence from other jurisdictions, noting families&#8217; challenges in accessing respite services,<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> waiting across many system checkpoints,<xref rid="R54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> understanding entitlements and service options coupled with inconsistent receipt of respite care.<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18 22 52</xref> This led parents to become advocates for desirable outcomes, often leaving those without strong advocacy skills unsupported.<xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref> The disconnect between various private, government, and non-profit service providers, and lack of standardisation further convolutes the respite system.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14 56</xref> Additionally, this study highlights the navigational challenges of respite as CYSHCN transition from daycare to school, to young adult (18+) care. Many of the barriers and challenges to respite care identified by families were present prior to the COVID-19 pandemic but were further exacerbated by pandemic restrictions. It is possible that the pandemic affected the number of hours of respite families received, however, interview questions asked about past respite as well during COVID-times. Findings specific to respite experiences during the pandemic warrant a separate article.</p><p>Unique to this study are families&#8217; perspectives that respite care system wait times are primarily due to overloaded caseworkers and respite worker shortages. This may be due to an undervaluing of respite workers, with lack of professional training resulting in higher turnover rates and worker shortages,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> further exacerbating family stress.<xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></p><p>Finally, the family-identified recommendations for a more collaborative, family-inclusive approach to respite services could be empowering, improving well-being for parents.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> For families who received respite services, it was &#8216;life-saving&#8217;, while for others, limited or lack of respite care resulted in depletion of emotional, financial and social reserves representing an uphill battle, which many could not afford.</p><sec id="s4-1"><title>Limitations</title><p>Although families from diverse ethnic backgrounds participated in the study, we did not attain diversity with respect to immigrant and refugee populations, which is warranted, as this population often has delayed access to respite services due to language barriers, and navigation of a foreign system. Thus, we could not make any conclusions on ethnic background. Similar to other studies, fathers&#8217; perspectives are also limited in our study. While our intentions were also to involve children with CYSHCN, most were either were unable to or declined to participate in the study.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Implications for clinicians, policy-makers and future research</title><p>The findings from our study can be used by clinicians, policy-makers and providers in other Canadian jurisdictions and beyond to address barriers to respite care for families. For example, provide more education on the various physical and developmental conditions which require special medical care to inform planning and practice. Clinicians who are in influential roles can advocate on behalf of their patients for adequate respite care that would support familial health and well-being. Streamlining and alignment of respite assessments, needs and services across agencies and jurisdictions is critical to ensure equitable access and receipt of respite care for families and CYSHCN.</p><p>Using findings from the current and previous studies which clearly underline the barriers to respite care and provide recommendations to address these issues, future research in this area should shift to programme evaluation and implementation science, moving evidence-based practices<xref rid="R58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref> of collaborative, family-centred respite care models into routine usage.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Findings from this study reinforce research exposing an inadequate, minimally funded respite care system as an issue. The collective disconnects between families and service providers exacerbated by accessibility and navigational challenges, along with undervalued caregiving, and caregiver stress continue to impact the health and well-being of families and their CYSHCN. This study addresses this issue by presenting families&#8217; recommendations along with innovative, actionable solutions that can aid funders, clinicians and policy-makers in advocating for and implementing a collaborative, responsive, family-centred system of respite care.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="d64e145" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Reviewer comments</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-073391.reviewer_comments.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="d64e146" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Author's
manuscript</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-073391.draft_revisions.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors are grateful to all the participants who shared their experiences with us.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Twitter:</bold> @WoodgateRoberta</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Contributors:</bold> RLW contributed to the conception and design of the study, as well as trained and supervised the hired research assistants who carried out data collection. KK and SK contributed to the conception and design of the study. RLW and AK conducted the interviews. RLW, CI and AK performed the data analysis, and drafted, reviewed and approved the manuscript. All authors agreed to be accountable for all aspects of the work. RLW is responsible for the overall content as the guarantor.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This work was supported by a Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR) Grant (Reference # PJT-162427) received by RLW, RLW is supported by a Tier 1 CanadianResearch Chair (CRC) in Child and Family Engagement in Health Research and Healthcare (CIHR&#8212;Canadian Research Chair&#8212;950-231845).</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> None declared.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient and public involvement:</bold> Patients and/or the public were involved in the design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research. Refer to the Methods section for further details.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Supplemental material:</bold> This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>No data are available. Data are not available as we did not receive permission from the participants to make data publicly available.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement"><title>Ethics statements</title><sec><title>Patient consent for publication</title><p content-type="ethics-consent-to-publish">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethics approval</title><p content-type="ethics-approval">This study involves human participants and was approved by University of Manitoba Health Research Ethics Board #HS22685. Participants gave informed consent to participate in the study before taking part.</p></sec></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Canadian Institute for Health Information</collab></person-group>. <source>Children and youth with medical complexity in Canada</source>. <publisher-loc>Ottawa, ON</publisher-loc>, <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Woodgate</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ripat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>How families of children with complex care needs participate in everyday life</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>1912</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2012.07.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22901669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Geuze</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goossensen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Exploring the experiences of Dutch parents caring for children with profound intellectual and multiple disabilities: a thematic analysis of their blogs</article-title>. <source>Glob Qual Nurs Res</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<elocation-id>23333936211028170</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/23333936211028170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34263011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8252404</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Edelstein</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schippke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sheffe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Children with medical complexity: a scoping review of interventions to support caregiver stress</article-title>. <source>Child Care Health Dev</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>323</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cch.12430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27896838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>DZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Children with medical complexity: an emerging population for clinical and research initiatives</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>127</volume>:<fpage>529</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2010-0910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21339266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3387912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Responding to the rising number of children living with complex chronic conditions</article-title>. <source>CMAJ</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>186</volume>:<fpage>1199</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>200</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1503/cmaj.141036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25316900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4216247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Spalding</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kenny</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Neither seen nor heard: children and Homecare policy in Canada</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>1624</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2006.12.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17240503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stille</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Building systems that work for children with complex health care needs: editor's note</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>141</volume>(<issue>Suppl 3</issue>):<fpage>S192</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2017-1284C</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29496969</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dewan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Birnie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Drury</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Experiences of medical traumatic stress in parents of children with medical complexity</article-title>. <source>Child Care Health Dev</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>292</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>303</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cch.13042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35947493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10087969</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hil&#225;rio</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Augusto</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Sibling caring roles and responsibilities when a child suffers from a chronic illness</article-title>. <source>Sociology Compass</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>16</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/soc4.12957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marquis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McGrail</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Using administrative data to examine variables affecting the mental health of siblings of children who have a developmental disability</article-title>. <source>Res Dev Disabil</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>103516</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ridd.2019.103516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31756693</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marquis</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McGrail</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A population-level study of the mental health of siblings of children who have a developmental disability</article-title>. <source>SSM Popul Health</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>100441</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ssmph.2019.100441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31334325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6617296</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmadi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sabery</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adib-Hajbaghery</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Burnout in the primary caregivers of children with chronic conditions and its related factors</article-title>. <source>JCCNC</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>48</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32598/JCCNC.7.2.360.1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Begley</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Respite care for children with complex care needs: a literature review</article-title>. <source>Compr Child Adolesc Nurs</source><year>2021</year>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/24694193.2021.1885523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33620262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Canadian Healthcare Association</collab></person-group>. <source>Respite Care in Canada</source>. <publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc>, <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Christi</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heung</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of respite care services availability on stress, anxiety and depression in military parents who have a child on the autism spectrum</article-title>. <source>J Autism Dev Disord</source><year>2022</year>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-022-05704-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9419919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36030352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Manitoba Department of Families</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Children&#8217;s disABILITY services (CDS)</article-title>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.gov.mb.ca/fs/cds/index.html">https://www.gov.mb.ca/fs/cds/index.html</uri> [Accessed <comment>28 Mar 2022</comment>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nuri</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aldersey</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ghahari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Experience of families in accessing government-led support for children with disabilities in Bangladesh</article-title>. <source>Disabil Rehabil</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>1354</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09638288.2020.1804000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32809849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peay</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Meiser</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kinnett</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Psychosocial needs and facilitators of mothers caring for children with Duchenne/Becker muscular dystrophy</article-title>. <source>J Genet Couns</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>197</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>203</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10897-017-0141-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28803420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Doig</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McLennan</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Urichuk</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>'Jumping through hoops': parents' experiences with seeking respite care for children with special needs</article-title>. <source>Child Care Health Dev</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>234</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2214.2008.00922.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19228157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Connaire</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Parental decision&#8208;making on utilisation of out&#8208;of&#8208;home respite in children&#8217;s palliative care: findings of qualitative case study research &#8208;A proposed new model</article-title>. <source>Child Care Health Dev</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cch.12300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26547275</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Parents' experiences of accessing respite care for children with autism spectrum disorder (ASD) at the acute and primary care interface: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>BMC Pediatr</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>244</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12887-020-02045-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32443974</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7243332</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Engwall</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hultman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Constructions of childhood: the assessment of respite care for children with disabilities in Sweden</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Social Work</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>617</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13691457.2020.1763260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Home health care for children with medical complexity: workforce gaps, policy, and future directions</article-title>. <source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>987</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2018.05531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31158008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Reversing gun sights: transnational civil society targets land mines</article-title>. <source>Int Org</source><year>1998</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>613</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/002081898550671</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Keck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sikkink</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Activists Beyond Borders: Advocacy Networks in International Politics</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>, <year>1998</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bob</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Rights on the rise: International mobilization for new human rights</article-title>. <comment>American PoliticalScience Association Annual Conference</comment>. <publisher-name>Washington, DC</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aruda</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Newinsky</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Unmet needs of children with special health care needs in a specialized day school setting</article-title>. <source>J Sch Nurs</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>209</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1059840510391670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21123847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Woodgate</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ripat</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Siblings of children with complex care needs: their perspectives and experiences of participating in everyday life</article-title>. <source>Child Care Health Dev</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>504</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cch.12345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27198644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The power to choose: supports for families caring for individuals with developmental disabilities</article-title>. <source>Health Soc Work</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>68</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hsw/25.1.59</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10689604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Neely-Barnes</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dia</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Families of children with disabilities: a review of literature and recommendations for interventions</article-title>. <source>JEIBI</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>107</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/h0100425</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Woodgate</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Isaak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hinds</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Receipt and non-receipt of respite services by families with a child or youth with special health care needs: a population-based approach</article-title>. <source>BMC Pediatr</source><year>2023</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Woodgate</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zurba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tennent</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Worth a thousand words? Advantages, challenges and opportunities in working with photovoice as a qualitative research method with youth and their families</article-title>. <source>Forum Qual Soc Res</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17169/fqs-18.1.2659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Woodgate</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zurba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tennent</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A day in the life of a young person with anxiety: arts-based boundary objects used to communicate the results of health research</article-title>. <source>Forum Qual Soc Res</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>18</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17169/fqs-18.3.2886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boddy</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Sample size for qualitative research</article-title>. <source>QMR</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>426</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/QMR-06-2016-0053</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Patton</surname><given-names>MQ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Qualitative research &amp; evaluation methods: integrating theory and practice</source>. <edition>4th</edition><comment>edn</comment>. <publisher-loc>LosAngeles, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>, <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Darbyshire</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>MacDougall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schiller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Multiple methods in qualitative research with children: more insight or just more</article-title>. <source>Qual Res</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>417</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1468794105056921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hemming</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Mixing qualitative research methods in children&#8217;s geographies</article-title>. <source>Area</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>152</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1475-4762.2008.00798.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lincoln</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guba</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pilotta</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Naturalistic inquiry</article-title>. <source>Int J Intercult Relat</source><year>1985</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>438</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0147-1767(85)90062-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McInnes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bonney</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>An exemplar of naturalistic inquiry in general practice research</article-title>. <source>Nurse Res</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7748/nr.2017.e1509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28102791</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Street</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Ecomapping: an innovative research tool for nurses</article-title>. <source>J Adv Nurs</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>545</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2648.2005.03434.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15882371</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jurkowski</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Photovoice as participatory action research tool for engaging people with intellectual disabilities in research and program development</article-title>. <source>Intellect Dev Disabil</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1352/0047-6765(2008)46[1:PAPART]2.0.CO;2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18271609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Depner</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tenzek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <part-title>Social media intervention for primary Caregivers of sick children</part-title>. In: <source>40th Annual Meeting of the Association of Death Education and Counseling</source>. <publisher-loc>Pittsburgh, PA</publisher-loc>, <year>2018</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>MacLean</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Reflections on researching with children using "family group interviews" as part of a qualitative longitudinal study</article-title>. <source>IJCYFS</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>4.1</issue>):<fpage>649</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18357/ijcyfs.macleana.5412014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dahan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moll</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <source>Photovoice Hamilton 2007: Manual and resource kit</source>. <publisher-loc>Ontario, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Association of County and City Health Officials</publisher-name>, <year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barbour</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Introducing qualitative research: A student guide to the craft of doing qualitative research</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Field</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Qualitative research methods for health professionals</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>, <year>1995</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>Sas&#174; 9.4</article-title>. <comment>Computer software</comment>. <publisher-loc>Cary, North Carolina</publisher-loc><publisher-name>SAS Institute Inc</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.sas.com/en_ca/software/sas9.html">https://www.sas.com/en_ca/software/sas9.html</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marcon</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Family dynamics and social network of families of children with special needs for complex/continuous cares</article-title>. <source>Rev Gaucha Enferm</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<elocation-id>S1983-14472020000100409</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1983-1447.2020.20190178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32491146</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boling</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The health of chronically Ill children: lessons learned from assessing family caregive quality of life</article-title>. <source>Fam Community Health</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>176</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>83</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00003727-200504000-00009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15778631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Not a nurse but more than a mother: the practics of mothering children with complex health care needs</article-title>. <source>Child Geogr</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>158</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14733285.2020.1755420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khanlou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sheehan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>It is an issue of not knowing where to go": service providers' perspectives on challenges in accessing social support and services by immigrant mothers of children with disabilities</article-title>. <source>J Immigr Minor Health</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1840</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10903-014-0122-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25376126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4628614</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pechlivanoglou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Health outcomes of parents of children with chronic illness: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>218</volume>:<fpage>166</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>77</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpeds.2019.10.068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31916997</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Identifying benefits and barriers to respite for carers of children with complex health needs: a qualitative study</article-title>. <source>Contemp Nurse</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>98</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>108</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5172/conu.2014.48.1.98</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25410200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>An Exploration of Parents&#8217; Experience of Accessing Respite Care for their Child with Autism Spectrum Disorder</source>. <publisher-name>University of Limerick</publisher-name>, <year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Grzyb</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morga&#322;a</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>, <collab>Silesian University of Technology</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Activities of institutions suppporting the family of a child with disabilities: selected areas of forecasting and standardizaion</article-title>. <source>KiE</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>132</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>79</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15804/kie.2021.02.05</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Caruk</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Manitobans who manage own home care squeezed by rising expenses, worker shortages</article-title>. <publisher-name>CBC News</publisher-name>; <year>2022</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Damschroder</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hagedorn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>An introduction to implementation science for the non-specialist</article-title>. <source>BMC Psychol</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40359-015-0089-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26376626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4573926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>