<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Pain Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Pain Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1405</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jpainres</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jpr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Pain Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1178-7090</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10800282</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10800282.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10800282</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10800282</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38260001</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/JPR.S439682</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">439682</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Engagement in Integrative and Nonpharmacologic Pain Management Modalities Among Adults with Chronic Pain: Analysis of the 2019 National Health Interview Survey</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Rodgers-Melnick et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Rodgers-Melnick et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0886-253X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodgers-Melnick</surname><given-names initials="SN">Samuel N</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trager</surname><given-names initials="RJ">Robert J</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Love</surname><given-names initials="TE">Thomas E</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dusek</surname><given-names initials="JA">Jeffery A</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Connor Whole Health, University Hospitals of Cleveland</institution>, <addr-line>Cleveland</addr-line>, <addr-line>OH</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Population and Quantitative Health Sciences, Case Western Reserve University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Cleveland</addr-line>, <addr-line>OH</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Medicine, Case Western Reserve University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Cleveland</addr-line>, <addr-line>OH</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Population Health and Equity Research Institute, The MetroHealth System</institution>, <addr-line>Cleveland</addr-line>, <addr-line>OH</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Family Medicine and Community Health, Case Western Reserve University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Cleveland</addr-line>, <addr-line>OH</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Samuel N Rodgers-Melnick, <institution>University Hospitals Connor Whole Health</institution>, <addr-line>11100 Euclid Avenue, Wearn 548A</addr-line>, <addr-line>Cleveland</addr-line>, <addr-line>OH</addr-line>, <addr-line>44106</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>, <phone>Tel +1 216 844 7727</phone>, <fax>Fax +1 216 201 6220</fax>, Email Samuel.RodgersMelnick@UHhospitals.org</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">452755</issue-id><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>16</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>22</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-01-30 21:25:23.013"><day>30</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2024 Rodgers-Melnick et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Rodgers-Melnick et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution &#8211; Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jpr-17-253.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Objective</title><p>To examine variables associated with engagement in (1) integrative health and medicine (IHM) and (2) nonpharmacologic modalities rather than opioids among United States adults with chronic pain.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Using the 2019 National Health Interview Survey, we examined sociodemographic, pain, and mental health predictors of (1) the sum of IHM modalities (ie, chiropractic care, yoga/Tai Chi, massage, or meditation/guided imagery) used to manage pain and (2) exclusive engagement in nonpharmacologic pain management modalities (ie, IHM, a chronic pain self-management program, support groups, or physical, rehabilitative, occupational, or talk therapy) or opioids in the past 3 months.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Metropolitan residency, higher family income, higher education levels, increased number of pain locations, and increased frequency of pain limiting life/work activities were associated with increased odds of IHM engagement. Older age, male sex, non-Hispanic Black/African American race/ethnicity, and daily opioid use were associated with decreased odds of IHM engagement. Older age, male sex, and increased depressive symptoms were associated with decreases in the count of IHM modalities used to manage pain. Metropolitan residency, higher family income, and higher education levels were associated with increased odds of exclusive nonpharmacologic modality engagement. Older age and increasing frequency of pain limiting life/work activities were associated with decreased odds of exclusive nonpharmacologic modality engagement.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>We identified several contrasts between factors prevalent among individuals with chronic pain and factors associated with engagement in nonpharmacologic and IHM modalities. These results support efforts to address barriers to accessing these modalities among subpopulations of adults with chronic pain (eg, older adults, individuals identifying as Black/African American, rural residents, and those with lower levels of education and income).</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Plain Language Summary</title><p>This study examined factors influencing the use of integrative health and non-drug treatments for chronic pain in the United States. Results revealed that metropolitan residence, higher income, and education were associated with increased use of these treatments, while older age, male sex, daily opioid use, and non-Hispanic Black/African American ethnicity were associated with decreased use. The findings emphasize the importance of addressing barriers to these forms of care, especially among older adults, Black/African American individuals, and those with higher depressive symptoms and lower education and income levels, who are more likely to have chronic pain.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>integrative medicine</kwd><kwd>chronic pain</kwd><kwd>nonpharmacologic</kwd><kwd>opioids</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Work on this manuscript by the first and fourth authors was provided by NCCIH</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>The funding organization had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>Work on this manuscript by the first and fourth authors was provided by NCCIH Grant No. R01AT010598. The funding organization had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="2"/><ref-count count="41"/><page-count count="12"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>According to the 2019 and 2020 National Health Interview Surveys (NHIS), 20.8% of adults in the United States (US) report chronic pain (ie, pain on most days or every day during the prior three months).<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Despite substantial harms<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> and lack of effectiveness,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> opioid use remains prevalent among US adults with chronic pain with 22.1% reporting opioid use in the past three months (2019 NHIS).<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> However, according to the Medical Expenditure Panel Survey, rates of opioid use have decreased from 2011 to 2019, while rates of using nonpharmacologic modalities have increased.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Nonpharmacologic modalities include a range of interventions from physical and occupational therapy to self-management programs and integrative health and medicine (IHM) modalities such as chiropractic care, yoga, Tai-Chi, acupuncture, meditation, and music therapy.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></p><p>A broader understanding of which factors predict engagement in IHM and nonpharmacologic modalities is necessary to improve implementation and identify populations with barriers to accessing these modalities.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> For example, lower income is associated with reduced engagement in nonpharmacologic and IHM modalities.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> This may be explained by inconsistent Medicare or Medicaid coverage, which presents access challenges for populations with limited discretionary income.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10&#8211;12</xref> IHM coverage remains inconsistent across health insurance carriers within the US<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10&#8211;12</xref> and even among nations with different healthcare systems (eg, universal coverage).<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></p><p>A few studies have examined factors potentially associated with use of these modalities among individuals with chronic pain. One recent analysis of the Medical Expenditure Panel Survey (2011&#8211;2019) found that female sex and higher levels of education and family income were associated with increased odds of visiting nonpharmacologic providers (eg, acupuncturists and physical therapists) rather than using opioids.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Older age, non-White race, Hispanic ethnicity, and having higher levels of pain interference and comorbidities were associated with lower odds of visiting nonpharmacologic providers exclusively.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Other studies have found that younger age, female sex, non-Hispanic (NH) White race/ethnicity, and higher levels of education, income, and pain limitations are associated with increased odds of IHM use among subjects with chronic pain,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> low back or neck pain,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> and arthritis.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></p><p>However, these prior studies are limited in that they did not examine (1) predictors of engagement in IHM (including office visits and personal use) specifically for chronic pain or (2) covariates including proximity to metropolitan areas, mental health measures (eg, Patient Health Questionnaire &#8211; 8 [PHQ-8]), opioid use, or number of pain locations. These covariates are important to consider as proximity to metropolitan areas may influence care access (eg, public transportation) or availability of IHM services,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> and depression and opioid dependence are positively associated with chronic pain.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Given the limited understanding of variables that influence IHM and nonpharmacologic care utilization, it is important to consider the influence of patient-level physical and mental comorbidities, opioid use, and geographic setting in addition to socio-demographics. To address these gaps, the present study uses the 2019 NHIS to examine which sociodemographic, pain, and mental health variables were associated with engagement in (1) the number of IHM modalities used for pain and (2) exclusively nonpharmacologic modalities rather than opioid utilization among US adults with chronic pain.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s0002-s2001"><title>Data Source</title><p>Data from the 2019 NHIS public-use data file were used.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> The NHIS is conducted to monitor illness and disability trends and track progress toward achieving national health objectives. US households are selected using a multistage area probability sample design with clustering and stratification to ensure the final sample is representative of the US population when sampling weights are used.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>All aspects of data collected for the 2019 NHIS were approved by the National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS) Research Ethics Review Board.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> This study was conducted using an anonymous public access dataset, and confidentiality was maintained at all times. Thus, it was not necessary to obtain the approval of an Institutional Review Board.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003"><title>Study Population</title><p>Of the 31,997 NHIS adult participants (&#8805;18 years), 7114 had chronic pain, defined by responding &#8220;most days&#8221; or &#8220;every day&#8221; to the question, &#8220;In the past 3 months, how often did you have pain?&#8221;<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> without missing data on the study outcomes.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004"><title>Data Management</title><p>Statistical analyses were performed in R Version 4.3.1 and RStudio Version 2023.09.1+494. Following data ingestion, recoding, and filtering, covariates were examined for missingness, with all missing data assumed to be missing at random. Of 7114 subjects, only 203 (2.9%) had missing values, with the maximum percentage of missingness within any variable being 1.5% of PHQ-8 total score values. Single imputation procedures were performed using robust linear regression, decision tree, and predictive mean matching from the &#8220;simputation&#8221; package.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2005"><title>Model 1: Engagement in IHM</title><p>For this model, the outcome was defined as the sum (ie, 0&#8211;4 modalities) of the number of questions in which subjects responded &#8220;yes&#8221; to having engaged in (1) chiropractic care, (2) yoga or Tai Chi, (3) massage, or (4) meditation, guided imagery, or other relaxation techniques to manage pain in the past 3 months. Covariates were included based on their use in prior literature examining predictors of IHM use<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7&#8211;9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> and clinical relevance to individuals with chronic pain. Socio-demographic variables included: (1) age, (2) sex (male or female), (3) race/ethnicity (NH White Only, Hispanic, NH Black/African American only, or other single and multiple races), (4) education (less than high school; high school graduate/general equivalency diploma [GED]; some college, no degree; associate&#8217;s or bachelor&#8217;s degree; or master&#8217;s, doctoral or professional degree), (5) family income, and (6) proximity to metropolitan area (nonmetropolitan, medium and small metropolitan, large fringe metropolitan, or large central metropolitan). Pain-related variables included the number of locations in which the subject reported being bothered at least &#8220;a little&#8221; by pain in the past three months (0&#8211;6 scale), and the frequency with which the subject reported pain limiting their life or work activities and using opioids in the past three months (ie, never, some days, most days, or every day). Total PHQ-8 score was included as a covariate for mental health (ie, depressive symptoms).</p><p>Groups were compared using Chi-square tests with Rao &amp; Scott&#8217;s second-order correction and Wilcoxon rank-sum tests for complex survey samples. Weighted bivariate comparisons between the full sample of subjects engaging in zero and at least one IHM modality were conducted using the &#8220;tbl_svysummary&#8221; function from the gtsummary package.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></p><p>Prior to multivariable analysis, the sample was split into training and testing samples, each containing 50% of the full sample to facilitate validation in the testing sample. Following a comparison of six modeling strategies using the training data, a weighted hurdle Poisson regression model was chosen based on an examination of rootograms, R<sup>2</sup>, root mean squared error (RMSE), and Akaike information criterion. A hurdle model is a two-part model that specifies one process for zero counts and another process for positive counts. The model assumes that positive counts occur once a threshold (ie, hurdle) is crossed (ie, engaging in &#8805;1 IHM modality).<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> The model was fit using the &#8220;hurdle&#8221; function from the pscl package.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Tables and plots were used to summarize adjusted odds ratios (aOR) for engaging in at least one IHM modality, relative changes in the count of IHM modalities assuming engagement in &#8805;1 IHM modality, and 95% confidence intervals (CI) associated with each covariate. The model was then applied to the testing data to generate tables and plots comparing observed and predicted values, R<sup>2</sup>, and RMSE within each sample.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2006"><title>Model 2: Nonpharmacologic Modalities Only Vs Opioids Only</title><p>For this model, the outcome was defined as engagement in nonpharmacologic modalities only (ie, engaging in IHM, a chronic pain self-management program, support groups, or physical, rehabilitative, occupational, or talk therapy while never using opioids) rather than opioids only (ie, using opioids on at least some days while not using any nonpharmacologic modalities). Data were filtered to include the 3300 subjects engaging in either nonpharmacologic only or opioids only. Covariates for Model 2 included all those defined previously minus frequency of opioid use. Following a bivariate comparison using the same methods described in Model 1, a weighted logistic model was fit using the &#8220;lrm&#8221; function from the rms package.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Bootstrap validation was then applied to the model using the &#8220;validate&#8221; function from the rms package<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> to obtain a validated c-statistic.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0003-s2001"><title>Model 1: Engagement in IHM</title><p><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> summarizes the socio-demographic, pain, and mental health variables among all adults with chronic pain providing complete outcome data (weighted total <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>=49,695,212). Substantial between-group differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001) were observed, with subjects engaging in IHM being younger (51.8 vs 57.3 years) and having higher family income ($71,700 vs $58,400), higher PHQ-8 scores (5.7 vs 5.0), and more pain locations (3.4 vs 3.0) than subjects not engaging in IHM. Compared to those not engaging in IHM, subjects that engaged in &#8805;1 IHM modality reported higher rates of identifying as female (60.3% vs 52.0%), having levels of education beyond high school, and living in large central metropolitan areas (27.2% vs 22.9%). Subjects engaging in &#8805;1 IHM modality reported lower rates of identifying as NH Black/African American (9.0% vs 12.1%), having less than a high school education (8.8% vs 19.2%), and having pain that never limited their life or work activities (22.9% vs 31.1%).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Socio-Demographic, Pain, and Mental Health Characteristics by IHM Engagement</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weighted Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">All with Chronic Pain</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IHM</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No IHM</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total, n</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49,695,212</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,610,400</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32,084,812</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age in years, mean</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.4 (54.9&#8211;55.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.8 (51.0&#8211;52.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.3 (56.7&#8211;57.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sex, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.9 (53.5&#8211;56.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.3 (57.9&#8211;62.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.0 (50.2&#8211;53.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.1 (43.7&#8211;46.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.7 (37.4&#8211;42.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.0 (46.3&#8211;49.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Race/Ethnicity, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NH White only</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.2 (71.9&#8211;74.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.8 (72.7&#8211;76.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.3 (70.6&#8211;73.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5 (9.59&#8211;11.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1 (8.79&#8211;11.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7 (9.52&#8211;12.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NH Black/African American only</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0 (10.1&#8211;11.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0 (7.73&#8211;10.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1 (11.0&#8211;13.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other single and multiple races</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3 (4.66&#8211;6.03)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (5.01&#8211;7.33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9 (4.11&#8211;5.81)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Education, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Less than high school</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5 (14.4&#8211;16.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8 (7.45&#8211;10.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.2 (17.7&#8211;20.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High school graduate/GED</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.4 (29.1&#8211;31.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.2 (23.1&#8211;27.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.2 (31.6&#8211;34.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some college, no degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1 (18.0&#8211;20.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3 (19.4&#8211;23.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8 (16.5&#8211;19.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Associate&#8217;s or bachelor&#8217;s degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2 (27.0&#8211;29.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.3 (32.2&#8211;36.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.8 (23.4&#8211;26.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Master&#8217;s, doctoral, or professional degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 (6.31&#8211;7.53)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3 (9.11&#8211;11.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0 (4.42&#8211;5.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Family income in $1000s, mean</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.1 (61.6&#8211;64.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.7 (69.0&#8211;74.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.4 (56.7&#8211;60.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Proximity to metro area, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nonmetropolitan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9 (18.8&#8211;21.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1 (14.5&#8211;17.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0 (20.6&#8211;23.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medium and small metro</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9 (32.6&#8211;35.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.1 (30.9&#8211;35.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.4 (32.8&#8211;36.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large fringe metro</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.7 (20.5&#8211;22.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.6 (21.6&#8211;25.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.6 (19.2&#8211;22.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large central metro</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.4 (23.2&#8211;25.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.2 (25.1&#8211;29.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9 (21.4&#8211;24.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Number of pain locations, mean</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1 (3.1&#8211;3.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 (3.3&#8211;3.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0 (2.9&#8211;3.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Pain limiting life/work, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2 (27.0&#8211;29.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9 (21.1&#8211;24.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.1 (29.5&#8211;32.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.6 (34.2&#8211;36.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.6 (36.2&#8211;40.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9 (32.2&#8211;35.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Most days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4 (14.4&#8211;16.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1 (15.2&#8211;19.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5 (13.3&#8211;15.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Every day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8 (19.7&#8211;22.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.5 (19.6&#8211;23.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.5 (19.1&#8211;21.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Opioid use in past 3 months, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.8 (83.7&#8211;85.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.5 (83.7&#8211;87.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.4 (83.1&#8211;85.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 (4.12&#8211;5.38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1 (3.97&#8211;6.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5 (3.86&#8211;5.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Most days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8 (1.47&#8211;2.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (1.63&#8211;2.91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (1.20&#8211;2.09)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Every day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7 (7.91&#8211;9.53)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2 (6.12&#8211;8.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5 (8.47&#8211;10.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PHQ-8 total, mean</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3 (5.1&#8211;5.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7 (5.4&#8211;6.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0 (4.8&#8211;5.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>a</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Note</bold>: Values in parentheses represent 95% confidence intervals. <sup>a</sup>Wilcoxon rank-sum test for complex survey samples. <sup>b</sup>Chi-squared test with Rao &amp; Scott&#8217;s second-order correction.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: CI, confidence interval; GED, general equivalency diploma; IHM, integrative health and medicine; metro, metropolitan; NH, Non-Hispanic; PHQ-8, Patient Health Questionnaire-8.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> and <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=439682.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental Table 1</ext-link></underline> summarize the aOR and 95% CI of each covariate on engagement in &#8805;1 IHM modality. Among subjects with chronic pain, the following were associated with increased odds (aOR, 95% CI) of engagement in IHM after adjusting for all other covariates: (1) higher family income (1.037, 1.021&#8211;1.053), (2) higher levels of education as compared to less than high school (ie, high school/GED [1.516, 1.163&#8211;1.975], some college, no degree [2.193, 1.661&#8211;2.896], associate&#8217;s or bachelor&#8217;s degree [2.868, 2.197&#8211;3.744], masters, doctoral, or professional degree [4.043, 2.815&#8211;5.806]), (3) living in large fringe (1.301, 1.027&#8211;1.648) or central (1.590, 1.261&#8211;2.004) metropolitan areas as compared to non-metropolitan areas, (4) increasing number of pain locations (1.198, 1.130&#8211;1.271), and (5) pain limiting life or work activities on some days (1.388, 1.147&#8211;1.680), most days (1.508, 1.186&#8211;1.916), or every day (1.604, 1.268&#8211;2.029) as compared to never. Alternatively, the following were associated with decreased odds of engagement in IHM: (1) older age (0.858, 0.820&#8211;0.899), (2) identifying as male as compared to female (0.804, 0.692&#8211;0.934), (3) identifying as NH Black/African American (0.683, 0.531&#8211;0.879) or other single and multiple races (0.702, 0.503&#8211;0.980) as compared to NH White, and (4) using opioids to manage pain every day as compared to never (0.708, 0.533&#8211;0.942).
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Adjusted Odds Ratios of Engaging in &#8805;1 IHM Modality for Pain.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JPR-17-253-g0001.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Notes:</bold> Red dots represent point estimates for adjusted odds ratios, and error bars represent 95% confidence intervals. Education covariates are placed on a separate axis given their size to not obscure the other covariates.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: aOR, adjusted odds ratio; Assoc, associate&#8217;s; Bach, bachelor&#8217;s; fam, family; GED, general equivalency diploma; HS, high school; L, large; M, medium; metro, metropolitan; NH, Non-Hispanic; PHQ-8, Patient Health Questionnaire-8; S, small; v., versus; yrs, years.</attrib></fig></p><p><underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=439682.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental Table 2</ext-link></underline> and <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> summarize the changes in the count of IHM modalities engaged in for pain assuming engagement in at least one IHM modality. Having higher levels of education beyond high school (ie, some college, no degree [1.894, 1.275&#8211;2.814], associate&#8217;s or bachelor&#8217;s degree [1.772, 1.199&#8211;2.619], master&#8217;s, doctoral, or professional degree [1.913, 1.236&#8211;2.959]) and more pain locations (1.102, 1.041&#8211;1.167) were associated with increases in the count of IHM modalities used to manage pain. Older age (0.866, 0.825&#8211;0.910), male sex (0.775, 0.663&#8211;0.907), and an increase of 5 units on the PHQ-8 (0.901, 0.834&#8211;0.973) were associated with decreases in the count of IHM modalities used to manage pain. <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=439682.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental Figure 1</ext-link></underline> provides a comparison between observed and predicted values to summarize the weighted hurdle Poisson model&#8217;s performance within the training (R<sup>2</sup>=0.1182, RMSE=0.8069) and testing (R<sup>2</sup>=0.0001, RMSE=0.9067) samples.
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Relative Change in Count of IHM Modalities Used for Pain.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JPR-17-253-g0002.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Notes:</bold> Red dots represent point estimates for relative change in count, and error bars represent 95% confidence intervals. Education covariates are placed on a separate axis given their size to not obscure the other covariates.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: aOR, adjusted odds ratio; Assoc, associate&#8217;s; Bach, bachelor&#8217;s; fam, family; GED, general equivalency diploma; HS, high school; L, large; M, medium; metro, metropolitan; NH, Non-Hispanic; PHQ-8, Patient Health Questionnaire-8; S, small; v., versus; yrs, years.</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002"><title>Model 2: Nonpharmacologic Only Vs Opioids Only</title><p><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> summarizes the socio-demographic, pain, and mental health variables among adults with chronic pain engaging in nonpharmacologic modalities only or opioids only (weighted total <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>=22,707,275). Substantial between-group differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001) were observed, with subjects engaging in nonpharmacologic modalities exclusively being younger (53.0 vs 59.2 years) and having higher family income ($72,800 vs $45,600) than subjects using opioids. Compared to those using opioids, subjects using nonpharmacologic modalities exclusively reported higher rates of having levels of education beyond high school, living in large fringe metropolitan areas (23.3% vs 15.7%), and pain never limiting their life or work activities (24.2% vs 10.9%). Compared to those using opioids only, having less than a high school education (9.6% vs 25.0%), living in nonmetropolitan areas (16.5% vs 25.9%), and having pain limit life or work activities every day (19.6% vs 36.0%) were less prevalent among subjects using nonpharmacologic modalities exclusively. Additionally, subjects engaging in nonpharmacologic modalities exclusively reported lower scores on the PHQ-8 compared to subjects using opioids (5.4 vs 6.5). No large between-group differences were observed in sex (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.797), race/ethnicity (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.221), or number of pain locations (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.086).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Socio-Demographic, Pain, and Mental Health Characteristics by Nonpharmacologic Modality Engagement</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weighted Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Combined Groups</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nonpharm Only</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Opioids Only</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total, n</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,707,275</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,099,216</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,608,059</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age in years, mean</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.0 (53.2&#8211;54.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.0 (52.2&#8211;53.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.2 (57.6&#8211;60.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sex, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.797<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.2 (57.1&#8211;61.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.4 (57.1&#8211;61.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.6 (53.0&#8211;63.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.8 (38.7&#8211;42.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.6 (38.4&#8211;42.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.4 (36.1&#8211;47.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Race/Ethnicity, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.221<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NH White only</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.3 (72.4&#8211;76.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.6 (72.6&#8211;76.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.6 (67.2&#8211;77.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1 (8.91&#8211;11.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0 (8.73&#8211;11.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7 (7.59&#8211;14.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NH Black/African American only</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8 (8.60&#8211;11.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2 (7.96&#8211;10.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8 (9.77&#8211;16.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other single and multiple races</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 (4.82&#8211;6.92)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (5.11&#8211;7.31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 (1.84&#8211;8.57)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Education, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Less than high school</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1 (10.7&#8211;13.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6 (8.25&#8211;11.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0 (20.3&#8211;30.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High school graduate/GED</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.7 (24.8&#8211;28.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.4 (23.5&#8211;27.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.4 (28.4&#8211;38.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some college, no degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4 (18.8&#8211;22.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.6 (18.8&#8211;22.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.4 (15.4&#8211;24.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Associate&#8217;s or bachelor&#8217;s degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2 (29.4&#8211;33.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.7 (31.6&#8211;35.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.3 (14.8&#8211;22.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Master&#8217;s, doctoral, or professional degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6 (8.54&#8211;10.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6 (9.47&#8211;11.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 (2.47&#8211;6.07)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Family income in $1000s, mean</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.5 (66.2&#8211;70.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.8 (70.3&#8211;75.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.6 (41.6&#8211;49.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Proximity to metro area, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nonmetropolitan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.0 (16.5&#8211;19.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5 (15.0&#8211;18.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.9 (21.7&#8211;30.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medium and small metro</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.0 (31.1&#8211;35.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.8 (30.8&#8211;34.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9 (28.9&#8211;39.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large fringe metro</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.1 (20.4&#8211;23.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.3 (21.5&#8211;25.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7 (12.4&#8211;19.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large central metro</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.8 (25.0&#8211;28.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3 (25.3&#8211;29.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.5 (19.8&#8211;29.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Number of pain locations, mean</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2 (3.2&#8211;3.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2 (3.1&#8211;3.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3 (3.2&#8211;3.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Pain limiting life/work, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.1 (20.5&#8211;23.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2 (22.4&#8211;26.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9 (8.13&#8211;14.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.5 (36.4&#8211;40.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.3 (37.1&#8211;41.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.3 (29.1&#8211;39.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Most days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.2 (15.8&#8211;18.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.9 (15.3&#8211;18.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9 (15.3&#8211;23.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Every day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.2 (20.5&#8211;24.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.6 (17.9&#8211;21.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.0 (30.9&#8211;41.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PHQ-8 total, mean</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6 (5.3&#8211;5.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4 (5.1&#8211;5.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 (5.9&#8211;7.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>a</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Note</bold>: Values in parentheses represent 95% confidence intervals. <sup>a</sup>Wilcoxon rank-sum test for complex survey samples. <sup>b</sup>Chi-squared test with Rao &amp; Scott&#8217;s second-order correction.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: CI, confidence interval; GED, general equivalency diploma; metro, metropolitan; NH, Non-Hispanic; Nonpharm, nonpharmacologic; PHQ-8, Patient Health Questionnaire-8.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref> and <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=439682.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental Table 3</ext-link></underline> summarize the aOR and 95% CI of each covariate on engagement in nonpharmacologic modalities exclusively rather than opioid utilization, with quantitative variables presented comparing the 75<sup>th</sup> to the 25<sup>th</sup> percentile. Within the weighted logistic regression model (validated c-statistic=0.728), the following were associated with increased odds (aOR, 95% CI) of engagement in nonpharmacologic modalities only after adjusting for all other covariates: (1) higher family income ($85,000 vs $22,000: 1.596, 1.352&#8211;1.883), (2) higher levels of education as compared to less than high school (ie, high school/GED [1.639, 1.232&#8211;2.179], some college, no degree [2.094, 1.522&#8211;2.881], associate&#8217;s or bachelor&#8217;s degree [3.176, 2.301&#8211;4.383], master&#8217;s, doctoral, or professional degree [3.943, 2.325&#8211;6.687]), and (3) living in medium/small (1.327, 1.016&#8211;1.734), large fringe (1.864, 1.356&#8211;2.562) or central (1.449, 1.075&#8211;1.954) metropolitan areas as compared to non-metropolitan areas. Older age (69 years vs 46 years: 0.614, 0.530&#8211;0.711) and having pain limiting life or work activities on some days (0.541, 0.390&#8211;0.750), most days (0.493, 0.341&#8211;0.713), or every day (0.363, 0.256&#8211;0.513) as compared to never were associated with decreased odds of engaging in nonpharmacologic modalities.
<fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Adjusted Odds Ratios of Using Nonpharmacologic Only vs Opioids Only.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JPR-17-253-g0003.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Notes:</bold> Red dots represent point estimates for adjusted odds ratios, and error bars represent 95% confidence intervals. Education covariates are placed on a separate axis given their size to not obscure the other covariates.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: aOR, adjusted odds ratio; Assoc, associate&#8217;s; Bach, bachelor&#8217;s; fam, family; GED, general equivalency diploma; HS, high school; L, large; M, medium; metro, metropolitan; NH, Non-Hispanic; PHQ-8, Patient Health Questionnaire-8; S, small; v., versus; yrs, years.</attrib></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study examined which demographic, pain, and mental health variables were associated with engagement in (1) the number of IHM modalities used for pain and (2) exclusively nonpharmacologic modalities rather than opioid utilization among a representative sample of US adults with chronic pain. Our study identified several contrasts between factors prevalent among individuals with chronic pain and factors associated with engagement in nonpharmacologic and IHM modalities.</p><p>While older adults report higher rates of chronic pain<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> and are more likely to take opioids for chronic pain,<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> our study found that increased age was associated with reduced odds of engagement in nonpharmacologic and IHM therapies, a finding consistent with previous studies.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6&#8211;9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> A qualitative study identified several barriers to engaging in these therapies among older adults with chronic pain including embarrassment, lack of faith in effectiveness, and lack of treatment availability.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Inconsistent Medicare coverage for nonpharmacologic treatments may also prohibit older adults from accessing these modalities.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10&#8211;12</xref></p><p>Chronic pain is more prevalent in rural areas,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> yet we found that non-metropolitan residence was associated with reduced odds of engagement in nonpharmacologic and IHM modalities. Previous NHIS studies examining predictors of engagement in these modalities used markers of US region (eg, Northeast, South) rather than proximity to metropolitan areas,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> hindering a direct comparison to our results. Nevertheless, our novel finding may be explained by a lack of access to healthcare facilities, nonpharmacologic modality providers, and public transportation in rural settings.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></p><p>Lower income is associated with increased risk of chronic pain.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> This is important given that we found that lower income was associated with reduced odds of engagement in nonpharmacologic and IHM modalities. This finding is consistent with previous studies.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> One possible contributing factor is that Medicaid health insurance provides inconsistent coverage for these modalities.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Similarly, chronic pain is more prevalent among those with lower levels of education,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> yet our study found that lower education was associated with reduced odds of engagement in nonpharmacologic and IHM modalities. This finding is consistent with previous studies,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6&#8211;9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> and may be explained by lack of exposure to a broader range of treatment options among individuals with chronic pain and lower levels of education.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></p><p>While an increasing frequency of pain limiting life or work activities was associated with higher odds of engagement in IHM modalities, it was also associated with lower odds of engaging in nonpharmacologic modalities exclusively. In addition, the positive association between pain limiting life or work activities and number of pain locations with IHM engagement supports the clinical relevance of these modalities for addressing pain rather than general wellness, which is a common reason for seeking IHM care among those without chronic pain.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></p><p>The association between opioid use and chronic pain is well-established.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Importantly, our study found that individuals taking opioids daily were less likely to engage in IHM. This finding supports a previous qualitative study which found that Veterans with chronic pain taking opioids long-term held pervasive attitudes that discouraged them from engaging in multimodal treatments.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> In addition, US practitioners (eg, chiropractors and yoga therapists) providing nonpharmacologic modalities or IHM to adults with chronic pain are often unable to prescribe opioids within their scope of practice. Accordingly, a negative association between daily opioid use and IHM could be explained by patients&#8217; general preference towards pharmacologic care pathways.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> We also found a negative relationship between increased PHQ-8 score and count of IHM modalities used for pain. Given the prevalence of depression among individuals with chronic pain<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> and the common neural mechanisms between the two conditions,<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> depressive symptoms may be a barrier to engaging in additional IHM modalities within this population.</p><p>Racial differences were also evident in our study. NH Black/African American adults were 31.7% less likely to engage in IHM modalities compared to individuals who identified as NH White after adjusting for all other covariates. A previous study among cancer-free adults with chronic pain similarly found that Black/African American individuals were 50% less likely to engage in nonpharmacologic therapies compared to White individuals.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> In addition, previous studies have reported lower odds of engagement in IHM modalities among Black/African American adults with low back pain (aOR=0.4)<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> and those receiving treatment at a multidisciplinary pain center (aOR=0.5).<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Specific reasons underlying racial and ethnic disparities specific to IHM and nonpharmacologic care may stem from biases in care delivery or cultural preferences and warrant further exploration.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> These findings underscore the need to address racial disparities in chronic pain management, particularly given the history of racial bias among healthcare professionals treating pain.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></p><p>Our study highlights a gap in IHM and nonpharmacologic utilization among those at greatest risk of chronic pain despite demonstrated efficacy and guideline recommendations for these forms of care.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> We suggest that several steps are necessary to mitigate barriers to accessing IHM and nonpharmacologic care. These include: (1) further qualitative exploration of reasons for use or non-use of IHM and nonpharmacologic modalities among patients or potential patients; (2) an examination of regional access to care including associations between socio-economic markers and clinician density; and (3) examination of IHM and nonpharmacologic care utilization between regions with expanded Medicaid versus those without, or pre- and post-comparisons of within-region changes following Medicaid expansion.</p><p>As the question of insurance coverage is beyond the scope of the present study, further research is needed to corroborate whether inadequate coverage is a limiting factor to accessing IHM and nonpharmacologic care. In addition, insurance coverage for IHM and nonpharmacologic modalities not only depends on the barriers we have identified, but stakeholder input and data demonstrating efficacy, effectiveness, and safety as well.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p><p>Our study had several limitations. Data were based on self-reported responses and thus potentially influenced by recall bias and respondents&#8217; willingness to report treatment engagement. While our analysis accounted for several socio-demographic, pain, and mental health covariates, we did not include other NHIS variables such as the specific etiology of chronic pain, pain severity, insurance coverage, employment, or self-reported general health status. The 2019 NHIS did not provide information regarding other clinically effective IHM modalities such as acupuncture and music therapy,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> the frequency or intensity of nonpharmacologic or IHM engagement, whether engagement involved personal practice (eg, yoga at home) or seeing a professional (eg, a licensed yoga therapist), or opioid dose.</p><p>These findings are specific to patterns of care utilization for chronic pain among US adults and may not generalize to other countries with differing healthcare systems, insurance coverage models, IHM availability, and cultural preferences. Additionally, we did not examine specific branches of IHM and nonpharmacologic care (eg, chiropractic or yoga) or specific pain conditions (eg, back pain or headache), and reasons for seeking individual therapies may vary according to condition. This study is limited by the lack of granular data in the NHIS regarding respondents&#8217; specific state of residence and whether that state had expanded Medicaid, thereby hindering an analysis of possible regional differences in IHM utilization. Strengths of this study include a multidisciplinary author team, use of a large, nationally representative sample of US adults with chronic pain, and using modalities specifically for pain management as outcome measures.</p></sec><sec id="s0005"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In conjunction with recent guidelines from the Centers for Disease Control<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> and American College of Physicians,<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> as well as position statements from The Pain Task Force of the Academic Consortium for Integrative Medicine and Health<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> advising clinicians to consider evidence-based nonpharmacologic modalities as first-line treatments for chronic pain, the present findings support the need to better understand and reduce barriers to accessing nonpharmacologic and IHM modalities. Our results support efforts to address barriers among adults with chronic pain who are older, identify as NH Black/African American, lack higher levels of education, reside in rural areas, have lower income, have higher levels of pain interference, report higher depressive symptoms, and have a high frequency of opioid use. Further mixed methods participatory action research is recommended to identify what patients within these populations perceive as barriers to accessing nonpharmacologic and IHM modalities. In turn, this research may inform policy change and help increase the utilization of IHM and nonpharmacologic care among populations with chronic pain.</p></sec></body><back><sec id="s0006"><title>Data Sharing Statement</title><p>Data are publicly available and can be accessed at <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhis/2019nhis.htm" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhis/2019nhis.htm</ext-link></underline>. Supporting documentation containing the R code (.qmd) file for the full statistical analysis is available at <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://samrodgersmelnick.github.io/NHIS2019ChronicPain/" ext-link-type="uri">https://samrodgersmelnick.github.io/NHIS2019ChronicPain/</ext-link></underline>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0007"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors reports no conflicts of interest in this work.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nahin</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feinberg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kapos</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Terman</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Estimated rates of incident and persistent chronic pain among us adults, 2019&#8211;2020</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e2313563</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.13563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37191961</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10189566</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tick</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Evidence-based nonpharmacologic strategies for comprehensive pain care: the consortium pain task force white paper</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Explore</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>177</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>211</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.explore.2018.02.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29735382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dowell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ragan</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>CDC clinical practice guideline for prescribing opioids for pain - United States, 2022</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">MMWR Recomm Rep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.rr7103a1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9639433</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36327391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A longitudinal study of the association of opioid use with change in pain interference and functional limitations in a nationally representative cohort of adults with osteoarthritis in the United States</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Adv Ther</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>819</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>832</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12325-019-01200-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31875300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7004429</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dahlhamer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bose</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zelaya</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prescription opioid use among adults with chronic pain: United States</article-title>; <year>2019</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://stacks.cdc.gov/view/cdc/107641" ext-link-type="uri">https://stacks.cdc.gov/view/cdc/107641</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed 2021 <month>Aug</month>, <day>5</day>.</date-in-citation><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34524076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baillargeon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Raji</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Trends in the use of opioids vs nonpharmacologic treatments in adults with pain, 2011&#8211;2019</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e2240612</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.40612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36342717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9641539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Complementary and alternative medicine use by U.S. adults with self-reported doctor-diagnosed arthritis: results from the 2012 national health interview survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PM R</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1059</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1069</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmrj.12124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30729749</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ndao-Brumblay</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Predictors of complementary and alternative medicine use in chronic pain patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pain Med</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>16</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1526-4637.2009.00767.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20447293</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ghildayal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kreitzer</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Complementary and alternative medicine use in the US adult low back pain population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Glob Adv Health Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>69</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>78</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7453/gahmj.2015.104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26937316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4756777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heyward</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Compton</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Coverage of nonpharmacologic treatments for low back pain among us public and private insurers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e183044</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2018.3044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30646222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6324451</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Candon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dusek</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Trends in insurance coverage for acupuncture, 2010&#8211;2019</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e2142509</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.42509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35019986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8756308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leach</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Full-coverage chiropractic in medicare: a proposal to eliminate inequities, improve outcomes, and reduce health disparities without increasing overall program costs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Chiropr Humanit</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.echu.2020.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33324134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7729103</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sharan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Espinosa</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gallego-Perez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Weeks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The path toward integration of traditional and complementary medicine into health systems globally: the world health organization report on the implementation of the 2014&#8211;2023 strategy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Altern Complement Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>869</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>871</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/acm.2019.29077.jjw</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31525106</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Complementary medicine use in patients with low back or neck pain: results of the 2017 national health interview survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pain Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2393</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2400</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pm/pnab169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34109412</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Quandt</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Grzywacz</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Arcury</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Use of complementary and alternative medicine by persons with arthritis: results of the national health interview survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arthritis Care Res</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>748</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>755</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.21443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16208669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mackenzie</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Coulter</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Whedon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Weeks</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The United States chiropractic workforce: an alternative or complement to primary care?</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Chiropr Man Therap</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>35</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2045-709X-20-35</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3551710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23171540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yakusheva</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tootoo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Titler</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bynum</surname><given-names>JPW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Access to chiropractic care and the cost of spine conditions among older adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Manag Care</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e230</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>e236</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.299.6.656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31419099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6699757</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dahlhamer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zelaya</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of chronic pain and high-impact chronic pain among adults &#8212; United States, 2016</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>36</issue>):<fpage>1001</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1006</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6736a2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30212442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6146950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>National Center for Health Statistics</collab>. <article-title>National health interview survey</article-title>. <publisher-name>National Center for Health Statistics</publisher-name>; <year>2023</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhis/2019nhis.htm" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhis/2019nhis.htm</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>April</month> 2021, <day>05</day>.</date-in-citation></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zelaya</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dahlhamer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chronic pain and high-impact chronic pain among U.S</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Adults</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>2020</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33151145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>simputation: simple imputation</article-title>; <year>2022</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=simputation" ext-link-type="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=simputation</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>January</month><day>04</day>, 2024</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sjoberg</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Whiting</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Curry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lavery</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Larmarange</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reproducible summary tables with the gtsummary package</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">R J</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>570</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>580</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32614/rj-2021-053</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name><collab>Getting Started with Hurdle Models</collab>. <article-title>University of Virginia library</article-title>; <year>2023</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://data.library.virginia.edu/getting-started-with-hurdle-models/" ext-link-type="uri">https://data.library.virginia.edu/getting-started-with-hurdle-models/</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>January</month><day>04</day>, 2024.</date-in-citation></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zeileis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kleiber</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jackman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Regression models for count data in R</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Stat Softw</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>25</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v027.i08</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>pscl: Classes and Methods for R Developed in the Political Science Computational Laboratory. Version R package version 1.5.5.1</collab>. <article-title>United States studies centre, university of Sydney</article-title>; <year>2020</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/atahk/pscl/" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/atahk/pscl/</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>January</month><day>04</day>, 2024.</date-in-citation></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><source>rms: Regression Modeling Strategies. Version R package version 6.7-0</source>. <year>2023</year>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=rms" ext-link-type="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=rms</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>January</month><day>04</day>, 2024.</date-in-citation></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Disparities in opioid prescribing for long-term chronic and short-term acute pain: findings from the 2019 national health interview survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Behav Health Serv Res</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>315</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>334</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11414-022-09790-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35237905</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hirz</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Manotas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hooyman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nonpharmacological pain management by ethnically diverse older adults with chronic pain: barriers and facilitators</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Gerontol Soc Work</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>487</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>508</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01634372.2013.808725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23822640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Douthit</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kiv</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dwolatzky</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Exposing some important barriers to health care access in the rural USA</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>129</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>611</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>620</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.puhe.2015.04.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26025176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The relationship between financial stressors, chronic pain, and high-impact chronic pain: findings from the 2019 national health interview survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Public Health Rep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>333549221091786</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/00333549221091786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10240893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35506496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Edmond</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Driscoll</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Use of non-pharmacological pain treatment modalities among veterans with chronic pain: results from a cross-sectional survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Gen Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-018-4322-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29633141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5902341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Andrews-Cooper</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kozachik</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>How patient education influences utilization of nonpharmacological modalities for persistent pain management: an integrative review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pain Manag Nurs Apr</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>157</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>164</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pmn.2019.06.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31521522</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Steel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lauche</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dobos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Prevalence</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Patterns, and predictors of yoga use: results of a u.s. nationally representative survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Prev Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>230</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>235</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2015.07.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26497261</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The prevalence, patterns, and predictors of chiropractic use among us adults: results from the 2012 national health interview survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Spine</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>1810</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1816</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/brs.0000000000002218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28459779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Simmonds</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Finley</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vale</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pugh</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A qualitative study of veterans on long-term opioid analgesics: barriers and facilitators to multimodality pain management</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pain Med Apr</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>726</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>732</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pme.12626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25528887</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0036"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boeri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Exploring patient preference heterogeneity for pharmacological treatments for chronic pain: a latent class analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Pain</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>648</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>667</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ejp.1892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34854164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9303786</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0037"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rayner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hotopf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Petkova</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Matcham</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McCracken</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Depression in patients with chronic pain attending a specialised pain treatment centre: prevalence and impact on health care costs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pain</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>157</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1472</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1479</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/j.pain.0000000000000542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26963849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4912238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0038"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The link between depression and chronic pain: neural mechanisms in the brain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neural Plast</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>2017</volume>:<fpage>9724371</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2017/9724371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28706741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5494581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0039"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Essien</surname><given-names>UR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ifidon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sue</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Black pain matters: prioritizing antiracism and equity in the opioid epidemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Hosp Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>638</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>639</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12788/jhm.3703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34613902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8494278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0040"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Booker</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>African Americans&#8217; perceptions of pain and pain management: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Transcult Nurs</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>73</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1043659614526250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24841472</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0041"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Qaseem</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wilt</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Forciea</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Noninvasive treatments for acute, subacute, and chronic low back pain: a clinical practice guideline from the American college of physicians</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>166</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>514</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>530</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M16-2367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28192789</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>