<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Prev Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Prev Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3815</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">pheelsevier</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Preventive Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-7435</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1096-0260</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Elsevier - PMC COVID-19 Collection</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10155467</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10155467.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10155467</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10155467</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37146730</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ypmed.2023.107533</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0091-7435(23)00113-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">107533</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Racial differences in COVID-19 severity associated with history of substance use disorders and overdose: Findings from multi-site electronic health records in New York City</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names initials="B">Bennett</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cr0005" ref-type="corresp">&#8270;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010"><name name-style="western"><surname>Basaraba</surname><given-names initials="C">Cale</given-names></name><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0015"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corbeil</surname><given-names initials="T">Thomas</given-names></name><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0020"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names initials="BD">Bianca D.</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0025"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names initials="FR">Frances R.</given-names></name><xref rid="af0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="af0020" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0030"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names initials="DM">Diana M.</given-names></name><xref rid="af0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="af0020" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0035"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schultebraucks</surname><given-names initials="K">Katharina</given-names></name><xref rid="af0025" ref-type="aff">e</xref><xref rid="af0030" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0040"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henry</surname><given-names initials="BF">Brandy F.</given-names></name><xref rid="af0035" ref-type="aff">g</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0045"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pincus</surname><given-names initials="HA">Harold A.</given-names></name><xref rid="af0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="af0020" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="PC_affzfzNQcWCMB" ref-type="aff">h</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0050"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arout</surname><given-names initials="C">Caroline</given-names></name><xref rid="af0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0055"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krawczyk</surname><given-names initials="N">Noa</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="af0005"><label>a</label>Center for Opioid Epidemiology and Policy, Department of Population Health, NYU Grossman School of Medicine, United States of America</aff><aff id="af0010"><label>b</label>Area Mental Health Data Science, New York State Psychiatric Institute, United States of America</aff><aff id="af0015"><label>c</label>Department of Psychiatry, Columbia University Irving Medical Center and New York State Psychiatric Institute, United States of America</aff><aff id="af0020"><label>d</label>Columbia University Vagelos College of Physicians and Surgeons, United States of America</aff><aff id="af0025"><label>e</label>Department of Psychiatry, NYU Grossman School of Medicine, United States of America</aff><aff id="af0030"><label>f</label>Department of Population Health, NYU Grossman School of Medicine, United States of America</aff><aff id="af0035"><label>g</label>College of Education, Consortium on Substance Use and Addiction, Social Science Research Institute, Pennsylvania State University, United States of America</aff><aff id="PC_affzfzNQcWCMB"><label>h</label>Irving Institute for Clinical and Translational Research, Columbia University, United States of America</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cr0005"><label>&#8270;</label>Corresponding author at: Center for Opioid Epidemiology and Policy, New York University Grossman School of Medicine, 180 Madison Avenue, 4<sup>th</sup> Floor, New York, NY 10016, United States of America.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>172</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">434837</issue-id><fpage>107533</fpage><lpage>107533</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>27</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>03</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>04</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-05-30 05:25:13.677"><day>30</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2023 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Elsevier Inc.</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="ab0005"><p>Substance use disorders (SUD) are associated with increased risk of worse COVID-19 outcomes. Likewise, racial/ethnic minority patients experience greater risk of severe COVID-19 disease compared to white patients. Providers should understand the role of race and ethnicity as an effect modifier on COVID-19 severity among individuals with SUD. This retrospective cohort study assessed patient race/ethnicity as an effect modifier of the risk of severe COVID-19 disease among patients with histories of SUD and overdose. We used merged electronic health record data from 116,471 adult patients with a COVID-19 encounter between March 2020 and February 2021 across five healthcare systems in New York City. Exposures were patient histories of SUD and overdose. Outcomes were risk of COVID-19 hospitalization and subsequent COVID-19-related ventilation, acute kidney failure, sepsis, and mortality. Risk factors included patient age, sex, and race/ethnicity, as well as medical comorbidities associated with COVID-19 severity. We tested for interaction between SUD and patient race/ethnicity on COVID-19 outcomes. Findings showed that Non-Hispanic Black, Hispanic/Latino, and Asian/Pacific Islander patients experienced a higher prevalence of all adverse COVID-19 outcomes compared to non-Hispanic white patients. Past-year alcohol (OR 1.24 [1.01&#8211;1.53]) and opioid use disorders (OR 1.91 [1.46&#8211;2.49]), as well as overdose history (OR 4.45 [3.62&#8211;5.46]), were predictive of COVID-19 mortality, as well as other adverse COVID-19 outcomes. Among patients with SUD, significant differences in outcome risk were detected between patients of different race/ethnicity groups. Findings indicate that providers should consider multiple dimensions of vulnerability to adequately manage COVID-19 disease among populations with SUDs.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="ks0005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Substance use disorders</kwd><kwd>Overdose</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Race/ethnicity</kwd><kwd>Health disparities</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0025">The SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19) pandemic remains a public health crisis despite vaccination and non-pharmaceutical interventions (<xref rid="bb0240" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization, 2023</xref>). In the United States, COVID-19 disproportionately affected racially and ethnically minoritized groups (<xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">Acosta et al., 2021</xref>). A meta-analysis identified non-Hispanic Black, Hispanic/Latino, Asian/Pacific Islander, and American Indian/Alaska Native individuals are at increased risk of COVID-19 test positivity and intensive care unit admission, compared to non-Hispanic White individuals (<xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">Magesh et al., 2021</xref>). Other work identified increased prevalence of COVID-19 risk factors among these populations (<xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">Lo et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0185" ref-type="bibr">Raifman and Raifman, 2020</xref>).</p><p id="p0030">COVID-19 also disproportionately affects persons with intersecting vulnerabilities, including individuals with substance use disorders (SUDs) and histories of drug use (Allen et al., 2021); <xref rid="bb0220" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">Krawczyk et al., 2022</xref>. The pandemic accelerated the national substance use and overdose epidemic; 2020 had the largest number of overdose deaths ever recorded (<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">Ahmad et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">Cartus et al., 2022</xref>). Disparities also increased, with overdose mortality occurring disproportionately among non-Hispanic Black and Hispanic/Latino populations (<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">Ahmad et al., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="bb0195" ref-type="bibr">Scholl et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Askari et al., 2023</xref>), and non-Hispanic Black and Hispanic/Latino more likely to experience disruptions to opioid use disorder (OUD) services than white individuals (<xref rid="bb0190" ref-type="bibr">Rosales et al., 2022</xref>). Early research also shows that non-Hispanic Black patients with alcohol and opioid use disorders have an increased risk of COVID-19 infection and higher rates of COVID-19 hospitalization, compared to non-Hispanic white patients (<xref rid="bb0220" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2021</xref>). Continued research is needed to better understand how race/ethnicity modifies COVID-19 severity among patients with SUDs to inform intervention strategies and reduce racial disparities.</p><p id="p0035">In this study, we use linked electronic health record (EHR) all-payer data from five large private healthcare systems in New York City (NYC) to estimate associations between SUD and drug overdose history with COVID-19 outcomes. We then assess race/ethnicity as an effect modifier for severe COVID-19 disease to identify potential disparities in COVID-19 severity across racial and ethnic groups. As an early COVID-19 epicenter and a racially and ethnically diverse jurisdiction with high rates of opioid and other drug overdose (<xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Askari et al., 2023</xref>), NYC is an ideal setting in which to begin to untangle the relationships between COVID-19, SUD/overdose, and racial/ethnic disparities.</p></sec><sec id="s0010"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="s0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Data source</title><p id="p0040">We conducted a retrospective review of data from the INSIGHT Clinical Research Network (INSIGHT), a database of de-identified EHRs from the five largest private healthcare systems in NYC: Columbia University Medical Center, Montefiore Medical Center, Mount Sinai Health System, NYU Langone Health, and Weill Cornell/NY-Presbyterian Medical Center. Participating health systems serve geographically, racially, ethnically, and socioeconomically diverse patient populations across greater NYC. INSIGHT contains demographic and clinical information on over 12 million patients from 2011 to 2021 (<xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">INSIGHT Clinical Research Network, n.d.</xref>). We utilized data on patients diagnosed with COVID-19 through either positive reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) assays or COVID-19 ICD-10 diagnosis between March 1, 2020 and February 23, 2021 (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#160;=&#160;116,498). Analysis involving de-identified secondary data was exempt from review by the NYU Langone Health Institutional Review Board.</p></sec><sec id="s0020"><label>2.2</label><title>Exposures, outcomes, and covariates</title><p id="p0045">We assessed six substance use-related exposures using ICD-9 and ICD-10 codes: any substance use disorder (SUD); alcohol use disorder (AUD); opioid use disorder (OUD); cannabis use disorder (CAUD); cocaine use disorder (COUD); and overdose for any drug type (OD). Exposures were captured for past-year patient histories, indexed prior to patients' first COVID-19 encounter.</p><p id="p0050">We assessed five outcomes using hospital and procedure codes: inpatient hospitalization, mechanical ventilation, acute kidney failure, severe sepsis, and death. Hospitalization and ventilation were defined as any hospital admission or use of mechanical ventilation during a COVID-19 encounter. Acute kidney failure and sepsis were defined as COVID-related if experienced within 28&#160;days of a COVID-19 encounter. We defined a COVID-19-related death as either mortality experienced during a COVID-19 encounter or within 14&#160;days of discharge from a COVID-19 encounter, specific cause of death was not available. We selected these time frames to reflect outcomes most likely related to COVID-19 in accordance with other literature that identified readmission after a first COVID admission (<xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p id="p0055">We assessed patient comorbidities known as risk factors for poor COVID-19 outcomes (<xref rid="bb0180" ref-type="bibr">Petrilli et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0210" ref-type="bibr">Vai et al., 2021</xref>) using ICD-9 and ICD-10 codes. Comorbidities included: cardiovascular disorders (heart failure, acute myocardial infarction, congestive heart failure, ischemic heart disease, and cardiac dysrhythmia); chronic kidney disease; pain disorders (chronic pain, chronic fatigue, fibromyalgia, and post-viral fatigue); diabetes; obesity; respiratory disorders (emphysema, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), and asthma); psychosis or bipolar disorders; and other psychiatric conditions (anxiety disorder, depressive disorder, and reaction to severe stress). Comorbidities were captured for past-year patient histories, indexed prior to patients' first COVID-19 encounters. Diagnostic codes identifying COVID-19, SUD exposures, and comorbidities are in Supplemental Table 1.</p><p id="p0060">Several patient demographic characteristics were assessed. These included sex (male and female), age group (0&#8211;17&#160;years, 18&#8211;44&#160;years, 45&#8211;64&#160;years, 65&#8211;74&#160;years, and 75&#160;years and older), and race/ethnicity (non-Hispanic white, non-Hispanic Black, Hispanic/Latino, Asian/Pacific Islander, other/multi-racial, and unknown). Other/multi-racial included patients for whom race/ethnicity was coded as American Indian or Alaska Native, multi-racial, or other. Data were not weighted to the NYC or United States population.</p><p id="p0065">Data for exposures, outcomes, comorbidities, and demographics were complete except for sex and race. Sex data for 27 patients (&lt; 0.01%) that was marked as missing or other were removed from analyses, bringing the final sample to 116,471. For race/ethnicity, 14.1% of patient data was unknown.</p></sec><sec id="s0025"><label>2.3</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0070">We calculated descriptive statistics of patient characteristics overall and stratified by race/ethnicity. We used logistic regression to estimate unadjusted and adjusted odds ratios between past-year substance use-related exposures and COVID-19 outcomes. Multivariable models were adjusted for sex, age, race/ethnicity, and past-year comorbidities. Given the high level of missing data for race/ethnicity (14%), and since inclusion of missing data as a discrete covariate category may bias analyses (<xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">Groenwold et al., 2012</xref>), we conducted sensitivity analyses by repeating multivariable using multiple imputation with chained equations (<xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">Austin et al., 2021</xref>). Race/ethnicity was imputed using available demographic and clinical covariates and five iterations. Compared to the complete case analyses presented here, imputation of race/ethnicity did not qualitatively change findings (results not shown).</p><p id="p0075">To test for effect modification between race/ethnicity and substance use-related exposures, we included an interaction term between race/ethnicity and each substance use-related exposure (<xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">Corraini et al., 2017</xref>). In cases where associations differed by race/ethnicity, as indicated by a statistically significant interaction term, subgroup odds ratios were presented separately. Otherwise, odds ratios were presented for the overall sample including all race groups. Statistical significance was defined as <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.05 after correction for multiple comparisons using the Benjamini-Hochberg procedure assuming a false discovery rate (FDR) of 5% (<xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">Benjamini and Hochberg, 1995</xref>). Analyses were conducted using Stata version 16.0 (StataCorp LLC, College Station, TX).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0030"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="s0035"><label>3.1</label><title>Sample characteristics</title><p id="p0080"><xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> presents demographic and clinical characteristics of patients positive for COVID-19 during the study period (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#160;=&#160;116,471). A majority of the sample (53.4%) was female. Approximately one-third of patients each were aged 18&#8211;44 (31.8%) or 45&#8211;64 (33.7%). A plurality of patients was non-Hispanic white (37.8%), followed by Hispanic/Latino (28.1%), and non-Hispanic Black (18.5%).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of patients positive for COVID-19 by race/ethnicity.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0010">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overall</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-Hispanic white</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-Hispanic Black</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hispanic/Latino</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asian/Pacific Islander</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other/multi-racial</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N (%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100,106 (100)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37,887 (37.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18,500 (18.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28,132 (28.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6476 (6.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9125 (9.1)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">53,494 (53.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19,467 (51.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,758 (58.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,559 (55.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3290 (50.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4420 (48.5)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46,612 (46.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18,417 (48.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7739 (41.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,569 (44.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3186 (49.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4701 (51.5)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">&#8232;&#8232;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Age</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0&#8211;17&#160;years</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4682 (4.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1398 (3.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">602 (3.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1951 (6.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">237 (3.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">494 (5.4)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18&#8211;44&#160;years</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31,867 (31.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11,370 (30.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5429 (29.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9442 (33.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2320 (35.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3306 (36.3)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45&#8211;64&#160;years</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">33,738 (33.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,085 (31.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7136 (38.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9362 (33.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2089 (32.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3066 (33.6)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">65&#8211;74&#160;years</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,254 (15.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6474 (17.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2870 (15.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3803 (13.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">894 (13.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1213 (13.3)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">75+ years</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,565 (14.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6557 (17.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2460 (13.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3570 (12.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">936 (14.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1042 (11.4)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">&#8232;&#8232;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Comorbidities (past year)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asthma</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8271 (8.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2465 (6.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1814 (9.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3023 (10.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">325 (5.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">644 (7.1)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cardiovascular conditions</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,445 (14.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6061 (16.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2973 (16.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3517 (12.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">756 (11.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1138 (12.5)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chronic kidney disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8179 (8.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2352 (6.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2512 (13.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2305 (8.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">398 (6.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">612 (6.7)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chronic pain</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6333 (6.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2005 (5.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1366 (7.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2277 (8.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">199 (3.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">486 (5.3)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diabetes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16,161 (16.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4252 (11.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4025 (21.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5428 (19.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">980 (15.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1476 (16.2)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Obesity</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,216 (12.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4114 (10.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2976 (16.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3896 (13.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">285 (4.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">945 (10.4)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Respiratory conditions</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4132 (4.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1888 (5.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">883 (4.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">944 (3.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">155 (2.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">262 (2.9)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Psychosis or bipolar disorders</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1757 (1.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">553 (1.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">525 (2.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">518 (1.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (0.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">119 (1.3)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other psychiatric conditions</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7156 (7.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2778 (7.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1151 (6.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2506 (8.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">253 (3.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">468 (5.1)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">&#8232;&#8232;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Substance use disorders (past year)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any substance use disorder</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2426 (2.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">612 (1.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">684 (3.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">903 (3.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41 (0.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">186 (2.0)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alcohol use disorder</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1200 (1.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">319 (0.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">286 (1.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">467 (1.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (0.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">103 (1.1)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Opioid use disorder</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">587 (0.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">142 (0.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">167 (0.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">235 (0.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (0.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (0.4)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cannabis use disorder</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">574 (0.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">114 (0.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">217 (1.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">188 (0.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (0.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (0.5)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cocaine use disorder</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">335 (0.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51 (0.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">139 (0.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">124 (0.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (0.2)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any drug overdose</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">602 (0.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">161 (0.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">193 (1.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">171 (0.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (0.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (0.5)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">&#8232;&#8232;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Outcomes</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hospitalization</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35,106 (35.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9910 (26.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7722 (41.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11,047 (39.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2731 (42.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3696 (40.5)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sepsis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025 (2.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">546 (1.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">498 (2.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">637 (2.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">116 (1.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">228 (2.5)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kidney failure</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6661 (6.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2087 (5.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.817 (9.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1729 (6.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">420 (6.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">608 (6.7)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ventilation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3758 (3.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">954 (2.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">883 (4.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1227 (4.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">231 (3.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">463 (5.1)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Death</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5408 (5.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1619 (4.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1212 (6.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1660 (5.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">370 (5.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">547 (6.0)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="sp0025"><p><italic toggle="yes">Notes</italic>: Substance use disorder history not mutually exclusive; percentages may not sum to 100% due to rounding and missing data.</p></fn><fn id="sp0030"><p><italic toggle="yes">Source</italic>: INSIGHT Clinical Research Network.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0085">Substance use disorders were generally rare among patients, with 2.4% of overall patients having any SUD. Alcohol use disorder was the most common SUD (1.2%), followed by opioid and cannabis use disorders. Less than 1% (0.6%) of the sample had a past-year history of drug overdose. Diabetes (16.4%), cardiovascular conditions (14.4%), and obesity (12.2%) were the most prevalent past-year comorbidities. Past-year psychiatric disorders, including psychosis, bipolar disorders, and other psychiatric conditions, were present in 9% of patients.</p><p id="p0090">Over one-third of patients (35.1%) experienced a COVID-19 hospitalization. Kidney failure was the second most prevalent adverse COVID-19 outcome (6.7%). Approximately 5% of the sample died. Most deaths were reported during a COVID-19 encounter (95.9%); with few (4.1%) reported within 14&#160;days of discharge from a COVID-19 encounter.</p><p id="p0095">Overall, a higher proportion of non-Hispanic Black (41.8%), Hispanic/Latino (39.3%), Asian/Pacific Islander (42.2%), and other/multi-racial (40.5%) patients were hospitalized for COVID-19, compared to non-Hispanic white patients (26.2%). Sepsis, kidney failure, and ventilation were more prevalent among non-Hispanic Black, Hispanic/Latino, Asian/Pacific Islander, and other/multi-racial patients compared to non-Hispanic white patients. A higher proportion of non-Hispanic Black (6.6%), Hispanic/Latino (5.9%), Asian/Pacific Islander (5.7%) and other/multi-racial patients (6.0%) died compared to non-Hispanic white patients (4.3%).</p></sec><sec id="s0040"><label>3.2</label><title>Overall association between SUD/overdose and COVID-19 outcomes</title><p id="p0100"><xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> presents adjusted odds ratios of adverse outcomes associated with past-year SUD and overdose history for the full sample. All estimates are adjusted for available demographic and diagnostic covariates. Reference groups were patients without the given substance use exposure. Unadjusted estimates are presented in Supplemental Table 2. Overall, past-year history of any SUD, alcohol use disorder, opioid use disorder, and drug overdose were significantly associated with increased odds of all outcomes (hospitalization, sepsis, kidney failure, ventilation, and mortality). Past-year history of cannabis and cocaine use disorders, in contrast, were significantly associated with increased odds of hospitalization but not with the four other outcomes.<fig id="f0005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Odds of adverse COVID-19 outcomes by substance use disorder and drug overdose history.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Notes</italic>: Models adjusted for available demographic and comorbidity variables; reference groups for each are patients without the condition; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values corrected for multiple comparisons with a 5% false discovery rate.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Source</italic>: INSIGHT Clinical Research Network.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0005">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1_lrg.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0045"><label>3.3</label><title>Association between SUD/overdose and COVID-19 outcomes by race/ethnicity</title><p id="p0105"><xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents associations between SUD history and COVID-19 outcomes by race/ethnicity after testing an interaction between SUD history and race/ethnicity. Where no significant interaction between SUD and any racial/ethnic group was detected (interaction <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&gt;&#160;0.05), odds ratios were not reported for individual racial/ethnic groups. Observed <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values for statistically significant interactions (<italic toggle="yes">P&#160;&lt;</italic>&#160;0.05 after correction for a 5% FDR) are reported in Supplemental Table 2.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>COVID-19 outcome risk associated with substance use history by race/ethnicity.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0015">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Substance use disorder history</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hospitalization<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sepsis<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kidney failure<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ventilation<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Death<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any substance use disorder</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.56 (2.34, 2.81) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.51 (1.25, 1.82) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.56 (1.37, 1.77) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.49 (1.27, 1.73) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.34 (1.15, 1.57) *</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Non-Hispanic white</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.80 (1.20, 2.70) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.44 (1.00, 2.07) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.42 (1.02, 2.00) *</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Non-Hispanic Black</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.73 (0.50, 1.07)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.90 (0.67, 1.23)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.19 (0.90, 1.58)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hispanic/Latino</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.59 (1.19, 2.13) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.55 (1.22, 1.97) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.28 (0.99, 1.66)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Asian/Pacific Islander</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.28 (1.45, 12.85) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.38 (4.44, 19.82) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.96 (2.50, 14.19) *</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other/multi-racial</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.42 (1.36, 4.32) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.03 (1.26, 3.25) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.04 (0.56, 1.93)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alcohol use disorder</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.53 (2.23, 2.88) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.56 (1.22, 1.99) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.44 (1.20, 1.71) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.30 (1.05, 1.60) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.24 (1.01, 1.53) *</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Non-Hispanic white</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.90 (1.13, 3.21) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.27 (0.77, 2.10)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.19 (0.75, 1.88)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Non-Hispanic Black</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.54 (0.29, 0.99) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.61 (0.37, 1.00)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (0.66, 1.50)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hispanic/Latino</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.73 (1.18, 2.52) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.44 (1.05, 1.99) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.25 (0.89, 1.77)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Asian/Pacific Islander</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.23 (0.71, 14.58)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.16 (2.69, 19.07) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.57 (1.54, 13.61) *</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other/multi-racial</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.07 (0.97, 4.43)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.45 (0.76, 2.78)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.87 (0.40, 1.94)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Opioid use disorder</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.89 (2.39, 3.50) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.81 (1.33, 2.48) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.80 (1.43, 2.26) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.85 (1.42, 2.41) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.91 (1.46, 2.49) *</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Non-Hispanic white</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.73 (2.59, 5.36) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.76 (0.87, 3.59)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Non-Hispanic Black</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.52 (1.72, 3.68) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.49 (0.92, 2.41)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hispanic/Latino</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.99 (1.47, 2.70) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.60 (1.06, 2.41) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Asian/Pacific Islander</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.88 (0.96, 64.57)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.85 (7.36, 113.16) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other/multi-racial</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.69 (1.62, 8.43) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.43 (0.90, 6.57)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cannabis use disorder</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.17 (1.81, 2.60) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.63 (0.37, 1.07)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.26 (0.95, 1.67)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.80 (0.54, 1.19)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.91 (0.60, 1.36)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Non-Hispanic white</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.67 (0.21, 2.22)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Non-Hispanic Black</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.85 (0.46, 1.57)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hispanic/Latino</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.23 (0.64, 2.36)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Asian/Pacific Islander</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.63 (3.28, 267.45) *</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other/multi-racial</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.67 (0.20, 2.21)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cocaine use disorder</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.45 (1.89, 3.17) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.75 (0.46, 1.20)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.13 (0.83, 1.53)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.93 (0.63, 1.37)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.18 (0.81, 1.73)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Non-Hispanic white</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.20 (0.36, 4.05)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Non-Hispanic Black</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.55 (0.29, 1.06)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hispanic/Latino</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95 (0.51, 1.80)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Asian/Pacific Islander</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.20 (0.36, 4.05)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other/multi-racial</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.25 (1.68, 16.40) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8764;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">History of drug overdose</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.07 (4.11, 6.24) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.50 (2.72, 4.50) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.49 (2.02, 3.07) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.92 (2.33, 3.66) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.45 (3.62, 5.46) *</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Non-Hispanic white</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.73 (2.85, 7.84) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.77 (3.10, 7.35) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Non-Hispanic Black</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.03 (1.22, 3.38) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.85 (1.18, 2.89) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hispanic/Latino</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.84 (1.77, 4.56) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.97 (1.27, 3.05) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Asian/Pacific Islander</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.72 (0.89, 8.29)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.22 (1.33, 7.80) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other/multi-racial</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.88 (4.56, 21.44) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.12 (2.98, 12.56) *</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="sp0040"><p><italic toggle="yes">Note</italic>: Models adjusted for age, sex, and comorbidities; * indicates statistical significance; &#8722; indicates no estimate presented because no statistically significant difference detected; &#8764; indicates no estimate due to small cell size; interaction estimates are reported without standalone stratified estimates by racial/ethnic groups; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values corrected for multiple comparisons with a 5% false discovery rate.</p></fn><fn id="sp0045"><p><italic toggle="yes">Source</italic>: INSIGHT Clinical Research Network.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0110">The association between SUD and sepsis was significant for most racial/ethnic patient groups but not non-Hispanic Black patients; tests of difference between racial/ethnic groups were significant (e.g., interaction term between non-Hispanic white and Black <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.009). The association between SUD and ventilation was significant for most racial/ethnic patient groups but not non-Hispanic Black patients (e.g., interaction term between non-Hispanic Black and Hispanic/Latino <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.026). SUD was associated with higher risk of death among non-Hispanic white and Asian/Pacific Islander patients, where this association was strongest.</p><p id="p0115">The association between AUD and sepsis was significant for all racial/ethnic patient groups, but the association was negative for non-Hispanic Black patients (e.g., interaction term between non-Hispanic white and Black <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.014). AUD was associated with increased risk of ventilation among Hispanic/Latino and Asian/Pacific Islander patients, for whom this association was strongest (e.g., interaction term between Hispanic/Latino and Asian/Pacific Islander <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.013).</p><p id="p0120">The association between OUD and hospitalization was significant for all racial/ethnic patient groups except Asian/Pacific Islander, and the association was strongest among non-Hispanic white patients (e.g., interaction term between non-Hispanic white and Hispanic/Latino <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.039). OUD was significantly associated with increased risk of ventilation for Hispanic/Latino and Asian/Pacific Islander patients, for whom this association was strongest (e.g., interaction term between Hispanic/Latino and Asian/Pacific Islander <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.008).</p><p id="p0125">Racial differences in associations between CAUD and COUD and most adverse COVID-19 outcomes were not identified. COUD was not associated with increased risk of ventilation for any racial/ethnic patient groups except for other/multi-racial (e.g., interaction term between Hispanic/Latino and other/multi-racial <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.010).</p><p id="p0130">The association between history of drug overdose and sepsis was significant for all racial/ethnic patient groups except Asian/Pacific Islander and was strongest for non-Hispanic white and other/multi-racial patients (e.g., interaction term between non-Hispanic white and Black <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.020). History of overdose was associated with increased risk of ventilation for all racial/ethnic patient groups and was strongest for non-Hispanic white and other/multi-racial patients (e.g., interaction term between non-Hispanic white and Black <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.016).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0050"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0135">This retrospective study of over 116,000 patients with COVID-19 across five healthcare systems in NYC examined associations of SUD and drug overdose history with COVID-19 severity across a large and diverse patient sample. To understand patient race/ethnicity as an effect modifier, we disaggregated analyses by race/ethnicity and tested for differences in the association between SUDs and adverse outcomes between race/ethnicity groups. Overall, a history of SUDs&#8212;in particular, OUD and prior drug overdose&#8212;were substantial risk factors for adverse COVID-19 outcomes, including mortality. This finding complements and corroborates prior findings by adding supportive data from a large clinical sample in a COVID-19 epicenter (<xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">Allen et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0220" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p id="p0140">Among race/ethnicity groups, non-Hispanic Black and Hispanic/Latino patients had higher prevalence of both SUDs and severe COVID-19 outcomes compared to patients of other race/ethnicity groups in our overall sample, as well as among patients with SUD and overdose histories. This is consistent with prior work demonstrating racial and ethnic disparities in the prevalence of COVID-19 and drug overdose death in NYC (<xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Ogedegbe et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">Allen et al., 2019</xref>), highlighting the urgency of healthcare system prioritization of racial equity in overdose intervention and response (<xref rid="bb0140" ref-type="bibr">Kunins, 2020</xref>).</p><p id="p0145">Among those with histories of any SUD, non-Hispanic Black patients had significantly lower sepsis and ventilation risk compared to other race/ethnicity groups, consistent with prior work that identified reduced risk of in-hospital complications among non-Hispanic Black COVID-19 patients in NYC (<xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Ogedegbe et al., 2020</xref>), despite increased overall out-of-hospital mortality (<xref rid="bb0250" ref-type="bibr">Zhong et al., 2022</xref>). This discrepancy may reflect pervasive racial and ethnic inequities in social determinants of health (e.g., housing, occupation, and access to healthcare) (<xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Ogedegbe et al., 2020</xref>), measured impacts of which persist across socioeconomic strata (<xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">Feldman and Bassett, 2021</xref>). Similarly lower risk of adverse outcomes was observed for non-Hispanic Black patients compared to other race/ethnicity groups among patients with AUD, despite a higher prevalence of AUD in this sample relative to other race/ethnicity groups, which may reflect similar disparities in access to timely care.</p><p id="p0150">Notably, cannabis and cocaine use disorders were not associated with adverse COVID-19 outcomes within our sample aside from hospitalization. For these SUD exposures, we did not detect evidence of effect modification by patient race/ethnicity. These findings are consistent with prior work identifying no significant relationship between cocaine use disorder and adverse COVID-19 outcomes in an analysis of Veterans Health Administration EHRs (<xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">Hasin et al., 2022</xref>). While not assessed in our analysis, prior work has identified an association between cocaine use disorder and COVID-19 test positivity and other risk factors (e.g., respiratory disease and diabetes) (<xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">Hasin et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">Board et al., 2022</xref>), suggesting that patients with COUD may be susceptible to other health conditions. Emergent work has identified that COVID-19 is associated with increased risk of future endocarditis among patients with COUD (<xref rid="bb0225" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2022a</xref>); future research is needed to better understand the long-term impacts of COVID-19 for high-risk patient groups with multiple comorbidities.</p><p id="p0155">History of OUD and drug overdose were the strongest risk factors for mortality. However, we did not detect significant differences in risk of mortality between race/ethnicity groups within either of these patient subgroups. Thus, patients with OUD and/or past overdose may constitute uniformly high-risk populations. Future research is necessary to understand mechanisms underlying this risk, including, but not limited to, the potential roles of complex medical histories (i.e., Are these patients sicker?), presentation timing after COVID-19 infection (i.e., Are these patients receiving COVID-19 treatment later than other patients?), and access to and quality of care (i.e., Are there economic or social/stigma barriers to high quality care for these patients?).</p><p id="p0160">Our findings around OUD and overdose as increased risk factors for mortality are suggestive of potential policy strategies that can jointly increase access to care, reduce patient OUD relapse and opioid overdose risk, and broadly address health disparities, such expanded eligibility for methadone take-home doses implemented in response to the COVID-19 pandemic and expanded access to long-acting buprenorphine (<xref rid="bb0170" ref-type="bibr">Nguemeni Tiako, 2021</xref>). Findings demonstrate that racial and ethnicity segregation is associated with disparate access to methadone and buprenorphine treatment for OUD, with highly segregated non-Hispanic Black and Hispanic/Latino communities having higher density of methadone treatment and non-Hispanic white communities having higher density of office-based buprenorphine treatment (<xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">Goedel et al., 2020</xref>). In New York City, this pattern holds (<xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">Hansen et al., 2013</xref>). As such, regulations relaxing access to methadone treatment, which reduces both OUD relapse and overdose risk (<xref rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr">Sordo et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">Fareed et al., 2011</xref>), have the potential to simultaneously reduce health disparities while mitigating risks for high-need patient groups in the post-pandemic era.</p><p id="p0165">Clinical and public health providers also must address medical mistrust and legacies of community neglect to increase access to and utilization of emergency and preventive care (<xref rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr">Newman, 2022</xref>). Recent work has identified increased breakthrough infection risk among vaccinated patients with SUDs, although no racial/ethnic disparities in risk therein were yet identified (<xref rid="bb0230" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2022b</xref>). Triangulating these emergent findings with our study's identification of consistently higher prevalence of all adverse COVID-19 outcomes and SUDs among patients from historically oppressed racial/ethnic groups may offer support for the hypothesis that COVID-19 risk among patients with SUDs sits at the nexus of race and class as social determinants of health (<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Chowkwanyun and Reed Jr., 2020</xref>). Findings underscore the need for continued bolstering of vaccination and non-pharmaceutical interventions, as well as occupational risk mitigation strategies, as part of health equity promotion (<xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">Corbie-Smith, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0245" ref-type="bibr">Zhen-Duan et al., 2022</xref>). Given the exploratory nature of our work, future research is necessary to fully understand the complex relationship between race/ethnicity and COVID-19 risk for patients with SUDs.</p><sec id="s0055"><label>4.1</label><title>Limitations</title><p id="p0170">This study is subject to several limitations. First, use of EHR data for observational research may be subject to bias from informative presence, as patients with greater access to and contact with a given healthcare system will have more complete records (<xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">McGee et al., 2022</xref>). However, our use of data from five large healthcare systems serving different patient populations bolsters our confidence in interpretations. Second, our data lacked information on cause and manner of death, instead capturing deaths among patients for whom a discharge disposition of death was recorded as part of a COVID-19 encounter. Of all patients who died, a minority (4.1%) died outside of a COVID-19 inpatient encounter; these patients died within 14&#160;days of discharge from a COVID-19 encounter, consistent with other epidemiological and clinical studies of COVID-19 mortality (<xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">Levine et al., 2021</xref>). Third, due to small sample sizes by SUD and overdose exposures for Asian/Pacific Islander patients, estimates for this sub-group may be unstable, limiting our ability to interpret findings for this group. Fourth, data were not available on NYC's public hospital system, and findings are not representative of the SUD risk for the NYC population overall. One potential artifact of this is the lower prevalence of SUDs in our sample compared to general population estimates (<xref rid="bb0205" ref-type="bibr">Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration, 2021</xref>). Our analysis utilized ICD codes to identify diagnoses, and it is possible that SUD remains underreported in our sample due to SUD underreporting through EHRs (<xref rid="bb0235" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al., 2022</xref>). Likewise, although all hospital systems captured in our sample accept and treat patients with public insurance and uninsured patients, we did not have access to patient insurance status, so were unable to assess the degree to which coverage may have differed between these patients and the general NYC population.</p><p id="p0175">Fifth, patient data were not weighted to the NYC or US populations, which may introduce selection bias due to employment, income, or other aspects of socioeconomic status that affects health care outcomes. Sixth, we acknowledge that race/ethnicity remains a single and indirect measure of the social determinants of health (<xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">Dalsania et al., 2022</xref>). More precise measurement of these social determinants through additional variables&#8212;such as insurance status or the facility at which encounters occurred&#8212;may affect the strength of our conclusions and should be the subject of future research (<xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">Wadhera et al., 2020</xref>), as it is possible that racial and ethnic groups are likely to be heterogeneous with respect to these factors (<xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">Amuta-Jimenez et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">Kao, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">Bustamante et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p id="p0180">Seventh, we acknowledge that the retention of the other/multi-racial category in analyses may present challenges to clinical and public health interpretation. However, we elected to retain this category to remain consistent with guidance for the reporting of race/ethnicity in epidemiological and medical studies (<xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">Flanagin et al., 2021</xref>), as well as to respect that patients may self-identify as multi-racial or as part of a racial or ethnicity group that does not conform to the categories captured by standard EHRs. Eighth, to assess interaction between race/ethnicity and SUD on risk of adverse COVID-19 outcomes, we conducted multiple interaction tests between different racial/ethnic groups (<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">Bender and Lange, 2001</xref>). Given the exploratory nature of this study, we elected to report all findings after correction for a 5% FDR using the Benjamini-Hochberg procedure (<xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">Benjamini and Hochberg, 1995</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0060"><label>5</label><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0185">This retrospective study of EHRs from the five largest private healthcare systems in NYC finds that SUD and overdose histories are significant risk factors for a range of severe COVID-19 outcomes. Although, exploratory, our study is the first to disaggregate the risks of adverse COVID-19 outcomes associated with SUDs by race, identifying group-specific SUD risk factors. Although we interpret findings cautiously, this study can guide future research on COVID-19 severity among patients with SUDs and provide emergent insight into the role of race/ethnicity as an effect modifier for COVID-19 severity.</p></sec><sec id="s0065"><title>Funding sources</title><p id="p0190">This publication was supported by the <funding-source id="gts0005"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100006108</institution-id><institution>National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (UL1TR001873). Bennett Allen received support from the <funding-source id="gts0010"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000026</institution-id><institution>National Institute on Drug Abuse</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (T32DA007233). Brandy F. Henry received support from the <funding-source id="gts0015"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000026</institution-id><institution>National Institute on Drug Abuse</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (T32DA037801). Frances R. Levin received support from the <funding-source id="gts0020"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000026</institution-id><institution>National Institute on Drug Abuse</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>, <funding-source id="gts0025"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100006108</institution-id><institution>National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>, <funding-source id="gts0030"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000058</institution-id><institution>Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>, and US World Meds. Diana Martinez received support from the <funding-source id="gts0035"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000026</institution-id><institution>National Institute on Drug Abuse</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (K24DA050087). Katharina Schultebraucks received support from the <funding-source id="gts0040"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000050</institution-id><institution>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (R01HL156134) and <funding-source id="gts0002">National Institute of Mental Health</funding-source> (R01MH129856).</p></sec><sec id="s0070"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0195"><bold>Bennett Allen:</bold> Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Project administration, Writing &#8211; original draft. <bold>Cale Basaraba:</bold> Data curation, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Project administration. <bold>Thomas Corbeil:</bold> Data curation, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Project administration. <bold>Bianca Rivera:</bold> Formal analysis, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. <bold>Frances R. Levin:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Supervision, Funding acquisition. <bold>Diana M. Martinez:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Supervision, Funding acquisition. <bold>Katharina Schultebraucks:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Investigation. <bold>Brandy F. Henry:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. <bold>Harold A. Pincus:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Supervision. <bold>Caroline Arout:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Project administration. <bold>Noa Krawczyk:</bold> Conceptualization, Investigation, Methodology, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Supervision.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title><p id="p0200">Dr. Levin&#160;receives research support from Aelis Pharma&#160;and&#160;medication from Indivior for research and royalties from APA publishing. In addition, she served as a nonpaid member of a Scientific Advisory Board for Alkermes, Indivior, Novartis, Teva, and US WorldMeds and is a consultant to Major League Baseball. Dr. Krawczyk is involved in ongoing opioid litigation. Dr. Pincus has served on clinical advisory committees for AbleTo, Cerebral, Magellan Studio, and Eleos. All other authors report no conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bi0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bb0005"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Acosta</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Racial and ethnic disparities in rates of COVID-19-associated hospitalization, intensive care unit admission, and in-hospital death in the United States from March 2020 to February 2021</article-title><source>JAMA Netw. Open</source><volume>4</volume><issue>10</issue><year>Oct 1 2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2130479</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.30479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8531997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34673962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0010"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>F.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cisewski</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossen</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>P S. Provisional drug overdose death counts. National Center for Health Statistics, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</part-title><year>2023</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0015"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nolan</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunins</surname><given-names>H.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paone</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Racial differences in opioid overdose deaths in New York City, 2017</article-title><source>JAMA Intern. Med.</source><volume>179</volume><issue>4</issue><year>Apr 1 2019</year><fpage>576</fpage><lpage>578</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2018.7700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30742218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6450294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0020"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Shahawy</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hochman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krawczyk</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of substance use disorders and drug overdose with adverse COVID-19 outcomes in New York City: January-October 2020</article-title><source>J. Public Health (Oxf).</source><volume>43</volume><issue>3</issue><year>Sep 22 2021</year><fpage>462</fpage><lpage>465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pubmed/fdaa241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33367823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7799011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0025"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amuta-Jimenez</surname><given-names>A.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health disparities and the heterogeneity of Blacks/African Americans in the United States: why should we care?</article-title><source>Health Promot. Pract.</source><volume>21</volume><issue>4</issue><year>Jul 2020</year><fpage>492</fpage><lpage>495</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1524839919895507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31876190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0030"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Askari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuazon</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mantha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>A. H. Unintentional Drug Poisoning (Overdose) Deaths in New York City in 2021. Vol. 133. New York City Department of Health and Mental Hygiene</part-title><year>2023</year><comment>Epi Data Brief</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0035"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>I.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Buuren</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Missing data in clinical research: a tutorial on multiple imputation</article-title><source>Can. J. Cardiol.</source><volume>37</volume><issue>9</issue><year>Sep 2021</year><fpage>1322</fpage><lpage>1331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cjca.2020.11.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33276049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8499698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0040"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adjusting for multiple testing--when and how?</article-title><source>J. Clin. Epidemiol.</source><volume>54</volume><issue>4</issue><year>Apr 2001</year><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0895-4356(00)00314-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11297884</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0045"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title><source>J. R. Stat. Soc. Ser. B Methodol.</source><volume>57</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1995</year><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>300</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0050"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Board</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for COVID-19 among persons with substance use disorder (PWSUD) with hospital visits - United States, April 2020-December 2020</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend.</source><volume>232</volume><year>Mar 1 2022</year><fpage>109297</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2022.109297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35033956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8747842</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0055"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rizzo</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heterogeneity in health insurance coverage among US Latino adults</article-title><source>J. Gen. Intern. Med.</source><volume>24 Suppl 3</volume><issue>Suppl. 3</issue><year>Nov 2009</year><fpage>561</fpage><lpage>566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-009-1069-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19842007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2764037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0060"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cartus</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macmadu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Forecasted and observed drug overdose deaths in the US during the COVID-19 pandemic in 2020</article-title><source>JAMA Netw. Open</source><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><year>Mar 1 2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e223418</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.3418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8938716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35311967</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0065"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chowkwanyun</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Racial health disparities and covid-19 - caution and context</article-title><source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source><volume>383</volume><issue>3</issue><year>Jul 16 2020</year><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMp2012910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32374952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0070"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corbie-Smith</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaccine hesitancy is a scapegoat for structural racism</article-title><source>JAMA Health Forum.</source><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><year>Mar 1 2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e210434</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamahealthforum.2021.0434</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36218456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0075"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corraini</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dekkers</surname><given-names>O.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandenbroucke</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect modification, interaction and mediation: an overview of theoretical insights for clinical investigators</article-title><source>Clin. Epidemiol.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/clep.S129728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28652815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5476432</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0080"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalsania</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fastiggi</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahlam</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The relationship between social determinants of health and racial disparities in COVID-19 mortality</article-title><source>J. Racial Ethn. Health Disparities</source><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><year>Feb 2022</year><fpage>288</fpage><lpage>295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40615-020-00952-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33403652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7785288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0085"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fareed</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vayalapalli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stout</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casarella</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drexler</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of methadone maintenance treatment on heroin craving, a literature review</article-title><source>J. Addict. Dis.</source><volume>30</volume><issue>1</issue><year>Jan 2011</year><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10550887.2010.531672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21218308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0090"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bassett</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variation in COVID-19 mortality in the US by race and ethnicity and educational attainment</article-title><source>JAMA Netw. Open</source><volume>4</volume><issue>11</issue><year>Nov 1 2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2135967</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.35967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8611482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34812846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0095"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flanagin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Updated guidance on the reporting of race and ethnicity in medical and science journals</article-title><source>Jama.</source><volume>326</volume><issue>7</issue><year>Aug 17 2021</year><fpage>621</fpage><lpage>627</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2021.13304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34402850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0100"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goedel</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cerd&#225;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadland</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>B.D.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of racial/ethnic segregation with treatment capacity for opioid use disorder in counties in the United States</article-title><source>JAMA Netw. Open</source><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><year>Apr 1 2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e203711</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.3711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7177200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32320038</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0105"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Groenwold</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>I.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donders</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moons</surname><given-names>K.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Missing covariate data in clinical research: when and when not to use the missing-indicator method for analysis</article-title><source>Cmaj.</source><volume>184</volume><issue>11</issue><year>Aug 7 2012</year><fpage>1265</fpage><lpage>1269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1503/cmaj.110977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22371511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3414599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0110"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>H.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Case</surname><given-names>B.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertollo</surname><given-names>D.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DiRocco</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galanter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variation in use of buprenorphine and methadone treatment by racial, ethnic, and income characteristics of residential social areas in New York City</article-title><source>J. Behav. Health Serv. Res.</source><volume>40</volume><issue>3</issue><year>Jul 2013</year><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11414-013-9341-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23702611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3818282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0115"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasin</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olfson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Substance use disorders and COVID-19: an analysis of nation-wide Veterans Health Administration electronic health records</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend.</source><volume>234</volume><year>May 1 2022</year><fpage>109383</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2022.109383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35279457</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8891118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0120"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Disease-specific factors associated with readmissions or mortality after hospital discharge in COVID-19 patients: a retrospective cohort study</article-title><source>J. Gen. Intern. Med.</source><volume>37</volume><issue>15</issue><year>Nov 2022</year><fpage>3973</fpage><lpage>3978</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-022-07610-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36104593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9473458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0125"><element-citation publication-type="other" id="rf0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>INSIGHT Clinical Research Network</surname></name></person-group><comment>Updated 2021</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://insightcrn.org/our-data" id="ir0010">https://insightcrn.org/our-data</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0130"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with ethnic differences in health insurance coverage and type among Asian Americans</article-title><source>J. Community Health</source><volume>35</volume><issue>2</issue><year>Apr 2010</year><fpage>142</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10900-009-9209-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20013061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0135"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krawczyk</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basaraba</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 complications among patients with opioid use disorder: a retrospective cohort study across five major NYC hospital systems</article-title><source>Addiction.</source><year>Dec 2 2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/add.16105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9878119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36459420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0140"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunins</surname><given-names>H.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural racism and the opioid overdose epidemic: the need for antiracist public health practice</article-title><source>J. Public Health Manag. Pract.</source><volume>26</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/phh.0000000000001168</pub-id><comment>May/Jun</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32235203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0145"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipsitz</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Co</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dykes</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samal</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Derivation of a clinical risk score to predict 14-day occurrence of hypoxia, ICU admission, and death among patients with coronavirus disease 2019</article-title><source>J. Gen. Intern. Med.</source><volume>36</volume><issue>3</issue><year>Mar 2021</year><fpage>730</fpage><lpage>737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-020-06353-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33274414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7713904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0150"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>L.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Race, ethnicity, community-level socioeconomic factors, and risk of COVID-19 in the United States and the United Kingdom</article-title><source>EClinicalMedicine.</source><volume>38</volume><year>Aug 2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101029</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.101029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8285255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34308322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0155"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Magesh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Disparities in COVID-19 outcomes by race, ethnicity, and socioeconomic status: a systematic-review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>JAMA Netw. Open</source><volume>4</volume><issue>11</issue><year>Nov 1 2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2134147</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.34147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8586903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34762110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0160"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGee</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haneuse</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coull</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weisskopf</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rotem</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the nature of informative presence bias in analyses of electronic health records</article-title><source>Epidemiology.</source><volume>33</volume><issue>1</issue><year>Jan 1 2022</year><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ede.0000000000001432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34711733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8633193</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0165"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moving beyond mistrust: centering institutional change by decentering the white analytical lens</article-title><source>Bioethics.</source><volume>36</volume><issue>3</issue><year>Mar 2022</year><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bioe.12992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34969146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0170"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguemeni Tiako</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Addressing racial &amp; socioeconomic disparities in access to medications for opioid use disorder amid COVID-19</article-title><source>J. Subst. Abus. Treat.</source><volume>122</volume><year>Mar 2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">108214</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2020.108214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7685132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33248862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0175"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0175"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogedegbe</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ravenell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessment of racial/ethnic disparities in hospitalization and mortality in patients with COVID-19 in New York City</article-title><source>JAMA Netw. Open</source><volume>3</volume><issue>12</issue><year>Dec 1 2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2026881</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.26881</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7718605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33275153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0180"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0180"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrilli</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with hospital admission and critical illness among 5279 people with coronavirus disease 2019 in New York City: prospective cohort study</article-title><source>Bmj.</source><volume>369</volume><year>May 22 2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">m1966</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.m1966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7243801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32444366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0185"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0185"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raifman</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raifman</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disparities in the population at risk of severe illness from COVID-19 by race/ethnicity and income</article-title><source>Am. J. Prev. Med.</source><volume>59</volume><issue>1</issue><year>Jul 2020</year><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2020.04.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32430225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7183932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0190"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0190"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosales</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yermash</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Persons from racial and ethnic minority groups receiving medication for opioid use disorder experienced increased difficulty accessing harm reduction services during COVID-19</article-title><source>J. Subst. Abus. Treat.</source><volume>132</volume><year>Jan 2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">108648</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2021.108648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8566093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34742607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0195"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0195"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scholl</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seth</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kariisa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug and opioid-involved overdose deaths - United States, 2013-2017</article-title><source>MMWR Morb. Mortal. Wkly Rep.</source><volume>67</volume><issue>5152</issue><year>Jan 4 2018</year><fpage>1419</fpage><lpage>1427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm675152e1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30605448</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6334822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0200"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0200"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sordo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrio</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bravo</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mortality risk during and after opioid substitution treatment: systematic review and meta-analysis of cohort studies</article-title><source>Bmj.</source><volume>357</volume><year>Apr 26 2017</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">j1550</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.j1550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5421454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28446428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0205"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0205"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration</surname></name></person-group><part-title><italic toggle="yes">Key substance use and mental health indicators in the United States: Results from the 2020 National Survey on Drug Use and Health</italic>. Vol. HHS Publication No. PEP21-07-01-003. Center for Behavioral Health Statistics and Quality, Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration</part-title><year>2021</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0210"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0210"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vai</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazza</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delli Colli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mental disorders and risk of COVID-19-related mortality, hospitalisation, and intensive care unit admission: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Lancet Psychiatry</source><volume>8</volume><issue>9</issue><year>Sep 2021</year><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>812</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s2215-0366(21)00232-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34274033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8285121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0215"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0215"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wadhera</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wadhera</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaba</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Variation in COVID-19 hospitalizations and deaths across New York City Boroughs</article-title><source>Jama.</source><volume>323</volume><issue>21</issue><year>Jun 2 2020</year><fpage>2192</fpage><lpage>2195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.7197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32347898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7191469</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0220"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0220"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaelber</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Volkow</surname><given-names>N.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 risk and outcomes in patients with substance use disorders: analyses from electronic health records in the United States</article-title><source>Mol. Psychiatry</source><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><year>Jan 2021</year><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41380-020-00880-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32929211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7488216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0225"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0225"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Volkow</surname><given-names>N.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>P.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaelber</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of COVID-19 with endocarditis in patients with cocaine or opioid use disorders in the US</article-title><source>Mol. Psychiatry</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41380-022-01903-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9918660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36510003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0230"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0230"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>P.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Volkow</surname><given-names>N.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased risk for COVID-19 breakthrough infection in fully vaccinated patients with substance use disorders in the United States between December 2020 and August 2021</article-title><source>World Psychiatry</source><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wps.20921</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34612005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8661963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0235"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0235"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>O.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>A.H.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Washington</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoggatt</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of substance use disorder diagnosis rates from electronic health record data with substance use disorder prevalence rates reported in surveys across sociodemographic groups in the veterans health administration</article-title><source>JAMA Netw. Open</source><volume>5</volume><issue>6</issue><year>Jun 1 2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2219651</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.19651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9247731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35771574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0240"><element-citation publication-type="other" id="rf0240"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>World Health Organization</surname></name></person-group><article-title>WHO Coronavirus (COVID-19) Dashboard. Updated February 7</article-title><comment>Accessed November 19, 2021</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://covid19.who.int/" id="ir0015">https://covid19.who.int/</ext-link><year>2023</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0245"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0245"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhen-Duan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gade</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falgas-Bagu&#233;</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sue</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeJonckheere</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alegr&#237;a</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using a structural vulnerability framework to understand the impact of COVID-19 on the lives of Medicaid beneficiaries receiving substance use treatment in New York City</article-title><source>Health Serv. Res.</source><volume>57</volume><issue>5</issue><year>Oct 2022</year><fpage>1104</fpage><lpage>1111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1475-6773.13975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35340033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9111318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0250"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0250"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwizera</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muennig</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neighborhood disparities in COVID-19 outcomes in New York city over the first two waves of the outbreak</article-title><source>Ann. Epidemiol.</source><volume>70</volume><year>Jun 2022</year><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annepidem.2022.04.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35487451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9042413</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="s0075" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0205">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ec0005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Tables</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Image 1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="da0005"><title>Data availability</title><p id="p0020">The authors do not have permission to share data.</p></sec><ack id="ac0005"><title>Acknowledgement</title><p id="p0255">This work was conducted through use of data from the INSIGHT Clinical Research Network and supported in part by the Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute (PCORI) PCORnet grant to the <funding-source id="gts0001">INSIGHT Clinical Research Network</funding-source> (RI-CRN-2020-004).</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="s0080" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0210">Supplementary data to this article can be found online at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ypmed.2023.107533" id="ir0005">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ypmed.2023.107533</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>