<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Transl Cancer Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Transl Cancer Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4137</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">transcancres</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TCR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Translational Cancer Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2218-676X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2219-6803</issn><publisher><publisher-name>AME Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10331452</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10331452.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10331452</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10331452</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37434692</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/tcr-22-2049</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">tcr-12-06-1452</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The association between cholecystectomy and the risk of colorectal cancer: an updated systematic review and meta-analysis of cohort studies</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu</surname><given-names initials="L">Lin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="W">Weina</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names initials="W">Wanlei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names initials="D">Doudou</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="afn2" ref-type="author-notes">^</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Endoscopy Center, Qingdao Hospital</institution>, <institution>University of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences (Qingdao Municipal Hospital)</institution>, <addr-line>Qingdao</addr-line>, <country country="cn">China</country>;</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Gastroenterology, Qingdao Hospital</institution>, <institution>University of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences (Qingdao Municipal Hospital)</institution>, <addr-line>Qingdao</addr-line>, <country country="cn">China</country>;</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Traditional Chinese Medicine</institution>, <institution>Qingdao Central Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Qingdao</addr-line>, <country country="cn">China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="afn1"><p><italic toggle="yes">Contributions:</italic> (I) Conception and design: Y Song, L Mu; (II) Administrative support: D Hu; (III) Provision of study materials or patients: L Mu, W Li; (IV) Collection and assembly of data: D Hu, Y Song; (V) Data analysis and interpretation: L Mu, Y Song; (VI) Manuscript writing: All authors; (VII) Final approval of manuscript: All authors.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><italic toggle="yes">Correspondence to:</italic> Yang Song, MMed. Department of Gastroenterology, Qingdao Hospital, University of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences (Qingdao Municipal Hospital), No. 1 Jiaozhou Road, Shibei District, Qingdao 266000, China. Email: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="derek_songyang@yeah.net">derek_songyang@yeah.net</email>.</corresp><fn id="afn2"><label>^</label><p>ORCID: 0000-0001-7993-8445.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>30</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue>6</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">440353</issue-id><fpage>1452</fpage><lpage>1465</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>30</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-07-12 11:25:16.183"><day>12</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>2023 Translational Cancer Research. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Translational Cancer Research.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><italic toggle="yes">Open Access Statement:</italic> This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 International License (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0), which permits the non-commercial replication and distribution of the article with the strict proviso that no changes or edits are made and the original work is properly cited (including links to both the formal publication through the relevant DOI and the license). See: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="tcr-12-06-1452.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The effect of cholecystectomy on the development of colorectal cancer (CRC) has prompted a large number of population-based studies. However, the results of these studies are debatable and inconclusive. Our aim in the present study was to conduct an updated systematic review and meta-analysis to explore the causality between cholecystectomy and CRC.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Cohort studies published in the PubMed, Web of Science, Embase, Medline, and Cochrane databases up to May 2022 were retrieved. Pooled relative risks (RRs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were analyzed using a random effects model.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Eighteen studies, involving 1,469,880 cholecystectomy and 2,356,238 non-cholecystectomy cases, were eligible for the final analysis. Cholecystectomy was not associated with the development of CRC (P=0.109), colon cancer (P=0.112), or rectal cancer (P=0.184). Subgroup analysis of sex, lag period, geographic region, and study quality revealed no significant differences in the relationship between cholecystectomy and CRC. Interestingly, cholecystectomy was significantly associated with right-sided colon cancer (RR =1.20, 95% CI: 1.04&#8211;1.38; P=0.010), especially in the cecum, the ascending colon and/or the hepatic flexure (RR =1.21, 95% CI: 1.05&#8211;1.40; P=0.007) but not in the transverse, descending, or sigmoid colon.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Cholecystectomy has no effect on the risk of CRC overall, but a harmful effect on the risk of right-sided colon cancer proximally.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords: </title><kwd>Cholecystectomy</kwd><kwd>colorectal cancer</kwd><kwd>cohort studies</kwd><kwd>meta-analysis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="sp1">the National Natural Science Foundation of China</funding-source><award-id rid="sp1">No. 81800543</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="ba" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Highlight box</title></caption><sec><title>Key findings</title><p>&#8226; Cholecystectomy has no effect on the overall risk of colorectal cancer (CRC), colon cancer (CC), or rectal cancer (RC), but does have a harmful effect on the risk of right-sided CC, especially in the cecum, ascending colon, and/or hepatic flexure.</p></sec><sec><title>What is known and what is new?</title><p>&#8226; Previous meta-analysis of cohort studies has demonstrated that cholecystectomy carries a high risk of CRC, CC and ascending CC, particularly in Western countries.</p><p>&#8226; This study indicates that cholecystectomy has a detrimental effect on the risk of right-sided CC, especially in the cecum, ascending colon, and/or hepatic flexure, but not on the risk of CRC, CC, or RC overall.</p></sec><sec><title>What is the implication, and what should change now?</title><p>&#8226; These results have critical implications that may warrant further investigation of colonoscopy surveillance strategies in patients undergoing cholecystectomy.</p></sec></boxed-text><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Colorectal cancer (CRC) has become the third most common cancer and the second leading cause of malignancy-related deaths worldwide (<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Large-scale epidemiological studies have identified several risk factors associated with CRC, including smoking, alcohol addiction, excessive consumption of red and processed meat, family history of CRC, obesity, male sex, and age (<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>-<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). However, the etiology of CRC remains debatable and obscure. Therefore, a major challenge in current research is to identify the possible causes of the initiation and progression of CRC.</p><p>Functions of the gallbladder include storing bile acids (BAs) and regulating the physiological homeostasis and enterohepatic circulation of BAs. For patients with gallstone disease (GSD), cholecystectomy, which is mostly performed laparoscopically, has become the first-line treatment (<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). However, surgical removal of the gallbladder can change the secretion rhythm of BAs (<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Furthermore, alternations in BA composition and concentration are characterized by the enhancement of bacterial dehydroxylation of cholic acid to deoxycholic acid (DCA), which is considered to be carcinogenic to the colonic epithelium (<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>).</p><p>There is controversy surrounding the results of cohort studies focusing on the association between cholecystectomy and CRC. A previous meta-analysis of cohort studies to demonstrate the pooled effect of cholecystectomy on CRC indicated that cholecystectomy carried a high risk of CRC, colon cancer (CC) and ascending CC, especially in Western countries (<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). However, previous meta-analysis had several limitations. An appropriate lag period was not taken into consideration and it should be adopted after cholecystectomy since CRC may already exist at the time the surgery is performed. In addition, significant heterogeneity was observed in the whole and subgroup analyses. These limitations resulted in more well-designed, population-based, confounding factors-adjusted cohort studies in recent years, which have added more solid evidence to the issue. Given the controversial results from previous studies and the need for further clarification, we performed an updated systematic review and meta-analysis of cohort studies to explore the association between cholecystectomy and CRC. We present this article in accordance with the PRISMA reporting checklist (available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://tcr.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/tcr-22-2049/rc" ext-link-type="uri">https://tcr.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/tcr-22-2049/rc</ext-link>) (<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Literature search strategy</title><p>This meta-analysis was registered on PROSPERO (ID: CRD42022332769). The review protocol was not published or submitted online. Published articles investigating the association between cholecystectomy and CRC published up to May 2022 were retrieved from the PubMed, Web of Science, Embase, Medline, and Cochrane Library databases. The search strategy was restricted to the English language and included the following terms: (&#8220;cholecystectomy&#8221; OR &#8220;cholecystectomies&#8221;) AND (&#8220;colorectal&#8221; OR &#8220;gastrointestinal&#8221;) AND (&#8220;carcinoma&#8221; OR &#8220;cancer&#8221; OR &#8220;neoplasm&#8221; OR &#8220;adenocarcinoma&#8221;) AND &#8220;cohort study&#8221;.</p></sec><sec><title>Selection criteria</title><p>The inclusion criteria were as follows: (I) a cohort study with original data provided, including hazard ratio (HR), relative risk (RR), incidence rate ratio, standardized incidence ratio (SIR), and the corresponding 95% confidence intervals (CIs), or data sufficient to compute these measures; (II) explored the effects of cholecystectomy on the development of CRC; (III) the exposure factor was a previous open or laparoscopic cholecystectomy; and (IV) the outcome of interest was the development of CRC. The exclusion criteria were as follows: (I) case reports/series, letters, reviews, guidelines, protocols, replies and cross-sectional studies; (II) studies which did not precisely report HRs and 95% CIs for the outcome; (III) studies with no original data or whose data were not calculable for the outcome; (IV) studies limited to specific populations, such as patients with inflammatory bowel disease or males or females only.</p><p>The titles and abstracts of the selected literature were separately screened by two authors (L Mu and W Li). Discrepancies in the review process were verified by the senior author (D Hu). The remaining articles were separately screened through a comprehensive reading of the full text. The reference lists of articles deemed relevant during the full-text review process were cross-checked to find any relevant studies.</p></sec><sec><title>Data extraction and quality assessment</title><p>Two researchers conducted the data extraction process independently (Y Song and L Mu). Discrepancies that arose between the two researchers during the data collection process were discussed and resolved through consultation with the senior author (D Hu). The basic features of all the relevant studies were recorded, including the author and publication year, study characteristics, diagnosis of cholecystectomy and CRC, outcome (CRC cases), and adjustments. The Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (NOS) (<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) was used to assess the study quality. We judged studies with a score of 7 to 9 to be of high quality, studies with a score of 4 to 6 to be of moderate quality, and studies with a score of 0 to 3 to be of low quality.</p><p>Two authors (Y Song and W Li) independently rated the certainty of the evidence using the GRADE system on the online GRADEpro software (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.gradepro.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.gradepro.org/</ext-link>) (<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). The GRADE system evaluates the certainty of a study in the following five dimensions: study limitations, consistency of effect, imprecision, indirectness, and publication bias (<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Using the GRADE system, the certainty of evidence in each dimension is categorized as: high, moderate, low, or very low quality.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>STATA software 17.0 (StataCorp LLC, College Station, TX, USA) was used to perform all data analyses. Pooled RRs and 95% CIs were computed from SIRs, incidence rate ratios, RRs, HRs, and 95% CIs using the DerSimonian and Laird method. For the studies with a time interval following cholecystectomy, RRs were extracted and computed from data with an appropriate lag period. Subgroup analysis was also conducted. The I<sup>2</sup> statistic was used to analyze heterogeneity (<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Significant heterogeneity was indicated by either P&lt;0.10 or an I<sup>2</sup> value &gt;50%. The presence of publication bias was verified by funnel plot and Egger&#8217;s test (<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). A sensitivity analysis was performed by removing each study in sequence to find the possible source of heterogeneity. P&lt;0.05 was considered as the significance level.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Study selection and characteristics</title><p>The flow diagram for literature selection is displayed in <xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig"><italic toggle="yes">Figure 1</italic></xref>. In total, 824 articles were identified through the database searches. Of these studies, 329 articles were excluded due to being duplicates. The remaining 495 articles were reviewed by title, and subsequently, 435 records were excluded for the following reasons: study aim not relevant (n=339); records not in English (n=53); case report/series, letter, review, guideline, protocol, or reply (n=34); case-control study (n=5); and basic science research (n=4). After further reading of the abstracts and full texts, 18 studies, involving a total of 1,469,880 cholecystectomy cases and 2,356,238 non-cholecystectomy cases, were eventually deemed eligible for inclusion (<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>-<xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="f1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The flow diagram for the search and selection processes of the meta-analysis.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="tcr-12-06-1452-f1.jpg"/></fig><p>The main characteristics of the included studies are displayed in <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 1</italic></xref>. Of the included studies, 11 were from Europe, 6 were from Asia, and 1 was from the USA. Most of the studies recruited cases either from general populations or from inpatient cohorts of individuals from healthcare programs or insurance systems. The identification of cholecystectomy was mostly based on International Classification of Diseases (ICD) codes, hospital medical records, and insurance claim codes, except in 1 study which used questionnaires (<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). The diagnosis of CRC was also mainly validated based on ICD codes (C18&#8211;C20). The results of data extraction and NOS scoring are displayed in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cdn.amegroups.cn/static/public/TCR-22-2049-Supplementary.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Table S1</ext-link>. The mean NOS score of the 18 studies was 7.11. The quality of 13 studies was high and that of the remaining 5 studies was moderate.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="t1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Characteristics of the studies included in the systematic review and meta-analysis</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="8.27%" span="1"/><col width="44.84%" span="1"/><col width="10.34%" span="1"/><col width="10.35%" span="1"/><col width="11.72%" span="1"/><col width="14.48%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Authors, year</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study characteristics</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Identification of CS</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosis of CRC</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome (CRC cases: CS/non-CS patients)</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjustment</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Linos <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1981, (<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort study (Rochester-Olmsted Epidemiology Program Project): 1681 CS cases (460 males and 1,221 females) at baseline</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Medical records</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Medical records</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">42/&#8211;</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Follow-up years: 13 years (mean)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Lag period: 6 months</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Adami <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1983, (<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective population-based cohort study: 16,773 CS patients (5,095 males and 11,678 females) at baseline</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">130/&#8211;</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Follow-up period: 11&#8211;14 completed years</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Lag period: none</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Adami <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1987, (<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective population-based cohort study: 16,439 CS patients (4,978 males and 11,461 females) at baseline</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">150/&#8211;</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Follow-up period: 14&#8211;17 completed years</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Lag period: none</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Nielsen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1991, (<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective cohort study: 3,425 CS individuals (857 males and 2,568 females) at baseline</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Icelandic Cancer Registry</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Icelandic Cancer Registry</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">57/&#8211;</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Follow-up period: 8&#8211;33 years</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Lag period: none</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Goldbohm <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1993, (<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective cohort study: 3,500 subjects (men: 1,688, 5.7% of gallstones and 4.7% of CS; women: 1,812, 14.7% of gallstones and 13.3% of CS) at baseline</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Questionnaire</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">53/408</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Age and large-bowel cancer in first-degree relatives</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Follow-up years: 3.3 years (mean)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Lag period: none</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Ekbom <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1993, (<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective population-based cohort study: 62,615 CS patients (20,745 males and 41,870 females) at baseline</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">633/&#8211;</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Follow-up end: until the end of 1987</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Lag period: 1 year</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Johansen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1996, (<xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort study: 42,098 GSD patients (72.4% with CS) at baseline</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Danish Classification of Surgical Procedures and Therapies</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">344/147</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Age, sex, and calendar year</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Follow-up years: 1&#8211;16 years</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Lag period: 1 year</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Lagergren <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2001, (<xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort study: 278,460 CS patients (90,987 males and 187,473 females) at baseline</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Swedish Classification of Operations and Major Procedures</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">3,425/&#8211;</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Follow-up years: 12.1 years (mean)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Lag period: 1 year</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Shao <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2005, (<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort study: 55,960 CS patients and 574,668 randomly selected controls at baseline</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">General Practice Research Database</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">General Practice Research Database</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">297/2,218</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Age</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Follow-up end: the first diagnosis of CRC, death, dropout, or the end of database entry (i.e., April 2002)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Lag period: 1 year</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Goldacre <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2005, (<xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort study: 39,254 CS individuals and 334,813 reference controls at baseline</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Hospital records</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Hospital records</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">505/3,731</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Follow-up end: the date of admission for cancer, or death, or March 31, 1999</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Lag period: 2 years</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Goldacre <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012, (<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort study: 327,460 CS individuals, 133,114 gallbladder disease individuals, and 3 million controls at baseline</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">2,245/3,622</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Age in 5-year bands, sex, time period in single calendar years, area deprivation score in quintiles, and region of residence</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Follow-up end: the date of the first record of colon cancer, death, or the end of the data file (March 31, 2008), whichever was the earliest</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Lag period: 1 year</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014, (<xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort study: 5,850 cholelithiasis patients with CS and 62,180 controls at baseline</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Registry for Catastrophic Illness Patient Database</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">67/76</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Sex, age, and comorbidities, such as diabetes mellitus, hyperlipidemia, hepatitis B infection, hepatitis C infection, menopause, and cirrhosis</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Follow-up years: not mentioned</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Lag period: none</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Shabanzadeh <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017, (<xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort study: 187 CS patients and 5,327 controls at baseline</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">11/183</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Age and sex</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Follow up years: 24.7 years (mean)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Lag period: no</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Lee <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018, (<xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort study: 11,362 CS patients and 696,301 non-CS controls at baseline</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">34/4,276</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Sex, diabetes mellitus, and inflammatory bowel disease</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Follow up years: 13.66 years (mean)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Lag period: 1 year</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020, (<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort study: 83,963 CS patients and 83,963 control subjects at baseline</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">638/1,170</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Age, gender, comorbidities of hypertension, diabetes mellitus, chronic kidney diseases, stroke, coronary artery disease, colorectal adenomas, and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Follow-up end: the development of CRC, death, withdrawal from the National Health Insurance program due to emigration or death, or 31 December, 2011</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Lag period: 6 months</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Kim <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020, (<xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort study: 3,588 CS patients at baseline</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Single hospital records</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Single hospital records</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">21/&#8211;</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Follow-up years: 15.0 (range, 0&#8211;146) months</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Lag period: 1 year</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Jung <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021, (<xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort study: 408,769 CS patients at baseline</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Insurance claims codes</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">1,773/&#8211;</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Follow-up years: 4.7 years (mean)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Lag period: 1 year</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Choi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2022, (<xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort study: A total of 123,295 control subjects and 123,925 age and sex-matched CS subjects at baseline</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Insurance claims codes</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">ICD code</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">1,078/1,003</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Age, sex, smoking status, body mass index, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, and dyslipidemia</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Follow-up years: 4.59 years (mean)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Lag period: 1 year</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>CS, cholecystectomy; CRC, colorectal cancer; ICD, International Classification of Diseases; GSD, gallstone disease.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Synthesis of the results</title><p>Synthesis of the studies&#8217; results was conducted using a random effects model. As shown in <xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig"><italic toggle="yes">Figure 2</italic></xref>, cholecystectomy exhibited no association with CRC (RR =1.12, 95% CI: 0.98&#8211;1.29; P=0.109; I<sup>2</sup>=95.0%). No statistically significant publication bias was detected through funnel plot analysis and Egger&#8217;s tests (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig"><italic toggle="yes">Figure 3</italic></xref>, P=0.411). A sensitivity analysis was also conducted, and the result was not affected by the removal of each study in sequence (<xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig"><italic toggle="yes">Figure 4</italic></xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="f2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Forest plot and pooled estimates of the effect of cholecystectomy on the risk of colorectal cancer. Weights are from a random effects model. CI, confidence interval; DL, DerSimonian and Laird.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="tcr-12-06-1452-f2.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="f3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Publication bias of the included studies. (A) Funnel plot for publication bias. (B) Egger&#8217;s test results. RR, relative risk; s.e., standard error.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="tcr-12-06-1452-f3.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="f4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Sensitivity analysis of the colorectal cancer risk associated with cholecystectomy. CI, confidence interval.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="tcr-12-06-1452-f4.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Subgroup analyses</title><p>Subgroup analyses were conducted based on sex, geographic region, lag period, study quality, time interval since cholecystectomy, and tumor location. Subgroup analyses of sex (male: P=0.365; female: P=0.274), geographic region (Europe: P=0.071; Asia: P=0.471; USA: P=0.101), lag period (with lag period: P=0.238; no lag period: P=0.237), study quality (high: P=0.243; moderate or low: P=0.215) showed no significant differences in the relationship between cholecystectomy and CRC (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 2</italic></xref>). Regarding the time interval after surgery, cholecystectomy was not associated with CC or rectal cancer (RC) in patients who had undergone cholecystectomy &#8804;4 years or &#8805;5 years (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 2</italic></xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="t2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Subgroup analyses of the association between cholecystectomy and the risk of colorectal cancer, stratified by sex, geographic region, lag period, study quality, and time interval since cholecystectomy</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="18.26%" span="1"/><col width="17.21%" span="1"/><col width="18.29%" span="1"/><col width="15.05%" span="1"/><col width="13.98%" span="1"/><col width="17.21%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subgroup</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR (95% CI)</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test for overall effect (P value)</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of studies</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterogeneity I<sup>2</sup>, %</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 (0.87&#8211;1.46)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.365</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 (0.91&#8211;1.41)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.274</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geographic region</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 (0.95&#8211;1.78)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Europe</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.99&#8211;1.16)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asia</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 (0.77&#8211;1.76)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.471</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lag period</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lag period</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 (0.94&#8211;1.31)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.238</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No lag period</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 (0.92&#8211;1.43)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.237</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study quality</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.94&#8211;1.26)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.243</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate or low</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 (0.91&#8211;1.55)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.215</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Time interval since cholecystectomy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;1&#8211;4 years</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 (0.90&#8211;1.73)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.178</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 (0.94&#8211;1.73)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.112</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#8805;5 years</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.98&#8211;1.15)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.82&#8211;1.12)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.572</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>RR, relative risk; CI, confidential interval; CC, colon cancer; RC, rectal cancer.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The subgroup analysis of tumor location revealed no association of cholecystectomy with CC overall (P=0.112), RC (P=0.184) or left-sided CC (P=0.836) (<xref rid="t3" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 3</italic></xref>; <xref rid="f5" ref-type="fig"><italic toggle="yes">Figure 5A</italic></xref>). However, the association was significant for the risk of right-sided CC (RR =1.20; 95% CI: 1.04&#8211;1.38; P=0.010; I<sup>2</sup>=64.6%; <xref rid="f5" ref-type="fig"><italic toggle="yes">Figure 5B</italic></xref>), especially in the cecum, the ascending colon, and/or the hepatic flexure (RR =1.21; 95% CI: 1.05&#8211;1.40; P=0.007; I<sup>2</sup>=49.3%), but not in the transverse (P=0.397), descending (P=0.769), or sigmoid (P=0.635) colon (<xref rid="t3" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 3</italic></xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="t3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Subgroup analyses of the association between cholecystectomy and the risk of colorectal cancer, stratified by tumor location</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="25.23%" span="1"/><col width="22.54%" span="1"/><col width="19.59%" span="1"/><col width="16.08%" span="1"/><col width="16.56%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subgroup</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR (95% CI)</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test for overall effect (P value)</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of studies</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterogeneity I<sup>2</sup>, %</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.98&#8211;1.19)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.112</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Left-sided </td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.88&#8211;1.18)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.836</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Right-sided </td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 (1.04&#8211;1.38)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Cecum/ascending colon/hepatic flexure</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21 (1.05&#8211;1.40)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Transverse</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.94&#8211;1.18)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.397</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Descending</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.64&#8211;1.85)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.769</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Sigmoid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.94&#8211;1.10)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.635</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.86&#8211;1.03)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.184</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.7</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>CC, colon cancer; RC, rectal cancer; RR, relative risk; CI, confidential interval.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="f5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Forest plot and pooled estimates of the effect of cholecystectomy on the risk of left-sided colon cancer (A) and right-sided colon cancer (B). Weights are from a random effects model. CI, confidence interval; DL, DerSimonian and Laird.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="tcr-12-06-1452-f5.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>In the current study, we explored the association of cholecystectomy with the development of CRC. The results show that the overall risk of CRC was comparable between patients with cholecystectomy and those without in the general population, as well as in subgroup analysis for sex, lag period, study quality, and geographic origin. However, a positive association was identified between cholecystectomy and the risk of right-sided CC, especially in the cecum, the ascending colon, and/or the hepatic flexure. These results have critical implications that may warrant further investigation for colonoscopy surveillance strategies in individuals who undergo cholecystectomy.</p><p>Cholecystectomy has remained one of the most frequently performed and effective treatments for gallbladder diseases, especially symptomatic GSD. However, increasing concern has been raised regarding the long-term risks of cholecystectomy, such as the development of CRC. Numerous case-control and cohort studies, as well as a previous meta-analysis, have provided substantial evidence of an increased CRC risk following cholecystectomy. Several mechanisms may account for this possible association. First, the circadian rhythmicity of BAs after cholecystectomy is diminished, resulting in continuous bile secretion into the bowel (<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Second, patients who undergo cholecystectomy have been found to exhibit higher concentrations of total fecal BA and DCA (<xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Third, constant exposure to high levels of BAs might cause DNA damage, such as oxidative stress, oncogene mutations, and microsatellite instability (<xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). Fourth, the composition and abundance of gut microbiota becomes altered after cholecystectomy, which is characterized by an elevated abundance of the <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> phylum, specifically members of the <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidaceae</italic> family and the genus <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroides </italic>(<xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>), as well as <italic toggle="yes">Blautia obeum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Veillonella parvula </italic>(<xref rid="r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>).</p><p>However, the results of studies regarding the above mechanisms remain disputable. For example, several studies have concluded that cholecystectomy has no prominent effect on the concentration and composition of BAs (<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). This controversy may be attributable to differences in subjects in the control group. In some studies, the control group, namely non-cholecystectomy group, is composed of individuals with normal gallbladder, patients with asymptomatic gall stones, gallbladder polyps, etc. Keren <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> reported that cholecystectomy-treated patients exhibited higher levels of BAs than the controls without GSD or cholecystectomy, but had comparable concentrations to patients with GSD (<xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Further analysis indicated that levels of primary and secondary BAs did not differ among the three groups (<xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Furthermore, as for microbiota change in relation to cholecystectomy, current studies mainly focused on the analysis limited to phylum and genus, while the real pro-carcinogenic influence of microbiota should be ascribed to specific species, such as the pro-carcinogenic effect of enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroides fragilis </italic>in CRC (<xref rid="r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>).</p><p>The main findings of the current study were that cholecystectomy was only associated with an increased risk of right-sided CC, especially in the cecum, the ascending colon, and/or the hepatic flexure, but not with the overall risk of CRC, CC, RC, or cancers in other segments of the colon. These findings represent interesting results which differ from those of a previous meta-analysis of cohort studies (<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). The preference of right-sided CC after cholecystectomy partially coincided with previous descriptive analysis indicating that highest proportion of ascending CC (10.5%) was observed following cholecystectomy (<xref rid="r44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), and with results of previous meta-analyses of case-control studies (<xref rid="r45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="r46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). One possible explanation for these findings is that the absorption of secondary BAs is more significant proximally than distally (<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). The distribution of BA in different segments of the colon might be another possible explanation. In a human study, the levels of total tissue-bound BA, especially chenodeoxycholic acid, were found to be higher in the ascending colon than in other parts of the colon (<xref rid="r47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). In animal studies, the levels of DCA and hyodeoxycholic acid in the cecum (16% and 21%, respectively) were higher than those in the colon (8% and 17%, respectively) (<xref rid="r48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Based on the pro-carcinogenic effect of DCA on CRC (<xref rid="r49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="r50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>), it was postulated that the proximal part of the large intestine was continuously exposed to higher concentrations of deleterious BAs, which may account for the predilection of right-sided CC.</p><p>Our meta-analysis has several limitations that warrant consideration. First, the certainty of the evidence was low according to assessment of several limitations, indirectness, and imprecision. For several study limitations, the evidence was downgraded due to, for example, the risk of selection bias or suspected potential reporting bias. When considering possible biases, imbalances between study groups, such as genetic differences that may lead to susceptibility to CRC and environmental and lifestyle-related factors, may represent potential sources of biases in this study. In addition, in some studies, the definition of the non-cholecystectomized group was unclear. Since patients with GSD and non-cholecystectomized individuals without GSD showed distinctions in BA concentration and composition, as well as other differences, discrepancies may have existed during the comparison.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This updated meta-analysis shows that while cholecystectomy has no effect on the overall risk of CRC, CC, and RC, it does have a harmful effect on the risk of right-sided CC, especially in the cecum, the ascending colon, and/or the hepatic flexure. However, additional evidence is needed to elucidate this complex association.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary</title><supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><p>The article&#8217;s supplementary files as</p></supplementary-material><supplementary-material position="anchor" id="su1" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="tcr-12-06-1452-rc.pdf" id="d64e1253" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/tcr-22-2049</object-id></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="tcr-12-06-1452-dss.pdf" id="d64e1256" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/tcr-22-2049</object-id></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="tcr-12-06-1452-prf.pdf" id="d64e1259" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/tcr-22-2049</object-id></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="tcr-12-06-1452-coif.pdf" id="d64e1262" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/tcr-22-2049</object-id></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="tcr-12-06-1452-supplementary.pdf" id="d64e1265" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/tcr-22-2049</object-id></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors thank Dr. Yao Tong (from Department of Anesthesia, Ruijin Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine, Shanghai) for his excellent assistance in data analysis. The authors also thank all the involved physicians and nurses for their efforts to this study.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Funding:</italic> This work was supported by a grant from <funding-source rid="sp1">the National Natural Science Foundation of China</funding-source> (<award-id rid="sp1">No. 81800543</award-id>).</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><italic toggle="yes">Reporting Checklist:</italic> The authors have completed the PRISMA reporting checklist. Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://tcr.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/tcr-22-2049/rc" ext-link-type="uri">https://tcr.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/tcr-22-2049/rc</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="fn2"><p><italic toggle="yes">Data Sharing Statement</italic>: Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://tcr.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/tcr-22-2049/dss" ext-link-type="uri">https://tcr.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/tcr-22-2049/dss</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="fn3"><p><italic toggle="yes">Peer Review File:</italic> Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://tcr.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/tcr-22-2049/prf" ext-link-type="uri">https://tcr.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/tcr-22-2049/prf</ext-link></p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><italic toggle="yes">Conflicts of Interest: </italic>All authors have completed the ICMJE uniform disclosure form (available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://tcr.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/tcr-22-2049/coif" ext-link-type="uri">https://tcr.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/tcr-22-2049/coif</ext-link>). The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="fn4"><p>(English Language Editors: C. Mullens and J. Reylonds)</p></fn></fn-group><notes><p content-type="note added in proof"><italic toggle="yes">Ethical Statement: </italic>The authors are accountable for all aspects of the work in ensuring that questions related to the accuracy or integrity of any part of the work are appropriately investigated and resolved.</p></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baidoun</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elshiwy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elkeraie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Colorectal Cancer Epidemiology: Recent Trends and Impact on Outcomes.</article-title><source>Curr Drug Targets</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>998</fpage>-<lpage>1009</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1389450121999201117115717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33208072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Botteri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borroni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sloan</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Smoking and Colorectal Cancer Risk, Overall and by Molecular Subtypes: A Meta-Analysis.</article-title><source>Am J Gastroenterol</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>115</volume>:<fpage>1940</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14309/ajg.0000000000000803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32773458</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Sullivan</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Town</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk Factors for Early-Onset Colorectal Cancer: A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis.</article-title><source>Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1229</fpage>-<lpage>1240.e5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cgh.2021.01.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33524598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farvid</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sidahmed</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Consumption of red meat and processed meat and cancer incidence: a systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective studies.</article-title><source>Eur J Epidemiol</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>937</fpage>-<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10654-021-00741-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34455534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sekiguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kakugawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Family history of colorectal cancer and prevalence of advanced colorectal neoplasia in asymptomatic screened populations in different age groups.</article-title><source>Gastrointest Endosc</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>1361</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gie.2020.01.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32004550</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elangovan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skeans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Landsman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Colorectal Cancer, Age, and Obesity-Related Comorbidities: A Large Database Study.</article-title><source>Dig Dis Sci</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>3156</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10620-020-06602-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32954457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamberts</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Indications of cholecystectomy in gallstone disease.</article-title><source>Curr Opin Gastroenterol</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>-<lpage>102</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MOG.0000000000000419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29256914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almond</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vlahcevic</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>CC</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bile acid pools, kinetics and biliary lipid composition before and after cholecystectomy.</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1973</year>;<volume>289</volume>:<fpage>1213</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM197312062892302</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4748594</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The influences of cholecystectomy on the circadian rhythms of bile acids as well as the enterohepatic transporters and enzymes systems in mice.</article-title><source>Chronobiol Int</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>673</fpage>-<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2018.1426596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29381405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kullak-Ublick</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paumgartner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berr</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term effects of cholecystectomy on bile acid metabolism.</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><year>1995</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>41</fpage>-<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.1840210109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7806167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cholecystectomy promotes colon carcinogenesis by activating the Wnt signaling pathway by increasing the deoxycholic acid level.</article-title><source>Cell Commun Signal</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12964-022-00890-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35614513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9131663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cholecystectomy can increase the risk of colorectal cancer: A meta-analysis of 10 cohort studies.</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<elocation-id>e0181852</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0181852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28771518</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5542607</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="expression-of-concern" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC10923401"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossuyt</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PRISMA 2020 explanation and elaboration: updated guidance and exemplars for reporting systematic reviews.</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>372</volume>:<issue>n160</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.n160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33781993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8005925</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">Wells GA, Shea BJ, O&#8217;Connell D, Peterson J, Welch V, Losos M, Tugwell P. The Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (NOS) for Assessing the Quality of Non-Randomized Studies in Meta-Analysis. Ottawa, ON: Ottawa Hospital Research Institute, 2009.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Best</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Briss</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Grading quality of evidence and strength of recommendations.</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>328</volume>:<fpage>1490</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.328.7454.1490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15205295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC428525</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oxman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vist</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GRADE: an emerging consensus on rating quality of evidence and strength of recommendations.</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>336</volume>:<fpage>924</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.39489.470347.AD</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18436948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2335261</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenland</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative methods in the review of epidemiologic literature.</article-title><source>Epidemiol Rev</source><year>1987</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.epirev.a036298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3678409</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harbord</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sterne</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A modified test for small-study effects in meta-analyses of controlled trials with binary endpoints.</article-title><source>Stat Med</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>3443</fpage>-<lpage>57</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/sim.2380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16345038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Linos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beard</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Fallon</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cholecystectomy and carcinoma of the colon.</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1981</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>379</fpage>-<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(81)90829-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6115156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adami</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meirik</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gustavsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Colorectal cancer after cholecystectomy: absence of risk increase within 11-14 years.</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>1983</year>;<volume>85</volume>:<fpage>859</fpage>-<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0016-5085(83)90436-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6884710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adami</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krusemo</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meirik</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Unaltered risk of colorectal cancer within 14-17 years of cholecystectomy: updating of a population-based cohort study.</article-title><source>Br J Surg</source><year>1987</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>675</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bjs.1800740807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3651768</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Theodors</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tulinius</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cholecystectomy and colorectal carcinoma: a total-population historical prospective study.</article-title><source>Am J Gastroenterol</source><year>1991</year>;<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>1486</fpage>-<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1928042</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldbohm</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Brandt</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van 't Veer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cholecystectomy and colorectal cancer: evidence from a cohort study on diet and cancer.</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>1993</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>735</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijc.2910530505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8449596</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekbom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adami</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cholecystectomy and colorectal cancer.</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>1993</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>142</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0016-5085(93)90019-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8514031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>J&#248;rgensen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk of colorectal cancer and other cancers in patients with gall stones.</article-title><source>Gut</source><year>1996</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>439</fpage>-<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gut.39.3.439</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8949651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1383353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lagergren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekbom</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intestinal cancer after cholecystectomy: is bile involved in carcinogenesis?</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>121</volume>:<fpage>542</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/gast.2001.27083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11522737</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cholecystectomy and the risk of colorectal cancer.</article-title><source>Am J Gastroenterol</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>1813</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1572-0241.2005.41610.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16086719</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldacre</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abisgold</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seagroatt</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cancer after cholecystectomy: record-linkage cohort study.</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>1307</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjc.6602392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15770220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2361962</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldacre</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wotton</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abisgold</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association between cholecystectomy and intestinal cancer: a national record linkage study.</article-title><source>Ann Surg</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>256</volume>:<fpage>1068</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SLA.0b013e3182759efb</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23154397</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cancer risk in patients with cholelithiasis and after cholecystectomy: a nationwide cohort study.</article-title><source>J Gastroenterol</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>923</fpage>-<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00535-013-0846-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23807230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shabanzadeh</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#248;rensen</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>J&#248;rgensen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Association Between Screen-Detected Gallstone Disease and Cancer in a Cohort Study.</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>152</volume>:<fpage>1965</fpage>-<lpage>1974.e1</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2017.02.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28238770</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Risk of Colorectal Cancer After Cholecystectomy or Appendectomy: A Population-based Cohort Study in Korea.</article-title><source>J Prev Med Public Health</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>281</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3961/jpmph.18.105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30514058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6283741</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The Effect of Cholecystectomy on the Risk of Colorectal Cancer in Patients with Gallbladder Stones.</article-title><source>Cancers (Basel)</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>550</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cancers12030550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32120781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7139669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and Risk Factors of Gastric and Colorectal Cancer after Cholecystectomy.</article-title><source>J Korean Med Sci</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<elocation-id>e354</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3346/jkms.2020.35.e354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33140590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7606888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>De Novo Cancer Incidence after Cholecystectomy in Korean Population.</article-title><source>J Clin Med</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1445</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm10071445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33916209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8037442</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increased Risk of Cancer after Cholecystectomy: A Nationwide Cohort Study in Korea including 123,295 Patients.</article-title><source>Gut Liver</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>465</fpage>-<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5009/gnl210009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35502586</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9099388</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pomare</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heaton</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of cholecystectomy on bile salt metabolism.</article-title><source>Gut</source><year>1973</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>753</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gut.14.10.753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4758655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1412788</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Breuer</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaekel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dommes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fecal bile acid excretion pattern in cholecystectomized patients.</article-title><source>Dig Dis Sci</source><year>1986</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>953</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01303216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3731987</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dvorak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hydrophobic bile acids, genomic instability, Darwinian selection, and colon carcinogenesis.</article-title><source>Clin Exp Gastroenterol</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>47</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/CEG.S4343</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21677822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3108627</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keren</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Konikoff</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paitan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interactions between the intestinal microbiota and bile acids in gallstones patients.</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol Rep</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>874</fpage>-<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1758-2229.12319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26149537</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chidambaram</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinross</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of the colonic microbiota and bile acids in colorectal cancer.</article-title><source>Curr Opin Gastroenterol</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>-<lpage>88</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MOG.0000000000000816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35098940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zamani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taslimi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarabi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enterotoxigenic Bacteroides fragilis: A Possible Etiological Candidate for Bacterially-Induced Colorectal Precancerous and Cancerous Lesions.</article-title><source>Front Cell Infect Microbiol</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>449</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2019.00449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32010637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6978650</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khodaverdi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeighami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jalilvand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High frequency of enterotoxigenic Bacteroides fragilis and Enterococcus faecalis in the paraffin-embedded tissues of Iranian colorectal cancer patients.</article-title><source>BMC Cancer</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1353</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12885-021-09110-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34937552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8693489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vernick</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuller</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lohsoonthorn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationship between cholecystectomy and ascending colon cancer.</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>1980</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>392</fpage>-<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/1097-0142(19800115)45:2&amp;#x0003c;392::AID-CNCR2820450234&amp;#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7351021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giovannucci</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colditz</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stampfer</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A meta-analysis of cholecystectomy and risk of colorectal cancer.</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>1993</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>130</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0016-5085(93)90018-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8514030</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>, harrison M, et al. <article-title>Cholecystectomy as a risk factor for colorectal cancer: a meta-analysis.</article-title><source>Scand J Gastroenterol</source><year>1996</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>160</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/00365529609031981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8658039</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Distribution of tissue bile acids in the human alimentary tract and colon polyps.</article-title><source>Jpn J Med</source><year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine1962.28.25</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2724643</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quantitative profiling of 19 bile acids in rat plasma, liver, bile and different intestinal section contents to investigate bile acid homeostasis and the application of temporal variation of endogenous bile acids.</article-title><source>J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>172</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsbmb.2017.05.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28583875</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Deoxycholic acid disrupts the intestinal mucosal barrier and promotes intestinal tumorigenesis.</article-title><source>Food Funct</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>5588</fpage>-<lpage>97</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C8FO01143E</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30339173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Secondary Bile Acids and Tumorigenesis in Colorectal Cancer.</article-title><source>Front Oncol</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<elocation-id>813745</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fonc.2022.813745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35574393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9097900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>