<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">S Afr J Psychiatr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">S Afr J Psychiatr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3540</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">sajpsy</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SAJPsy</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The South African Journal of Psychiatry : SAJP : the Journal of the Society of Psychiatrists of South Africa</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1608-9685</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2078-6786</issn><publisher><publisher-name>AOSIS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11163387</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11163387.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11163387</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11163387</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38860147</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4102/sajpsychiatry.v29i0.2018</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">SAJPsy-29-2018</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Readmission of adolescent psychiatric patients to a specialised unit in Gauteng, South Africa</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5439-4258</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names initials="SA">Sarah-Anne</given-names></name><xref rid="AF0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5304-5603</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Moeketsi</surname><given-names initials="TD">Tshepiso D.</given-names></name><xref rid="AF0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5880-3680</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Musekiwa</surname><given-names initials="A">Alfred</given-names></name><xref rid="AF0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6656-8964</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Moodley</surname><given-names initials="SV">Saiendhra V.</given-names></name><xref rid="AF0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Pretoria, Pretoria, South Africa</aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>Department of Psychiatry, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Pretoria, Pretoria, South Africa</aff><aff id="AF0003"><label>3</label>School of Health Systems and Public Health, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Pretoria, Pretoria, South Africa</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Sarah-Anne Brown, <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sarah294142@gmail.com">sarah294142@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>29</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">428259</issue-id><elocation-id>2018</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>02</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>27</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>10</day><month>06</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-06-11 17:25:12.997"><day>11</day><month>06</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2023. The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>Licensee: AOSIS. This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="SAJPsy-29-2018.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Background</title><p>Readmission rates to child and adolescent psychiatric units among the youth have been reported to be increasing.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Aim</title><p>The study aimed to determine the readmission rate and factors associated with readmission of adolescent psychiatric patients at a child and adolescent psychiatric unit.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Setting</title><p>A specialised psychiatric hospital in Gauteng province, South Africa.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Methods</title><p>This retrospective cohort study utilised data from the records of patients admitted to the adolescent inpatient unit over a period of five years. The cumulative incidence and incidence rate of readmission within one year of discharge from the index admission was calculated using survival analysis methods. Characteristics significantly associated with readmission were determined by applying the multivariable Cox proportional hazards regression model.</p></sec><sec id="st5"><title>Results</title><p>Among the 189 patients included in the analysis, the cumulative incidence of readmission within one year of discharge was 17.5%. The incidence rate was 5.31 readmissions per 10 000 person-days. The final multivariable model showed that a diagnosis of schizophrenia (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.015), a diagnosis of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.039), and coming from a child and youth care centre or temporary safe care (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.018) increased the risk of readmission while having a medical condition (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.008) reduced the risk.</p></sec><sec id="st6"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Psychiatric diagnosis and residential care could be potential risk markers for readmission. Improving the collaboration between health and social services in residential care would be beneficial.</p></sec><sec id="st7"><title>Contribution</title><p>Identifying factors that predispose adolescent psychiatric patients to readmission can inform and improve management and risk assessments.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>psychiatry</kwd><kwd>South Africa</kwd><kwd>adolescent</kwd><kwd>adolescent psychiatry</kwd><kwd>readmission</kwd><kwd>readmission factors</kwd><kwd>readmission rate</kwd><kwd>Gauteng</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Worldwide, it has been reported that 10% &#8211; 20% of children and adolescents will experience a mental disorder with a majority of these individuals not seeking or receiving care.<sup><xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> It has been reported that 18.5% of South Africa&#8217;s population are adolescents, estimated at over 10 million individuals.<sup><xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Although data are not readily available on prevalence rates of mental health in South Africa, one study found an overall prevalence of 17% for children and adolescents.<sup><xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> High levels of depression and post-traumatic stress symptoms have been found in adolescents from South Africa&#8217;s largest city of Johannesburg.<sup><xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup></p><p>In the United States of America, 15% of all paediatric hospitalisations were attributed to psychiatric hospitalisations.<sup><xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Previous studies report the incidences of readmission in adolescent psychiatric patients to be between 12% and 37%.<sup><xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Since the onset of managed care, readmission rates for psychiatric hospitalised youth have increased with studies indicating that 33% &#8211; 38% will be readmitted within 1 year of discharge.<sup><xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> A systematic review and meta-analysis on readmission among children and adolescents found that 13.2% of adolescents were readmitted.<sup><xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> A study done in the Western Cape province, South Africa, found the rate of readmission in adolescents to be 36%.<sup><xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> The rates of repeated admission to psychiatric inpatient care among the youth are increasing and the risk of rehospitalisation after psychiatric inpatient treatment is becoming more frequent.<sup><xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup></p><p>Little is known about the predictors of readmission among adolescent psychiatric patients.<sup><xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> While there is a lot of literature focusing on adult readmission, there are relatively fewer studies and less knowledge about factors that predispose adolescents to readmission. Previous studies reported inconsistent findings regarding the effects of demographic characteristics on the readmission of adolescents. Based on previous research, it is also difficult to draw definitive conclusions as different diagnostic criteria, factors and methodologies were used in different studies.<sup><xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></p><p>Of the research that has been done internationally, common findings have found suicidality at index admission<sup><xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> as well as discharge to residential treatment to be risk factors for readmission of adolescent psychiatric patients.<sup><xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> A history of sexual abuse has also been found in some studies to have an association with readmission.<sup><xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> Prior hospitalisation history has been found to result in a higher risk of readmission in the adolescent patient.<sup><xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> Patients with more severe psychotic disturbances and psychotic disorders were found at a significantly higher risk of readmission compared to those without a psychotic disorder.<sup><xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup></p><p>The research in this area in South Africa is very limited. A study done by Pieterse et al.<sup><xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> in the Western Cape province examined the risk factors associated with adolescent psychiatric readmission. The study found that prior admission and older age were associated with readmission of adolescent psychiatric patients.<sup><xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> Furthermore, lower grade of schooling and dropping out of school were associated with readmission, making schooling a protective factor against readmission.<sup><xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup></p><p>Identifying risk factors that predispose adolescent psychiatric patients to readmission will assist health care practitioners to provide better care, treatment and rehabilitation for the patients and further assist to implement better risk assessment tools and strategies to lower readmission rates among the adolescent psychiatric patients. The study aimed to determine the cumulative incidence and incidence rate of readmission of adolescent patients to a child and adolescent psychiatric unit in the Gauteng province of South Africa and to determine the factors associated with readmission of adolescent inpatients.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Research methods and design</title><sec id="s20003"><title>Study design</title><p>This study was a retrospective cohort study using patient records. The clinical files of all adolescent patients who were admitted during the period 01 January 2013 to 31 December 2017 to the hospital were reviewed. The patient&#8217;s index admission and discharge dates were recorded, and information was gathered for multiple &#8216;exposures&#8217; (potential risk factors) at the time of index admission. These records for each patient were then reviewed for a period of 1 year post-discharge from their index admission to ascertain if they were readmitted or not in this period.</p></sec><sec id="s20004"><title>Study setting</title><p>This study was conducted at a public sector specialised psychiatric hospital situated in Gauteng province, South Africa. The hospital has a child and adolescent unit which caters for children who are younger than 13 years and adolescents who are between the ages of 13 and 18 years.</p></sec><sec id="s20005"><title>Study population and sampling strategy</title><p>The study population were adolescent patients admitted to the hospital during the period of January 2013 to December 2017. Only patients over the age of 13 years and under the age of 18 years were included in the study. Patients admitted directly to the hospital as well as those who were initially admitted at a different facility and then transferred to the hospital for continuation of care, treatment and rehabilitation were included in the study. There was no sampling as all patients who met the inclusion criteria (namely adolescent patients admitted to the unit between the ages of 13 and 18 years from January 2013 to December 2017) were included in the study.</p></sec><sec id="s20006"><title>Measurements and data collection</title><p>Data were collected from clinical files of the adolescent patients using a structured data capture sheet. These files contained documents including admission forms, progress forms, prescription forms, consultation notes and supporting documents such as affidavits or school reports. These files also contained notes from other health care workers including nurse&#8217;s reports, psychologist notes and social care worker involvement. The date of admission and discharge for their index inpatient stay was captured as well as demographic information, psychiatric diagnosis and social history (comprising of substance use, physical abuse, emotional abuse and sexual abuse) at the time of the index admission. The date of their first readmission following that discharge was recorded if the patient was readmitted within 1 year of discharge from the index admission.</p></sec><sec id="s20007"><title>Statistical methods</title><p>The data were captured in Microsoft Excel and exported to Stata version 16 for analysis.<sup><xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> Frequencies and proportions were calculated for the demographic characteristics of the participants. Kaplan-Meier survival analysis was performed.<sup><xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> The cumulative incidence was calculated by dividing the number of patients readmitted within 365 days of discharge from their index admission by the total number of patients in the study population that were discharged from their index admission. The incidence rate of readmission was calculated by dividing the number of patients readmitted within 365 days of discharge from their index admission by the total number of person-days at risk. Person-days at risk was calculated by adding the number of days to readmission or 365 days for those that were not readmitted.</p><p>Demographic and clinical characteristics associated with readmission within 1 year of discharge were determined using the Cox proportional hazards regression model. All variables that were found to have <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.25 on univariate Cox regression model were included in a multivariable Cox regression model. A manual backward elimination process was used to arrive at a final model. Results are displayed using a table showing the unadjusted and adjusted hazard ratios with their corresponding 95% confidence intervals and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values. A <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &#8804; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. Individuals with missing data on either outcome or risk factor were excluded from analysis, and therefore a complete case analysis was performed. No data imputation was performed, and the statisticians assumed the data to be missing completely at random.</p></sec><sec id="s20008"><title>Ethical considerations</title><p>Ethical approval was granted for this study by the Faculty of Health Sciences Research Ethics Committee of the University of Pretoria (278/2019). Permission was obtained to collect data from the psychiatric hospital from its Chief Executive Officer. The names of the patients were not included on the data sheet, with a unique study number allocated to each patient instead to ensure anonymity of the patients. A separate electronic spreadsheet was kept with the names of the patients and their unique study number to prevent double counting of records and to ensure files could be accessed in the event of a data query; this was deleted immediately after the statistical analysis was conducted. Patient confidentiality was maintained throughout the research process.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0009"><title>Results</title><p>In total, the records for 212 patients were reviewed. However, only records for 189 patients were included in the analysis. Those excluded did not meet the inclusion criteria, did not have the required data for almost all variables or did not have a discharge date that could be ascertained. Of the 189 patients, 33 were admitted within 1 year of discharge, which is a cumulative incidence of 17.5%. The incidence rate was 5.31 readmissions per 10 000 person-days (33/62154 days). The median time to readmission for the 33 patients that were readmitted within 1 year of discharge was 118 days (range = 8&#8211;351 days). Of these 33 patients readmitted within 1 year of discharge, four patients (12.1%) were readmitted within 1 month of discharge, 15 patients (45.6%) were readmitted 1 to 6 months post-discharge and 14 patients (42.4%) were readmitted more than 6 months post-discharge. The Kaplan-Meier graph is shown in <xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F0001" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Kaplan-Meier survival estimate of adolescent patients being readmitted to the psychiatric hospital within one year of discharge.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="SAJPsy-29-2018-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>The demographic characteristics of the patients in the study at the time of their index admission are shown in <xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. More than 40% of patients in the study were between 15 and 16 years of age. There were more male (53.4%) than female patients (46.6%). Most patients were in grade 8&#8211;12. Most patients were from an urban area with only four patients (2.2%) from a rural area. The most common primary caregiver was a combination of a biological parent and nonbiological parent (23.0%). More than 10% of patients were from a child and youth care centre or temporary safe care.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T0001" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Demographic characteristics of adolescent patients at index admission to the psychiatric hospital.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<bold>Age (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 189)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13&#8211;14 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8211;16 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#8211;18 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<bold>Gender (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 189)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<bold>Highest level of education (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 182)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Special school</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 1&#8211;4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 5&#8211;7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 8&#8211;12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<bold>Type of residential area (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 186)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">City or town (including suburbs)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Township</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<bold>Primary caregiver (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 187)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biological parents still married</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biological parent and nonbiological parent</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single parent previously married</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single parent never married</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adoptive parents</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">child and youth care centre or temporary safe care</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The unadjusted hazard ratios for readmission within 1 year of discharge and demographic characteristics at index admission are shown in <xref rid="T0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The only unadjusted hazard ratio with respect to the demographic variables that was statistically significant was primary caregiver, specifically patients from child and youth care centre or temporary safe care were at a higher risk for readmission (HR 10.84, 95% CI 1.33&#8211;88.16, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.026) when compared to biological parents that were still married.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T0002" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>Unadjusted hazard ratios for readmission of adolescent patients within 1 year of discharge from the psychiatric hospital and demographic characteristics at their index admission (univariate Cox regression).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hazard ratio</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% confidence interval</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Age in years (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 189)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13&#8211;14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8211;16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43&#8211;2.45</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.953</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#8211;18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44&#8211;2.70</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.860</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Gender (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 189)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30&#8211;1.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.182</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Type of residential area (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 181<xref rid="TFN0001" ref-type="table-fn">&#8224;</xref>)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Township</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">City or town including suburbs</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39&#8211;1.81</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.663</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Highest level of education (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 182)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 1&#8211;7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 8&#8211;12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44&#8211;2.62</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.875</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Special school</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04&#8211;3.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.360</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Primary caregiver (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 187)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biological parents still married</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biological parent and nonbiological parent</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77&#8211;47.77</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single parent previously married</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38&#8211;30.28</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.276</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single parent never married</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.52</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64&#8211;47.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.119</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adoptive parents</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84&#8211;77.77</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child and youth care centre or temporary safe care</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.84</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33&#8211;88.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57&#8211;45.76</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.144</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN0001"><label>&#8224;</label><p>, &#8216;Rural&#8217; and &#8216;Other&#8217; excluded due to insufficient data.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The unadjusted hazard ratios for readmission within 1 year of discharge and clinical characteristics at index admission are shown in <xref rid="T0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. The unadjusted hazard ratios with respect to clinical characteristics that were statistically significant were presence of medical condition(s), a diagnosis of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD), a diagnosis of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) and presence of multiple psychiatric disorders. Patients with one or more medical conditions were at a lower risk for readmission (HR 0.41, 95% CI 0.18&#8211;0.95, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.039) than those without a medical condition. Compared to patients with other diagnoses, those with ADHD (HR 2.37, 95% CI 1.03&#8211;5.46, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.043) and PTSD (HR 4.19, 95% CI 1.00&#8211;17.55, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.050) were at higher risk of readmission. Patients with multiple psychiatric disorders (HR 2.16, 95% CI 1.08&#8211;4.31, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.029) were more likely to be readmitted than those with a single disorder.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T0003" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 3</label><caption><p>Unadjusted hazard ratios for readmission of adolescent patients within 1 year of discharge from the psychiatric hospital and clinical characteristics at their index admission (univariate Cox regression).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hazard ratio</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% confidence interval</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Patient history</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous Weskoppies Hospital admission</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49&#8211;3.32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.610</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suspected abuse (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 153)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43&#8211;1.97</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.827</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confirmed abuse (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 133)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45&#8211;2.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.991</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Social worker involvement (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 165)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83&#8211;4.49</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Criminal history (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 132)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75&#8211;4.20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.191</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Substance use (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 172)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30&#8211;1.37</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.253</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family upbringing problems (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 172)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37&#8211;4.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.738</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical condition(s) (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 180)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18&#8211;0.95</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family history of psychiatric disorders (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 114)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36&#8211;2.22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.814</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Diagnoses</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intellectual disability (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 186)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06&#8211;3.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.414</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Communication disorders (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 186)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insufficient data</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autism (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 186)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insufficient data</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 186)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.37</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03&#8211;5.46</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specific learning disorders (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 186)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30&#8211;16.35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.429</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mood disorders (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 186)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48&#8211;1.94</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.919</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schizophrenia (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 186)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.89</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90&#8211;3.98</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.092</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bipolar disorder (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 186)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23&#8211;1.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.183</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety disorders (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 186)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74&#8211;13.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.120</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-traumatic stress disorder (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 186)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00&#8211;17.55</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.050</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elimination disorders (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 186)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insufficient data</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feeding disorders (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 186)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insufficient data</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disruptive disorders (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 186)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.72</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77&#8211;3.80</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.184</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Substance disorders (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 186)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51&#8211;2.70</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.711</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurocognitive disorders (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 186)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insufficient data</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other disorders (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 186)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07&#8211;3.53</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.473</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple psychiatric disorders (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 186)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08&#8211;4.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Treatment (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 187)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychotropic medication</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychotherapy</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51&#8211;129.72</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.139</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both psychotropic medication and psychotherapy</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69&#8211;37.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.111</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The initial multivariable Cox regression model consisted of gender, primary caregiver, social worker involvement, criminal history, presence of medical condition(s), diagnosis of ADHD, diagnosis of schizophrenia, diagnosis of bipolar disorder, diagnosis of an anxiety disorder, diagnosis of PTSD, diagnosis of disruptive disorder, presence of multiple psychiatric disorders and treatment. Following backward elimination, the final model consisted of child and youth care centre or temporary safe care as the primary caregiver, presence of a medical condition, diagnosis of ADHD and diagnosis of schizophrenia (see <xref rid="T0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Patients from child and youth care centres or temporary safe care (HR 2.99, 95% CI 1.21&#8211;7.42, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.018), patients with a diagnosis of schizophrenia (HR 2.68, 95% CI 1.21&#8211;5.94, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.015) and patients with a diagnosis of ADHD (HR 2.68, 95% CI 1.05&#8211;6.85, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.039) were significantly more likely to be readmitted within 1 year of discharge, while patients who had one or more medical conditions (HR 0.32, 95% CI 0.13&#8211;0.74, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.008) were significantly less likely to be readmitted within 1 year of discharge.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T0004" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 4</label><caption><p>Multivariate Cox regression model for readmission of adolescent psychiatric patients to the psychiatric hospital within 1 year of discharge (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 179) from their index admission.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hazard ratio</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% confidence interval</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child and youth care centre or temporary safe care</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.99</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21&#8211;7.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical condition(s)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13&#8211;0.74</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.68</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05&#8211;6.85</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schizophrenia</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.68</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21&#8211;5.94</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s0010"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our study aimed to determine readmission rates and factors that predispose adolescent psychiatric patients to readmission at a specialised psychiatric hospital in the Gauteng Province, South Africa. The readmission cumulative incidence found in this study (17.5%) seems to be similar to other studies (12%&#8211;37%) done elsewhere.<sup><xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> The wide range of readmission incidences among previous studies could be due to different methodologies and definitions. Multivariable Cox regression model was used to identify the factors significantly associated with readmission within 1 year of discharge. The factors identified in this study with an increased risk of readmission were adolescents coming from a child and youth care centre or temporary safe care, a diagnosis of ADHD or a diagnosis of schizophrenia while having a medical condition seemed to decrease the risk for readmission.</p><p>Our finding of schizophrenia predisposing adolescent psychiatric patients to readmission has been found in previous studies.<sup><xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> Schizophrenia is known to be chronic in nature and has shown to have a poorer prognosis in comparison to other mental illnesses.<sup><xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> Schizophrenia presents with symptomatology which is difficult to treat; psychotic symptoms have been found to require longer acute treatment and are more likely to be treated in a hospital setting.<sup><xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Adolescent onset schizophrenia has been found to have a poorer prognosis than adult-onset psychosis with less chance of full recovery; only a minority of youths display a complete recovery.<sup><xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> Due to the severity of the illness and complex treatment, this is shown as a contribution to this diagnosis being associated with readmission.</p><p>Another explanation of this finding could be linked to poor aftercare of the schizophrenia adolescent. It has been shown that caregivers report difficulty to care for a mentally ill adolescent.<sup><xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> Adequate aftercare with good follow-up compliance has shown to have a positive correlation with lower readmission rates in adults.<sup><xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> Because most district and regional hospitals in South Africa cannot manage the severity of schizophrenia, most of these patients are referred to tertiary units. These referrals, instead of receiving adequate management at these hospitals, may contribute to the high readmission rate.</p><p>The study suggests that having the diagnosis of ADHD is associated with readmission to a psychiatric hospital. In this study, all readmitted adolescents diagnosed with ADHD had other psychiatric comorbidities with the most common comorbidity being disruptive and/or conduct disorder followed by bipolar disorder. Studies have found a strong correlation between readmission and bipolar disorder in adolescents.<sup><xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> However, we did not find bipolar disorder to be an independent risk factor for readmission. A complex burden of psychiatric comorbidities in adolescents diagnosed with ADHD may predispose these adolescents to being readmitted to a psychiatric hospital.</p><p>This study found that coming from a child and youth care centre or temporary safe care<sup><xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup> predisposes adolescents to readmission to a psychiatric hospital. Although the literature has noted the importance of mental health service needs among the youth care centre and temporary safe care population, the high workload and social worker crisis in South Africa seems to result in social workers focusing more on the physical needs of child and youth care centre and temporary safe care youth while neglecting more of their psychosocial needs.<sup><xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup></p><p>Youth in a child and youth care centre or temporary safe care would be more vulnerable to not receiving care due to lacking a person in their life who is responsible and accountable for them.<sup><xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> One study found that youth in a child and youth care centre or temporary safe care have an increased risk of not receiving services necessary for their needs; this could be due to financial costs and poor health care systems.<sup><xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> Children in residential care need safety and supportive relationships with direct care staff as it is a critical element to recovery, growth and development.</p><p>A study found mental health service utilisation in this population to be poor; much of child and youth care or temporary safe care was found to be delivered without significant mental health services for children.<sup><xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup> Little research is available with regard to the mental health needs of child and youth care or temporary safe care children in South Africa. Further research is needed to establish the mental health service accessibility to child and youth care or temporary safe care. Poor compliance to treatment, especially outpatient treatment, could be a possible reason for readmission in the adolescent population.</p><p>This study found that adolescent patients with a comorbid medical condition were less likely to be admitted. This finding has not been reported in the literature previously and would benefit from exploration in future research. Possible explanations of this finding could be that the presenting psychiatric condition may have been a psychological reaction to a newly diagnosed medical condition which could have led to a temporary or brief psychiatric disorder or it could have been a complication of the medical condition so that appropriate management of the medical condition prevented further readmissions. Furthermore, a diagnosis of a medical condition could allow the patient to have potentially better and more frequent access to medical care. This could further assist in addressing comorbid psychiatric problems in other clinical settings, thereby avoiding admission or readmission to psychiatric hospitals. Future research is needed when examining treatment factors and community-level factors with regard to readmission.</p><sec id="s20011"><title>Limitations</title><p>This study was a retrospective review of clinical files which has limitations with respect to data availability. Patient history, illegible handwriting, missing information, availability of collateral information and follow-up information all negatively affected the available data. A few patients could not be included due to missing data in their record for the key variables.</p><p>As we used the definition of readmission as readmission within a 1 year period post-discharge from the index admission, we did not collect data and cannot report on readmissions that may have occurred after that time period. Readmissions to other psychiatric hospitals were also not taken into consideration and we only looked at readmissions of the patient during their adolescent years, meaning that if a readmission were to happen 1 year out of the designated age, this too would not be counted.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0012"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Approximately 17.5% of adolescent psychiatric patients at a specialised psychiatric hospital in the Gauteng province of South Africa were readmitted within 1 year of discharge. A diagnosis of schizophrenia, ADHD and coming from a child and youth care centre or temporary safe care increased the risk of readmission while having a medical condition appeared to reduce the risk of readmission. A lack of aftercare services, social development services, adequate hospital care and mental health care services for adolescent psychiatric patients may contribute to readmission of these patients. Improved collaboration between the Department of Health and Department of Social Development is needed to improve and ensure management of adolescent psychiatric patients and to develop policies that are aimed at reducing readmission of these patients into psychiatric hospitals.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to thank Dr Lucretia Rangasamy for her assistance in reviewing the literature related to this topic and with the data collection. The authors would also like to thank Dr Astrid Turner and the University of Pretoria Faculty of Health Sciences Undergraduate Research Forum to allow for this opportunity. The authors also thank Weskoppies Hospital, the clerks involved who helped retrieve the files and the staff who helped facilitate the research being conducted on the premises.</p><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s20013"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no financial or personal relationships that may have inappropriately influenced them in writing this article.</p></sec><sec id="s20014"><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>S.B. and T.M. conceptualised the project. S.B., T.M. and S.V.M. developed the study methodology with A.M. contributing to the data analysis methodology. S.B. collected the data. S.V.M. and A.M. conducted the data analysis. All authors contributed to the first and subsequent drafts of the article.</p></sec><sec id="s20015"><title>Funding information</title><p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s20016"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data is available on reasonable request from the corresponding author S.B.</p></sec><sec id="s20017"><title>Disclaimer</title><p>The views and opinions expressed in this article are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the official policy or position of any affiliated agency of the authors.</p></sec></ack><fn-group><fn><p><bold>How to cite this article:</bold> Brown S-A, Moeketsi TD, Musekiwa A, Moodley SV. Readmission of adolescent psychiatric patients to a specialised unit in Gauteng, South Africa. S Afr J Psychiat. 2023;29(0), a2018. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.4102/sajpsychiatry.v29i0.2018" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.4102/sajpsychiatry.v29i0.2018</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><ref-list id="references"><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization, WH</collab></person-group>. <source>Child and adolescent mental health [homepage on the Internet]</source>. <comment>[cited 2021 Jul 24]. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/mental_health/maternal-child/child_adolescent/en/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/mental_health/maternal-child/child_adolescent/en/</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Statistics South Africa</collab></person-group>. <source>Mid-year population estimates, South Africa 2006 [homepage on the Internet]</source>. <publisher-loc>Pretoria</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Statistics</publisher-name><year>2016</year><comment>[cited 2021 Jul 08]. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.statssa.gov.za/publications/Report%2003-00-10/Report%2003-00-102016.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.statssa.gov.za/publications/Report%2003-00-10/Report%2003-00-102016.pdf</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kleintjes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Flisher</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The prevelance of mental disorders among children, adolescents and adults in the Western Cape, South Africa</article-title>. <source>S Afr J Psychiatr</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>157</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>160</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/ajpsy.v9i3.30217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The association between social support and mental health among vulnerable adolescents in Five Cities: Findings from the study of the well-being of adolescents in vulnerable environments</article-title>. <source>J Adolesc Health</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>S31</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>S38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jadohealth.2014.08.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25454000</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gay</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zima</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Coker</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Postacute care after pediatric hospitalizations for a primary mental health condition</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>193</volume>:<fpage>222</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>228</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpeds.2017.09.058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29162345</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Blader</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Symptom, family, and service predictors of children&#8217;s psychiatric rehospitalization within one year of discharge</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Child and Adolesc Psychiatry</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>440</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>451</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004583-200404000-00010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15187804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2953818</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fontanella</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zuravin</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burry</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of a medicaid managed care program on patterns of psychiatric readmission among adolescents: evidence from Maryland</article-title>. <source>J Behav Health Serv Res</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>39</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11414-005-9004-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16636907</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Steelesmith</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Campo</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pradhan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fontanella</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Factors associated with multiple psychiatric readmissions for youth with mood disorders</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>619</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>631</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaac.2019.05.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31170443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7561034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Edgcomb</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sorter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lorberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zima</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Psychiatric readmission of children and adolescents: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Serv</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>269</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>279</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.201900234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31822241</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pieterse</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Temmingh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Factors associated with readmission in South African adolescents discharged from two inpatient psychosocial rehabilitation units</article-title>. <source>J Child Adolesc Ment Health</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>199</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>212</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2989/17280583.2016.1259165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27998264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Joyce</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lebois</surname><given-names>LAM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ressler</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Buonopane</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Predicting psychiatric rehospitalization in adolescents</article-title>. <source>Adm Policy Ment Health</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>807</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>820</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10488-019-00982-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31584109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6886255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Romansky</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lehner</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Factors related to psychiatric hospital readmission among children and adolescents in state custody</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Serv</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>356</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>362</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.54.3.356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12610244</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bobier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Warwick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Factors associated with readmission to adolescent psychiatric care</article-title>. <source>Aust NZJ Psychiatry</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>600</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>606</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/j.1440-1614.2005.01632.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15996141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jairam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rocca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goddard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Matthey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Why do adolescents return to an acute psychiatric unit?</article-title><source>Australasian Psychiatry</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>551</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>555</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/10398562.2010.501380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21117843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fontanella</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The influence of clinical, treatment, and healthcare system characteristics on psychiatric readmission of adolescents</article-title>. <source>Am J Orthopsychiatry</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>187</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>198</lpage>. <comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1037%2Fa0012557" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1037%2Fa0012557</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18954182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1037/a0012557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2596608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Van Alphen</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pridgen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Auerbach</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Predictors of rehospitalization for depressed adolescents admitted to acute psychiatric treatment</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychiatry</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>592</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>598</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4088/jcp.15m10326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27529444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5313382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Czyz</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Berona</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Rehospitalization of suicidal adolescents in relation to course of suicidal ideation and future suicide attempts</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Serv</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>332</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>338</lpage><comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1176%2Fappi.ps.201400252" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1176%2Fappi.ps.201400252</ext-link>.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26725287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1176/appi.ps.201400252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5037573</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Enns</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Inayatulla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Personality predictors of outcome for adolescents hospitalized for suicidal ideation</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>720</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>727</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.chi.0000046847.56865.b0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12921480</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pullen</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cayce</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors leading to increased rehospitalization rates among adolescents admitted to an acute care child and adolescent psychiatric hospital</article-title>. <source>J Child Adolescent Psychiatr Nurs</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>105</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>111</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcap.12180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28921761</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>W E-SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Psychiatric rehospitalization of children and adolescents: Implications for social work intervention</article-title>. <source>Child Adolescent Social Work Journal</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>483</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>496</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fadum</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Diep</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mehlum</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Self-poisoning with medications in adolescents: A national register study of hospital admissions and readmissions</article-title>. <source>Gen Hosp Psychiatry</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>709</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>715</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2014.09.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25307514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leon</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cloutier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Polihronis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Child and adolescent mental health repeat visits to the emergency department: A systematic review</article-title>. <source>Hosp Pediatr</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>177</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>186</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/hpeds.2016-0120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28196831</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>CWT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gula</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of outpatient aftercare on psychiatric rehospitalization among children and emerging adults in Alberta, Canada</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Serv</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>696</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>703</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.201600211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28245702</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Toomey</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zaslavsky</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Readmission after pediatric mental health admissions</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>140</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e20171571</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2017-1571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29101224</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gearing</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Charach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Medication adherence for children and adolescents with first-episode psychosis following hospitalization</article-title><source>Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>587</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>595</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00787-009-0018-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19381709</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aarkrog</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A 10-year follow-up study of adolescent psychiatric clientele and early predictors of readmission</article-title>. <source>Nord J Psychiatry</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>11</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/080394801750093643</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11827601</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kam</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baiden</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Predicting length of stay and readmission for psychiatric inpatient youth admitted to adult mental health beds in Ontario, Canada</article-title>. <source>Child Adolesc Ment Health</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>115</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>121</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/camh.12022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32878390</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>StatCorp</collab></person-group>. <source>Strata Statistical Software: Release 16</source>. <publisher-loc>College Station, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>StataCorp LLC</publisher-name>; <year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><source>Microsofy Excel.160. [computer program]</source>. <publisher-loc>Redmond Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Microsoft Coorporation</publisher-name>; <year>2016</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kleinbaum</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Survival analysis a self-learning text</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>1996</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Frosch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Davarya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leaf</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Factors associated with a six-month return to emergency services among child and adolescent psychiatric patients</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Serv</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1489</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1492</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/ps.2007.58.11.1489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17978263</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Neighbors</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Munday</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Trierweiler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Length of stay, referral to aftercare, and rehospitalization among psychiatric inpatients</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Serv</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1271</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1276</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.54.9.1271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12954945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pavkov</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goerge</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <conf-name>Child and adolescent inpatient psychiatric care: An examination of the state hospital population in Illinois 7th Annual Research Conference, A System of Care for Children&#8217;s Mental Health: Expanding the Research Base</conf-name>; <conf-loc>Tampa, FL</conf-loc>; <year>1994</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bernardo</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Forchuk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Factors associated with readmission to a psychiatric facility</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Serv</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1100</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1102</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.52.8.1100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11474059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Doupnik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jonathan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zima</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Readmissions after pediatric hospitalization for suicide ideation and suicide attempt</article-title>. <source>J Hosp Med</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>743</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>751</lpage>. <comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.12788%2Fjhm.3070" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.12788%2Fjhm.3070</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30484776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.12788/jhm.3070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7253152</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Trask</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fawley-King</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Garland</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aarons</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Do aftercare mental health services reduce risk of psychiatric rehospitalization for children?</article-title><source>Psychol Serv</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>127</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>132</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/ser0000043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26147361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Masi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liboni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Management of schizophrenia in children and adolescents focus on pharmacotherapy</article-title>. <source>Drugs</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>208</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/11585350-000000000-00000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21275445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lay</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Blanz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The psychosocial outcome of adolescent-onset schizophrenia: A 12-year followup</article-title>. <source>Schizophrenia Bulletin</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>801</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>816</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.schbul.a033495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11087013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fleischhaker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tepper</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hennighausen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Remschmidt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term course of adolescent schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Schizophrenia Bulletin</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>769</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>780</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sbi014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16123530</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schepp</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Lessons learned from research with adolescents with schizophrenia and their families</article-title>. <source>Arch Psychiatr Nurs</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>198</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>203</lpage>. <comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1093%2Foxfordjournals.schbul.a007046" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093%2Foxfordjournals.schbul.a007046</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23915698</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.apnu.2013.03.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Knock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kline</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schiffman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maynard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Burdens and difficulties experienced by caregivers of children and adolescents with schizophrenia-spectrum disorders: A qualitative study</article-title>. <source>Early Interv Psychiatry</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>349</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>354</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1751-7893.2011.00305.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22032549</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Olfson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ascher-Svanum</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Faries</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Predicting psychiatric hospital admission among adults with schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Serv</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1138</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1145</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/ps.62.10.pss6210_1138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21969639</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Grudnikoff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McNeilly</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Babiss</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Correlates of psychiatric inpatient readmissions of children and adolescents with mental disorders</article-title>. <source>Elsevier</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>282</volume>:<fpage>112596</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2019.112596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31662187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jonathan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Louw</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Textbook of psychiatry for Southern Africa</source>. <edition>2nd</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Cape Town</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><source>South Africa: Act No.38 of 2005, Childrens Act [statute on the Internet]</source>. <comment>[cited 2022 Oct 26]. Available from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.justice.gov.za/legislation/acts/2005-038%20childrensact.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.justice.gov.za/legislation/acts/2005-038%20childrensact.pdf</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>A descriptive study on infants&#8217; emotional status in foster care placement in a welfare organisation</source> in <publisher-loc>Cape Town</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stellenbosch University</publisher-name>; <year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kerker</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dore</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Mental health needs and treatment of foster youth: Barriers and opportunities</article-title>. <source>Am J Orthopsychiatry</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>76</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>138</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>147</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0002-9432.76.1.138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16569139</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Romanelli</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Mental health services for children placed in foster care: An overview of current challenges</article-title>. <source>Child Welf: J Policy Pract Prog</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>88</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>5</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>26</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3061347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19653451</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>