<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Health Serv Insights</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Health Serv Insights</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2508</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">hsi</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HIS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Health Services Insights</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1178-6329</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10291413</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10291413.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10291413</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10291413</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37377884</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/11786329231183317</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_11786329231183317</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Identifying Unique Subgroups of High-Cost Patients With Schizophrenia: A Population-Based Study Using Latent Class Analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9773-2686</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names initials="AJ">Andrew J</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1-11786329231183317" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patten</surname><given-names initials="SB">Scott B</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1-11786329231183317" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2-11786329231183317" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiest</surname><given-names initials="KM">Kirsten M</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1-11786329231183317" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names initials="TS">Tyler S</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1-11786329231183317" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wick</surname><given-names initials="JP">James P</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2-11786329231183317" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ronksley</surname><given-names initials="PE">Paul E</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1-11786329231183317" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="corresp1-11786329231183317" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-11786329231183317"><label>1</label>Department of Community Health Sciences, Cumming School of Medicine, University of Calgary, AB, Calgary, Canada</aff><aff id="aff2-11786329231183317"><label>2</label>Department of Medicine, Cumming School of Medicine, University of Calgary, Calgary, AB, Canada</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-11786329231183317">Paul E Ronksley, Department of Community Health Sciences, Cumming School of Medicine, University of Calgary, TRW 3E18B, 3280 Hospital Drive NW, Calgary, AB T2N 4Z6, Canada. Email: <email>peronksl@ucalgary.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">426299</issue-id><elocation-id>11786329231183317</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>24</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>27</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-06-28 17:25:09.517"><day>28</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications Ltd unless otherwise noted. Manuscript content on this site is licensed under Creative Commons Licenses</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits any use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access page (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10.1177_11786329231183317.pdf"/><abstract><p>Schizophrenia does not present uniformly among patients and as a result this patient population is characterized by a diversity in the type and amount of healthcare supports needed for daily functioning. Despite this, little work has been completed to understand the heterogeneity that exists among these patients. In this work we used a data-driven approach to identify subgroups of high-cost patients with schizophrenia to identify potentially actionable interventions for the improvement of outcomes and to inform conversations on how to most efficiently allocate resources in an already strained system. Administrative health data was used to conduct a retrospective analysis of &#8220;high-cost&#8221; adult patients with schizophrenia residing in Alberta, Canada in 2017. Costs were derived from inpatient encounters, outpatient primary care and specialist encounters, emergency department encounters, and drug costs. Latent class analysis was used to group patients based on their unique clinical profiles. Latent class analysis of 1659 patients revealed the following patient groups: (1) young, high-needs males early in their disease course; (2) actively managed middle-aged patients; (3) elderly patients with multiple chronic conditions and polypharmacy; (4) unstably housed males with low treatment rates; (5) unstably housed females with high acute care use and low treatment rates. This taxonomy may be used to inform policy, including the identification of interventions most likely to improve care and reduce health spending for each subgroup.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Schizophrenia</kwd><kwd>comorbidity</kwd><kwd>health services research</kwd><kwd>economic analysis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group specific-use="FundRef"><award-group id="award1-11786329231183317"><funding-source id="funding1-11786329231183317"><institution-wrap><institution>Institute of Health Services and Policy Research</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100000037</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id rid="funding1-11786329231183317">PJT-168829</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January-December 2023</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>typesetter</meta-name><meta-value>ts1</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="section1-11786329231183317"><title>Background</title><p>A small proportion of patients account for a disproportionate amount of health spending in countries with advanced healthcare systems. In North America, patients in the top 1% of healthcare spending account for approximately 25-40% of total healthcare expenditures.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Prior studies have described the clinical and demographic profiles of these &#8220;high-cost&#8221; patients and have found an over-representation of mental health diagnoses.<sup><xref rid="bibr3-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="bibr4-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr5-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Unfortunately, the heterogeneous nature of this patient population makes it difficult to develop and implement strategies to improve care and curb health spending for all high-needs, high-cost patients.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr6-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
</sup> This is especially true for patients with schizophrenia as this disorder is well known for its association with high levels of disability and healthcare utilization.<sup><xref rid="bibr7-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="bibr8-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr9-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> Further, the economic costs of providing mental health services varies widely between patients.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr10-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
</sup></p><p>There is growing interest in stratifying high-cost patients into subgroups to facilitate the application of targeted inventions.<sup><xref rid="bibr11-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><xref rid="bibr12-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr13-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr14-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr15-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> Common approaches used to characterize high-cost patient subgroups have focused on identification of independent demographic and clinical factors through regression modeling.<sup>3,<xref rid="bibr16-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">16</xref><xref rid="bibr17-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr18-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> A limitation of this approach is that it assumes these variables are discrete representations of risk factors and may not account for the fact that interrelated combinations of these variables may better represent the underlying mechanisms that drive patient need. Patient health data can be analyzed from this perspective using latent class analysis (LCA) which is a statistical method for identifying unmeasured class membership among subjects.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr19-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
</sup> This technique allows researchers to identify and accurately enumerate the number of high-cost patient groups (or classes), estimate the prevalence of the groups, and highlight the characteristics that define class membership.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr20-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
</sup></p><p>Given the patient and health system burden associated with schizophrenia, there is a need to better match unique patient needs with available interventions to improve quality of life, patient outcomes, and address growing healthcare spending. We used LCA to develop a taxonomy of unique subgroups of high-cost patients with schizophrenia living in Alberta, Canada which may be targetable by specific interventions. Our goal was to use a data-driven approach to better understand the heterogeneity among high-cost patients with schizophrenia (ie, those in the upper 95th percentile of annual healthcare spending). Within the research community there exists a long-term ambition of identifying interventions most likely to improve care and reduce health spending for different subgroups of high-cost patients with schizophrenia. As such, we also matched potential interventions to each group identified within our LCA to not only demonstrate the utility of this proposed taxonomy, but to drive the research agenda forward in this important area.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="section2-11786329231183317"><title>Methods</title><sec id="section3-11786329231183317"><title>Data</title><p>This study used administrative health data from a 10-year patient cohort (January 1, 2008 and December 31, 2017) of high-cost adult patients with schizophrenia residing in Alberta, Canada. A detailed description of the cohort creation has been published previously.<sup><xref rid="bibr21-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="bibr22-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> Briefly, a case ascertainment algorithm was used to identify patients who received care for schizophrenia between 2008 and 2017. The definition for schizophrenia used was: &#8220;1 hospitalization or 2 physician billing claims in 2 years or less associated with an F20.X, F21.X, F23.2 or F25.X ICD-10 code or a &#8216;295.X&#8217; ICD-9 code.&#8221;<sup><xref rid="bibr23-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="bibr24-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr25-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> This algorithm has a reported positive predictive value of 87% and a sensitivity of 87%.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr23-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
</sup> Patients with schizophrenia entered the cohort on the date of their first schizophrenia-specific ICD code and were followed until death, outmigration, or end of study follow-up (December 31, 2017). Finally, a &#8220;high-cost&#8221; patient cohort was created as a subset of the total patient population for the period of January 1 to December 31, 2017 (1 year cohort) to remove secular trends in patient demographics and health spending observed in prior work by our team.<sup><xref rid="bibr21-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="bibr22-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> Given the exploratory nature of this investigation, to facilitate comparison with existing high-cost literature,<sup><xref rid="bibr1-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr5-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="bibr26-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="bibr27-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> a &#8220;high-cost&#8221; patient with schizophrenia was defined as an individual with annual direct healthcare costs in the 95th percentile or greater.</p><sec id="section4-11786329231183317"><title>Independent variables</title><p>Risk factors for high-cost status considered in this work were informed by the Gelberg-Andersen Behavioral Model for Vulnerable Populations.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr28-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
</sup> This model takes a holistic approach in describing factors associated with healthcare utilization and includes 3 domains with special attention to exposures particularly relevant to vulnerable populations: Environmental Factors (eg, geography, social environment), Population Characteristics (eg, pre-disposing, enabling, and need factors), and Health Behaviors (eg, seeking specialist care, and other patterns of healthcare access). Demographic and clinical characteristics of all patients were extracted from the same administrative datasets. This included age, sex, and postal code (to derive estimates of population density). A proxy measure for housing stability was also generated by searching healthcare records for a record of homelessness (Z59 ICD-10 code), or a shelter-associated postal code. To obtain further detail on patient need, comorbidity profiles were determined through the use of 29 case-ascertainment algorithms defined by Tonelli et al.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr23-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
</sup> The proportion of patients with each unique chronic condition was determined and multimorbidity was defined and categorized based on the co-occurrence of these conditions (0, 1-2, 3+).</p><p>Information related to healthcare resource use was derived from the administrative data sources described above. This included number of hospitalizations, ED visits, and specialist visits in the prior year (categorized as 0, 1-2, 3+ encounters). Finally, annual prescription information (Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical (ATC) and date of prescription) was used to determine the number of unique pharmaceuticals prescribed to each patient within the calendar year. Individuals were exposed to &#8220;polypharmacy&#8221; if they were prescribed 5 to 9 unique medications and exposed to &#8220;extreme polypharmacy&#8221; if prescribed 10 or more medications.</p></sec><sec id="section5-11786329231183317"><title>Analytic Approach</title><p>LCA is a statistical method in which observed variables are used to categorize individuals into otherwise unobserved &#8220;classes&#8221; through patterns of conditional probabilities for each individual. As there is no gold standard for determining the number of latent classes that best fit a dataset, we followed model specification procedures used previously in the literature.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr29-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
</sup> This began with the specification of a model with 2 classes and adding classes iteratively until the Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC) were minimized while ensuring that models converged.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr29-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
</sup> The prevalence of demographic characteristics, measures of system use, specialty involvement, and various comorbidities, as well as the risk ratio of the characteristic&#8217;s prevalence in the group compared to the overall prevalence across all subgroups were tabulated to aid in the identification of the defining characteristics of each subgroup. The proportions of cost attributable to each type of encounter (inpatient, ED, outpatient, medication) as well as the costliest and most frequent diagnostic codes (hospitalizations, ED encounters, physician claims) and ATC codes (prescribed medications) within each subgroup were also determined using costing techniques described previously.<sup><xref rid="bibr21-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="bibr22-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup></p><p>All analyses were completed using STATA 16.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr30-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
</sup> This study follows the REporting of studies Conducted using Observational Routinely-collected Data (RECORD) statement<sup>
<xref rid="bibr31-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
</sup> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/suppl/10.1177/11786329231183317" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental A</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="section6-11786329231183317"><title>Results</title><sec id="section7-11786329231183317"><title>High-cost population: Demographic characteristics and health system use</title><p>The 95th percentile for cost included 1659 &#8220;high-cost&#8221; Alberta patients over the age of 18 with schizophrenia in 2017. More males than females were present in the cohort (n&#8201;=&#8201;931 vs 728). Middle-aged patients (40-69&#8201;years of age) comprised 47.8% of this cohort and geographically most patients were found to live in Alberta&#8217;s larger urban centers. High-cost patients were found to have high levels of material deprivation (25% in the most deprived quartile) and 70.5% had 3 or more chronic conditions (<xref rid="table1-11786329231183317" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The most common chronic conditions were depression, alcohol misuse, and hypertension (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/suppl/10.1177/11786329231183317" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental B</ext-link>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table1-11786329231183317" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Clinical and demographic characteristics of each latent class.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_11786329231183317-table1.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8201;</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8201;Class 1 (n&#8201;=&#8201;514)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Class 2 (n&#8201;=&#8201;353)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Class 3 (n&#8201;=&#8201;374)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Class 4 (n&#8201;=&#8201;241)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Class 5 (n&#8201;=&#8201;177)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Cohort (N&#8201;=&#8201;1659)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Age</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;18-29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">323 (62.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (3.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (2.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (13.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">365 (22.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;30-39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132 (25.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (28.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (13.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (24.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">306 (18.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;40-69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (11.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">239 (67.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">191 (51.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">202 (83.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111 (62.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">793 (47.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;70+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (3.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">183 (48.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">195 (11.8%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">357 (69.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">191 (54.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143 (38.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">240 (99.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">931 (56.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">157 (30.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">162 (45.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">231 (61.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">177 (100%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">728 (43.9%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Location of Residence</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Rural</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (10.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (10.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (9.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (13.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (11.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">179 (10.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Small</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (8.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (8.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (10.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (7.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (10.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">151 (9.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Medium</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (9.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (8.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (9.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (9.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (13.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">159 (9.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Urban</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">269 (52.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">222 (62.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">227 (60.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149 (61.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 (59.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">972 (58.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No Information</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (1.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (1.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (1.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (1.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Unstably Housed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146 (28.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (3.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 (41.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (33.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">319 (19.2%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Annual ED visits</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (15.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (22.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (9.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (5.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (5.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">217 (13.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1-2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">152 (29.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">179 (50.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">140 (37.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (22%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (14.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">549 (33.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;3 or more</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">282 (54.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (26.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">198 (52.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176 (73%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143 (80.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">893 (53.8%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Annual Hospitalizations</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (11.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (22.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (5.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (1.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">167 (10.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1-2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">228 (44.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">270 (76.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">209 (55.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (24.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (17.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">797 (48.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;3 or more</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">227 (44.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (0.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">145 (38.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">177 (73.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143 (80.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">695 (41.9%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">&#8201;Specialist Involvement in Care</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (7.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (8.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (1.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (1.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (4.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1-2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">231 (44.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">119 (33.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (16.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (14.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (19.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">482 (29.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;3 or more</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">243 (47.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">205 (58.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">307 (82.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">204 (84.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">140 (79.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1099 (66.2%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Material Deprivation</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Missing Address</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (4.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (9.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (15.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (16.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (11.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">173 (10.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;First Quintile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (15.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (13.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (11.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (13.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (11.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">225 (13.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Second Quintile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (11.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (11.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (6.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (4.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (10.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149 (9.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Third Quintile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (15%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (15.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (16.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (10.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (15.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">246 (14.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Fourth Quintile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (14%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (16.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (17.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (20.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (18.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">276 (16.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Fifth Quintile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">116 (22.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (25.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88 (23.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (28.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (29.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">415 (25%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Antipsychotic Treatment</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">154 (30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132 (37.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">235 (62.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 (43.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (44.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">705 (42.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Oral</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">334 (65%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">202 (57.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135 (36.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127 (52.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (53.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">892 (53.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Injection</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (5.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (5.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (1.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (3.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (3.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Oral&#8201;+&#8201;Injectable</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (3.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (3.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (0.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (2.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (2.4%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Polypharmacy</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;0 Unique ATC&#8217;s</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1-4 Unique ATC&#8217;s</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">195 (37.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88 (24.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (10.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (7.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (7.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">354 (21.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;5-9 Unique ATC&#8217;s (Polypharmacy)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">171 (33.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (24.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (12.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (17.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (9.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">363 (21.9%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;10 or more Unique ATC&#8217;s (Extreme Polypharmacy)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">148 (28.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">178 (50.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">289 (77.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">180 (74.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">147 (83.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">942 (56.8%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Comorbidity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;0 Comorbidities</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (5.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (2.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (2.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1-2 Comorbidities</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">327 (63.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 (30.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (5.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (3.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">455 (27.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;3 or more Comorbidities</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">161 (31.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">237 (67.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">372 (99.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">229 (95.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">171 (96.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1170 (70.5%)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The frequency of ED visits in this population was high with 54% of the high-cost cohort utilizing emergency services 3 or more times in the prior year. In contrast, hospitalizations were less frequent with 58% of patients being hospitalized 2 or fewer times over the same period. Polypharmacy was found to be extremely high with 1305 (78.7%) patients being prescribed 5 or more unique drugs. Over half of the high-cost cohort (58.5%) were prescribed antipsychotic treatments which were most commonly oral formulations (<xref rid="table1-11786329231183317" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Treatment of schizophrenia/schizoaffective disorders ranked highly within the top 10 most frequently used administrative codes associated with each latent class (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/suppl/10.1177/11786329231183317" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental C</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="section8-11786329231183317"><title>Derivation of high-cost subgroups through latent class analysis</title><p>LCA identified 5 unique classes of patients. High-cost patients were well-represented across each of the latent classes with the largest class including 514 (31.0%) patients and the smallest class including 177 (10.7%) patients. These 5 subgroups predominantly included individuals that were:</p><list list-type="simple" id="list1-11786329231183317"><list-item><p>(1)&#8201;&#8201;young, high-needs males early in their disease course,</p></list-item><list-item><p>(2)&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;actively managed middle-aged patients,</p></list-item><list-item><p>(3)&#8201;&#8201;elderly patients with multiple chronic conditions and extreme polypharmacy,</p></list-item><list-item><p>(4)&#8201;&#8201;unstably housed males with low treatment rates,</p></list-item><list-item><p>(5)&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;unstably housed females with high acute care use and low treatment rates.</p></list-item></list><p>The unique demographic and clinical profiles for each of these classes are summarized in <xref rid="table1-11786329231183317" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and <xref rid="fig1-11786329231183317" ref-type="fig">Figures 1</xref> to <xref rid="fig3-11786329231183317" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and stratified costs for each class are summarized in <xref rid="fig4-11786329231183317" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>. We provide a summary of the unique characteristics that define each latent class below.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1-11786329231183317" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Age distribution of patients stratified by latent class (risk ratios)*.</p><p>*Risk ratio of the prevalence of each age stratum in each class compared to the overall prevalence across all subgroups (ie, the entire high-cost cohort).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_11786329231183317-fig1.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig2-11786329231183317" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Prescription patterns stratified by latent class (risk ratios)*.</p><p>*Risk ratio of the prevalence of each treatment type in each class compared to the overall prevalence across all subgroups (ie, the entire high-cost cohort).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_11786329231183317-fig2.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig3-11786329231183317" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Comorbidity prevalence stratified by latent class (risk ratios)*.</p><p>*Risk ratio of the prevalence of each comorbidity in each class compared to the overall prevalence across all subgroups (ie, the entire high-cost cohort).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_11786329231183317-fig3.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig4-11786329231183317" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Direct healthcare costs stratified by latent class and spending category.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_11786329231183317-fig4.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section9-11786329231183317"><title>Class 1: Young, high-needs patients early in their disease course</title><p>Class 1 was the most prevalent class identified. Younger high-cost patients were best represented in this subgroup with 88.5% under the age of 30. This class was also heavily skewed toward males (69.5%). Approximately one quarter were unstably housed and 36.9% had no ED encounters or hospitalizations (35.3%) in the prior year. Over two-thirds (68%) were exposed to polypharmacy and included the highest numbers of patients prescribed oral and injectable antipsychotics.</p></sec><sec id="section10-11786329231183317"><title>Class 2: Actively managed middle-aged patients</title><p>Class 2 had the greatest representation of middle-aged patients (aged 40-69) and included an almost equal proportion of males and females. Healthcare utilization was the lowest of the classes identified. Further, they had the lowest risk of being unstably housed, and the lowest risk for high acute care use and specialist involvement in their care relative to other high-cost classes. This was corroborated by low risk ratios for most comorbidities with only Class 1 having lower risk estimates (<xref rid="fig3-11786329231183317" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). This class also had a high proportion receiving injectable antipsychotic medications.</p></sec><sec id="section11-11786329231183317"><title>Class 3: Elderly patients with multiple chronic conditions and polypharmacy</title><p>This class represented the second highest number of high-cost patients (n&#8201;=&#8201;374). The age and sex profiles captured within this class were distinct from those in Classes 1 and 2. Most (93.8%) were aged 70&#8201;years or older and did not include any patients under the age of 40 (<xref rid="fig1-11786329231183317" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). There was a higher proportion of females in this class and 95.7% were stably housed. The risk ratio of most chronic conditions was higher than all other classes particularly for dementia and cardiovascular comorbidities. In addition, a high level of &#8220;extreme polypharmacy&#8221; (10 or more unique drug prescriptions) was observed (<xref rid="fig2-11786329231183317" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). The top 10 most frequent diagnostic codes for ED visits, hospitalizations, and physician claims reflected a different profile than those observed for other classes where these patients received more care for comorbidity and age-related pathologies (eg, rehabilitative care, urinary tract infections, and chest pain) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/suppl/10.1177/11786329231183317" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental C</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="section12-11786329231183317"><title>Class 4: Unstably housed males with low treatment rates</title><p>Class 4 was entirely composed of males apart from the inclusion of one female patient. They were more likely to be older (aged 40-69) and had the highest risk of being homeless/unstably housed (<xref rid="table1-11786329231183317" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). They also had lower risk of receiving medications for their underlying chronic conditions (<xref rid="fig2-11786329231183317" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>) and a higher risk of being recurrent users of acute healthcare services (ED visits and hospitalizations) relative to other high-cost classes. Patients within this class were more commonly treated for alcohol toxicity and other stimulants compared with the other classes (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/suppl/10.1177/11786329231183317" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental C</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="section13-11786329231183317"><title>Class 5: Unstably housed females with high acute care use and low treatment rates</title><p>While Classes 4 and 5 appeared most similar in profile, there were unique characteristics that distinguished this subgroup. This was the smallest group of high-cost patients (n&#8201;=&#8201;177) and composed entirely of female patients. The risk of being homeless/unstably housed was slightly lower than Class 4 but use of ED services and hospitalizations was highest. Comorbidity profiles also differed with the highest risk for gastrointestinal conditions such as irritable bowel syndrome and disease (IBS and IBD) in addition to non-metastatic cancer, asthma, and chronic pain. They also had the lowest risk of receiving any prescribed medications for their chronic conditions and the second lowest risk of receiving injectable antipsychotics compared with the other classes.</p></sec><sec id="section14-11786329231183317"><title>Cost distribution</title><p><xref rid="fig4-11786329231183317" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref> displays direct healthcare costs stratified by spending category and latent class membership. Costs were heavily skewed and median costs ranged from $90121.06 (Q1-Q3: $74125.63&#8722;$159169.80) in Class 2 (actively managed middle-aged patients) to $109336.40 (Q1-Q3: $80537.89&#8722;$180157.50) in Class 3 (elderly patients with multiple chronic conditions and polypharmacy). Class 1 was associated with the highest estimated cumulative spending with Classes 4 and 5 representing the lowest cumulative spending. The greatest contributors to cost for Classes 1 and 2 were prescribed medications and the greatest contributors to costs for the remaining classes were hospitalizations.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section15-11786329231183317"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this population-based study, we used administrative healthcare data and LCA to develop a taxonomy of 5 unique subgroups of patients with schizophrenia which may be targetable by specific interventions. These 5 classes have distinct demographic and clinical characteristics, patterns of healthcare use, and health behaviors. Further, this data-driven approach provides key insights into the different profiles of high-cost patients with schizophrenia and can inform care strategies based on their disease course, healthcare needs, and social circumstances.</p><p>While little work has focused on high-cost mental health patients,<sup>
<xref rid="bibr4-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
</sup> many of our findings are supported by previous literature. Rosella et al found that being a high-cost patient was strongly associated with being older and having multiple chronic conditions<sup>
<xref rid="bibr16-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
</sup> and Wang et al found that comorbidity was an important predictor of high-cost status in this patient population.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr32-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>
</sup> While studies such as these have identified independent risk factors for high-cost status, latent class methodologies allow us to develop a taxonomy that describe how different predictors co-exist to create unique patient subgroups. This permits a more precise approach to improving care for this population by offering avenues to prioritize more individualized treatment strategies. In the following paragraphs we provide our interpretation of these profiles along with a discussion of interventions/supports that offer promise in shifting these patients away from high use of healthcare resources while potentially addressing quality of life and overall health outcomes.</p><sec id="section16-11786329231183317"><title>Class 1: Young, high-needs males early in their disease course</title><p>Patients in this group were characterized as being younger, living with less comorbidity, but having highly diverse healthcare needs (as characterized by high reliance on inpatient and outpatient services). Pharmaceutical treatment costs were also found to be the highest spending category in this class. From a policy perspective, generic formulations may offer significant cost savings while still delivering the same benefits of the currently available patented drugs. Unfortunately, generic formulations aren&#8217;t likely to become available for several years and availability of competing formulations is scarce in Canada.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr33-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>
</sup> Fortunately, there is some political will for the Implementation of National Pharmacare and the Schizophrenia Society of Canada recommends the pursuit of this goal.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr34-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>
</sup> Economic analyses also suggest that combining the purchasing power of multiple provinces under a national framework may help realize reductions in Canadian prescription drug expenditures.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr35-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>
</sup></p><p>This group of high-cost patients is also well positioned to benefit from preventative medicine interventions. The Lancet Psychiatry Commission recommends that &#8220;among those with mental illness, a healthy lifestyle should ideally be adopted in the early stages of illness to build health habits and to protect physical health as much as possible.&#8221;<sup>
<xref rid="bibr36-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>
</sup> Some transdiagnostic case-management supports currently exist in Alberta which may facilitate this. For example, patients with chronic psychotic disorders can access the Adult Psychosis program which connects them with a network of living skills instructors, occupational therapists, psychiatrists, psychologists, registered nurses, registered psychiatric nurses and social workers.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr37-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>
</sup> There may be value in investigating options for expanding this program to additional sites, expanding the variety of professional supports available beyond those commonly associated with mental healthcare (eg, dieticians, physiotherapists), and opening new referral pathways for younger patients.</p></sec><sec id="section17-11786329231183317"><title>Class 2: Actively managed middle-aged patients</title><p>Patients in class 2 were generally older and appeared to present a more uniform profile when it came to healthcare resource utilization. There appeared to be reduced reliance on acute healthcare services and an increased reliance on more expensive pharmaceutical treatments (ie, injectable antipsychotics). Thus, patients in this subgroup also stand to benefit from the recommendations made above. This includes both the use of case managers to facilitate/organize transdiagnostic approaches to treatment along with structural changes to the way pharmaceutical costs are negotiated in Canada.</p></sec><sec id="section18-11786329231183317"><title>Class 3: Elderly patients with multiple chronic conditions and polypharmacy</title><p>Patients in this group were generally over the age of 70 with an increased reliance on acute healthcare services, increased levels of comorbidity, and polypharmacy. It is well-established that older patients with schizophrenia have lower levels of community integration than age-matched peers<sup>
<xref rid="bibr38-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>
</sup> which may be a contributing factor to this trend. Programs that aim to improve community integration of patients are offered in Alberta, but their scope is limited. For example, the Schizophrenia Society of Alberta fosters peer connections though a province-wide senior&#8217;s phone peer support group that meets weekly. Older patients with schizophrenia may benefit from technology skills training that would allow them to access additional formal and semi-formal ways to connect and interact with their community and the healthcare system. In addition, patients with schizophrenia are faced with new challenges with the onset of age-related morbidity. The delivery of personalized medicine is time intensive and given pressures that already exist within the healthcare system these needs may be best met by dedicated case management and a focus on &#8220;upstream interventions&#8221; associated with preventative medicine.</p></sec><sec id="section19-11786329231183317"><title>Classes 4 and 5: Unstably housed individuals with high acute care use and low treatment rates</title><p>Classes 4 and 5 were both characterized by high levels of homelessness/unstable housing and high acute care use while accessing prescribed antipsychotics at lower rates. However, classes 4 and 5 could be differentiated from one another primarily through sex with class 4 being &gt;99% males and class 5 only including females. Given the reliance of these high-cost populations on acute care services we believe that these groups would benefit the most from Assertive Community Treatment (ACT). Prior meta-analyses have found that ACT is effective at reducing hospitalizations which in turn improves patient quality of life and addresses growing inpatient spending in this subset of patients.<sup><xref rid="bibr39-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="bibr40-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> In fact, studies on ACT have found increased levels of treatment engagement and reductions in those with homelessness<sup><xref rid="bibr41-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">41</xref><xref rid="bibr42-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr43-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> which would shift the profile of these patients closer to those seen in class 2. As class 2 remains a high-cost group this shift may not curb health spending, but from a patient-centric perspective this shift may remain a valuable outcome. In addition, our review of hospital service codes suggest that male patients may benefit from interventions focused on harm reduction for alcohol and stimulants.</p><p>The high proportion of unstably housed patients in these groups suggest that housing remains an issue. The Schizophrenia Society of Alberta provides some support in this area providing supportive housing to a small number of patients with schizophrenia at a cost of approximately $72 per day.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr44-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>
</sup> Unfortunately, this is only a subset of Alberta&#8217;s homeless schizophrenia population, and our cohort suggests that patients continue to fall through the gaps. The benefits associated with the provision of housing supports for this population are well established,<sup>
<xref rid="bibr45-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>
</sup> however associated costs cannot be ignored. For example, after speaking with industry experts, Phan estimated that High Supportive Housing is associated with a cost of $130 to 150 per day.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr46-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>
</sup> There is a clear need for discussions on the value of increasing the capacity of programs such as those delivered by the Schizophrenia Society of Alberta. However, this would require rigorous evaluation to determine cost effectiveness and long-term effects on patient outcomes.</p></sec></sec><sec id="section20-11786329231183317"><title>Strengths &amp; Limitations</title><p>A key strength of this study is its use of detailed and diverse administrative data sources allowing for identification of high-cost individuals at a provincial level. Further, the use of LCA allows for a more precise taxonomy than many other studies in this area, while ensuring that the resulting groups have face validity, are clinically meaningful, and offer opportunity for targeted interventions. Despite its strengths, the results of the study should be interpreted considering its limitations. Our taxonomy is driven by the data sources used as its inputs. As a result, important measures of the social determinants of health such as education level and food insecurity were not captured and may have missed key latent classes. Further, while the groupings are mutually exclusive, there are characteristics that overlap across all 5 classes and patients may shift between classes as their disease progresses, their social and medical circumstances change, or as they age. We also recognize that this latent class analysis was conducted on a group of patients classified as &#8220;high-cost&#8221; in a single year and patients can move between high-cost and non-high-cost states over time.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr47-11786329231183317" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>
</sup> Thus, further insights into the variability of LCA groupings in this patient population may be gleaned by contrasting our findings with LCA groupings generated from cohorts of patients classified as &#8220;high-cost&#8221; across multiple years (ie, persistently high-cost patients). This may improve the chances that targeted interventions would truly affect health spending and more importantly patient outcomes. However, identifying the key characteristics of each subgroup, even for a 1&#8201;year cohort, highlights areas for potential cost containment at a specific point in time and is highly relevant from both a clinical and public health perspective. Finally, our taxonomy hinges on our measure of &#8220;high-cost&#8221; status. While we did not conduct sensitivity analyses, future research may consider exploring alternative cost cut-offs (eg, upper 10% of upper 2.5% of patients) or different high-cost definitions that rely on frequencies of healthcare encounters (ie, number of hospitalizations or emergency department visits) to determine the validity of our 5 proposed subgroups of high-cost patients with schizophrenia.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="section21-11786329231183317"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The results of this analysis indicate that high-cost patients with schizophrenia are not a homogenous group, and several distinct subgroups exist. Our data-driven approach using LCA was able to uncover 5 classes. When aligned with available interventions such as case-management, policy aimed at reducing costs of injectable antipsychotics, assertive community treatment, housing initiatives, and improved access to supports for elderly patient may help us realize cost savings in the vulnerable population while improving health outcomes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="section22-11786329231183317" specific-use="figshare"><title>Supplemental Material</title><supplementary-material id="suppl1-11786329231183317" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>sj-docx-1-his-10.1177_11786329231183317 &#8211; Supplemental material for Identifying Unique Subgroups of High-Cost Patients With Schizophrenia: A Population-Based Study Using Latent Class Analysis</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sj-docx-1-his-10.1177_11786329231183317.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media><p>Supplemental material, sj-docx-1-his-10.1177_11786329231183317 for Identifying Unique Subgroups of High-Cost Patients With Schizophrenia: A Population-Based Study Using Latent Class Analysis by Andrew J Stewart, Scott B Patten, Kirsten M Fiest, Tyler S Williamson, James P Wick and Paul E Ronksley in Health Services Insights</p></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="suppl2-11786329231183317" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>sj-docx-2-his-10.1177_11786329231183317 &#8211; Supplemental material for Identifying Unique Subgroups of High-Cost Patients With Schizophrenia: A Population-Based Study Using Latent Class Analysis</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sj-docx-2-his-10.1177_11786329231183317.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media><p>Supplemental material, sj-docx-2-his-10.1177_11786329231183317 for Identifying Unique Subgroups of High-Cost Patients With Schizophrenia: A Population-Based Study Using Latent Class Analysis by Andrew J Stewart, Scott B Patten, Kirsten M Fiest, Tyler S Williamson, James P Wick and Paul E Ronksley in Health Services Insights</p></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="suppl3-11786329231183317" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>sj-docx-3-his-10.1177_11786329231183317 &#8211; Supplemental material for Identifying Unique Subgroups of High-Cost Patients With Schizophrenia: A Population-Based Study Using Latent Class Analysis</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sj-docx-3-his-10.1177_11786329231183317.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media><p>Supplemental material, sj-docx-3-his-10.1177_11786329231183317 for Identifying Unique Subgroups of High-Cost Patients With Schizophrenia: A Population-Based Study Using Latent Class Analysis by Andrew J Stewart, Scott B Patten, Kirsten M Fiest, Tyler S Williamson, James P Wick and Paul E Ronksley in Health Services Insights</p></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>This study is based in part by data provided by Alberta Health and Alberta Health Services. The interpretation and conclusions are those of the researchers and do not represent the views of the Government of Alberta. Neither the Government of Alberta nor Alberta Health express any opinion in relation to this study.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This work is supported by an operating grant from the Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR), and Trainee support provided in part through the Calgary Chapter of the Schizophrenia Society of Alberta (Dr. S.K. Littman Graduate Award).</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethical Standards:</bold> This study was approved by the University of Calgary&#8217;s Conjoint Health Research Ethics Board and granted a waiver of patient consent (REB 16-1575).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Data Access:</bold> Paul Ronksley had full access to all the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. We are not able to make our data set available to other researchers due to our contractual arrangements with the provincial health ministry (Alberta Health), who is the data custodian.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Andrew J. Stewart <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="10.1177_11786329231183317-img1.jpg"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9773-2686" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9773-2686</ext-link></p></fn><fn fn-type="supplementary-material"><p><bold>Supplemental material:</bold> Supplemental material for this article is available online.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-11786329231183317"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wodchis</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A 3-year study of high-cost users of health care</article-title>. <source>Can Med Assoc J</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>188</volume>:<fpage>182</fpage>-<lpage>188</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26755672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1503/cmaj.150064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4754179</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-11786329231183317"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wammes</surname><given-names>JJG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Wees</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanke</surname><given-names>MAC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Westert</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeurissen</surname><given-names>PPT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Systematic review of high-cost patients&#8217; characteristics and healthcare utilisation</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e023113</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2018-023113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6129088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30196269</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-11786329231183317"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Revie</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stryhn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Defining 'actionable' high- costhealth care use: results using the Canadian Institute for Health Information population grouping methodology</article-title>. <source>Int J Equity Health</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31707981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12939-019-1074-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6842471</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-11786329231183317"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vigod</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurdyak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Patients with high mental health costs incur over 30 percent more costs than other high-cost patients</article-title>. <source>Health Aff</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>-<lpage>43</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1377/hlthaff.2015.0278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26733699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-11786329231183317"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ronksley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Segmenting persistently high-cost individuals into actionable groups</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>50</volume>:200. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyab168.570</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-11786329231183317"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blumenthal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chernof</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fulmer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lumpkin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Caring for high-need, high-cost patients - an urgent priority</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>375</volume>:<fpage>909</fpage>-<lpage>911</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27602661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMp1608511</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-11786329231183317"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abate</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abate</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Global, regional, and national incidence, prevalence, and years lived with disability for 354 diseases and injuries for 195 countries and territories, 1990-2017: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease study 2017</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>392</volume>:<fpage>1789</fpage>-<lpage>1858</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30496104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)32279-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6227754</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-11786329231183317"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goeree</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farahati</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The economic burden of schizophrenia in Canada in 2004</article-title>. <source>Curr Med Res Opin</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>2017</fpage>-<lpage>2028</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16368053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1185/030079905X75087</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-11786329231183317"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maj</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sartorius</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Schizophrenia</source>. <edition>2nd ed.</edition><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>; <year>2003</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-11786329231183317"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCrone</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leese</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thornicroft</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>A comparison of needs of patients with schizophrenia in five European countries: The EPSILON Study</article-title>. <source>Acta Neurol Scand</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>370</fpage>-<lpage>379</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1034/j.1600-0447.2001.00207.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11380307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-11786329231183317"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Segmentation of high-cost adults in an integrated healthcare system based on empirical clustering of acute and chronic conditions</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>2171</fpage>-<lpage>2179</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30182326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-018-4626-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6258619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-11786329231183317"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Subgroups of high-cost medicare advantage patients: an observational study</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>218</fpage>-<lpage>225</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30511290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-018-4759-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6374249</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-11786329231183317"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joynt Maddox</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beaulieu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wild</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Concentration of potentially preventable spending among high-cost Medicare subpopulations: an observational study</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>167</volume>:<fpage>706</fpage>-<lpage>713</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29049488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7326/M17-0767</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-11786329231183317"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piegari</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosland</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fihn</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identifying latent subgroups of high-risk patients using risk score trajectories</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>2120</fpage>-<lpage>2126</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30225769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-018-4653-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6258600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-11786329231183317"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keeney</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belanger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joyce</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mor</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>High-need phenotypes in Medicare beneficiaries: drivers of variation in utilization and outcomes</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>70</fpage>-<lpage>77</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31454082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jgs.16146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6952536</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-11786329231183317"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosella</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wodchis</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calzavara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>High-cost health care users in Ontario, Canada: demographic, socio-economic, and health status characteristics</article-title>. <source>BMC Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25359294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12913-014-0532-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4221677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-11786329231183317"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chechulin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nazerian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rais</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malikov</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Predicting patients with high risk of becoming high-cost healthcare users in Ontario (Canada)</article-title>. <source>Healthc Policy</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>68</fpage>-<lpage>79</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24726075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3999564</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-11786329231183317"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hensel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vigod</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rates of mental illness and addiction among high-cost users of medical services in Ontario</article-title>. <source>Can J Psychiatry</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>358</fpage>-<lpage>366</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27254845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0706743716644764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4872244</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-11786329231183317"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oberski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <part-title>Mixture models: latent profile and latent class analysis</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaptein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>Modern Statistical Methods for HCI</source>. <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>; <year>2016</year>;<fpage>275</fpage>-<lpage>287</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-11786329231183317"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Magidson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vermunt</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A nontechnical introduction to latent class models</article-title>. <source>Stat Innov White Pap</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-11786329231183317"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patten</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiest</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wick</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ronksley</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Factors associated with high health care spending among patients with schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Health Promot Chronic Dis Prev Can</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>431</fpage>-<lpage>439</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36223158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.24095/hpcdp.42.10.02</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9584173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-11786329231183317"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patten</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiest</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wick</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ronksley</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>10-year trends in healthcare spending among patients with schizophrenia in Alberta, Canada</article-title>. <source>Can J Psychiatry</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>723</fpage>-<lpage>733</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35244485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/07067437221082885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9449136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-11786329231183317"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tonelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiebe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fortin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Methods for identifying 30 chronic conditions: application to administrative data</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Inform Decis Mak</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12911-015-0155-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4415341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25886580</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-11786329231183317"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lurie</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Popkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dysken</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moscovice</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Accuracy of diagnoses of schizophrenia in Medicaid claims</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Serv</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1176/ps.43.1.69</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1544654</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-11786329231183317"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moscovice</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lurie</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Minnesota: plan choice by the mentally ill in Medicaid prepaid health plans</article-title>. <source>Adv Health Econ Health Serv Res</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>265</fpage>-<lpage>278</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10304288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-11786329231183317"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>DJT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McAlister</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Identifying subgroups of adult high-cost health care users: a retrospective analysis</article-title>. <source>CMAJ Open</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>E390</fpage>-<lpage>E399</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.9778/cmajo.20210265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9022936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35440486</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-11786329231183317"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berk</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monheit</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The concentration of health care expenditures, revisited</article-title>. <source>Health Aff</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>9</fpage>-<lpage>18</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1377/hlthaff.20.2.9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11260963</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-11786329231183317"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gelberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leake</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The behavioral model for vulnerable populations: application to medical care use and outcomes for homeless people</article-title>. <source>Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1273</fpage>-<lpage>1302</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10654830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1089079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-11786329231183317"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Porcu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giambona</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Introduction to latent class analysis with applications</article-title>. <source>J Early Adolesc</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>-<lpage>158</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-11786329231183317"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Stata Statistical Software: Release 16</collab> [computer program]. <publisher-name>StataCorp LLC</publisher-name>.; <year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-11786329231183317"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benchimol</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smeeth</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guttmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The REporting of studies conducted using observational routinely-collected health data (RECORD) statement</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e1001885</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26440803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4595218</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-11786329231183317"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iyengar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Predicting future high-cost schizophrenia patients using high-dimensional administrative data</article-title>. <source>Front Psychiatry</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>114</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28713293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpsyt.2017.00114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5491596</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-11786329231183317"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Citrome</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Long-acting injectable antipsychotics: what, when, and how - Addendum</article-title>. <source>CNS Spectr</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>118</fpage>-<lpage>129</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/S1092852921000456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33928884</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-11786329231183317"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>The Schizophrenia Society of Canada</collab>. <source>The Schizophrenia Society of Canada and The Schizophrenia Society of Canada Foundation 2019/2020 Annual Report</source>. <year>2021</year>. <comment>Accessed May 11, 2023</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://schizophrenia.ca/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/SSC-Annual-Report-2021-22-1_compressed-1_compressed.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://schizophrenia.ca/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/SSC-Annual-Report-2021-22-1_compressed-1_compressed.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr35-11786329231183317"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shearer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prescription drug coverage in Canada: a review of the economic, policy and political considerations for universal pharmacare</article-title>. <source>J Pharm Policy Pract</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30443371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s40545-018-0154-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6220568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr36-11786329231183317"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Firth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiqi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koyanagi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The Lancet Psychiatry Commission: a blueprint for protecting physical health in people with mental illness</article-title>. <source>Lancet Psychiatry</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>675</fpage>-<lpage>712</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31324560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2215-0366(19)30132-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr37-11786329231183317"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Alberta Health Services</collab>. <article-title>Adult Psychosis Program</article-title>. <year>2022</year>. <comment>Accessed May 11, 2023</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.albertahealthservices.ca/findhealth/Service.aspx?serviceAtFacilityID=1032037" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.albertahealthservices.ca/findhealth/Service.aspx?serviceAtFacilityID=1032037</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr38-11786329231183317"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdallah</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez-Almira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Community integration and associated factors among older adults with schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Serv</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>1642</fpage>-<lpage>1648</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19952155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1176/ps.2009.60.12.1642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr39-11786329231183317"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catty</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lockwood</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Use of intensive case management to reduce time in hospital in people with severe mental illness: systematic review and meta-regression</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>335</volume>:<fpage>336</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17631513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.39251.599259.55</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1949434</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr40-11786329231183317"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dieterich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Irving</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khokhar</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Intensive case management for severe mental illness</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>2017</volume>:1-273. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD007906.pub3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6472672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28067944</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr41-11786329231183317"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mueser</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Latimer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Assertive community treatment for people with severe mental illness</article-title>. <source>Dis Manag Health Outcomes</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>141</fpage>-<lpage>159</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr42-11786329231183317"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mueser</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Resnick</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Models of community care for severe mental illness: a review of research on case management</article-title>. <source>Schizophr Bull</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9502546</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/oxfordjournals.schbul.a033314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr43-11786329231183317"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Slade</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valenstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Visnic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cost savings from assertive community treatment services in an era of declining psychiatric inpatient use</article-title>. <source>Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>-<lpage>217</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22594523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1475-6773.2012.01420.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3589962</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr44-11786329231183317"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Schizophrenia Society of Alberta</collab>. <article-title>Supportive Housing</article-title>. <comment>Accessed May 11, 2023</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.schizophrenia.ab.ca/programs-services/housing-services" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.schizophrenia.ab.ca/programs-services/housing-services</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr45-11786329231183317"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aubry</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsemberis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Housing first for people with severe mental illness who are homeless: a review of the research and findings from the at home-chez soi demonstration project</article-title>. <source>Can J Psychiatry</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>467</fpage>-<lpage>474</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26720504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/070674371506001102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4679127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr46-11786329231183317"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Improving the understanding and care management of mental health high-cost patients</source>. Master&#8217;s thesis. <publisher-name>Institute of Health Policy, Management and Evaluation, University of Toronto</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>. <comment>Accessed May 11, 2023</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://hdl.handle.net/1807/79234" ext-link-type="uri">https://hdl.handle.net/1807/79234</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr47-11786329231183317"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ronksley</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobewka</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mulpuru</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Patterns of health care use in a high-cost inpatient population in Ottawa, Ontario: a retrospective observational study</article-title>. <source>CMAJ Open</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>E111</fpage>-<lpage>E118</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.9778/cmajo.20140049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4382037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25844363</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>