<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Explor Res Clin Soc Pharm</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Explor Res Clin Soc Pharm</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4203</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ercsp</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Exploratory Research in Clinical and Social Pharmacy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2667-2766</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10405092</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10405092.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10405092</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10405092</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37554927</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rcsop.2023.100307</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2667-2766(23)00088-4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100307</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Assessing treatment switch among patients with multiple sclerosis: A machine learning approach</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="J">Jieni</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yinan</given-names></name><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0015"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names initials="GJ">George J.</given-names></name><xref rid="af0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0020"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aparasu</surname><given-names initials="RR">Rajender R.</given-names></name><email>rraparasu@uh.edu</email><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cr0005" ref-type="corresp">&#8270;</xref></contrib><aff id="af0005"><label>a</label>Department of Pharmaceutical Health Outcomes and Policy, College of Pharmacy, University of Houston, TX, USA</aff><aff id="af0010"><label>b</label>Department of Pharmacy Administration, College of Pharmacy, University of Mississippi, Oxford, MS, USA</aff><aff id="af0015"><label>c</label>Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cr0005"><label>&#8270;</label>Corresponding author. <email>rraparasu@uh.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>9</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">438911</issue-id><elocation-id>100307</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>8</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>10</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>08</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-08-09 19:25:12.597"><day>09</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2023 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="ab0005"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Patients with multiple sclerosis (MS) frequently switch their Disease-Modifying Agents (DMA) for effectiveness and safety concerns. This study aimed to develop and compare the random forest (RF) machine learning (ML) model with the logistic regression (LR) model for predicting DMA switching among MS patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>This retrospective longitudinal study used the TriNetX data from a federated electronic medical records (EMR) network. Between September 2010 and May 2017, adults (aged &#8805;18) MS patients with &#8805;1 DMA prescription were identified, and the earliest DMA date was assigned as the index date. Patients prescribed any DMAs different from their index DMAs were considered as treatment switch. . The RF and LR models were built with 72 baseline characteristics and trained with 70% of the randomly split data after up-sampling. Area Under the Curves (AUC), accuracy, recall, G-measure, and F-1 score were used to evaluate the model performance.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>In this study, 7258 MS patients with &#8805;1 DMA were identified. Within two years, 16% of MS patients switched to a different DMA. The RF model obtained significantly better discrimination than the LR model (AUC&#160;=&#160;0.65 vs. 0.63, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.0001); however, the RF model had a similar predictive performance to the LR model with respect to F- and G-measures (RF: 72% and 73% vs. LR: 72% and 73%, respectively). The most influential features identified from the RF model were age, type of index medication, and year of index.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Compared to the LR model, RF performed better in predicting DMA switch in MS patients based on AUC measures; however, judged by F- and G-measures, the RF model performed similarly to LR. Further research is needed to understand the role of ML techniques in predicting treatment outcomes for the decision-making process to achieve optimal treatment goals.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="ks0005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Multiple sclerosis</kwd><kwd>Treatment switching</kwd><kwd>Real-world evidence</kwd><kwd>Machine learning</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0005">Multiple sclerosis (MS) is a central nervous system inflammatory disease resulting in demyelination and axonal degradation.<xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> MS is mainly diagnosed in the reproductive age of women and affects about 0.9 million individuals in the United States (US).<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Diagnosis of MS is associated with functional impairments, lower health-related quality of life (HRQoL), and a significant economic burden.<xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Meanwhile, research has found that over 65% of all healthcare-related costs among MS patients were attributed to prescription drugs.<xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> There is no specific autoimmune target for MS management; therefore, none of the medications for MS are curative.<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> Accordingly, the introduction of disease-modifying agents (DMA) has changed the management landscape by reducing relapse rates, improving patients' HRQoL, and delaying the development of disability.<xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></p><p id="p0010">In recent years, treatment options are quickly evolving in MS patients with the introduction of several DMAs.<xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Specifically, the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) had authorized 21 DMAs to treat MS.<xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> With many treatment options for MS, deciding on the initial DMA therapy plan can be challenging.<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> More importantly, each medication failure might result in cumulative neurologic damage, emphasizing the importance of an appropriate therapy plan for newly diagnosed individuals.<xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> If the initial DMA is ineffective for MS patients, other DMAs are often prescribed. The findings from the 2019 Milliman MS report suggested that 25.8% of patients switched to another DMA within 12&#160;months after their initial DMA.<xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> Several considerations, including tolerability, safety, and effectiveness, influence the decision to change the current DMA for MS patients.<xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> Moreover, previous studies based on the traditional regression models identified that age, sex, year of index, relapse, and MS severity were associated with treatment switching among MS patients.<xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></p><p id="p0015">Machine learning (ML) algorithms are gaining traction as viable alternatives to traditional regression approaches for prediction and categorization. ML models are increasingly being used in healthcare to generate evidence for improving the quality of care.<xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Moreover, ML-derived individual treatment options were proven to generate better outcomes in various diseases.<xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> However, applications of ML models in MS were limited to predicting the onset, subtypes, and progression of MS with clinical data.<xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="bb0140" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> To the best of our knowledge, ML algorithms have not been applied to examine the treatment-related considerations in MS. Identifying the subpopulation at high risk for treatment switching helps to guide clinical decisions, which is critical for improving health outcomes in MS patients. ML prediction model has the potential to obtain improved accuracy for treatment switching in MS. Hence, this study aimed to develop and validate the ML model to predict DMA switching and further compare the ML model with the traditional regression model for treatment switching among patients with MS.</p></sec><sec id="s0010"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="s0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Study design and data sources</title><p id="p0020">This retrospective cohort study used the TriNetx, a federated electronic medical record (EMR), from 2009 to 2019 to evaluate treatment switching in MS. TriNetX data consisted of electronic health records for over 84 million patients from 55 healthcare organizations (HCO).<xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> In the TriNetX data, both inpatient and outpatient records from the HCOs were included. Overall, the de-identified information in patients' demographic characteristics, diagnoses, procedures, lab tests, vital signs, and prescriptions was combined to assess the utilization of healthcare services. This study was deemed exempt under Category 4 from the Institutional Review Board at the University of Houston.</p></sec><sec id="s0020"><label>2.2</label><title>Study population</title><p id="p0025">Patients with at least one injectable (including glatiramer acetate and interferon beta) or oral DMA prescription (including fingolimod, dimethyl fumarate, and teriflunomide) were identified during the study period (September 2010&#8211;May 2017). Considering the data availability, the DMAs approved before 2017 were considered in this study. Patients' DMA prescription records were identified using RxNorm (produced by the National Library of Medicine) or Healthcare Common Procedure Coding System (HCPCS) codes.<xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> The date of the earliest DMA prescription was identified as the index date. Next, patients were selected if they had at least one MS diagnosis within 12&#160;months before or after the index date (identified by the International Classification of Diseases Ninth/Tenth Revision Clinical Modification [ICD-9/10-CM] codes: 340 or G35).<xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> Patients with any DMA different from their index drug within 24&#160;months from the index date were considered as treatment switching, and the rest of the patients were flagged as non-switching.</p><p id="p0030">This study did not include patients &lt;18&#160;years old at the index date. Also, patients who were prescribed any DMAs during 12&#160;months washout period were excluded to eliminate the prevalent bias. Moreover, to ensure that patients were continuously involved within the system during the study period, patients with no outpatient visit and no prescription visit within either 12&#160;months pre-index date or 24&#160;months post-index date were excluded. Due to the higher rate of relapse reduction and lower disability progression, infusion DMAs were considered as the high-efficacy treatment. <xref rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bb0170" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> Accordingly, patients with any infusion DMA prescriptions (Alemtuzumab, Mitoxantrone, Natalizumab, Ocrelizumab) within 12&#160;months before the index date to the earlier date of the DMA switching or 24&#160;months after the index date were excluded.</p></sec><sec id="s0025"><label>2.3</label><title>Conceptual framework and measurement of variables</title><p id="p0035">A total of 72 variables were selected for training the ML modelbased on a review of existing literature that identified factors assocated with treatment switching in MS.<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> These factors were further conceptualized based on the Andersen Behavioral Model (ABM) of Health Services Use, which provides a strong conceptual foundation for predicting treatment switching.<xref rid="bb0180" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> According to the ABM, healthcare utilization depends on predisposing, enabling, and need factors. Predisposing factors that explain patients' predisposition to use healthcare services include demographic and socioeconomic factors. Enabling factors affect an individual's ability to access healthcare services. Finally, need factors reflect perceived and actual health status.</p><p id="p0040">The following factors were included in this study for model training: (1) Predisposing factors: age, sex, race, and ethnicity; (2) Enabling factors: time-period (year of the index date); and (3) Need factors: Elixhauser Comorbidities, MS-related symptoms (speech symptoms, brainstem symptoms, general symptoms, cerebellar symptoms, difficulty in walking, pyramidal symptoms, sensory symptoms, bladder/bowel symptoms or sexual dysfunction, visual symptoms, and cerebral/cognitive symptoms), MS symptomatic medication use (fatigue medications, spasticity drugs, antidepressants, analgesics, bladder dysfunction medications, anticonvulsant medications, and cognition medications), relapse drugs use, and healthcare utilization (emergency room visits, inpatient visits, outpatient visits, and use of magnetic resonance imaging [MRI] procedures).<xref rid="bb0185" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> To ensure the differences between the approval date of DMAs would not impact the results, the year of the index data was included in the analysis. All of the above factors were measured 12&#160;months before the index date to capture patients' clinically relevant characteristics.</p></sec><sec id="s0030"><label>2.4</label><title>Machine learning methods</title><p id="p0045">This study used a 70% random sample for the training purpose, in which the model was trained to predict treatment switching. The remaining 30% of the data was used for testing purposes to evaluate the model performance. The non-switching class vastly outnumbered the switching class in the training dataset, with the ratio of switching to non-switching being about 1 to 6, resulting in a class imbalance problem. The imbalanced data might lead to biased prediction toward the non-switching class for machine learning classifiers.<xref rid="bb0190" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bb0195" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> Thus, the up-sampling method that duplicated random records from the minority class (switching cohort) to generate balanced cohorts was applied to create more balanced data, facilitating the classifiers to deal with the switching and non-switching classes.<xref rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref> Another advantage of the up-sampling method is that it can outperform the down-sampling method, which reduces the sample size and increases the risk of overfitting.<xref rid="bb0205" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref> The up-sampling method was implemented using the R package &#8220;caret&#8221;.<xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> All of the analyses were conducted in R version 3.6.0 (R core team, Vienna, Austria).</p><sec id="s0035"><label>2.4.1</label><title>Random forest (RF) model</title><p id="p0050">The RF model is one of the most popular predictive approaches due to its higher prediction accuracy than other classification and regression models.<xref rid="bb0210" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref> The tree-based ML method applied the decision tree framework to segregate values of predictors in a series of binary splits. The RF model is a supervised tree-based ensemble learning method that creates many decision trees inferred from bootstrap samples using bagging approaches.<xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref> Further, using the random feature selection, the ensemble's predictions are aggregated (majority vote) to make the final prediction.<xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref> Thus, the RF model is more resistant to the over-fitting issue than the classification and regression tree model.<xref rid="bb0220" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bb0225" ref-type="bibr"><sup>45</sup></xref> Compared to traditional regression models, the critical advantage of the RF algorithm that it is a very flexible algorithm that can evaluate more predictor variables that are not limited by model assumptions, such as multicollinearity.<xref rid="bb0230" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref> This study implemented the RF model with the R package &#8220;randomForest&#8221;.<xref rid="bb0235" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47</sup></xref></p><p id="p0055">There were three critical hyperparameters in the RF model that this study focused on: (1) the number of trees (ntree), which indicated the number of trees that the algorithm creates before taking the most votes or averaging the predictions; (2) the number of variables randomly sampled at each split (mtry), which could influence the model's error rates, stability, and accuracy of single trees; (3) the maximal number of leaf nodes for each tree (maxdepth), which impacts the balance and complexity of trees.<xref rid="bb0240" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref> The optimal values for the above parameters were tuned in the 10-fold cross-validation and then used to decide the final model. Since a large number of trees are built, the RF model will not require a substantial tuning process; in this study, a model consisting of 200 distinct trees (ntree) was generated, sufficiently large enough for out-of-bag error (OOB) to settle down.<xref rid="bb0245" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref> The default of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:msqrt><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:msqrt></mml:math></inline-formula> (n means the total number of predictors at each node) is used for the selected features at each node (mtry&#160;=&#160;16).<xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref> Moreover, the maximal number of leaf nodes for each tree was tuned in a grid ranging between 10 and 200, and the optimal number of terminal node trees was obtained at 50. The most influential predictors were identified based on the mean decreased accuracy and mean decreased Gini of the RF model.<xref rid="bb0250" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref></p></sec><sec id="s0040"><label>2.4.2</label><title>Logistic regression (LR) model</title><p id="p0060">The LR model is a traditional regression method for classification, primarily for dichotomous outcomes. The assumptions of the LR model (e.g., linearity assumption, multicollinearity, and homoscedasticity) are challenging to be satisfied because the underlying data-generating model is unknown. In the LR model, the 10-fold cross-validation was applied to get the best value based on the misclassification error to optimize the values for the punishment parameter (&#955;) while keeping the minimized model deviance. The important predictors for switching were identified based on the statistical significance. In this study, the LR model was implemented with the &#8220;glmnet&#8221; package.<xref rid="bb0255" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0045"><label>2.5</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0065">Using the testing data, this study assessed the LR and the RF model with the area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUROC).<xref rid="bb0260" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52</sup></xref> The Receiver Operating Characteristics (ROC) curve plot shows the sensitivity (true positive rate) as a function of the specificity (false negative) rate for a variety of thresholds. The area under the curve (AUC) for the LR and the RF machine learning classifiers were compared using the 2-sided DeLong test.<xref rid="bb0265" ref-type="bibr"><sup>53</sup></xref> In addition, considering the imbalanced data, the F-measure and G-measure were introduced for evaluating these models from the testing data.<xref rid="bb0270" ref-type="bibr"><sup>54</sup></xref> The F-measure has been widely employed in most ML applications, especially for a binary outcome.<xref rid="bb0275" ref-type="bibr"><sup>55</sup></xref> The F-measure was calculated by the harmonic mean of precision and recall that could integrate precision and recall into a single measurement that accounts for both perspectives.<xref rid="bb0280" ref-type="bibr"><sup>56</sup></xref> G-measure (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Precision</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#215;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Recall</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:math></inline-formula>) aimed to evaluate the model performance in predicting the majority and minority groups.<xref rid="bb0285" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bb0290" ref-type="bibr"><sup>58</sup></xref> Also, the G-measure is a measurement that aims to evaluate the model performance by preventing the overfitting of the negative class and underfitting of the positive class in the model.<xref rid="bb0295" ref-type="bibr"><sup>59</sup></xref> Accordingly, both measures could provide additional justification for unbalanced data. The F- and G- measures for the RF classifier and the LR model were compared based on absolute difference.<xref rid="bb0285" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bb0290" ref-type="bibr"><sup>58</sup></xref> Other performance measurements (accuracy, specificity, precision, and recall) in evaluating the RF and the LR model were also reported based on a confusion matrix using the caret package.<xref rid="bb0300" ref-type="bibr"><sup>60</sup></xref></p><p id="p0070">Furthermore, this study compared switching and non-switching cohorts for their baseline characteristics. Additionally, to ensure the power of validation, each baseline characteristic was compared between the training and testing data. All analyses were conducted using server SAS statistical software version 9.4 (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA) at a 0.05 level of significance.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0050"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="s0055"><label>3.1</label><title>Cohort characteristics</title><p id="p0075">This study identified 7258 MS patients who were prescribed &#8805;1 DMA between September 2010 and May 2017 after applying the inclusion/exclusion criteria. (See <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>) Overall, 1161 (16%) of MS patients switched to a different DMA within two years. From this study sample, 5079 (69.98%) MS patients were selected for the training data, and 2179 (30.02%) MS patients were set into the testing data. Additionally, after applying the up-sampling method, 8566 MS patients (4283 patients in each cohort) were considered in building up the RF and ML model.<fig id="f0005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Study design diagram.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0005">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0060"><label>3.2</label><title>Study population characteristics</title><p id="p0080">Patients who switched to different DMAs were younger than those who did not (mean age: 42.83 vs. 47.09, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.0001, <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). A higher percentage of patients from the non-switching cohort had oral DMA as their index medication (29.63% vs. 37.56%, p&#160;&lt;&#160;0.0001). The most prevalent comorbidities among patients who switched were connective tissue diseases (27.56%), mood disorders (20.50%), and depression (20.07%). Patients who switched had a higher proportion of brainstem symptoms (12.06% vs. 9.89%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.0255), walking difficulties (11.20% vs. 7.77%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.0001), sensory symptoms (20.24% vs. 16.43%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.0016), and visual symptoms (12.58% vs. 10.04%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.0096), as well as being more likely to be prescribed at least one MS symptomatic medication (64.34% vs. 59.46%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.0018), and corticosteroids (23.86% vs. 18.09%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.0001). Patients from the switching cohort had more outpatient visits (10.07 vs. 8.98, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.0051), and more of them had at least one MRI procedure during the baseline period (30.84% vs. 25.68%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.0003). No significant differences were observed in patients' characteristics between the testing and training datasets (Supplemental Table 1).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Patients baseline characteristics.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0015">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Patients with treatment switching<hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Patients without treatment switching<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">1161 (16.00%)<hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">6097 (84.00%)<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Predisposing Factors</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Age Category</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Mean, SD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.83</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.90</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.09</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Younger adults (18&#8211;44&#160;years)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">646</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.64%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2602</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.68%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Middle-aged adults (45&#8211;64&#160;years)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">471</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.57%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.22%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Old adults (&#8805;65&#160;years)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">44</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.79%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">494</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.10%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Sex</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Female</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">883</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.06%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4634</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.00%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9705</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">278</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.94%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1463</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.00%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9705</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Race</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;African American</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">123</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.59%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">573</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.40%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2045</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Whites</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">955</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.26%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5061</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">83.01%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5333</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Others</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">83</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.15%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">463</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.59%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5984</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Ethnicity</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hispanic or Latino</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.31%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">219</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.59%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2374</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Not Hispanic or Latino</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1031</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">88.80%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5455</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">89.47%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.499</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Unknown</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">80</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.89%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">423</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.94%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9537</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Enabling Factor</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Time-period (of index date)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;2010&#8211;11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">148</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.75%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1108</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.17%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;2012&#8211;13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">391</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.68%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1576</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.85%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;2014&#8211;15</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">461</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.71%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2364</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.77%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5497</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;2016&#8211;17</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">161</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.87%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1049</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.21%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0052</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Index Drug</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Injectable DMA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">817</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.37%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3807</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.44%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Interferon beta 1a</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">253</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.79%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1154</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.93%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0237</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Interferon beta 1b</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">55</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.74%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">235</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.85%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1592</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Peginterferon beta</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.55%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.67%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0023</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Glatiramer acetate</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">491</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.29%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2377</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.99%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0348</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Oral DMA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">344</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.63%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2290</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.56%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Fingolimod</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.61%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">796</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.06%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Dimethyl fumarate</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">202</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.40%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1170</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.19%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1531</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Teriflunomide</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.62%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">324</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.31%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0155</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Need Factors</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Elixhauser Comorbidities</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Congestive heart failure</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.60%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.71%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6992</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Cardiac arrhythmia</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.50%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">218</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.58%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0634</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Valvular disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.21%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6032</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Pulmonary circulation disorders</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.26%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.59%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1561</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Peripheral vascular disorders</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">69</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.13%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4158</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hypertension uncomplicated</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">121</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.42%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">781</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.81%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0238</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hypertension complicated</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.69%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.66%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8988</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Paralysis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.19%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">228</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.74%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3575</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other neurological disorders</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">158</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.61%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">705</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.56%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0484</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Chronic pulmonary disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">59</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.08%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">306</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.02%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9283</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Diabetes uncomplicated</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.31%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">265</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.35%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9514</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Diabetes complicated</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.72%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">84</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.38%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3647</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hypothyroidism</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">68</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.86%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">364</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.97%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8813</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Renal failure</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.60%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.82%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4423</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Peptic ulcer disease, excluding bleeding</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.60%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">62</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1828</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;AIDS/HIV</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.34%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3253</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Lymphoma</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4497</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Metastatic cancer</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.17%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.16%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9494</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Liver disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0507</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Solid tumor without metastasis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.21%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">98</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.61%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.309</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Rheumatoid arthritis/collagen related disorders</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.24%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">127</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.08%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7338</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Coagulopathy</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.34%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">62</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.027</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Obesity</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">49</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.22%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">275</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.51%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6611</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Weight loss</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.43%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">71</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.16%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0244</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Fluid and electrolyte disorders</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.53%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">234</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.84%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6161</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Blood loss anemia</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1022</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Deficiency anemia</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.21%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">98</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.61%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.309</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Alcohol abuse</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.69%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">53</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.87%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5376</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Drug abuse</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.60%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">86</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.41%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0249</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Psychoses</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.78%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">76</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.25%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1713</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Depression</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">233</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.07%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1056</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.32%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0247</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Elixhauser Comorbidities Score</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Mean, SD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.22</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.01</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.47</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.67</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0577</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#8804;0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">926</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">79.76%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4902</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">80.40%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6146</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;1&#8211;4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">47</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.05%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">277</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.54%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4541</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#8805;5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">188</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.19%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">918</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.06%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3234</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Other Comorbidities</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Cancer</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.58%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">202</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.31%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1955</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Metabolic Disorder</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Thyroid disorders</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">92</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.92%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">439</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.20%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3853</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Nutritional deficiencies</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">140</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.06%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">840</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.78%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1163</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Lipid disorders</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">92</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.92%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">568</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.32%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1306</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Mental Illness</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Anxiety</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">116</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.99%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">582</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.55%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6368</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Mood disorders</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">238</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.50%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1084</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.78%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0277</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Other Neurological disorders</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Paralysis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.01%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">227</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.72%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2356</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Epilepsy, convulsions</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.19%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">195</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.20%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9839</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Headache; including migraine</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">197</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.97%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">805</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.20%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0007</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Eye disorders</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">133</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.46%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">528</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.66%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0024</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Ear and sense organ disorders</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.10%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">183</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.00%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8561</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Circulatory/vascular disorders</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Heart diseases</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.33%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">220</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.61%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0271</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Cerebrovascular disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.55%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">117</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.92%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3942</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Respiratory disorders</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and bronchiectasis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.26%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">53</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.87%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0292</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Genitourinary disorders</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Diseases of the urinary system</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">166</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.30%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">896</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.70%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7253</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Diseases of skin and subcutaneous tissue</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.07%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">125</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.05%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9701</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Musculoskeletal disorders</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Non-traumatic joint disorders</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">121</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.42%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">588</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.64%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4132</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Spondylosis; intervertebral disc disorders; other back problems</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">194</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.71%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1076</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.65%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4406</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other connective tissue diseases (including fibromyalgia)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">320</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.56%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1575</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.83%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2187</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Ill-defined conditions</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Nausea, vomiting/abdominal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">49</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.22%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">234</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.84%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5371</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;MS-Related Symptoms</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Bladder/bowel symptoms or sexual dysfunction</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">182</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.68%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">989</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.22%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6436</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Brainstem symptoms</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">140</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.06%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">603</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.89%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0255</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Cerebellar symptoms</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.52%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">59</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.135</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Cerebral/Cognitive symptoms</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">133</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.46%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">600</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.84%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0942</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Difficulty walking</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">130</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.20%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">474</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.77%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;General symptoms</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">232</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.98%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1252</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.53%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6691</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Pyramidal symptoms</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">95</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.18%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">522</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.56%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6713</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Sensory symptoms</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">235</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.24%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1002</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.43%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0016</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Speech symptoms</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.38%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">112</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.84%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2763</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Visual symptoms</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">146</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.58%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">612</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.04%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0096</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;None of the above</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">506</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.58%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2883</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.29%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0205</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;MS Severity Score</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Mean, SD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.93</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.55</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.85</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.51</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;MS Symptomatic Medication Use</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Analgesics</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">382</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.90%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1811</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.70%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0296</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Antidepressants</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">342</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.46%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1580</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.91%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0122</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Bladder dysfunction medications</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">92</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.92%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">554</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.09%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2024</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Cognition medications</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.67%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4801</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Fatigue medications</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">160</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.78%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">771</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.65%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2889</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other anticonvulsant medications</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">135</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.63%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">570</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.35%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0162</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Spasticity drugs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">388</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.42%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1922</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.52%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2037</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;None of the above</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">414</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.66%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2472</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.54%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0018</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Relapse Drugs</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Any corticosteroids</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">277</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.86%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1103</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.09%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;All-Cause Healthcare Utilization</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Any emergency room visits</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">159</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.70%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">762</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.50%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2614</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;# of emergency room visits</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.30</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0786</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Any inpatient visits</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">101</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.70%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">429</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.04%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0459</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;# of inpatient visits</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.82</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.63</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1053</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Length of stays</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.61</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.52</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.51</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4005</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Any outpatient visits</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1161</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100.00%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6097</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100.00%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;# of outpatient visits</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.07</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.01</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.98</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.67</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0051</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;MS-related Healthcare Utilization</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Any emergency room visits</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">95</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.18%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">470</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.71%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5807</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;# of emergency room visits</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.68</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.51</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2711</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Any inpatient visits</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">79</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.80%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">358</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.87%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2207</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;# of inpatient visits</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.65</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.42</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2103</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Length of stays</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.47</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.69</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.41</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.97</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4662</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Any outpatient visits</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1040</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">89.58%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5363</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">87.96%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1173</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;# of outpatient visits</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.45</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.01</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.08</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0077</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Any MRI procedures</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">358</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.84%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1566</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.68%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0003</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;# of MRI procedures</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.44</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.76</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.34</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.68</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Vital Sign</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;BMI</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Underweight, &lt;18</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">379</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.64%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1993</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.69%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9767</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Healthy, 18&#8211;25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">62</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.828</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Overweight, 26&#8211;29</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">267</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.00%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1490</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.44%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2935</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Obese, &#8805;30</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">217</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.69%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1076</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.65%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3947</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Not recorded</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">287</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.72%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1476</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.21%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7096</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Blood Pressure Diastolic</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Normal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">539</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.43%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3159</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.81%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0008</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Abnormal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">361</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.09%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1692</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.75%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0205</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Not recorded</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">261</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.48%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1246</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.44%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1155</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Blood Pressure Systolic</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Normal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">539</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.43%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3159</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.81%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0008</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Abnormal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">227</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.55%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1043</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.11%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0444</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Not recorded</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">395</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.02%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1895</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.08%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0481</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Lab Test</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Hemoglobin [Mass/volume]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Normal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">576</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.61%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2833</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.47%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0489</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Abnormal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">107</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.22%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">599</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.82%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5215</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Not recorded</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">478</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.17%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2665</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.71%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1096</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Leukocytes [#/volume]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Normal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">546</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.03%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2583</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.37%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0033</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Abnormal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">114</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.82%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">495</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.12%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0555</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Not recorded</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">501</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.15%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3019</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.52%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Hematocrit [Volume Fraction]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Normal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">546</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.03%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2490</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.84%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Abnormal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.73%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">549</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.00%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4294</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Not recorded</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">502</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.24%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3058</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.16%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Platelets [#/volume]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Normal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">633</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">54.52%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2882</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.27%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Abnormal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.50%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">143</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.35%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7543</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Not recorded</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">499</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.98%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3072</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.39%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Creatinine [Mass/volume]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Normal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">511</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.01%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2606</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.74%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4225</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Abnormal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">61</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.25%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">372</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.10%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2639</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Not recorded</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">589</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.73%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3119</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.16%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.791</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">&#160;Monocytes [#/volume]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Normal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">592</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.99%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2874</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.14%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.016</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Abnormal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.29%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.69%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0329</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Not recorded</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">554</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.72%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3181</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.17%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0054</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="sp0020"><p>SD: Standard deviation.</p></fn><fn id="sp0025"><p>DMA: Disease Modifying Agent.</p></fn><fn id="sp0030"><p>AIDS/ HIV: Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome/ Human Immunodeficiency Virus.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0065"><label>3.3</label><title>Important predictors of switching</title><p id="p0085">From the RF model, the top five most influential predictors identified in this study were: age, type of index medication, year of index, number of outpatient visits, and Body mass index (BMI) (See <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Meanwhile, age, year of index, Elixhauser Comorbidities Score, type of index medication, BMI, comorbidities conditions (cerebral/cognitive symptoms, eye disorders, nutritional deficiencies, hypertension, other neurological disorders, diabetes, thyroid disorders, heart diseases, and spondylosis), lab test (hemoglobin level, platelet count, and monocyte count), and healthcare utilization (inpatient visits, MS-related inpatient, and MS-related outpatient) were statistically significant factors associated with the treatment switching in the LR model.<fig id="f0010" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Top 10 Most Influential Predictors from the Random Forest Model.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0010">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0070"><label>3.4</label><title>Comparison of random forest model and logistic regression</title><p id="p0090">The RF model improved the AUC (0.65 vs. 0.63, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.0001) using the testing data compared to the LR model. However, the RF model had a similar G-Measure score as the LR model (0.73 vs. 0.73); the RF model had an almost equal F-Measure score as the LR model (0.72 vs. 0.72). Other performance measurements for both models varied: for RF: the accuracy was 0.61, specificity was 0.63, precision was 0.89, and recall was 60%; for LR, the accuracy was 0.63, specificity was 0.57, precision was 0.87, the recall was 61%. The AUCs observed in training data were comparable to the AUCs observed in testing data in both models. Details of all performance measures can be found in <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Model Performance: Random Forest vs. Logistic Regression.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0020">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Test AUC</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Accuracy</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Specificity</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Precision</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recall (Sensitivity)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">F-1</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">G-measure</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">p-value</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Train AUC</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Logistic Regression</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6318</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6007&#8211;0.6229</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">63%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">57%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">87%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">61%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">72%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">73%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6748</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Random Forest</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6513</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6204&#8211;0.6823</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">61%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">63%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">89%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">60%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">72%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">73%</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7900</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="sp0040"><p>AUC: Area under the ROC (Receiver Operating Characteristics) curve.</p></fn><fn id="sp0045"><p>CI: Confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0075"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0095">ML methods have been broadly applied to predict healthcare utilization (e.g., readmissions and inpatient mortality). <xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bb0265" ref-type="bibr"><sup>53</sup></xref> In MS, ML models have been applied to predict the onset of MS, MS subtypes, and the progression of MS.<xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="bb0140" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> However, studies utilizing the ML approach to evaluate treatment considerations are very limited. To the best of our knowledge, this study is the first attempt to leverage ML methods, namely RF, to predict treatment switching in MS patients. This study developed and compared the RF model with the LR model to predict treatment switching among MS patients using national electronic medical record data. Accurately identifying MS patients at risk of switching to inform targeted intervention may improve MS patients' health outcomes. Literature has supported that ML-derived individual treatment selections were proven to generate better disease outcomes.<xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> A previous study found that patients who took the RF model suggested epilepsy treatment had considerably higher success rates and lower healthcare utilization than those who took different treatments.<xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> Thus, personalized and evidence-based medicine might be achieved using ML approaches for treatment selection and optimizing patient outcomes.</p><p id="p0100">This study adds to existing research regarding the utility and value of ML for treatment considerations. The AUC observed in this study for the RF model was 0.65, an improvement over the AUC of 0.63 observed in the LR model. A previous study found involving the RF model found an AUC of 0.70 for epilepsy treatment, but the treatment change was different from our study, which included any regimen changes or a complete withdrawal.<xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> However, the AUC indicated an acceptable model performance distinguishing between switchers and non-switching patients. Additionally, in the case of predicting treatment switching among MS patients, it is preferable to have a greater sensitivity than specificity since identifying patients at risk for treatment switching could assist providers in their treatment decision-making process. As a result, in the interest of healthcare providers who aimed to determine the true positives correctly, a higher sensitivity is preferred , especially when evaluating the model performance.</p><p id="p0105">There is an ongoing debate about the comparative performance of traditional regression approaches compared to ML models.<xref rid="bb0305" ref-type="bibr"><sup>61</sup></xref> Thus, this study applied several performance metrics to evaluate the relative performance of the RF model vs. the LR model in predicting treatment switching for MS patients. When data is imbalanced, the ROC curve, which plots sensitivity against specificity, was marked as a more robust measurement than accuracy.<xref rid="bb0310" ref-type="bibr"><sup>62</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bb0315" ref-type="bibr"><sup>63</sup></xref> However, misinterpreting specificity might also deceive the AUC when evaluating ML models in imbalanced data.<xref rid="bb0320" ref-type="bibr"><sup>64</sup></xref> Considering the limitations of AUC, F- and G-measures were identified as more valuable tools because of the ability to detect the true positives correctly.<xref rid="bb0315" ref-type="bibr"><sup>63</sup></xref> In this study, the RF reported fair scores for F- and G- measures. Although findings showed that the RF offered a notable improvement over LR based on AUC, RF performed similarly to LR judged by F- and G-measures.</p><p id="p0110">Predictive factors are valuable in identifying targets to optimize treatment selection and associated health outcomes in patients with MS. Results from the LR model can help identify the factors and the strength of association with treatment switching among MS patients. Additionally, one of the advantages of applying the RF algorithm is that the model could generate this desired ranking by its relative importance.<xref rid="bb0325" ref-type="bibr"><sup>65</sup></xref> Among all the factors, the RF model identified the most critical factor in this study was age. This finding is consistent with previous studies that recognize the importance of age on the treatment patterns in MS patients.<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> A systematic review found that age could impact MS progression, immunosenescence, and DMA selection and engagement.<xref rid="bb0330" ref-type="bibr"><sup>66</sup></xref> Also, the progression of the disease is observed to be slower among older MS patients than among young and middle-aged MS patients, which might decrease the need for treatment switching among older patients. Furthermore, adverse drug events, such as severe infections, are more commonly observed among the older population.<xref rid="bb0335" ref-type="bibr"><sup>67</sup></xref> Additionally, the risk-benefit consideration of selecting DMA could be influenced by age-related comorbidities, leading to potential treatment switching among older MS patients.<xref rid="bb0330" ref-type="bibr"><sup>66</sup></xref></p><p id="p0115">Moreover, the type of index medication and the year of the index date were observed as the other two top important factors in predicting treatment switching, which could be explained by the introduction of the first oral DMA in 2010.<xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> This might also be due to the prescriber's experience and the availability of oral DMAs on the market. Many MS patients switched from injectable to oral DMAs after the launch of oral DMAs.<xref rid="bb0245" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bb0340" ref-type="bibr"><sup>68</sup></xref> Also, evidence from clinical trials and real-world data showed that oral DMAs were associated with reduced relapse rates, delayed MS progression, and higher treatment adherence rates than injectable DMAs.<xref rid="bb0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="bb0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, <xref rid="bb0355" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>, <xref rid="bb0360" ref-type="bibr">72</xref> In addition to demographic and clinical factors, the RF model revealed the association between BMI and treatment switching among MS patients. Several studies have evaluated the influence of nutrition and diet on the pathophysiology of MS.<xref rid="bb0365" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>, <xref rid="bb0370" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>, <xref rid="bb0375" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>, <xref rid="bb0380" ref-type="bibr">76</xref> For instance, obese MS patients were reported with higher disease activity than normal or underweight patients.<xref rid="bb0380" ref-type="bibr"><sup>76</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bb0385" ref-type="bibr"><sup>77</sup></xref> Thus, consideration of BMI could add value to making treatment decisions for MS patients based on the literature and findings from this study. Consistent with the results from the RF model, the LR model also found that the abovementioned top important factors were statistically significantly associated with treatment switching among MS patients.</p><sec id="s0080"><label>4.1</label><title>Strength and limitations</title><p id="p0120">To our knowledge, this is the first study that applied ML methods to examine DMA treatment switching among MS patients. Using a predictive analytics framework to evaluate treatment switching can help manage MS care better and more efficiently. Factors considered in this study involved both demographic and clinical characteristics that are generally richer in the EMR than in claims data. This study also considered healthcare utilization and lab test when predicting treatment switching. In addition, the study's findings can provide real-world insights into patients' treatment patterns and the factors that could influence treatment switching in MS.</p><p id="p0125">This study, however, also had some limitations that need to be considered. First, medical records from the TriNetX data were mainly gathered from academic hospitals, which may restrict the generalizability of our findings. Secondly, though the rate of treatment switching was low compared to prior research using claims data, the study finding was consistent with previous analyses using electronic medical records.<xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> Thirdly, this study developed and compared models in predicting any DMA switching among patients with MS; future studies should compare the treatment switching with different types of DMAs to improve MS care. Fourth, this study evaluated the model performance with an internal validation dataset; more work is needed applying those models with an external dataset to implement the model when predicting treatment switching. Furthermore, several sociodemographic, clinical, and behavioral characteristics, such as insurance status, prescribers, and patients' preferences, were not available in the TriNetX data, which might result in residual confounding and limit the further investigation of our findings. The TriNetX data lacked information on MS activity and duration of MS. Nevertheless; our analysis included the MS severity score, which had previously been validated as a proxy for the disease severity and the disability status.<xref rid="bb0390" ref-type="bibr"><sup>78</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bb0395" ref-type="bibr"><sup>79</sup></xref></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0085"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0130">The RF model developed in this study provided a better prediction for treatment switching in MS compared to the LR model based on the AUC. The important contributing factors the RF model identified for treatment switching were age, type of index DMA, and time-period of the initial DMA. These factors may help identify targets to optimize treatment selection and associated health outcomes in patients with MS. More research is needed to understand the role and impact of ML algorithms in therapy selection for improving MS care.</p></sec><sec id="s0090"><title>Funding</title><p id="p0135">We have no founding support regarding this study.</p></sec><sec id="s0095"><title>Disclosures</title><p id="p0140">We confirm that this work is original and has not been published elsewhere, nor is it currently under consideration for publication elsewhere. A part of the study findings was submitted to the 2022 International Society for Pharmacoeconomics and Outcomes Research (ISPOR) National Conference.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title><p id="p0145">Dr. Aparasu has received research funding from Astellas Inc., Incyte Corp., Gilead, and Novartis Inc. for projects unrelated to the current work. Dr. Hutton reports grants from Biogen, Novartis, MedImmune, Hoffman-LaRoche, E.M.D. Serono, Sanofi, and personal fees from Novartis, Sanofi, Celgene outside the submitted work. The other authors declare no conflicts of interest for this article.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bi0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bb0005"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kutzelnigg</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lassmann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathology of multiple sclerosis and related inflammatory demyelinating diseases</article-title><source>Handb Clin Neurol</source><volume>122</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24507512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/B978-0-444-52001-2.00002-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0010"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallin</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Culpepper</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The prevalence of MS in the United States</article-title><source>Neurology.</source><volume>92</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000007035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6442006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30770430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0015"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGinley</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldschmidt</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rae-Grant</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis and treatment of multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>JAMA.</source><volume>325</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.26858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33620411</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0020"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overview and diagnosis of multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Am J Manag Care</source><volume>22</volume><issue>6 Suppl</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>s141</fpage><lpage>s150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27356023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0025"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghushchyan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McQueen</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Burden of multiple sclerosis on direct, indirect costs and quality of life: national US estimates</article-title><source>Mult Scler Relat Disord</source><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25878010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.msard.2013.09.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0030"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Earla</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aparasu</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Marginal health care expenditure burden among US civilian noninstitutionalized individuals with multiple sclerosis: 2010-2015</article-title><source>J Manag Care Spec Pharm</source><volume>26</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>741</fpage><lpage>749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32463779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18553/jmcp.2020.26.6.741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10391019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0035"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zakeri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aparasu</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health-related quality of life of patients with multiple sclerosis: analysis of ten years of national data</article-title><source>Mult Scler Relat Disord</source><volume>66</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">104019</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.msard.2022.104019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35839614</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0040"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rae-Grant</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>G.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marrie</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Practice guideline recommendations summary: disease-modifying therapies for adults with multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Neurology.</source><volume>90</volume><issue>17</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000005347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29686116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0045"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Comi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Radaelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soelberg</surname><given-names>S&#248;rensen P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolving concepts in the treatment of relapsing multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>389</volume><issue>10076</issue><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(16)32388-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27889192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0050"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elsisi</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hincapie</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expenditure, utilization, and cost of specialty drugs for multiple sclerosis in the US Medicaid population, 2008-2018</article-title><source>Am Health Drug Benefits</source><volume>13</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32724502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7370830</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0055"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gajofatto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benedetti</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment strategies for multiple sclerosis: when to start, when to change, when to stop?</article-title><source>World J Clin Cases</source><volume>3</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>545</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12998/wjcc.v3.i7.545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26244148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4517331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0060"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chitnis</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trojano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complexity of MS management in the current treatment era</article-title><source>Neurology.</source><volume>90</volume><issue>17</issue><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000005399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29686111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0065"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sacc&#224;</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanzillo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Signori</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Determinants of therapy switch in multiple sclerosis treatment-na&#239;ve patients: a real-life study</article-title><source>Mult Scler J</source><volume>25</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1352458518790390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30044207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0070"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naismith</surname><given-names>R.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple sclerosis therapeutic strategies: start safe and effective, reassess early, and escalate if necessary</article-title><source>Neurol Clin Pract</source><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/CPJ.0b013e31823cc2b0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23634357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3613188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0075"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="rf0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Milliman Client Report</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple Sclerosis: New Perspectives on the Patient Journey - 2019 Update2019</article-title><comment>Accessed October 7, 2021</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.milliman.com/-/media/milliman/importedfiles/uploadedfiles/insight/2019/ms-patient-journey-2019.ashx" id="ir0010">https://us.milliman.com/-/media/milliman/importedfiles/uploadedfiles/insight/2019/ms-patient-journey-2019.ashx</ext-link><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0080"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kee</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retrospective Claims Analysis of Treatment Patterns, Relapse, Utilization, and Cost Among Patients with Multiple Sclerosis Initiating Second-Line Disease-Modifying Therapy</article-title><source>Drugs Real World Outcomes</source><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2021 Dec</year><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40801-021-00251-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34136997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8605953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0085"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahesri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gagne</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Utilization patterns of Oral disease-modifying drugs in commercially insured patients with multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>J Manag Care Spec Pharm</source><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18553/jmcp.2019.25.1.113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10397781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30589630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0090"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chikermane</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Earla</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aparasu</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with switching from injectable to oral disease modifying agents among patients with multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Mult Scler Relat Disord</source><volume>60</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">103703</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.msard.2022.103703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35278846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0095"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predictive value of intraoperative facial motor evoked potentials in vestibular schwannoma surgery under 2 anesthesia protocols</article-title><source>World Neurosurg</source><volume>111</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>e267</fpage><lpage>e276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29258928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.wneu.2017.12.029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0100"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Q.V.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Deep learning for healthcare decision making with EMRs</part-title><source>2014 IEEE International Conference on Bioinformatics and Biomedicine (BIBM<italic toggle="yes">)</italic></source><year>2014</year><publisher-name>IEEE</publisher-name><fpage>556</fpage><lpage>559</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0105"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manogaran</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A survey of big data architectures and machine learning algorithms in healthcare</article-title><source>Int J Biomed Eng Technol</source><volume>25</volume><issue>2&#8211;4</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>211</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0110"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchlak</surname><given-names>Q.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esmaili</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leveque</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Machine learning applications to clinical decision support in neurosurgery: an artificial intelligence augmented systematic review</article-title><source>Neurosurg Rev</source><volume>43</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>1235</fpage><lpage>1253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31422572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10143-019-01163-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0115"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Devinsky</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dilley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozery-Flato</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Changing the approach to treatment choice in epilepsy using big data</article-title><source>Epilepsy Behav</source><volume>56</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2015.12.039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26827299</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0120"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luedtke</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadikova</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development and validation of a machine learning individualized treatment rule in first-episode schizophrenia</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e1921660</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.21660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7043195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32083693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0125"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Senders</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Staples</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karhade</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Machine learning and neurosurgical outcome prediction: a systematic review</article-title><source>World Neurosurg</source><volume>109</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>476</fpage><lpage>486.e1</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2017.09.149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28986230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0130"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seccia</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salvetti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crisanti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palagi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grassi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Machine learning use for prognostic purposes in multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Life.</source><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>122</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/life11020122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33562572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7914671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0135"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Darvishi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamidi</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poorolajal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prediction of multiple sclerosis disease using machine learning classifiers: a comparative study</article-title><source>J Prev Med Hyg</source><volume>62</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>E192</fpage><lpage>E199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15167/2421-4248/jpmh2021.62.1.1651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34322636</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8283630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0140"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eshaghi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wijeratne</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identifying multiple sclerosis subtypes using unsupervised machine learning and MRI data</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>2078</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-22265-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33824310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8024377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0145"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>V&#225;zquez-Marrufo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarrias-Arrabal</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garc&#237;a-Torres</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;n-Clemente</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Izquierdo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A systematic review of the application of machine-learning algorithms in multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Neurologia (Engl Ed)</source><year>2021 Feb 3</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nrl.2020.10.017</pub-id><comment>S0213-4853(20)30431-X. English, Spanish</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33549371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0150"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stapff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilderbrand</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First-line treatment of essential hypertension: a real-world analysis across four antihypertensive treatment classes</article-title><source>J Clin Hypertens</source><volume>21</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jch.13531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8030363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30980608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0155"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ontaneda</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carraro</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative effectiveness of dimethyl fumarate versus fingolimod and teriflunomide among MS patients switching from first-generation platform therapies in the US</article-title><source>Mult Scler Relat Disord</source><year>2019</year><fpage>27</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.msard.2018.09.038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30368221</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0160"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Culpepper</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marrie</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langer-Gould</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Validation of an algorithm for identifying MS cases in administrative health claims datasets</article-title><source>Neurology.</source><volume>92</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>e1016</fpage><lpage>e1028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000007043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30770432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6442008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0165"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Butzkueven</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhib-Jalbut</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Brain health: time matters in multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Mult Scler Relat Disord</source><volume>9</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>S5</fpage><lpage>S48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.msard.2016.07.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27640924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0170"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vollmer</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>v., Williams IM, Alvarez E.</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple sclerosis phenotypes as a continuum</article-title><source>Neurol Clin Pract</source><volume>11</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>342</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/CPJ.0000000000001045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34476126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8382415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0175"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0175"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>The caret package</part-title><source>R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria</source><year>2023</year><comment>URL</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cranr-projectorg/package=caret" id="ir0015">https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/caret/caret.pdf</ext-link><comment>Published March 21, 2023</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0180"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0180"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>RM.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Revisiting the behavioral model and access to medical care: does it matter?</article-title><source>J Health Soc Behav</source><volume>36</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1995 Mar</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7738325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0185"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0185"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elixhauser</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comorbidity measures for use with administrative data</article-title><source>Med Care</source><volume>36</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1998</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005650-199801000-00004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9431328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0190"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0190"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blagus</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lusa</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Class prediction for high-dimensional class-imbalanced data</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20961420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2105-11-523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3098087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0195"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0195"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamalov</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thabtah</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>H.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Feature Selection in Imbalanced Data</article-title><source>Ann. Data. Sci.</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40745-021-00366-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0200"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0200"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Provost</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Machine learning from imbalanced data sets 101</part-title><source>Proceedings of the AAAI&#8217;2000 Workshop on Imbalanced Data Sets</source><volume>vol. 68</volume><year>2000</year><publisher-name>AAAI Press</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>3</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0205"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0205"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Smeden</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moons</surname><given-names>K.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Groot</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sample size for binary logistic prediction models: beyond events per variable criteria</article-title><source>Stat Methods Med Res</source><volume>28</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>2455</fpage><lpage>2474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0962280218784726</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29966490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6710621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0210"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0210"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verikas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gelzinis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bacauskiene</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mining data with random forests: a survey and results of new tests</article-title><source>Pattern Recogn</source><volume>44</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>330</fpage><lpage>349</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0215"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0215"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Breiman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Random forests</article-title><source>Mach Learn</source><volume>45</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2001</year><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1010933404324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0220"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0220"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Acion</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelmansky</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Laan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahker</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arndt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of a machine learning framework to predict substance use disorder treatment success</article-title><source>PloS One</source><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2017</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0175383</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0175383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5386258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28394905</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0225"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0225"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liaw</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breiman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Using Random Forest to Learn Imbalanced Data</part-title><volume>110(1&#8722;12)</volume><year>2004</year><publisher-name>University of California</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc><fpage>24</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0230"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0230"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deo</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nallamothu</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Learning about machine learning: the promise and pitfalls of big data and the electronic health record</article-title><source>Circ Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes</source><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>618</fpage><lpage>620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28263936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.116.003308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5832331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0235"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0235"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liaw</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiener</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Classification and regression by randomForest</article-title><source>R News</source><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0240"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0240"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Probst</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boulesteix</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hyperparameters and tuning strategies for random forest</article-title><source>Wiley Interdiscip Rev Data Min Knowl Discov</source><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e1301</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0245"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0245"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>v., Vaduganathan M, Evers T, Schneeweiss S.</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of machine learning methods with traditional models for use of administrative claims with electronic medical records to predict heart failure outcomes</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e1918962</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.18962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6991258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31922560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0250"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0250"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeLong</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeLong</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke-Pearson</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparing the areas under two or more correlated receiver operating characteristic curves: a nonparametric approach</article-title><source>Biometrics.</source><volume>44</volume><issue>3</issue><year>1988</year><fpage>837</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2531595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3203132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0255"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0255"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastie</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regularization paths for generalized linear models via coordinate descent</article-title><source>J Stat Softw</source><volume>33</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20808728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2929880</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0260"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0260"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeLong</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeLong</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke-Pearson</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparing the areas under two or more correlated receiver operating characteristic curves: a nonparametric approach</article-title><source>Biometrics.</source><volume>44</volume><issue>3</issue><year>1988</year><fpage>837</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2531595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3203132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0265"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0265"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delong</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delong</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke-Pearson</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Comparing the Areas under Two or More Correlated Receiver Operating Characteristic Curves: A Nonparametric Approach</part-title><volume>44</volume><year>1988</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://about.jstor.org/terms" id="ir0020">https://about.jstor.org/terms</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3203132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0270"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0270"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dugan</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bavuso</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Fault trees and sequence dependencies</part-title><source>Annual Proceedings on Reliability and Maintainability Symposium</source><year>1990</year><publisher-name>IEEE</publisher-name><fpage>286</fpage><lpage>293</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0275"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0275"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chicco</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jurman</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The advantages of the Matthews correlation coefficient (MCC) over F1 score and accuracy in binary classification evaluation</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>6</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-019-6413-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31898477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6941312</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0280"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0280"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taha</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanbury</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metrics for evaluating 3D medical image segmentation: analysis, selection, and tool</article-title><source>BMC Med Imaging</source><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26263899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12880-015-0068-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4533825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0285"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0285"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kubat</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holte</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matwin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Machine learning for the detection of oil spills in satellite radar images</article-title><source>Mach Learn</source><volume>30</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1998</year><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>215</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0290"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0290"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sokolova</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Japkowicz</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szpakowicz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Beyond Accuracy, F-Score and ROC: A Family of Discriminant Measures for Performance Evaluation</part-title><year>2006</year><fpage>1015</fpage><lpage>1021</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/11941439_114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0295"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0295"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Josephine</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Predictive accuracy: a misleading performance measure for highly imbalanced data classified negative</part-title><year>2017</year><publisher-name>SAS Global Forum</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0300"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0300"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Building predictive models in R using the caret package</article-title><source>J Stat Softw</source><volume>28</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0305"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0305"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Christodoulou</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>G.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steyerberg</surname><given-names>E.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verbakel</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Calster</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A systematic review shows no performance benefit of machine learning over logistic regression for clinical prediction models</article-title><source>J Clin Epidemiol</source><volume>110</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30763612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2019.02.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0310"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0310"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goadrich</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>The relationship between Precision-Recall and ROC curves</part-title><source>Proceedings of the 23rd International Conference on Machine Learning</source><year>2006</year><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>240</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0315"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0315"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehmsmeier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The precision-recall plot is more informative than the ROC plot when evaluating binary classifiers on imbalanced datasets</article-title><source>PloS One</source><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2015</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0118432</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0118432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4349800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25738806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0320"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0320"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Learning from imbalanced data</article-title><source>IEEE Trans Knowl Data Eng</source><volume>21</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>1263</fpage><lpage>1284</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0325"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0325"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wadekar</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding opioid use disorder (OUD) using tree-based classifiers</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source><volume>208</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">107839</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.107839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31962227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0330"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0330"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakimovski</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zivadinov</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinstock-Guttman</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Considering patient age when treating multiple sclerosis across the adult lifespan</article-title><source>Expert Rev Neurother</source><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14737175.2021.1886082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33595379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0335"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0335"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Penaherrera</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zieger</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wicklein</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical characteristics of middle-aged and older patients with MS treated with interferon beta-1b: post-hoc analysis of a 2-year, prospective, international, observational study</article-title><source>BMC Neurol</source><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>324</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12883-021-02347-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34425763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8381478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0340"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0340"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Earla</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paranjpe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kachru</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aparasu</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of disease modifying agents in patients with multiple sclerosis: analysis of ten years of national data</article-title><source>Res Social Adm Pharm</source><volume>16</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sapharm.2020.02.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32171597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0345"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0345"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Earla</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aparasu</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative adherence trajectories of Oral Fingolimod and injectable disease modifying agents in multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Patient Prefer Adherence</source><volume>14</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/PPA.S270557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7649232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33177813</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0350"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0350"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boster</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative effectiveness research of disease-modifying therapies for the Management of Multiple Sclerosis: analysis of a large health insurance claims database</article-title><source>Neurol Ther</source><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40120-017-0064-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5447557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28211024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0355"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0355"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>English</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aloi</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New FDA-approved disease-modifying therapies for multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Clin Ther</source><volume>37</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinthera.2015.03.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25846320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0360"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0360"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scolding</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cader</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of British Neurologists: revised (2015) guidelines for prescribing disease-modifying treatments in multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Pract Neurol</source><volume>15</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/practneurol-2015-001139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26101071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0365"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0365"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Markianos</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evangelopoulos</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koutsis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davaki</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sfagos</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Body mass index in multiple sclerosis: associations with CSF neurotransmitter metabolite levels</article-title><source>Int Sch Res Notices</source><year>2013</year><fpage>2013</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2013/981070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3800568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24205443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0370"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0370"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gianfrancesco</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barcellos</surname><given-names>L.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Obesity and multiple sclerosis susceptibility: a review</article-title><source>J Neurol Neuromed</source><volume>1</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.29245/2572.942x/2016/7.1064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5156319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27990499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0375"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0375"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mowry</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Body mass index, but not vitamin D status, is associated with brain volume change in MS</article-title><source>Neurology.</source><volume>91</volume><issue>24</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>e2256</fpage><lpage>e2264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30429274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1212/WNL.0000000000006644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6329329</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0380"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0380"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kvistad</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Myhr</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holm&#248;y</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Body mass index influence interferon-beta treatment response in multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>J Neuroimmunol</source><volume>288</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26531700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jneuroim.2015.09.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0385"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0385"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dardiotis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsouris</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aslanidou</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Body mass index in patients with multiple sclerosis: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Neurol Res</source><volume>41</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>836</fpage><lpage>846</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01616412.2019.1622873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31146649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0390"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0390"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ontaneda</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carraro</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development of an algorithm to identify multiple sclerosis (MS) disease severity based on healthcare costs in a US Administrative Claims Database (P2.052)</article-title><source>Neurology</source><volume>88</volume><issue>16 Supplement</issue><year>2017</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://n.neurology.org/content/88/16_Supplement/P2.052" id="ir0025">https://n.neurology.org/content/88/16_Supplement/P2.052</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0395"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0395"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toliver</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barner</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rascati</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of a claims-based algorithm to estimate disease severity in the multiple sclerosis Medicare population</article-title><source>Mult Scler Relat Disord</source><volume>49</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">102741</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.msard.2021.102741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33476882</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="s0100" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0150">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ec0005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material for Patient Baseline Characteristics by Training and Testing Sample</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Image 1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="s0105" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0155">Supplementary data to this article can be found online at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rcsop.2023.100307" id="ir0005">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rcsop.2023.100307</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>