<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Subst Use Addict Treat</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Subst Use Addict Treat</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3815</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">pheelsevier</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Substance Use and Addiction Treatment</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2949-8767</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2949-8759</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Elsevier - PMC COVID-19 Collection</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10063455</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10063455.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10063455</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10063455</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37003539</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.josat.2023.209028</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2949-8759(23)00078-4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">209028</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Predictors of opioid overdose during the COVID-19 pandemic: The role of relapse, treatment access and nonprescribed buprenorphine/naloxone</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kline</surname><given-names initials="A">Anna</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cr0005" ref-type="corresp">&#8270;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names initials="JM">Jill M.</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0015"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names initials="ML">Marc L.</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0020"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattern</surname><given-names initials="D">Dina</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0025"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chesin</surname><given-names initials="M">Megan</given-names></name><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0030"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borys</surname><given-names initials="S">Suzanne</given-names></name><xref rid="af0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0035"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaguturu</surname><given-names initials="V">Vamsee</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="af0005"><label>a</label>Rutgers-Robert Wood Johnson Medical School, Department of Psychiatry, 317 George Street, New Brunswick, NJ 08901, United States</aff><aff id="af0010"><label>b</label>William Paterson University, 300 Pompton Road, Wayne, NJ 07470, United States</aff><aff id="af0015"><label>c</label>New Jersey Department of Human Services, Division of Mental Health and Addiction Services, 222 S. Warren St., PO Box 700, Trenton, NJ 08625-0700, United States</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cr0005"><label>&#8270;</label>Corresponding author.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>149</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">432422</issue-id><fpage>209028</fpage><lpage>209028</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>7</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>31</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>31</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-09-18 04:25:46.157"><day>18</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2023 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Elsevier Inc.</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="ab0005"><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Emerging data indicate a disproportionate increase in overdose deaths since the onset of COVID-19. Speculation about causes for the increase center on rising drug use, illicit drug supply changes, and reduced treatment access. Possible overdose mitigation factors include reduced federal MOUD prescribing restrictions, naloxone distribution programs, and increased use of telehealth. Similarly, nonprescribed buprenorphine (NPB) use, increasingly described as a harm reduction strategy in the absence of treatment, may have moderated overdose risk. This study explored factors associated with pandemic-related overdose in people who use opioids (PWUO) in New Jersey.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We surveyed 342 PWUO from March to May 2021. Approximately 50&#160;% of our sample was treated at some time since the COVID-19 emergency declaration in March 2020. The risk and protective factors associated with overdose were identified using Pearson's chi square test and ANOVA and tested in a series of multivariable logistic regression models for the full sample and the subsample of PWUO treated during the pandemic.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Forty-eight percent of respondents increased their drug use during the pandemic, including 32&#160;% who relapsed after previous abstinence. Fifteen percent overdosed at least once since March 2020. In the full sample, overdose was associated with Hispanic ethnicity (AOR&#160;=&#160;3.51; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;1.22&#8211;10.11), pre-pandemic overdose (AOR&#160;=&#160;6.75; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;3.03&#8211;15.02), lack/loss of medical insurance (AOR&#160;=&#160;3.02; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;1.01&#8211;9.02), relapse (AOR&#160;=&#160;2.94; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;1.36&#8211;6.36), and nonprescribed use of buprenorphine/naloxone (AOR&#160;=&#160;3.16; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;1.49&#8211;6.70). The study found similar trends in the treatment sample, with the exceptions that heroin/fentanyl use also predicted overdose (AOR&#160;=&#160;3.43; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;1.20&#8211;9.78) and the association of overdose with nonprescribed buprenorphine/naloxone was stronger (AOR&#160;=&#160;4.91; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;2.01&#8211;12.03). Potential mitigating factors, such as take-home methadone and telehealth, were not significant.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Relapse during the pandemic was widespread and a significant contributor to overdose. Lack/loss of medical insurance further exacerbated the risk. Despite the growing literature reporting &#8220;therapeutic&#8221; use of NPB, people using nonprescribed buprenorphine/naloxone in the current study experienced up to five times the risk of overdose as nonusers. This finding suggests that, despite therapeutic intent, PWUO may be using NPB in ways that are ineffectual for addiction management, especially in the context of changing buprenorphine induction protocols in the context of fentanyl.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="ks0005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Opioid overdose</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Relapse</kwd><kwd>Nonprescribed buprenorphine</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0025">The United States has faced, and continues to face, two public health crises&#8212;the coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic (COVID-19) and the epidemic of opioid misuse and overdose. The two crises are not unrelated. Although an upward trend in drug overdose deaths in the United States has occurred since 1999, culminating in a 31&#160;% increase between 2019 and 2020 (<xref rid="bb0140" ref-type="bibr">Hedegaard, Mini&#241;o, Spencer, &amp; Warner, 2021</xref>), emerging data indicate a disproportionate increase in overdose deaths since the onset of COVID-19 (<xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">Ahmad, Rossen, &amp; Sutton, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">Friedman &amp; Akre, 2021</xref>). Between the first and second quarters of 2020, for example, overdose death rates rose by up to 60&#160;% across jurisdictions in the United States and 58&#160;% in Canada (<xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">Imtiaz et al., 2021</xref>). These trends suggest a synergism between the two health crises, with some of the most consequential effects of the pandemic falling on people who use drugs (<xref rid="bb0180" ref-type="bibr">Linas et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p id="p0030">There has been much speculation about the pandemic-related mechanisms fueling the rise of drug-related overdoses. Social isolation, job loss, financial burdens, health concerns, and other pandemic stressors may have provoked increases in substance use or the resumption of use among those in recovery (<xref rid="bb0180" ref-type="bibr">Linas et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0225" ref-type="bibr">Rodgers, Shepherd, Garey, &amp; Zvokensky, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0230" ref-type="bibr">Rosenbaum et al., 2021</xref>). A recent national study, moreover, found a significant increase in positive urine drug screens four months after, compared to four months before, the national emergency declaration of March 2020, especially for fentanyl, heroin, cocaine, and methamphetamines (<xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">Haley &amp; Saitz, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0295" ref-type="bibr">Wainwright et al., 2020</xref>). Additionally, pandemic-related disruptions in illicit drug supply chains and closures of overseas production facilities may have led to the production of more lethal street drugs (<xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">CCENDU, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0275" ref-type="bibr">Tyndall, 2020</xref>). Although the trend of increasing fentanyl proliferation began years before the pandemic, 97&#160;% of all heroin seizures in New Jersey in 2020 were contaminated with fentanyl (<xref rid="bb0205" ref-type="bibr">New Jersey State Police, 2021</xref>). Further, disruptions in public transportation; reduced hours or closures of treatment facilities, doctor's offices, self-help groups and pharmacies; loss of medical insurance; and the fear of COVID-19 exposure may have all reduced treatment access, including access to medications to treat opioid use disorder (MOUD) (<xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">Davis &amp; Samuels, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Galarneau et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">Gleason et al., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="bb0180" ref-type="bibr">Linas et al., 2021</xref>). Moreover, disruptions in medication access may have deadly consequences. A recent study, for example, observed high risk for overdose death 8&#8211;14&#160;days from MOUD treatment discontinuation among veterans (<xref rid="bb0285" ref-type="bibr">Vakkalanka et al., 2021</xref>), underscoring the need for daily or near daily dosing.</p><p id="p0035">To alleviate pandemic-related barriers to treatment, a number of federal and local changes to prescribing and treatment practices were instituted. Existing federal limitations on MOUD prescribing were eased, permitting methadone providers to dispense take-home doses and buprenorphine prescribers to use telemedicine for medication initiation and follow-up (<xref rid="bb0180" ref-type="bibr">Linas et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0260" ref-type="bibr">SAMHSA, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">DEA, 2020</xref>). Similarly, financial barriers to treatment were reduced through the emergency expansion of Medicaid (<xref rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr">Kaiser Family Foundation, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">Bachireddy, Chen, &amp; Dar, 2020</xref>), and many individual treatment providers offered telemedicine as an alternative to in-person attendance (<xref rid="bb0180" ref-type="bibr">Linas et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bb0210" ref-type="bibr">Ng, Niles, Kinderknecht, Strohmeyer, &amp; Olin, 2022</xref>; <xref rid="bb0220" ref-type="bibr">Oesterle et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0280" ref-type="bibr">Uscher-Pines, Sousa, Raja, Mehrotra, &amp; Barnett, 2020</xref>).</p><p id="p0040">In addition to institutional changes, people who use opioids (PWUO) may have engaged in harm reduction strategies to help ameliorate the consequences of reduced treatment access. The use of nonprescribed buprenorphine (NPB) (<xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">Chilcoat, Amick, Sherwood, &amp; Dunn, 2019</xref>), for example, has been increasingly portrayed in the literature as a potential harm reduction strategy when PWUO lack access to treatment. Although the misuse of MOUD, including buprenorphine and buprenorphine combined with naloxone (Suboxone&#174;), is common (<xref rid="bb0315" ref-type="bibr">Yokell at el., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bb0185" ref-type="bibr">Lofwall &amp; Walsh, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">Chilcoat et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bb0290" ref-type="bibr">Vidal-Trecan, Varescon, Nabet, &amp; Boissinnas, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">Blazes &amp; Morrow, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Lewis &amp; Walter, 1992</xref>), emerging research suggests that NPB is used less for its euphoric effects than for &#8220;therapeutic&#8221; reasons (<xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">Chilcoat et al., 2019</xref>), such as to manage cravings, withdrawal symptoms, and anxiety/depression and to achieve and maintain abstinence in the absence of treatment (<xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">Chilcoat et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">Cicero, Ellis, Surratt, &amp; Kurtz, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">Genberg et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">Novak, Wenger, Lorvick, &amp; Kral, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bb0245" ref-type="bibr">Schuman-Olivier et al., 2010</xref>). Some observers thus believe that used therapeutically, NPB may yield unintended public health benefits (<xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">Carlson, Daniulaityte, Silverstein, Nahhas, &amp; Martins, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">Chilcoat et al., 2019</xref>). In the context of the pandemic, NPB may have also limited the harms associated with reduced treatment access.</p><p id="p0045">Despite much speculation about the possible drivers of pandemic-related overdose, little research to date has examined the specific mechanisms contributing to increased overdose risk or the extent to which mitigation efforts may have reduced that risk. In this article, we examine the association between nonfatal opioid overdose during the COVID-19 pandemic and both drug use behaviors and treatment access in a sample of 342 in- and out-of-treatment PWUO in New Jersey. We further examine associations between specific treatment-related experiences and overdose in a subset of individuals admitted to addiction treatment during the pandemic.</p></sec><sec id="s0010"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="s0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Overview of study design</title><p id="p0050">This mixed methods study used an exploratory sequential design (<xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">Fetters, Curry, &amp; Creswell, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">Hong, Pluye, Bujold, &amp; Wassef, 2017</xref>) to assess the factors contributing to pandemic-related overdose among PWUO in New Jersey. In the first study phase (October&#8211;November 2020), the study conducted in-depth qualitative telephone interviews about pandemic-related challenges, drug use, and treatment experiences with 40 PWUO (20 in-treatment and 20 out-of-treatment). The study recruited the in-treatment sample from five treatment programs in Northern and Central New Jersey, selected to represent a diversity of modalities, including one methadone maintenance program, two outpatient programs (intensive and regular), and one long-term residential program that served residents from across the state. The study recruited out-of-treatment participants from a community social service agency in northern New Jersey that houses a needle-exchange program. After conducting preliminary content analysis on the qualitative data using NVivo, VS 2020, we incorporated major themes emerging from the interviews into a standardized, web-based survey and in study phase two (March&#8211;May 2021), targeted the survey to all clients of the agencies participating in study phase one. A total of 443 individuals who used drugs were enrolled in the second survey, including 342 PWUO. This article is based on data from the subsample of PWUO and reports the quantitative findings obtained from the second study phase. Use of the qualitative findings for further interpretation of the current findings, however, is pending a more systematic analysis of the qualitative data. The Rutgers University Health Sciences IRB approved the study.</p></sec><sec id="s0020"><label>2.2</label><title>Eligibility requirements and recruitment</title><p id="p0055">Study eligibility requirements included being aged 18 or older, English-speaking, and either currently in addiction treatment or an active or recent (last 12&#160;months) user of illicit street drugs. For the current analysis, the study further limited the sample to individuals reporting a lifetime history of illicit opioid use (either heroin/fentanyl, nonprescribed opioid medication and/or other opioid drugs).</p><p id="p0060">Flyers containing the study description and survey link were posted at all participating agencies. Additionally, staff at the two (nonmethadone) outpatient programs sent out initial emails containing a study description and survey link to all current clients, followed by reminder emails to encourage participation. At the residential program, staff personally informed all current residents of the study opportunity, as did needle exchange program staff who notified all arriving clients daily. The large client population at the methadone clinic, coupled with staffing and scheduling disruptions created by the pandemic, prevented a systematic recruitment effort by agency staff. Instead, the study recruited participants through flyers and staff personally informed clients of the study opportunity when possible.</p><p id="p0065">We received a total of 527 responses to the online survey. Of those, we eliminated 63 who did not meet eligibility requirements, 6 duplicates, 10 partial responses (&lt;50&#160;% completed), and 5 surveys with multiple internally inconsistent responses, leaving a total of 443 valid surveys. Of these, 224 were recruited from the needle exchange program, 37 from the methadone clinic, 124 from the residential program, 32 from the outpatient programs, and 25 by word of mouth (through clients of participating agencies). We accepted word-of-mouth respondents if they met eligibility screening criteria.</p></sec><sec id="s0025"><label>2.3</label><title>Survey administration</title><p id="p0070">Surveys were anonymous, approximately 30&#160;min in length, and self-administered by means of a web-based, computerized instrument programmed in Qualtrics. Outpatient clients accessed the survey through personal computers or smart phones. Participants at the needle exchange program who lacked internet access completed the survey on secure iPads in a private room at the agency. Agency staff assisted with the logon process and provided troubleshooting for technical problems. A similar process was carried out at the residential programs, where clients completed surveys with the technical assistance of agency staff on in-house, program-supplied computers. All participants who completed the survey received a $25 VISA gift certificate.</p></sec><sec id="s0030"><label>2.4</label><title>Sample</title><p id="p0075">The current analysis is based on a subsample of respondents having a lifetime history of illicit opioid use (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#160;=&#160;342), including use of heroin, fentanyl, and nonprescribed use of opioid medication. Of these, 208 respondents (47&#160;%) were in treatment at the time of the survey and an additional 12 respondents (3.5&#160;%) had been treated at some time during the pandemic but were not currently in treatment. The remainder was active or recent users who had not been treated since March 2020.</p></sec><sec id="s0035"><label>2.5</label><title>Measures</title><p id="p0080"><italic toggle="yes">Nonfatal overdose during the pandemic</italic>, our outcome measure, was measured with the item: &#8220;How many overdoses have you experienced since the start of the pandemic in March 2020?&#8221; Responses were dichotomized into &#8220;0&#8221; (none) and &#8220;1&#8221; (one or more).</p><p id="p0085"><italic toggle="yes">Pre-pandemic overdose</italic> was measured with the question: &#8220;How many overdoses have you experienced in your lifetime?&#8221; We subtracted pandemic overdoses from total overdoses, and the remainder categorized as either &#8220;0&#8221; or &#8220;1&#8221; (1 or more).</p><p id="p0090"><italic toggle="yes">Mental health status</italic> was measured by questions asking respondents if they were ever diagnosed with anxiety, depression, bipolar disorder, PTSD, schizophrenia/schizoaffective disorder, or an eating disorder (yes/no for each condition) by a medical professional.</p><p id="p0095"><italic toggle="yes">Incarceration during pandemic</italic> was measured with the yes/no item: &#8220;Since March 2020, did you spend any time in prison or jail?&#8221;</p><p id="p0100"><italic toggle="yes">Treatment during pandemic</italic> was coded as &#8220;yes&#8221; if the participant was referred by a treatment provider or reported being treated since March 2020. Treatment included a variety of modalities, including short- and long-term residential treatment, clinic- and office-based outpatient programs, methadone treatment, and inpatient detoxification.</p><p id="p0105"><italic toggle="yes">Relapse</italic> was measured by the item: &#8220;At any time since March 2020, did you suffer a relapse after not using drugs or alcohol for a while?&#8221; The study coded those checking the response, &#8220;yes, relapsed on drugs&#8221; or &#8220;yes, relapsed on drugs and alcohol&#8221; as having a drug-related relapse. Relapse could thus involve reuse of any drug, not just opioids.</p><p id="p0110"><italic toggle="yes">Increase in drug use without relapsing</italic> was measured by the item: &#8220;At any time since the start of the pandemic in March 2020, did your use of drugs increase, even if it was only temporary?&#8221; Those responding &#8220;yes&#8221; to this question and &#8220;no&#8221; to relapse were coded as increasing their drug use without relapsing.</p><p id="p0115"><italic toggle="yes">Change in injection practices</italic> was measured among respondents who ever injected drugs by the following question: &#8220;Since March 2020, did you change how often you inject drugs?&#8221; Answers were recoded into a four-category variable with the values: 1. Never injected; 2. Began or increased injection; 3. Continued injection/no changes; and 4. Injected less or stopped.</p><p id="p0120"><italic toggle="yes">Use of substances</italic> was obtained through a list of yes/no questions probing use and time frames of use of the following substances: alcohol, marijuana, heroin, cocaine, methamphetamines, MDMA, other hallucinogens, and non-prescribed use of prescription pain killers, tranquilizers, sedatives, and stimulants. The study considered those indicating past 12-month use to have used during the pandemic. We specifically did not ask about fentanyl use since, as noted earlier, almost all heroin in New Jersey is now contaminated with fentanyl (<xref rid="bb0205" ref-type="bibr">NJSP, 2021</xref>), and PWUO are typically unsure if their drug purchases contain fentanyl (<xref rid="bb0195" ref-type="bibr">Mars, Rosenblum, &amp; Ciccarone, 2019</xref>). Because of the extent of contamination in New Jersey, we subsequently refer to heroin as &#8220;heroin/fentanyl&#8221; throughout the paper.</p><p id="p0125"><italic toggle="yes">Misuse of buprenorphine/naloxone and methadone</italic> was measured with the item: &#8220;Since March 2020, did you ever buy methadone or Suboxone on the street without a prescription?&#8221; Answer choices included: &#8220;Yes, Suboxone; yes, methadone; yes, methadone and Suboxone; No, never bought either drug.&#8221; The study also asked respondents if they had sold their prescribed addiction medicine on the street and whether they had used more medication than was prescribed (yes/no).</p><p id="p0130"><italic toggle="yes">Treatment access problems</italic> were measured by asking respondents if any of a list of treatment barriers had delayed or prevented them from entering treatment during the pandemic (yes/no). Barriers included three main types: 1. Lack/loss of medical insurance; 2. Closed programs/long waits; 3. Inability to meet COVID-19 entry requirements (i.e. to quarantine or complete a COVID-19 test).</p><p id="p0135"><italic toggle="yes">MOUD treatment during the pandemic</italic> was measured with the question &#8220;As part of any of your treatments during the pandemic, did you receive any of the following medications (yes/no)?&#8221; Possible responses included 1. Methadone; 2. Suboxone; 3. Vivitrol; 4. None of these medications. We measured buprenorphine/naloxone treatment specifically, and not buprenorphine generally, because New Jersey buprenorphine prescribing guidelines (<xref rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr">NJ-DAS, 2007</xref>) recommend that most buprenorphine patients be switched to buprenorphine/naloxone once they complete detoxification and are stabilized. It would be uncommon for someone in New Jersey to be prescribed mono-buprenorphine instead of buprenorphine/naloxone.</p><p id="p0140"><italic toggle="yes">Other treatment characteristics measured</italic> included yes/no questions asking about receipt of take-home methadone doses and availability of telehealth services. <italic toggle="yes">Treatment problems</italic> were measured using a series of 3-point scale questions (Not at all, somewhat, very true) asking about difficulty accessing addiction medications, fearing COVID-19 exposure while in or traveling to treatment, and limited access due to pandemic-related changes in hours/schedules. Respondents were considered to have a problem if they answered &#8220;somewhat&#8221; or &#8220;very true&#8221;.</p><p id="p0145">Finally, all respondents were asked a series of standard demographic questions, including age, race/ethnicity, gender, education, employment and marital status.</p></sec><sec id="s0040"><label>2.6</label><title>Data analysis</title><p id="p0150">We used descriptive statistics to examine demographic characteristics, overdose history, drug behaviors, and treatment-seeking behaviors in the full sample and also explored treatment experiences in a subset of respondents treated during the pandemic. Using Pearson's chi square test and analysis of variance, as appropriate, we compared characteristics of respondents who did and did not experience an overdose since the start of COVID-19 on all relevant measures. Our analyses of relationships between overdose and use of specific drugs focused only on the most frequently used drugs and those historically having the greatest association with overdose: opioids (heroin/fentanyl and non-prescribed pain pills), cocaine, methamphetamines, and tranquilizers (<xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">Hedegaard, Mini&#241;o, &amp; Warner, 2020</xref>).</p><p id="p0155">We next examined predictors of overdose in a series of multivariable logistic regression models, basing our selection of independent variables for all models on the significance of their bivariate association with overdose (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;<italic toggle="yes">&#8804;</italic>&#160;.05) as well as on assessments of collinearity and theoretical relevance to our outcome. Our first set of models aimed at identifying overdose predictors in the sample as a whole. Because relapse and drug use during the pandemic were highly collinear, we created two multivariable models, one that examined the influence of relapse but not individual drug types (model 1) and one that examined the influence of drug types but not relapse (model 2). All other predictor variables remained consistent in both models. To examine the effects of treatment characteristics on the risk of overdose, we followed a similar procedure for the subsample of individuals treated during the pandemic. The treatment models included all variables predictive of overdose in the full sample as well as the additional treatment factors having significant bivariate associations with overdose (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;<italic toggle="yes">&#8804;</italic>&#160;.05).</p><p id="p0160">To better elucidate the influence of prescribed and nonprescribed buprenorphine/naloxone on overdose, we built models 1 and 2 of the treatment sample and model 2 of the full sample in two steps, entering all relevant variables except nonprescribed buprenorphine/naloxone in step 1, and entering non-prescribed buprenorphine/naloxone in step 2. In the treatment sample, this allowed us to assess the extent to which misuse of buprenorphine/naloxone mediated the relationship between buprenorphine/naloxone treatment and overdose. Additionally, in model 2 in both samples, it allowed us to assess the relative effect of each drug type on overdose before and after adjusting for the effect of using nonprescribed buprenorphine/naloxone. In the full sample, our measure of nonprescribed buprenorphine/naloxone was defined as purchasing the medication on the street. In the treatment sample, however, we created a dichotomous variable that included either street purchase and/or exceeding prescribed dosage vs. neither. Before creating the combined variable, we ran regressions including each variable separately, with no change in results.</p><p id="p0165">Finally, to better understand relationships among MOUD prescribing, misuse, and overdose, we performed ad hoc chi-square analyses comparing buprenorphine/naloxone, methadone, and naltrexone treatment patients on access to medications during the pandemic, exceeding prescribed MOUD dosages, and street purchase and sale of MOUD. We also used chi-square and ANOVA to examine associations between nonprescribed buprenorphine/naloxone use and addiction severity, measured by past year heroin/fentanyl use and days of use. These findings are presented in the Discussion. We carried out all analyses using Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS) (V.28.0; IBM, Armonk, New York, USA).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0045"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="s0050"><label>3.1</label><title>Sample characteristics and risk behaviors</title><p id="p0170">Respondents had a mean age of 40, were mostly male (62&#160;%) and predominantly non-Hispanic Black (48&#160;%) or non-Hispanic White (38&#160;%) (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
). Individuals identifying as Hispanic composed 12&#160;% of the sample. Most completed high school (46&#160;%) or beyond (33&#160;%), and 68&#160;% were never married. About two thirds were unemployed. &gt;56&#160;% had a lifetime mental health diagnosis, and 24&#160;% were incarcerated during the COVID-19 pandemic.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Respondent characteristics and association with overdose during the COVID-19 pandemic: people who use opioids.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0005">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">All people who use opioids (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#160;=&#160;342) n (%) or <italic toggle="yes">x&#773;</italic> (SD)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overdose during pandemic (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#160;=&#160;52) n (%) or <italic toggle="yes">x&#773;</italic> (SD)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">No overdose during pandemic (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#160;=&#160;290) n (%) or <italic toggle="yes">x&#773;</italic> (SD)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#967;<sup>2</sup> or F</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Background characteristics</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean age</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.42 (10.89)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.48 (9.07)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.77 (11.16)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.95</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race/ethnicity</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;White</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">129 (37.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (51.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">102 (35.2)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>16.6</bold><bold>0</bold><xref rid="tf0015" ref-type="table-fn">&#8270;&#8270;&#8270;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Black</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">165 (48.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (23.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">153 (52.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hispanic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41 (12.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (21.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (10.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (2.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (1.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">209 (62.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (68.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">175 (61.2)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.84</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Female</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">127 (37.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (32.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">111 (38.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Education status</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Less than H.S.</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">73 (21.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (26.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">59 (20.3)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.30</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;HS graduate</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">157 (45.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (40.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">136 (46.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Some college or beyond</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">112 (32.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (32.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">95 (32.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Marital status</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Married or cohabiting</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45 (13.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (21.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (11.7)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.70</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Never married</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">234 (68.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (59.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">203 (70.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Divorced/separated/widowed</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">63 (18.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (19.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">53 (18.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current employment status</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Full-time or part-time</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">108 (32.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (25.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">95 (33.9)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.84</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Unemployed/looking</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">122 (36.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (37.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">103 (36.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Unemployed/not looking</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">101 (30.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (37.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">82 (29.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Incarcerated during pandemic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">81 (23.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (36.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">62 (21.4)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>5.61</bold><xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">&#8270;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mental health diagnosis in lifetime</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">193 (56.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41 (78.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">152 (52.4)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>12.53</bold><xref rid="tf0015" ref-type="table-fn">&#8270;&#8270;&#8270;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overdosed before March 2020</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">84 (24.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (63.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51 (17.6)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>50.08</bold><xref rid="tf0015" ref-type="table-fn">&#8270;&#8270;&#8270;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">&#8232;&#8232;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Drug use characteristics during pandemic</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ever overdosed</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">103 (30.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overdosed after March 2020</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">52 (15.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Changes in amount of use</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>36.47</bold><xref rid="tf0015" ref-type="table-fn">&#8270;&#8270;&#8270;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Increased drug use but did not relapse</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">57 (16.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (5.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">54 (18.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Relapsed</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">108 (31.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 (67.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">73 (25.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No increase in use</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">177 (51.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (26.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">163 (56.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Used heroin/fentanyl</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">237 (69.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">44(84.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">193 (66.6)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>6.76</bold><xref rid="tf0010" ref-type="table-fn">&#8270;&#8270;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Used opioid pain pills</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">109 (31.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (30.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">93 (32.1)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Used methamphetamines</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (7.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (25.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (3.8)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>30.39</bold><xref rid="tf0015" ref-type="table-fn">&#8270;&#8270;&#8270;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Used cocaine</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">85 (26.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (39.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">69 (24.9)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3.63</bold><xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">&#8270;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Used tranquilizers</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (8.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (11.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (7.6)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.24</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Changes in injection behavior</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>9.23</bold><xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">&#8270;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Never injected</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">175 (51.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (44.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">152 (52.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Began or increased injection</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (8.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (19.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (6.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Continued injecting at same level</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">121 (35.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (34.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">103 (35.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Injected less or stopped</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (4.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (5.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Used non-prescribed methadone</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">82 (24.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (28.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">67 (23.1)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.80</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Used non-prescribed buprenorphine/naloxone</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">91 (26.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (44.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">68 (23.4)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>9.75</bold><xref rid="tf0010" ref-type="table-fn">&#8270;&#8270;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">&#8232;&#8232;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Treatment characteristics during the pandemic</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Attempted to enter treatment</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">184 (53.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">44 (84.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">140 (48.3)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>23.43</bold><xref rid="tf0015" ref-type="table-fn">&#8270;&#8270;&#8270;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Received treatment</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">179 (52.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (82.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">136 (46.9)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>22.65</bold><xref rid="tf0015" ref-type="table-fn">&#8270;&#8270;&#8270;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Treatment access problems</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Programs full/long waits</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">79 (23.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (46.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">55 (19.0)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>18.35</bold><xref rid="tf0015" ref-type="table-fn">&#8270;&#8270;&#8270;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Lacked/lost medical insurance</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (8.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (19.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (6.2)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>9.95</bold><xref rid="tf0010" ref-type="table-fn">&#8270;&#8270;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Difficulty meeting pandemic entry requirements (COVID-19 test or quarantine)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (2.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (2.8)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf0005"><label>&#8270;</label><p id="np0005"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf0010"><label>&#8270;&#8270;</label><p id="np0010"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf0015"><label>&#8270;&#8270;&#8270;</label><p id="np0015"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.001.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0175">About 30&#160;% of respondents had a lifetime history of overdose and 15&#160;% had overdosed at least once since March 2020. During the pandemic, about 24&#160;% of the sample remained abstinent from all drugs and alcohol, about 25&#160;% were abstinent from illicit drugs but not alcohol, and 26&#160;% reported no opioid use but used either alcohol or other drugs (not shown). Increased drug use was reported by 48&#160;%, including 32&#160;% who relapsed. &lt;14&#160;% reported changing their injection habits during the pandemic, with only 9&#160;% increasing or initiating injection use.</p><p id="p0180">About 70&#160;% of respondents reported past-12-month heroin/fentanyl use, and 32&#160;% reported past-12-month use of opioid pain pills. Cocaine was used by 27&#160;% of respondents. Only 7&#160;% reported past 12-month methamphetamine use and 8&#160;%, past 12-month use of tranquilizers. Street purchase of methadone and buprenorphine/naloxone was reported by 24&#160;% and 27&#160;%, respectively.</p><p id="p0185">About 54&#160;% of respondents attempted to enter treatment during the pandemic and most (52&#160;% of all respondents) were treated. Treatment access problems were common, however, with 23&#160;% of all respondents (or, about 43&#160;% of treatment-seekers) reporting long waits and full programs. Similarly, 8&#160;% of all respondents (15&#160;% of treatment-seekers) reported lack of medical insurance and 3&#160;% (5&#160;% of treatment-seekers) reported difficulties meeting COVID-19 entrance requirements.</p><p id="p0190">Among those who were treated (<xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
), 73&#160;% received MOUD, including methadone (31&#160;%), buprenorphine/naloxone (43&#160;%), and injection naltrexone (Vivitrol) (7&#160;%). Of all treated, 16&#160;% (22&#160;% of those treated with MOUD) reported exceeding their prescribed dosage. Twenty-two percent of everyone treated (&gt;70&#160;% of methadone clients) received take-home methadone and 52&#160;% of treated respondents were offered telehealth services. Many reported negative pandemic-related impacts on treatment; however, with 41&#160;% being dissatisfied with program changes to individual or group therapy, 44&#160;% fearing COVID-19 exposure during, and 29&#160;% while traveling to, treatment, and 17&#160;% facing barriers due to program scheduling changes.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Characteristics of treatment experience during COVID-19 pandemic and association with overdose: people treated during the pandemic.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0010">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">All people treated during pandemic (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#160;=&#160;179) n (%) or <italic toggle="yes">x&#773;</italic> (SD)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overdose during pandemic (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#160;=&#160;43) n (%) or <italic toggle="yes">x&#773;</italic> (SD)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">No overdose during pandemic (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#160;=&#160;136) n (%) or <italic toggle="yes">x&#773;</italic> (SD)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#967;<sup>2</sup> or F</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Treated with any MOUD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">130 (72.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">38 (88.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">92 (67.6)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>7.05</bold><xref rid="tf5010" ref-type="table-fn">&#8270;&#8270;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Treated with methadone</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">56 (31.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (32.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (30.9)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Treated with buprenorphine/naloxone</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">77 (43.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (60.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51 (37.5)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>7.03</bold><xref rid="tf5010" ref-type="table-fn">&#8270;&#8270;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Treated with injection naltrexone</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (7.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (9.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (6.6)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.35</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Took more MOUD than prescribed</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (16.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (34.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (10.3)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>14.55</bold><xref rid="tf5005" ref-type="table-fn">&#8270;&#8270;&#8270;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Received take-home methadone</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 (22.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (23.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (22.1)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Offered telehealth</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">84 (52.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (50.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">64 (52.9)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.10</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pandemic-related treatment problems</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Individual/group therapy hampered by program changes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">73 (40.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (51.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51 (37.5)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.53</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Difficulty accessing MOUD in treatment</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (15.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (18.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (14.7)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.38</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Feared COVID-19 exposure in treatment</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">79 (44.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (48.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">58 (42.6)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.51</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Feared COVID-19 exposure traveling to treatment</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51 (28.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (32.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37 (27.2)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.46</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Reduced hours/changed schedules limited access</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (16.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (22.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (14.9)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.25</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>&#8270;</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf5005"><label>&#8270;&#8270;</label><p id="np10010"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf5010"><label>&#8270;&#8270;&#8270;</label><p id="np10015"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.001.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0055"><label>3.2</label><title>Bivariate analysis of factors associated with overdose</title><sec id="s0060"><label>3.2.1</label><title>Full sample (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>)</title><p id="p0195">Pandemic-related overdose occurred most frequently among Hispanics and non-Hispanic Whites and least frequently among non-Hispanic Blacks (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;16<sub>.</sub>60, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.001). Also associated with overdose were incarceration (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;5.61, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.05), a lifetime mental health diagnosis (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;12.53, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.001), and having overdosed prior to the start of the pandemic (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;50.08, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.001).</p><p id="p0200">In terms of drug use, relapse was highly related to overdose (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;36.47, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.001) as was past-year use of heroin/fentanyl (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;6.76, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.01), methamphetamine (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;30.39, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.001), and cocaine (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;3.63, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.05). Beginning or increasing injection drug use during the pandemic was also significantly associated with overdose (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;9.23, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.05). Nonprescribed buprenorphine/naloxone use significantly increased overdose risk (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;9.75, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.01), while nonprescribed methadone use was unrelated to overdose.</p><p id="p0205">Both attempting to enter treatment (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;23.43, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.001) and entering treatment (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;22.65, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.001) were highly associated with overdose, likely reflecting a self-perceived need for treatment following overdose, relapse, or increased use. At the same time, long waits for program entry (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;18.35, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.001) and lack of medical insurance (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;9.95, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.01) significantly increased overdose risk. Neither COVID-19 precautionary entrance requirements nor the treatment modality entered however were related to overdose risk.</p></sec><sec id="s0065"><label>3.2.2</label><title>Treatment sample (<xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>)</title><p id="p0210">Among those treated during the pandemic, receiving MOUD treatment was highly related to overdose (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;7.05, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.01), although this relationship was primarily associated with buprenorphine/naloxone treatment (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;7.03, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.01); neither methadone nor injection naltrexone treatment correlated with increased overdose risk. Using more MOUD than prescribed was also strongly associated with pandemic-related overdose (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;14.55, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.01). No relationship existed between overdose and pandemic-related treatment problems or program-instituted measures to facilitate access.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0070"><label>3.3</label><title>Multivariable analysis (<xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, <xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>)</title><p id="p0215">In model 1 for the sample as a whole (<xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>), overdose was significantly associated with Hispanic ethnicity (AOR&#160;=&#160;3.51; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;1.22&#8211;10.11), pre-pandemic overdose (AOR&#160;=&#160;6.75; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;3.03&#8211;15.02), lack/loss of medical insurance (AOR&#160;=&#160;3.02; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;1.01&#8211;9.02), relapse (AOR&#160;=&#160;2.94; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;1.36&#8211;6.36), and nonprescribed buprenorphine/naloxone use (AOR&#160;=&#160;3.16; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;1.49&#8211;6.70). In model 2, examining the influence of individual drugs but not relapse, heroin/fentanyl use, but not methamphetamines or cocaine use, predicted overdose in step 1 (AOR&#160;=&#160;2.92; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;1.14&#8211;7.46). In step 2, nonprescribed buprenorphine/naloxone use became the only drug to predict overdose (AOR&#160;=&#160;2.78; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;1.30&#8211;5.96) and heroin/fentanyl use was no longer significant. Significance trends for all other variables in step 2 were similar to those in step 1.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0015" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Predictors of non-fatal overdose during the COVID-19 pandemic: all PWUO.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0015">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Variable</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="2">MODEL 1<hr/></th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">MODEL 2<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Step 1<hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Step 2<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">AOR (95&#160;% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">AOR (95&#160;% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">AOR (95&#160;% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-Hispanic White</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.55 (0.65&#8211;3.66)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.322</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.22 (0.52&#8211;2.88)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.652</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.31 (0.55&#8211;3.12)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.548</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hispanic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3.51 (1.22&#8211;10.11)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.020</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3.71 (1.31&#8211;10.46)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.013</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3.93 (1.35&#8211;11.41)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.012</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lifetime mental health diagnosis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.08 (0.46&#8211;2.53)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.867</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.36 (0.58&#8211;3.16)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.481</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.19 (0.50&#8211;2.83)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.687</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">History of overdose pre-pandemic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>6.75 (3.03&#8211;15.02)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>6.74 (3.07&#8211;14.81)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>7.59 (3.35&#8211;17.19)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Incarcerated during pandemic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.76 (0.34&#8211;1.69)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.494</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.08 (0.49&#8211;2.40)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.854</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.99 (0.44&#8211;2.25)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.988</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lacked/lost medical insurance</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3.02 (1.01&#8211;9.02)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.047</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3.25 (1.12&#8211;9.48)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.031</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3.21 (1.06&#8211;9.67)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.039</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Long waits/treatment programs full</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.22 (0.53&#8211;2.82)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.642</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.50 (0.66&#8211;3.39)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.331</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.61 (0.70&#8211;3.70)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.265</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Initiated or increased injection during pandemic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.41 (0.48&#8211;4.13)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.530</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (0.34&#8211;2.94)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.998</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.08 (0.35&#8211;3.30)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.895</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Relapsed</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.94 (1.36&#8211;6.36)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.006</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Used heroin/fentanyl</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.92 (1.14&#8211;7.46)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.025</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.44 (0.93&#8211;6.39)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.070</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Used cocaine</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12 (0.49&#8211;2.50)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.805</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.09 (0.47&#8211;2.51)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.838</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Used methamphetamine</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.45 (0.79&#8211;7.58)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.121</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.34 (0.72&#8211;7.61)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.156</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Used non-prescribed buprenorphine/naloxone</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3.16 (1.49&#8211;6.70)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.003</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.78 (1.30&#8211;5.96)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.009</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nagelkerke R<sup>2</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.368</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.339</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.368</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Bolded AORs indicate significant realtionships at p&#160;&#8804;&#160;.05 or better.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="t0020" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Association of behavioral risk factors and treatment experiences with overdose during the COVID-19 pandemic: PWUO who were treated during the pandemic.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0020">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Variable</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Model One<hr/></th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Model Two<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Step 1<hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Step 2<hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Step 1<hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Step 2<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">AOR (95&#160;% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">AOR (95&#160;% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">AOR (95&#160;% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">AOR (95&#160;% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hispanic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.61 (0.53&#8211;4.85)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.401</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.71 (0.51&#8211;5.74)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.384</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.14 (0.71&#8211;6.47)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.177</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.33 (0.70&#8211;7.77)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.168</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">History of overdose pre-pandemic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>5.70 (2.47&#8211;13.15)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>7.67 (3.05&#8211;19.27)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>6.52 (2.80&#8211;15.16)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>8.35 (3.33&#8211;20.95)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lacked/lost medical insurance during pandemic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3.16 (1.01&#8211;9.91)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.049</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.11 (0.98&#8211;9.91)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.055</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3.17 (1.04&#8211;9.65)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.042</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3.15 (1.01&#8211;9.84)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.048</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prescribed buprenorphine/naloxone</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.55 (1.15&#8211;5.65)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.021</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.83 (0.78&#8211;4.28)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.166</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.54 (1.14&#8211;5.68)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.023</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.88 (0.80&#8211;4.42)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.148</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Relapsed during pandemic</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3.34 (1.42&#8211;7.86)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.006</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.85 (1.17&#8211;6.96)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.021</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Used heroin/fentanyl</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&#8211;</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&#8211;</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&#8211;</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&#8211;</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>4.74 (1.70&#8211;13.20)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.003</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3.43 (1.20&#8211;9.78)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.021</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Used non-prescribed buprenorphine/naloxone</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>4.91 (2.01&#8211;12.03)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>4.39 (1.78&#8211;10.82)</bold></td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nagelkerke R<sup>2</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.312</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.395</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.329</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.398</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Bolded AORs indicate significant realtionships at p&#160;&#8804;&#160;.05 or better.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0220">In the treatment sample (<xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>), model 1, step 1, overdose was associated with pre-pandemic overdose (AOR&#160;=&#160;5.70; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;2.47&#8211;13.15), relapse (AOR&#160;=&#160;3.34; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;1.42&#8211;7.86), lack of medical insurance (AOR&#160;=&#160;3.16; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;1.01&#8211;9.91), and buprenorphine/naloxone treatment (AOR&#160;=&#160;2.55; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;1.15&#8211;5.65). In step 2, nonprescribed buprenorphine/naloxone use was highly related to overdose (AOR&#160;=&#160;4.91; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;2.01&#8211;12.03) and buprenorphine/naloxone treatment was no longer significant. Trends for other predictors remained the same as in step 1, except for lack of medical insurance, which became nonsignificant. In model 2, step 1, overdose was associated with pre-pandemic overdose (AOR&#160;=&#160;6.52; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;2.80&#8211;15.16), buprenorphine/naloxone treatment (AOR&#160;=&#160;2.54; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;1.14&#8211;5.68), lack/loss of medical insurance (AOR&#160;=&#160;3.17; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;1.04&#8211;9.65), and heroin/fentanyl use (AOR&#160;=&#160;4.74; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;1.70&#8211;13.20). In model 2, step 2, nonprescribed buprenorphine/naloxone use was highly associated with overdose (AOR&#160;=&#160;4.39; 95&#160;% CI&#160;=&#160;1.78&#8211;10.82) and buprenorphine/naloxone treatment was no longer significant. However, all other variables remained significant in step 2.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0075"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0225">The findings of this study suggest that the COVID-19 pandemic adversely affected the drug use trajectories and outcomes of PWUO. Nearly half of the sample reported increasing their substance use after the emergency declaration in March 2020, with most of this increase occurring as a result of relapse among those who were previously abstinent. Overall, about 15&#160;% of all respondents experienced at least one overdose since March 2020.</p><p id="p0230">At the same time, PWUO experienced significant barriers to accessing addiction treatment. Although most of those who sought treatment (54&#160;%) eventually received it (97&#160;% of treatment-seekers), treatment-seekers reported long waits for treatment entry and access problems due to lack of medical insurance. Among those who entered treatment, many expressed fear of COVID-19 exposure, while &gt;40&#160;% felt that the quality of their therapeutic experience suffered due to COVID-19 restrictions. Many patients, however, reported that their programs had taken ameliorative steps to promote engagement, with 71&#160;% of methadone patients receiving take-home doses and more than half of all treatment-goers being offered telehealth services.</p><p id="p0235">In multivariate analysis of data from both the full sample and treatment subgroup, relapse significantly predicted overdose, increasing the overdose risk by about three times that of PWUO who did not relapse. This finding is consistent with multiple observational studies linking overdose to opioid reuse following periods of abstinence (<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">Alex et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Binswanger, Blatchford, Mueller, &amp; Stern, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Clausen, Waal, Thoresen, &amp; Gossop, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bb0190" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2018</xref>). Overdose has also been linked to gaps in use, sporadic use (<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">Brugal et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bb0270" ref-type="bibr">Tagliaro, De Battisti, Smith, &amp; Marigo, 1998</xref>), and fluctuations in opioid dosage (<xref rid="bb0240" ref-type="bibr">Rowe et al., 2019</xref>)&#8212;all of which may cause a loss of physiological tolerance and increase susceptibility to overdose when opioids are re-used (<xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">Blazes &amp; Morrow, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0240" ref-type="bibr">Rowe et al., 2019</xref>). In the current study, however, increased use without relapse did not heighten overdose risk, despite expectations that those exceeding their usual level of use might also exceed their tolerance. While this finding may lend support to the few studies questioning links between overdose, sporadic use, and low tolerance (<xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">Druid et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">Evans et al., 2012</xref>), the current lack of association may also reflect measurement limitations in this study, which did not operationalize &#8220;increased use&#8221; in terms of frequency or quantity.</p><p id="p0240">Pandemic-related barriers to treatment further heightened the risk of overdose in the current study. Both treatment inaccessibility due to closures/long waitlists and the lack or loss of medical insurance were associated with overdose in bivariate analyses, although only lack of medical insurance predicted overdose in multivariable models. Lack of medical insurance during a pandemic, moreover, may be uniquely stressful, not only limiting access to addiction treatment but also to treatment for other psychiatric and medical conditions, including those associated with COVID-19. Numerous studies show that multiple medical and psychiatric disorders complicate addiction problems in PWUO (<xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">Cragg et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">Davis, Lin, Liu, &amp; Sites, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bb0265" ref-type="bibr">Sullivan, Edlund, Zhang, Unutzer, &amp; Wells, 2006</xref>). In the current study, 56&#160;% of respondents had a history of psychiatric illness and 75&#160;% reported one or more physical health problems considered a risk factor for severe COVID-19 infection, including obesity, Hepatitis C, HIV, and diabetes.</p><p id="p0245">In the context of increased drug relapse and widespread delays in treatment access, we hypothesized that nonprescribed MOUD use might represent a beneficial harm reduction strategy, since PWUO typically report using the medication therapeutically (<xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">Carlson et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">Chilcoat et al., 2019</xref>). Contrary to expectations, however, individuals who used nonprescribed buprenorphine/naloxone experienced more than three times the risk of overdose as those who did not, while use of nonprescribed methadone was unrelated to overdose. Although a recent study found a positive association between NPB use and subsequent improved treatment retention and reduced opioid use (<xref rid="bb0300" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al., 2022</xref>), most research reporting harm reduction benefits has relied on self-reported motives for use. Few quantitative studies have examined associations between nonprescribed use and actual reduction in harm (<xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">Chilcoat et al., 2019</xref>), especially overdose. One of the few studies to do so was conducted by <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">Carlson et al. (2020)</xref>, who found a significant decrease in drug overdose as the frequency of NPB use increased. However, more frequent use of buprenorphine, like more consistent use of opioids in general, may have protected against the reductions or fluctuations in tolerance accompanying sporadic use (<xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">Blazes &amp; Morrow, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0270" ref-type="bibr">Tagliaro et al., 1998</xref>). Further, because this study only sampled individuals who used NPB, comparisons of overdose risk among nonusers were not possible, shedding no light on whether frequent, nonprescribed use conferred any benefit over nonuse.</p><p id="p0250">In the current study, any nonprescribed use of buprenorphine/naloxone clearly heightened overdose risk compared to those who did not misuse the medication, with nonprescribed buprenorphine/naloxone use increasing the overdose risk by almost three times that of nonusers in the sample as a whole and by nearly five times that of nonusers in the treatment sample. The higher overdose risk associated with NPB is unlikely to be due to the abuse potential of the medication itself, since the buprenorphine/naloxone formula discourages injection of the medication (<xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">Degenhardt et al., 2009</xref>) and those using opioids intravenously have shown a preference for heroin/fentanyl over even the mono-buprenorphine formulas (<xref rid="bb0310" ref-type="bibr">Winstock &amp; Lea, 2010</xref>). Further, because buprenorphine is a partial agonist, it has a low potential for respiratory depression and overdose (<xref rid="bb0305" ref-type="bibr">Williams, Samples, Crystal, &amp; Olfson, 2020</xref>), making overdose deaths solely or partially attributable to buprenorphine or buprenorphine/naloxone rare (<xref rid="bb0315" ref-type="bibr">Yokell, Zaller, Green, &amp; Rich, 2011</xref>; Wightmen et al). However, use of NPB may be a marker for illness severity, a possibility supported by findings of <xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">Bazazi, Yokell, Fu, Rich, and Zaller (2011)</xref>, who found higher nonprescribed use among injectors vs. noninjectors and among high frequency vs. low frequency opioid users. In the current study, nonprescribed buprenorphine/naloxone users were more likely than nonusers to have used heroin/fentanyl in the last 12&#160;months (86.8&#160;% vs. 67.3&#160;%, &#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;12.72; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;=&#160;.001) and, among current heroin/fentanyl users, to have used heroin/fentanyl more frequently in the last 30&#160;days (M&#160;=&#160;26.6&#160;days vs. 19.6&#160;days; F&#160;=&#160;18.6; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;=&#160;.001). During the pandemic, more frequent users might have had greater difficulty accessing enough heroin/fentanyl to maintain their habit, needing intermittent buprenorphine/naloxone for temporary abstinence and withdrawal management. This on-and-off use of opioids could have negatively affected tolerance and further raised the risk of overdose.</p><p id="p0255">Further, the unique pharmacokinetic profile of fentanyl has complicated buprenorphine induction protocols, with standard protocols used for heroin and other opioids found to precipitate withdrawal symptoms in those exposed to illicit fentanyl (<xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">Antoine et al., 2021</xref>). As a result, induction guidelines in areas of high fentanyl prevalence call for using lower doses of buprenorphine (<xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">Antoine et al., 2021</xref>), a fact likely to be unknown by many users of NPB. Moreover, studies show that those self-treating with buprenorphine, have been challenged by buprenorphine's unpredictability in the presence of fentanyl, with many experiencing precipitated withdrawal following NPB use at usual dosages (<xref rid="bb0250" ref-type="bibr">Silverstein, Daniulaityte, Martins, Miller, &amp; Carlson, 2019</xref>). Precipitated withdrawal, in turn, may further increase the risk of overdose by spurring immediate reuse of heroin/fentanyl to eliminate withdrawal. Additionally, unpredictability of buprenorphine's effects may lead PWUO to turn to other, more dangerous substances to manage opioid withdrawal symptoms (<xref rid="bb0250" ref-type="bibr">Silverstein et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p id="p0260">In multivariable analysis of those treated during the pandemic, buprenorphine/naloxone treatment was also associated with a higher risk of overdose than other MOUD, or non-medication-based treatment, although this effect became insignificant after controlling for nonprescribed buprenorphine/naloxone use. In ad hoc analysis comparing buprenorphine/naloxone, methadone and naltrexone patients, buprenorphine/naloxone patients showed significantly higher rates of misuse than other patients, including a greater tendency to buy (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;9.70, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.01) and sell (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;11.23, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.01) MOUD illicitly and to exceed recommended dosages (&#967;<sup>2</sup>&#160;=&#160;8.27, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#160;&#8804;&#160;.05). Although findings of studies investigating the relative potential for diversion/misuse of buprenorphine vs. methadone are mixed (<xref rid="bb0255" ref-type="bibr">Soyka, 2014</xref>), a greater risk of diversion of buprenorphine, including buprenorphine/naloxone, has been documented in several studies (<xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">Johnson &amp; Richert, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bb0170" ref-type="bibr">Larance et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bb0310" ref-type="bibr">Winstock &amp; Lea, 2010</xref>). Such a finding may be explained by the stricter regulations governing methadone administration compared to buprenorphine, which is available through physician prescription (<xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">Johnson &amp; Richert, 2015</xref>). While few studies have examined reasons for buprenorphine misuse among buprenorphine patients, some research has found an association between buprenorphine injection and inadequate dosing (<xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">Fareed, Vayalapalli, Caserella, &amp; Drexler, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bb0235" ref-type="bibr">Roux et al., 2008</xref>), a factor that may explain misuse by buprenorphine/naloxone patients in the current study.</p><p id="p0265">Whether used by individuals in or out of treatment, NPB is often described as being used &#8220;therapeutically&#8221; to differentiate it from being used to produce euphoria. In actual practice, however, PWUO may be using NPB in ways that are ineffectual for addiction management or overdose prevention, especially if use is sporadic and dosing is inappropriate in the context of fentanyl. The current study did not assess dosage or frequency of NPB use, making it impossible to know the extent to which use of the medication was likely to produce therapeutic effects; however, in many cases the dose and dosing frequency may not have been optimal. As a result, unmonitored use of buprenorphine may be ineffective in reducing the harms associated with opioid use, regardless of the motivations of those using it.</p><sec id="s0080"><label>4.1</label><title>Limitations</title><p id="p0270">This study is affected by a number of limitations. First, because it is based on a convenience sample, the study participants are not representative of all PWUO, either in New Jersey or elsewhere. Although half our sample was currently out of treatment, most of these individuals were recruited from a social service agency that houses a needle-exchange program, resulting in a bias in the out-of-treatment group toward those who inject. Further, the sample may also be biased in favor of those with greater computer literacy, since the survey was administered using a self-administered, computerized instrument. Also, the data are cross-sectional, thus limiting inferences about causality. Similarly, questions asking for historical information may be affected by recall bias. Finally, the study did not obtain precise measures of drug use frequency or quantity, thus limiting interpretations of findings pertaining to increased use. However, the mixed-methods sequential study design allowed us to broaden our topical focus beyond that reflected in many standardized questionnaires and to shed light on important drug use and treatment-related issues deserving of further study.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0085"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0275">The results of this study suggest that increased drug use, especially relapse, was frequent during the first 14&#160;months of the pandemic and occurred in the context of reduced treatment accessibility. Together, these factors may have fueled the heightened overdose rates observed since the start of the pandemic. The current findings also suggest a need to prioritize resources for relapse-prevention during pandemics, since those who relapse may be more vulnerable to overdose than those continuing opioid use at pre-pandemic levels.</p><p id="p0280">An unexpected finding of this study was the highly significant association between nonprescribed buprenorphine/naloxone use and increased overdose risk, countering recent suggestions that nonprescribed use may confer public health benefits when treatment is inaccessible (<xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">Carlson et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">Chilcoat et al., 2019</xref>). Despite the potential adverse consequences of unmonitored use, however, buprenorphine remains a critical tool in combatting the opioid crisis. We would thus caution against overinterpreting our findings in a way that leads to further restrictions on the use of this life-saving medication. Rather, the widespread use of NPB among those with the most severe illness in the current study argues for a more rapid expansion of access to buprenorphine treatment for those most in need, including increasing buprenorphine induction in hospital emergency departments, a measure currently being implemented in New Jersey.</p></sec><sec id="s0090"><title>Role of funding source</title><p id="p0285">The funding source for this project was the <funding-source id="gts0005"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100004844</institution-id><institution>New Jersey Department of Human Services</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>, Division of Mental Health and Addiction Services. The funding source participated in the review and editing of this paper.</p></sec><sec id="s0095"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0290"><bold>Anna Kline:</bold> Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Funding acquisition, Methodology, Investigation, Project administration, Supervision, Writing &#8211; original draft, Visualization, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. <bold>Jill M. Williams:</bold> Conceptualization, Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. <bold>Marc L. Steinberg:</bold> Conceptualization, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. <bold>Dina Mattern:</bold> Data curation, Validation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Visualization, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. <bold>Megan Chesin:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. <bold>Suzanne Borys:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. <bold>Vamsee Chaguturu:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0300">None.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bi0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bb0005"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf202303300646053646"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>F.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossen</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Provisional drug overdose death counts</part-title><year>2021</year><publisher-name>National Center for Health Statistics, CDC National Statistics Rapid Release</publisher-name><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nvss/vsrr/drug-overdose-data.htm" id="ir0005">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nvss/vsrr/drug-overdose-data.htm</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0010"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300705187496"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alex</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaba</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosner</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Venters</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Death after jail release</article-title><source>Journal of Correctional Healthcare</source><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1078345816685311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28040993</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0015"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300705199126"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Antoine</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huhn</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strain</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jardot</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Method for successfully inducting individuals who use illicit fentanyl onto buprenorphine/naloxone</article-title><source>The American Journal on Addictions</source><volume>30</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32572978</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/ajad.13069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7755703</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0020"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300646066126"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bachireddy</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Securing the safety net and protecting public health during a pandemic: Medicaid&#8217;s response to COVID-19</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>233</volume><issue>20</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>2009</fpage><lpage>2010</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.4272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32191260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0025"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300705215456"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bazazi</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yokell</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaller</surname><given-names>N.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Illicit use of buprenorphine/naloxone among injecting and noninjecting opioid users</article-title><source>Journal of Addiction Medicine</source><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ADM.0b013e3182034e31</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21844833</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3157053</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0030"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300705227226"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Binswanger</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blatchford</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mortality after prison release: Opioid overdose and other causes of death, risk factors, and time trends from 1999 to 2009</article-title><source>Annals of Internal Medicine</source><volume>159</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>592</fpage><lpage>600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-159-9-201311050-00005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24189594</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5242316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0035"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300647185276"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blazes</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reconsidering the usefulness of adding naloxone to buprenorphine</article-title><source>Frontiers in Psychology</source><volume>11</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">549272</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.549272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7517938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33061915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0040"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300647240296"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brugal</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrio</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luis De</surname><given-names>L.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Regidor</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Royuela</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suelves</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with non-fatal heroin overdose: Accessing the effect of frequency and route of heroin administration</article-title><source>Addiction</source><volume>97</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1360-0443.2002.00058.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11964108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0045"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf202303300656469427"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Canadian Centre on Substance Use and Addiction (CCENDU)</collab></person-group><part-title>CCENDU alert: changes related to COVID-19 in the illegal drug supply and access to services and resulting health harms</part-title><comment>May</comment><year>2020</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ccsa.ca/Impacts-COVID-19-Substance-Use" id="ir0010">https://www.ccsa.ca/Impacts-COVID-19-Substance-Use</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0050"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300647394686"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daniulaityte</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nahhas</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unintentional drug overdose: Is more frequent use of non-prescribed buprenorphine associated with lower risk of overdose?</article-title><source>International Journal of Drug Policy</source><volume>79</volume><issue>102722</issue><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugpo.2020.102722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9387534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32311513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0055"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300705241206"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chilcoat</surname><given-names>H.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amick</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherwood</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Buprenorphine in the United States: Motives for abuse, misuse, and diversion</article-title><source>Journal of Substance Abuse Treatment</source><volume>104</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2019.07.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31370979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0060"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300705279986"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cicero</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Surratt</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurtz</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors contributing to the rise of buprenorphine misuse: 2008&#8211;2013</article-title><source>Drug and Alcohol Dependence</source><volume>142</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2014.06.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24984689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0065"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300647510196"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clausen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waal</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thoresen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gossop</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mortality among opiate users: Opioid maintenance therapy, age and causes of death</article-title><source>Addiction</source><volume>104</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>1356</fpage><lpage>1362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1360-0443.2009.02570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19426288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0070"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300705415956"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cragg</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hau</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitchen</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doyle-Waters</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hohl</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors for misuse of prescribed opioids: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Annals of Emergency Medicine</source><volume>74</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>634</fpage><lpage>646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annemergmed.2019.04.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31229388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0075"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300705509466"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samuels</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Opioid policy changes during the COVID-19 pandemic - and beyond</article-title><source>Journal of Addiction Medicine</source><volume>14</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>e4</fpage><lpage>e5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ADM.0000000000000679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32433363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7273953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0080"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300705428126"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sites</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prescription opioid use among adults with mental health disorders in the United States</article-title><source>The Journal of the American Board of Family Medicine</source><volume>30</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3122/jabfm.2017.04.170112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28720623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0085"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300705522416"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larance</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winstock</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lintzeris</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheuer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattick</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Injection of medications used in opioid substitution treatment in Australia after the introduction of a mixed partial agonist-antagonist formulation</article-title><source>The Medical Journal of Australia</source><volume>191</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5694/j.1326-5377.2009.tb02729.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19645647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0090"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf202303300657015437"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Drug Enforcement Agency (DEA)</collab></person-group><part-title>Letter to DEA qualifying practitioners</part-title><comment>Published Mar 31, 2020</comment><year>2020</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.samhsa.gov/sites/default/files/dea-samhsa-buprenorphine-telemedicine.pdf?mc_cid=8dffbfc637&amp;mc_eid=d4494a732e" id="ir0015">https://www.samhsa.gov/sites/default/files/dea-samhsa-buprenorphine-telemedicine.pdf?mc_cid=8dffbfc637&amp;mc_eid=d4494a732e</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0095"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300705532616"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Druid</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strandberg</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alkass</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nystrom</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kugelberg</surname><given-names>F.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kronstrand</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the role of abstinence in heroin overdose deaths using segmental hair analysis</article-title><source>Forensic Science International</source><volume>168</volume><issue>2&#8211;3</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.forsciint.2006.02.047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16564148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0100"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300706020726"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsui</surname><given-names>J.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lum</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mortality among young injection drug users in San Francisco: A 10-year follow-up of the UFO study</article-title><source>American Journal of Epidemiology</source><volume>175</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>302</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwr318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22227793</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3271816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0105"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300647533916"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fareed</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vayalapalli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caserella</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drexler</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of buprenorphine dose on treatment outcome</article-title><source>Journal of Addictive Diseases</source><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10550887.2011.642758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22356665</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0110"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300647547186"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fetters</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curry</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Creswell</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Achieving integration in mixed methods designs-principles and practices</article-title><source>Health Services Research</source><volume>48</volume><issue>6 Pt 2</issue><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1475-6773.12117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4097839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24279835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0115"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300706187006"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akre</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 and the drug overdose crisis: Uncovering the deadliest months in the United States, January&#8211;July 2020</article-title><source>American Journal of Public Health</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2021.306256</pub-id><comment>e1&#8211;e8, [Epub ahead of print]</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8493145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33856885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0120"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300647577586"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galarneau</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilburt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Neill</surname><given-names>Z.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buxton</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheuermeyer</surname><given-names>F.X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaczorowski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orkin</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbic</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bath</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moe</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grier</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrod</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kestler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experiences of people with opioid use disorder during the COVID-19 pandemic: A qualitative study</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>16</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0255396</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0255396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8320992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34324589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0125"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300648072056"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Genberg</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johanson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Astemborski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>G.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vlahov</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and correlates of street-obtained buprenorphine use among current and former injectors in BaltimoreMaryland</article-title><source>Journal of Addictive Behaviors</source><volume>38</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>2868</fpage><lpage>2873</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.addbeh.2013.08.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24018232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3805723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0130"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300648152096"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gleason</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nolan</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Habrock</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Durkin</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Barriers to care experienced by patients who inject drugs during the COVID-19 pandemic: A qualitative analysis</article-title><source>Journal of Addiction Medicine</source><volume>16</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>e133</fpage><lpage>e136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ADM.0000000000000853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33840774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8497648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0135"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300706194486"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haley</surname><given-names>D.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saitz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The opioid epidemic during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>324</volume><issue>16</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>1615</fpage><lpage>1617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.18543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32945831</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0140"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf202303300657469387"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedegaard</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mini&#241;o</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Drug overdose deaths in the United States, 1999&#8211;2020</part-title><source>NCHS Data Brief, no 428</source><year>2021</year><publisher-name>National Center for Health Statistics</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hyattsville, MD</publisher-loc><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15620/cdc:112340</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0145"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf202303300658341237"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedegaard</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mini&#241;o</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Drug overdose deaths in the United States, 1999-2019</part-title><source>NCHS data brief, no 394</source><year>2020</year><publisher-name>National Center for Health Statistics</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hyattsville, MD</publisher-loc><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data/databriefs/db394-H.pdf" id="ir0020">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data/databriefs/db394-H.pdf</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0150"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300648403716"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Q.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pluye</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bujold</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wassef</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Convergent and sequential synthesis designs: Implications for conducting and reporting systematic reviews of qualitative and quantitative evidence</article-title><source>Systematic Reviews</source><volume>6</volume><issue>61</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13643-017-0454-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28335799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5364694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0155"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300649216956"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Imtiaz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nafeh</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elton-Marshall</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehm</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of the novel coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic on drug overdose-related deaths in the United States and Canada: A systematic review of observational studies and analysis of public health surveillance data</article-title><source>Substance Abuse Treatment, Prevention and Policy</source><volume>16</volume><issue>87</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13011-021-00423-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34844624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8628272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0160"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300706202066"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richert</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversion of methadone and buprenorphine by patients in opioid substitution treatment in Sweden: Prevalence estimates and risk factors</article-title><source>International Journal of Drug Policy</source><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugpo.2014.10.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25465344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0165"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf202303300659141087"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Kaiser Family Foundation (KFF)</collab></person-group><part-title>Medicaid emergency authority tracker: Approved state actions to address COVID-19</part-title><comment>Retrieved from</comment><year>2021</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.kff.org/coronavirus-covid-19/issue-brief/medicaid-emergency-authority-tracker-approved-state-actions-to-address-covid-19/" id="ir0025">https://www.kff.org/coronavirus-covid-19/issue-brief/medicaid-emergency-authority-tracker-approved-state-actions-to-address-covid-19/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0170"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300706207446"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larance</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lintzeris</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winstock</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dietze</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattick</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horyniak</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-marketing surveillance of buprenorphine-naloxone in Australia: Diversion, injection and adherence with supervised dosing</article-title><source>Drug and Alcohol Dependence</source><volume>118</volume><issue>2&#8211;3</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2011.04.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21565452</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0175"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300649286896"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Buprenorphine &#8211; background to its development as a treatment for opiate dependence</article-title><source>NIDA Research Monograph Index</source><volume>121</volume><year>1992</year><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/e496132006-003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1406910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0180"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300649406606"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Linas</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Savinkina</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cerda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keyes</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chhatwal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A clash of epidemics: Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic response on opioid overdose</article-title><source>Journal of Substance Abuse Treatment</source><volume>120</volume><issue>108158</issue><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2020.108158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7536128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33298298</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0185"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300649453436"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lofwall</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review of buprenorphine diversion and misuse: The current evidence base and experiences from around the world</article-title><source>Journal of Addictive Medicine</source><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">10.1097/ADM. 0000000000000045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/ADM.0000000000000045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4177012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25221984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0190"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300649508816"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blow</surname><given-names>F.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ilgen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of medication-assisted treatment on mortality among opioids users: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Molecular Psychiatry</source><volume>24</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1868</fpage><lpage>1883</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41380-018-0094-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29934549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0195"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300706213386"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mars</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenblum</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciccarone</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Illicit fentanyl in the opioid street market: Desired or imposed?</article-title><source>Addiction</source><volume>114</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>774</fpage><lpage>780</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/add.14474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30512204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6548693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0200"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf202303300701284917"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>New Jersey Division of Addiction Services</collab></person-group><part-title>Buprenorphine guidelines</part-title><comment>April</comment><source>Administrative bulletin</source><year>2007</year><publisher-name>State of New Jersey, Department of Human Services, Division of Mental Health and Addiction Services</publisher-name><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.state.nj.us/humanservices/dmhas/regulations/bulletins/Addictions/Buprenorphine.pdf" id="ir0030">https://www.state.nj.us/humanservices/dmhas/regulations/bulletins/Addictions/Buprenorphine.pdf</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0205"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf202303300702081397"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>New Jersey State Police: Drug Monitoring Initiative</collab></person-group><part-title>Office of Drug Monitoring &amp; Analysis Quarterly Report, July 1 2021 - September 30, 2021</part-title><comment>November 16</comment><year>2021</year><publisher-name>Office of Drug Monitoring and Analysis</publisher-name><comment>ROIC202110-20164D</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0210"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf202303300651328867"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niles</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinderknecht</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strohmeyer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Changes in Access to Medication Treatment During COVID-19 Telehealth Expansion and Disparities in Telehealth Use for Medicare Beneficiaries With Opioid Use Disorder</part-title><year>2022</year><publisher-name>Office of Minority Health (OMH) Data Highlight No. 28. Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services (CMS)</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0215"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300651599807"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wenger</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorvick</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kral</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The misuse, abuse and diversion of opioid replacement therapies among street abusers</article-title><source>Drug and Alcohol Dependence</source><volume>146</volume><year>2015</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e54</object-id><comment>10/1016/j.drugalcdep.2014.09.517</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0220"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300702448848"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oesterle</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolla</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Risma</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breitinger</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rakocevic</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loukianova</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall-Flavin</surname><given-names>D.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gentry</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rummans</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Substance use disorders and telehealth in the COVID-19 pandemic era: A new outlook</article-title><source>Mayo Clinical Proceedings</source><volume>95</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>2709</fpage><lpage>2718</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mayocp.2020.10.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7577694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33276843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0225"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300652017907"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garey</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zvokensky</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychological factors associated with substance use initation during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Psychiatry Research</source><volume>293</volume><issue>113407</issue><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7434361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32827993</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0230"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300652134637"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenbaum</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zandrow</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Satz</surname><given-names>W.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isenberg</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#8217;Orazio</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gentile</surname><given-names>N.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schreyer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of a shelter-in-place order during the COVID-19 pandemic on the incidence of opioid overdoses</article-title><source>American Journal of Emergency Medicine</source><volume>41</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajem.2020.12.047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33387928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7836717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0235"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300653540687"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villes</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanche</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bry</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spire</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feroni</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrieri</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Buprenorphine in primary care: Risk factors for treatment injection and implications for clinical management</article-title><source>Drug and Alcohol Dependence</source><volume>97</volume><issue>1&#8211;2</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2008.03.025</pub-id><comment>IISN 0376-8716</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18479840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0240"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300653586027"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vittinghoff</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Behar</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coffin</surname><given-names>P.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantity fluctuations of illicitly used opioids and overdose risk</article-title><source>International Journal of Drug Policy</source><volume>58</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugpo.2018.05.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6419728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29807248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0245"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300654055817"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuman-Olivier</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albanese</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roland</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puopolo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klinker</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaffer</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-treatment: Illicit buprenorphine use by opioid-dependent treatment seekers</article-title><source>Journal of Substance Abuse Treatment</source><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2010.03.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20434868</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0250"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300706235966"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daniulaityte</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#8220;Everything is not right anymore&#8221;: Buprenorphine experiences in an era of illicit fentanyl</article-title><source>International Journal of Drug Policy</source><volume>74</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31563098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugpo.2019.09.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6914257</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0255"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300703096838"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soyka</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Buprenorphine use and risk of abuse and diversion</article-title><source>Advanced Pharmacoepidemiology &amp; Drug Safety</source><volume>3</volume><issue>145</issue><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4172/2167-1052.1000145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0260"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf202303300704066767"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration (SAMHSA)</collab></person-group><part-title>FAQs: Provision of methadone and buprenorphine for the treatment of opioid use disorder in the COVID-19 emergency</part-title><year>2020</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.samhsa.gov/sites/default/files/faqs-for-oud-prescribing-and-dispensing.pdf" id="ir0035">https://www.samhsa.gov/sites/default/files/faqs-for-oud-prescribing-and-dispensing.pdf</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0265"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300654132707"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edlund</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Unutzer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between mental health disorders, problem drug use, and regular prescription opioid use</article-title><source>Archives of Internal Medicine</source><volume>166</volume><issue>19</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>2087</fpage><lpage>2093</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.166.19.2087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17060538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0270"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300654147857"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tagliaro</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Battisti</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>F.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marigo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Death from heroin overdose: Findings from hair analysis</article-title><source>The Lancet</source><volume>351</volume><issue>9120</issue><year>1998</year><fpage>1923</fpage><lpage>1925</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0140-6736(97)10101-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9654260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0275"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300654232677"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyndall</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Safer opioid distribution in response to the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>International Journal of Drug Policy</source><volume>82</volume><issue>102880</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugpo.2020.102880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7383133</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32739148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0280"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300654337217"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uscher-Pines</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raja</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrotra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of opioid use disorder during COVID-19: Experiences of clinicians transferring to telemedicine</article-title><source>Journal of Substance Abuse Treatment</source><volume>118</volume><issue>108124</issue><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2020.108124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7456454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32893047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0285"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300654384827"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vakkalanka</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arndt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Field</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlton</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carnahan</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between buprenorphine for opioid use disorder and mortality risk</article-title><source>American Journal of Preventative Medicine</source><volume>61</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>418</fpage><lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2021.02.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8384722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34023160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0290"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300654472967"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vidal-Trecan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varescon</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nabet</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boissinnas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intravenous use of prescribed sublingual buprenorphine tablets by drug users receiving maintenance therapy in France</article-title><source>Drug and Alcohol Dependence</source><volume>69</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0376-8716(02)00312-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12609698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0295"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300706247996"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wainwright</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikre</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitley</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huskey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lukowiak</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giroir</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of drug test results before and after the US declaration of a national emergency concerning the COVID-19 outbreak</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>324</volume><issue>16</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>1674</fpage><lpage>1677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.17694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32945855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7501585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0300"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300705168426"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mauro</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olfson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><x xml:space="preserve">&#8230;</x><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiodo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Non-prescribed buprenorphine preceding treatment intake and clinical outcomes for opioid use disorder</article-title><source>Journal of Substance Abuse Treatment</source><volume>139</volume><year>August 2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2022.108770</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9187606</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35337715</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0305"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300706271686"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samples</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crystal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olfson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute care, prescription opioid use, and overdose following discontinuation of long-term buprenorphine treatment for opioid use disorder</article-title><source>American Journal of Psychiatry</source><volume>177</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2019.19060612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31786933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7002204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0310"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300654567317"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winstock</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lea</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversion and injection of methadone and buprenorphine among clients in public opioid treatment clinics in New South WalesAustralia</article-title><source>Substance Use and Misuse</source><volume>45</volume><issue>1&#8211;2</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/10826080903080664</pub-id><comment>PMID: 20025451</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20025451</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0315"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202303300654594827"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yokell</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaller</surname><given-names>N.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>T.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Buprenorphine and buprenorphine/naloxone diversion, misuse, and illicit use: An international review</article-title><source>Current Drug Abuse Reviews</source><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1874473711104010028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21466501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3154701</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ac0005"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="p0305">We would like to thank the New Jersey Department of Human Services, Division of Mental Health and Addiction Services, for their funding and other support of this project. We are also grateful to the staff of the New Jersey treatment programs and social services agencies who generously contributed their time and assistance to ensuring the success of this project. Last but not least, we are grateful to the many individuals who participated in our study and provided important insights into the effects of the COVID-19 pandemic on their daily lives.</p></ack></back></article></pmc-articleset>