<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Alpha Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Alpha Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4295</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">alphapsych</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AP</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Alpha Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2757-8038</issn><publisher><publisher-name>IMR Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11916059</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11916059.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11916059</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11916059</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40110386</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.31083/AP38792</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2757-8038(25)02002-6</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Trends in Benzodiazepine and Z-Drug Prescriptions in Eastern China (2015&#8211;2021)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0009-3723-7419</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7835-4314</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="H">Hualiang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"><sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"><sup>*</sup>
</xref><email>chenhualing0055@163.com</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Pharmacy, The Seventh People&#8217;s Hospital of Shaoxing, 312000 Shaoxing, Zhejiang, China
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><sup>*</sup>Correspondence:
<email>chenhualing0055@163.com</email> (Hualiang Chen)
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">484436</issue-id><elocation-id>38792</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>2</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>28</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>19</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-03-20 09:25:38.623"><day>20</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#169; 2025 The Author(s). Published by IMR Press.
</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
CC BY 4.0 license</ext-link>.
</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="2757-8038-26-1-38792.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Objective:</title><p>This study analyses trends in the prescription and usage of benzodiazepines (BZDs) and Z-drugs within specialised medical institutions and emergency outpatient services in China from 2015 to 2021, focusing on demographics and prescribing patterns to promote better management practices.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>A retrospective study was conducted from 2015 to 2021, reviewing prescription information and population characteristics from 10 hospitals, including specialised psychiatric institutions and general hospitals in Zhejiang, Jiangsu, and Shanghai. The study analysed a total of 33,569 valid prescriptions.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>There was a noticeable increase in the total defined daily doses of both benzodiazepines and Z-drugs, with significant variations among different drugs. Lorazepam and zopiclone showed the most substantial increases in usage. Drugs like clonazepam and lorazepam were predominantly prescribed, indicating specific patterns in disease management, particularly for insomnia and anxiety.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions:</title><p>This study reveals a significant increase in benzodiazepine and Z-drug prescriptions, particularly among elderly and female patients. The findings highlight the need for targeted interventions and policy reforms to ensure safe prescribing practices and mitigate the risks associated with long-term use in these vulnerable populations.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>benzodiazepines</kwd><kwd>Z-drugs</kwd><kwd>outpatient and emergency prescriptions</kwd><kwd>trend analysis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>This research received no external funding.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><title>Main Points</title><p id="S1.p1">1. Increasing Trend in Drug Usage: Our analysis indicates a consistent 
year-over-year increase in the prescription and use of benzodiazepines (BZDs) and 
Z-drugs in specialised medical institutions and outpatient settings, underscoring 
a growing reliance on these medications.</p><p id="S1.p2">2. Demographic Insights: The study reveals significant demographic disparities 
in drug usage, with higher prescription rates among elderly female patients. This 
suggests a targeted need for monitoring and potentially adjusting prescription 
practices for this demographic.</p><p id="S1.p3">3. Drug Safety Concerns: Our findings highlight safety concerns related to the 
increased use of potentially addictive medications among older populations. This 
calls for enhanced oversight and the implementation of stricter prescribing 
guidelines to prevent misuse and dependency.</p><p id="S1.p4">4. Regional Variations in Prescriptions: The study documents notable differences 
in prescription trends across different regions, reflecting varying medical 
practices and accessibility to healthcare services. This emphasises the need for 
region-specific strategies to optimise drug use.</p><p id="S1.p5">5. Implications for Policy and Practice: The results advocate for policy reforms 
and educational initiatives aimed at promoting the rational use of BZDs and 
Z-drugs to mitigate risks and improve patient outcomes.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>1. Introduction</title><p id="S2.p1">Benzodiazepine receptor agonists (BZRAs) are currently the most commonly used 
sedative-hypnotic and anti-anxiety drugs. This class includes traditional 
benzodiazepines (BZDs) and non-BZD Z-drugs. Benzodiazepines primarily produce 
their effects by binding to benzodiazepine receptors on the gamma-aminobutyric 
acid (GABA) receptor complex, enhancing the effect of GABA and leading to 
sedation and hypnotic, anticonvulsant, and muscle relaxation effects [<xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. 
Z-drugs, although similar in function to BZDs, are primarily used for their 
sedative&#8211;hypnotic properties and are not typically considered anxiolytics. Most 
BZDs are internationally classified as Class IV controlled drugs and can cause 
serious social harm if acquired via illicit channels [<xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Benzodiazepines bind to 
specific sites on the GABA-A receptors in the brain and enhance the effects of 
GABA. This leads to increased chloride ion influx into the neurons, which 
hyperpolarises the cell membrane and reduces neuronal excitability [<xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Z-drugs 
are structurally different from BZDs but act on the same GABA-A receptor complex 
as BZDs [<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. They bind to a specific site on the receptor complex that is 
distinct from the benzodiazepine site. Benzodiazepines are the most commonly 
abused type of prescription drug, according to the World Health Organization 
(WHO) Global Drug Report 2018 [<xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. A previous study examined the prevalence and 
prescribing patterns of BZDs and Z-drugs in older nursing home residents across 
six European countries [<xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Another study analysed trends in the consumption 
rates of BZDs and Z-drugs in the health region of Lleida, Spain, from 2002 to 
2015 [<xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The current article focuses on the drug use trends of BZDs and Z-drugs 
in regional specialised medical institutions in China, which is a developing 
country. The study aims to address an existing knowledge gap by providing more 
specific and detailed information on the drug-use trends of BZDs and Z-drugs in 
rapidly developing areas, such as China&#8217;s East Coast, which differ from general 
hospitals or community settings in developed countries. 
</p><p id="S2.p2">In recent years, the use of BZDs has been on the rise, and their excessive and 
irregular use has become a new topic [<xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The excessive and irregular use of BZDs 
has been investigated in countries around the world, revealing significant 
dependence and adverse effects risks. Previous study reveals that while 
benzodiazepine use is common among US adults, misuse and use disorders are 
relatively rare, though certain demographics are at higher risk for misuse and 
associated health issues [<xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Corresponding studies in China have shown similar 
patterns, highlighting the need for stricter regulation and better management 
practices to mitigate these risks [<xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. This study aims to understand Zhejiang 
Provincial Hospital&#8217;s guidelines for the prescription of BZDs, as well as the 
selective BZD drugs that are used in this clinical setting. It also aims to 
analyse the prescription drug types, dosage, and quantity, and to understand the 
population characteristics of those who use prescription drugs. This will provide 
a scientific basis for the rational use of these drugs. The significance of this 
study is to present a better understanding of the actual situation behind the 
increase of prescriptions; the variety, dosage, and quantity of prescription 
drugs; and the structural factors, such as the gender, age, and disease of 
patients who use prescription drugs. This study aims to guide the rational use of 
drugs in the corresponding population and reduce drug abuse. By identifying 
trends in prescription practices and highlighting demographic groups at higher 
risk, our findings provide a basis for targeted interventions, such as 
educational programmes for healthcare providers and the implementation of 
stricter prescribing guidelines. The purpose of this study is to better 
understand the usage patterns of BZDs, which have a high potential for addiction, 
and to promote their rational use. By analysing prescription data based on 
gender, age, and disease factors, we aim to identify trends and improve 
management practices. Our findings are based on a sample from China&#8217;s eastern 
coastal regions, which are economically developed and have a higher usage rate of 
BZDs due to an ageing population [<xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="S3"><title>2. Purpose</title><p id="S3.p1">This study aims to understand Zhejiang Provincial Hospital&#8217;s guidelines for the 
prescription of BZDs, as well as the selective BZD drugs that are being used. 
This includes examining factors such as dosage, frequency, and patient 
demographics to ensure that prescriptions are made according to the best 
practices outlined in the hospital&#8217;s guidelines. It also aims to analyse the 
prescription drug types, dosage, and quantity, and to gain a better understanding 
of the population characteristics of those who use prescription drugs. The 
outcomes aim to provide a scientific basis for the rational use of these drugs.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>3. Method</title><sec id="S4.SS1"><title>3.1 Research Design</title><p id="S4.SS1.p1">This pharmacoepidemiology retrospective study reviewed prescribing information 
and population characteristics from 2015 to 2021. The study utilised a stratified 
random sampling approach, selecting data from 10 major hospitals in Zhejiang, 
Jiangsu, and Shanghai. This method ensured a representative sample across 
different types of hospitals, including specialised psychiatric institutions and 
general hospitals, thereby providing a comprehensive view of benzodiazepine and 
Z-drug prescription trends.</p></sec><sec id="S4.SS2"><title>3.2 Institutions</title><p id="S4.SS2.p1">This study focused on the use of BZDs and non-BZDs in major psychiatric 
hospitals in economically developed areas of eastern China from 2015 to 2021, as 
well as prescriptions for BZDs and non-BZDs in outpatient and emergency 
departments from 2017 to 2021.</p></sec><sec id="S4.SS3"><title>3.3 Participants</title><p id="S4.SS3.p1">The data of BZDs and non-BZDs in the hospital information system (HIS) refer to 
actual clinical usage and do not include data that are not actually used. 
Prescriptions for BZDs and non-BZDs used in outpatient and emergency 
prescriptions, with complete information and excluding unqualified returned 
prescriptions, were eligible for use in this study.</p></sec><sec id="S4.SS4"><title>3.4 Variables</title><p id="S4.SS4.p1">Defined daily dose (DDD) value: This refers to the average daily dose of 
medication. The DDD value is the total mean daily dose of the drug. The DDD 
values of each drug were queried and registered according to the DDD values 
published on the WHO&#8217;s website.</p><p id="S4.SS4.p2">Prescription: This refers to an outpatient or emergency prescription issued by a 
registered physician.</p><p id="S4.SS4.p3">Second-class mental prescriptions: In China, psychotropic drugs are divided into 
Class I and Class II psychotropic drugs. Class I psychotropic drugs are 
prescribed as special prescriptions for narcotic drugs, whereas Class II 
psychotropic drugs are prescribed with special prescriptions for Class II 
psychotropic drugs.</p><p id="S4.SS4.p4">Drugs: These refer to BZDs and non-BZDs (class Z). The drugs include primarily 
BZDs, such as lorazepam tablets, oxazepam, estazolam tablets, alprazolam, 
clonazepam, diazepam needles, diazepam and nitrazepam tablets, while non-BZDs 
(class Z) include zopiclone tablets.</p><p id="S4.SS4.p5">Diagnosis (name of disease): The names of mental diseases are classified 
according to the broad categories of related mental diseases denoted in the 
Treatment Guide: Psychosis Volume [7th edition] compiled by Australian Treatment 
Guidelines Limited, 2015. They include insomnia, sleep and anxiety disorders, and 
depression. Non-mental illness names are classified as &#8216;other diseases&#8217;.</p></sec><sec id="S4.SS5"><title>3.5 Quantitative Variables</title><p id="S4.SS5.p1">The DDD values of each drug were queried and registered according to the DDD 
values published on the WHO&#8217;s website.</p><p id="S4.SS5.p2">Annual data were calculated and tabulated according to the drug name, 
specification, quantity, total measurement, and DDD number. Drug names were 
classified individually according to the prevailing chemical name of the drug.</p><p id="S4.SS5.p3">Prescriptions: These were categorised by year, gender, age group, and drug name.</p></sec><sec id="S4.SS6"><title>3.6 Data Sources and Measurements</title><p id="S4.SS6.p1">Drug quantity: The quantity data of BZDs and Z-drugs that were used in relevant 
hospitals from 2015 to 2021 were collected, including the year, drug name, 
specification, unit price, and quantity. The data for this study were collected 
as part of a comprehensive research project on the prescription patterns of BZDs 
and Z-drugs in China. The study involved a total of 10 hospitals located in three 
provinces: Zhejiang, Jiangsu, and Shanghai. This included specialised psychiatric 
institutions and general hospitals with significant outpatient and emergency 
services.</p><p id="S4.SS6.p2">Prescribed: The information system was based on the individual HIS of each 
hospital for drugs. Data were collected from 2017 to 2021 about the prescription 
and use of BZD drugs. The prescriptions contained no privacy information, as the 
names were displayed as &#8216;surname * *&#8217;. Patient data included their gender, age, 
diagnosis of diseases (name), drug name, quantity, usage, dosage, and 
prescription date. The collected data were checked for privacy and compliance.</p></sec><sec id="S4.SS7"><title>3.7 Bias</title><p id="S4.SS7.p1">The quantity of drugs refers to the actual consumption of said specific drug 
throughout the hospital as a whole.</p><p id="S4.SS7.p2">Number of prescriptions: This was 8%&#8211;10% of the total sample collected for 
all 10 hospitals.</p></sec><sec id="S4.SS8"><title>3.8 Statistical Methods</title><p id="S4.SS8.p1">To ensure rigorous analysis and interpretation of the data collected, we 
employed a comprehensive statistical approach using the SPSS Statistics 21 
software (IBM, Armonk, NY, USA). This section outlines the detailed statistical 
methods used in our study.</p><p id="S4.SS8.p2">Data Preparation and Cleaning: Initially, data underwent preprocessing to ensure 
accuracy and consistency. This involved checking for outliers, handling missing 
values through imputation where appropriate, and verifying the data integrity 
against entry errors.</p><p id="S4.SS8.p3">Descriptive Statistics: We computed descriptive statistics to summarise the 
demographic and prescription data. This included calculating the means, standard 
deviations and ranges for continuous variables, as well as frequencies and 
percentages for categorical variables.</p><sec id="S4.SS8.SSS1"><title>Inferential Statistics</title><p id="S4.SS8.SSS1.p1">&#9899; Chi-Square Tests: We applied chi-square tests to examine the 
associations between categorical variables, such as gender, age groups, and types 
of prescriptions.</p><p id="S4.SS8.SSS1.p2">&#9899; Analysis of Variance (ANOVA): To compare the means of continuous 
variables across multiple groups, such as age groups and drug types, we used 
one-way ANOVA tests.</p><p id="S4.SS8.SSS1.p3">&#9899; Regression Analysis: Logistic regression was utilised to explore the 
predictors of drug use, adjusting for potential confounders like age, gender, and 
diagnosis.</p><p id="S4.SS8.SSS1.p4">Measures of Association: Results from the logistic regression provided odds 
ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs), providing insights into the 
strength and direction of the associations between demographic factors and drug 
prescription patterns.</p><p id="S4.SS8.SSS1.p5">Data Visualisation: To aid in the interpretation of the results, we produced 
various charts and graphs, including histograms for distribution views, and line 
graphs to depict trends over time.</p><p id="S4.SS8.SSS1.p6">Significance Levels: All tests were two-tailed, with a significance level set at 
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="w1" alttext="&lt;" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 0.05. This threshold was used to determine the statistical 
significance of the findings.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="S5"><title>4. Results</title><sec id="S5.SS1"><title>4.1 Study Population and Groups</title><p id="S5.SS1.p1">Study population: Male (38.2%) and female (61.8%) patients aged 14&#8211;80 years 
old who required the use of BZDs and non-BZDs.</p><p id="S5.SS1.p2">Age group: The groups were <inline-formula><mml:math id="w2" alttext="\leq" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>&#8804;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>17, 18&#8211;34, 35&#8211;44, 45&#8211;64, 65&#8211;75, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="w3" alttext="&gt;" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>75 
years of age.</p><p id="S5.SS1.p3">There was a total hospital consumption of 8 different BZD types and 1 type of 
Z-drug in the 6 years from 2015 to 2021.</p><p id="S5.SS1.p4">A total of 33,569 valid BZD and Z-drug outpatient and emergency prescriptions 
were collected from 2017 to 2021.</p><p id="S5.SS1.p5">Inclusion Criteria: 
</p><p id="S5.SS1.p6">Patients who received benzodiazepine or Z-drug prescriptions between 2015 and 
2021.</p><p id="S5.SS1.p7">Data from both specialised psychiatric institutions and general hospitals in 
Zhejiang, Jiangsu, and Shanghai were collected.</p><p id="S5.SS1.p8">Exclusion Criteria:</p><p id="S5.SS1.p9">Incomplete or missing prescription data.</p><p id="S5.SS1.p10">Patients who were not prescribed BZDs or Z-drugs.</p><p id="S5.SS1.p11">Inpatient prescriptions were excluded.</p></sec><sec id="S5.SS2"><title>4.2 Defined Daily dose Value of Drug Use</title><p id="S5.SS2.p1">The total DDD values of the drugs that were used were calculated according to 
the general name of each drug, based on the DDD value of said drug, published on 
the WHO website. The annual DDDs of the total drugs showed an upward trend. 
Zolpiclone is the primary Z-drug available in the regions where our study was 
conducted. Eszopiclone and Zolpidem are less commonly prescribed due to regional 
pharmaceutical regulations and availability. According to the annual DDD value of 
individual drugs, lorazepam and zopiclone tablets showed a rapid rising trend; 
oxazepam and estazolam tablets showed a slow rising trend; and alprazolam, 
clonazepam, and diazepam showed a slight rise, followed by a steady decline. 
Diazepam and nitrazepam tablets tended to be reduced to non-use. See Table <xref rid="S5.T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and 
Fig. <xref rid="S5.F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="S5.F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.
</label><caption><p>
<bold>Trends in benzodiazepines and non-benzodiazepines drug use data 
(DDDs), 2015&#8211;2021</bold>.
</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="S5.F1.g1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="2757-8038-26-1-38792-g1.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="S5.T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.
</label><caption><p><bold>In 2015&#8211;2021 benzodiazepines and Z-drug use data (DDDs)</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="border-top:1px solid #000;border-bottom:1px solid #000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug name</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2021</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diazepam Injection</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35,631</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41,100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42,477</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38,900</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47,409</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35,343</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42,008</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alprazolam Tablets</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">359,120.768</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">407,427</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">392,942</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">440,784</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">430,069</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">430,521</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">412,809.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estazolam Tablets</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">189,380.6667</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">232,187</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">234,288</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">272,133</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">279,163</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">292,580</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">286,880</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxazepam Tablets</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2334.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43,792</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48,936</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66,990</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63,988</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21,841</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65,760</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrazepam Tablets</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,207</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9863</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,341</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9432</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8629</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9240</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zopiclone Tablet</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73,922.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71,799</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83,087</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131,808</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">158,681</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150,166</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">329,952</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lorazepam Tablets</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">116,098</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">138,094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">251,344</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">396,718</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">508,118</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">624,603.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">634,227.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clonazepam Tablets</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">360,920.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">372,080</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">368,418</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">446,312</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">383,140</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">381,630</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">376,038.8</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom:1px solid #000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Summation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,149,615.135</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,316,612</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,432,833</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,808,645</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,880,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,945,313.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,156,915.6</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Note: DDDs, Defined daily doses of the total drugs.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="S5.SS3"><title>4.3 Statistics of Outpatient and Emergency Prescriptions</title><sec id="S5.SS3.SSS1"><title>4.3.1 Population Characteristics of the Drug Users</title><p id="S5.SS3.SSS1.p1">
<bold>Gender</bold>
</p><p id="S5.SS3.SSS1.p2">Of the total number of 33,569 effective prescriptions, 12,836 prescriptions for 
men accounted for 38.2% and 20,762 prescriptions for women accounted for 61.8%. 
See Table <xref rid="S5.T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Among those aged 50&#8211;75, 6937 men accounted for 36.7%, and 11,964 
women accounted for 63.3%. See Table <xref rid="S5.T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="S5.T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.
</label><caption><p><bold>Characteristics of the population using these drugs</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="border-top:1px solid #000;border-bottom:1px solid #000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valid Percent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valid Percent</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="w4" alttext="\leq" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>&#8804;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">592</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">183</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.91%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">409</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.09%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8211;34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3847</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1499</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.97%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2348</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.03%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35&#8211;49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6739</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2682</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4057</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.20%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#8211;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,846</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4107</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.67%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7739</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.33%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65&#8211;75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7055</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2830</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.11%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4225</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.89%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="w5" alttext="&gt;" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3519</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1535</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.62%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1984</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.38%</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom:1px solid #000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Summation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33,598</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,836</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.20%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,762</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.80%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="S5.SS3.SSS1.p3">
<bold>Age</bold>
</p><p id="S5.SS3.SSS1.p4">Among the total 33,569 effective prescriptions, 592 prescriptions for the 
<inline-formula><mml:math id="w6" alttext="\leq" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>&#8804;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>17 age group accounted for 1.8%, 3847 patients aged 18&#8211;34 accounted for 
11.4%, 6739 prescriptions for the 35&#8211;49 age group accounted for 20.0%, 11,846 
prescriptions for the 50&#8211;64 age group accounted for 35.2%, 7055 prescriptions 
for the 65&#8211;75 age group accounted for 21.0%, and in the <inline-formula><mml:math id="w7" alttext="&gt;" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>75 age group, 3519 
accounted for 10.5%. There was little difference between the male age ratio and 
the total age ratio.</p><p id="S5.SS3.SSS1.p5">
<bold>Primary diagnosis and age</bold>
</p><p id="S5.SS3.SSS1.p6"><bold>Insomnia and sleep disorders</bold>: There were 33,569 effective 
prescriptions, 12,684 of which were diagnosed as insomnia and sleep disorders, 
accounting for 37.7%. Among the samples diagnosed with insomnia and sleep 
disorders, 42.3% were men and 57.7% were women. Insomnia and sleep disorders 
accounted for 41.7% of the prescription statistics for men and 35.2% of the 
prescription statistics for females. Among the age groups with insomnia, 71.4% 
were over the age of 50. The 18&#8211;34 age group accounted for 8.2%, and the 35&#8211;49 
age group accounted for 19.8%. The <inline-formula><mml:math id="w8" alttext="\leq" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>&#8804;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>17-years age group accounted for 
0.5%.</p><p id="S5.SS3.SSS1.p7"><bold>Anxiety disorders</bold>: The total number of effective prescriptions 
was 33,569, 9910 of which were diagnosed as being anxiety disorders (29.4%). 
Among the sample of patients diagnosed with anxiety disorder, 34.3% were men and 
65.7% were women. Anxiety disorders accounted for 26.4% of prescriptions for 
men and 31.3% of prescriptions for women. Among all of the age groups, 64.1% 
were over the age of 50. The 18&#8211;34 age group accounted for 18.9%, and the 
35&#8211;49 age group accounted for 23.0%. The <inline-formula><mml:math id="w9" alttext="\leq" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>&#8804;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>17 age group accounted for 
1.4%.</p><p id="S5.SS3.SSS1.p8"><bold>Depression</bold>: Among the total effective prescriptions, 5620 were for a 
diagnosis of depression, accounting for 16.7%. In the sample of patients 
diagnosed with depression, men accounted for 35.1% and women for 64.9%. 
Depression accounted for 15.3% of the prescription statistics for men, 17.6% 
for women, 54.3% for those over 50 years of age, 20.4% of the 18&#8211;34 age group, 
20.6% of the 35&#8211;49 age group, and 4.7% for the <inline-formula><mml:math id="w10" alttext="\leq" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>&#8804;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>17 age group.</p></sec><sec id="S5.SS3.SSS2"><title>4.3.2 Drug Composition and Disease Distribution</title><p id="S5.SS3.SSS2.p1">The total effective prescriptions were 33,569, of which 8849 accounted for 
clonazepam tablets (26.3%), 9425 for lorazepam tablets (28.0%), 5284 for 
estazolam tablets (15.7%), 5179 for alprazolam tablets (15.4%) and 3303 
accounted for zopiclone tablets (9.8%). Furthermore, 3085 accounted for oxazepam 
tablets (9.2%), 70 for diazepam tablets (0.2%) and 11 for nitrazepam tablets. 
The proportion of estazolam and zopiclone tablets for insomnia and sleep 
disorders was higher, and the proportion of lorazepam tablets for anxiety was 
higher. See Table <xref rid="S5.T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="S5.T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.
</label><caption><p><bold>Statistical table of commonly used benzodiazepines and Z-drug 
prescriptions for diagnosis of diseases</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="border-top:1px solid #000;border-bottom:1px solid #000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug category</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety disorders</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insomnia, sleep disorders</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other diseases</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Summation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alprazolam Tablets</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.60%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.10%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5179</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxazepam Tablets</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.40%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.60%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.90%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.90%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3085</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estazolam Tablets</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.30%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.70%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5284</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clonazepam Tablets</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.30%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.30%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.20%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.20%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8849</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diazepam Tablets</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.60%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.20%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrazepam Tablets</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.10%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.40%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zopiclone Tablets</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.20%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3303</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom:1px solid #000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lorazepam Tablets</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.20%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.20%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9428</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="S5.SS3.SSS3"><title>4.3.3 Annual</title><p id="S5.SS3.SSS3.p1">Statistics show that from 2017, the proportion of second-class mental health in 
outpatient and emergency prescriptions rose slowly to 33.10% in 2021. The 
proportion of second-class mental health showed a slowly increasing trend year by 
year, and the number of second-class mental health also showed a slowly 
increasing trend each year as shown in Table <xref rid="S5.T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="S5.T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4.
</label><caption><p><bold>Statistical table of outpatient and emergency prescriptions and 
second-class mental prescriptions in specialized hospitals from 2017 to 2021</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="border-top:1px solid #000;border-bottom:1px solid #000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second-class mental prescriptions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient emergency treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106,134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">356,348</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.78%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97,023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">325,565</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.80%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109,745</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">360,212</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.47%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110,558</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">334,798</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.02%</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom:1px solid #000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">115,156</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">347,856</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.10%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="S5.SS3.SSS3.p2">A total of 33,598 valid prescriptions were sampled, 5480 of which had been 
issued in 2018 (16.4%), 6468 in 2019 (19.2%), 7749 in 2020 (23.1%), and 13,733 
were issued in 2021 (40.9%). For 2017, there were only 21 days of data due to a 
system update (see Table <xref rid="S5.T5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). The statistics indicated that the prescriptions of 
different age groups also showed an increasing trend year by year (see Fig. <xref rid="S5.F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="S5.F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.
</label><caption><p>
<bold>Summary of sample prescriptions for benzodiazepines and Z-drugs 
by age group from 2018 to 2021</bold>.
</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="S5.F2.g1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="2757-8038-26-1-38792-g2.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="S5.T5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5.
</label><caption><p><bold>Summary of sample prescriptions for 
benzodiazepines and Z-drugs by age group from 2018 to 2021</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="border-top:1px solid #000;border-bottom:1px solid #000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="w11" alttext="\leq" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>&#8804;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>17 years old</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8211;34 years old</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35&#8211;49 years old</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#8211;64 years old</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65&#8211;75 years old</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="w12" alttext="&gt;" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>75 years old</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">639</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1330</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1883</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">972</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">595</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">864</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1386</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2242</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1184</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">688</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">185</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1573</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2668</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1591</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">720</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">240</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1319</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2403</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4991</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3283</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1497</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom:1px solid #000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Summation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">590</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3834</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6692</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,784</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7030</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3500</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="S5.SS3.SSS4"><title>4.3.4 Prescribing Patterns between General and Psychiatric 
Hospitals</title><p id="S5.SS3.SSS4.p1">Significant differences in prescribing patterns were observed between hospitals 
and psychiatric hospitals, while the differences among psychiatric hospitals were 
not notable (see Table <xref rid="S5.T6" ref-type="table">6</xref>, Ref. [<xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="S5.T6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6.
</label><caption><p><bold>Percentage of prescriptions for benzodiazepines and Z-drugs in 
psychiatric hospitals and general hospitals&#8217; outpatient and emergency 
departments</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="border-top:1px solid #000;border-bottom:1px solid #000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of hospital</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average ratio of benzodiazepine and Z-drug prescriptions to total prescriptions in outpatient and emergency departments (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regional specialized psychiatric hospital</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.23%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.78%&#8211;33.10%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017&#8211;2021</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom:1px solid #000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Five large general hospitals in the 1990s</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.16%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32%&#8211;7%*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1997&#8211;2016</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*There are no significant differences in the follow-up [<xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="S5.SS3.SSS5"><title>4.3.5 Prescription Frequency and Monitoring Trends from 2017 to 
2021</title><p id="S5.SS3.SSS5.p1">From 2017 to 2021, prescription frequency data-based on patient IDs showed that 
the highest frequency was 27 times for 1 patient (see Table <xref rid="S5.T7" ref-type="table">7</xref>). Most 
prescriptions were for intermittent rather than long-term use, with fewer cases 
of repeated prescriptions for the same patient. This trend may be due to the new 
hospital system implemented after 2017, which included special monitoring and 
limitations on certain medications. Additionally, continuous monitoring and the 
regulation of prescriptions, as well as patient education on safe and rational 
medication use, remain a necessity.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="S5.T7" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 7.
</label><caption><p><bold>Prescription frequency statistics for patient name from 2017 to 
2021</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="border-top:1px solid #000;border-bottom:1px solid #000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effective percentage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumulative percentage</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="17" colspan="1">Effective</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,106</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3967</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">942</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">294</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom:1px solid #000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25,594</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec></sec><sec id="S6"><title>5. Discussion</title><sec id="S6.SS1"><title>5.1 Dosage </title><p id="S6.SS1.p1">There is growing concern about the potential for misuse/abuse, dependence, and 
addiction to BZD drugs, which are increasingly being prescribed in developed 
countries. Benzodiazepines were used in 16.6 million of 133.3 million outpatient 
visits, and in 1.9 million of 18.1 million emergency department visits from 2001 
to 2010 in the United States [<xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In 2018, more than 47 million BZD 
prescriptions, and more than 14 million Z-drugs prescriptions were written in the 
United States alone [<xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Long-term BZD prescriptions in Australia increased from 
4.4% in 2011 to 5.8% in 2015, with a relatively stable annual growth rate of 
+2.5% between 2015 and 2018 [<xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p id="S6.SS1.p2">There were more than 50 million health care consultations between 2011 and 2018 
[<xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The prescriptions of BZDs or Z-drugs in Ireland increased from 
11.9% in 2005 to 15.3% in 2015 [<xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. From January 2017 to December 2020, 1.442 
billion BZDs were dispensed across Canada [<xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p id="S6.SS1.p3">This study found that the annual DDDs of BZDs and Z-drugs showed an upward 
trend. Furthermore, the proportion of second-class psychiatric prescriptions in 
outpatient and emergency prescriptions rose slowly from 29.78% in 2017 to 
33.10% in 2021, and the proportion of second-class psychiatric prescriptions and 
the number of second-class psychiatric prescriptions showed a slowly increasing 
trend year by year.</p></sec><sec id="S6.SS2"><title>5.2 Age </title><p id="S6.SS2.p1">Expanding on these initial observations, BZDs were used by 16% of elderly 
patients in Australia&#8217;s 65-year-old population [<xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Older patients were 
six times more likely than younger patients to be on long-term BZD prescriptions. 
American adults aged 50 years and older were more likely than younger adults to 
use BZDs more frequently than prescribed [<xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], and 13.75% of elderly patients in 
the general hospitals of large cities in Germany were dependent on BZDs and 
Z-drugs [<xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. A study on the correlation between sleep status and frailty in 
Chinese adults aged 30&#8211;79 years found that insomnia disorder was associated with 
an increased proportion of frailty [<xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. This study showed that the prescriptions 
in different age groups also showed an increasing trend year by year, and the 
increasing trend was larger in 50&#8211;64 and 65&#8211;75-year-olds than in other age 
groups.</p></sec><sec id="S6.SS3"><title>5.3 Women</title><p id="S6.SS3.p1">A total of 38% of women aged <inline-formula><mml:math id="w13" alttext="&gt;" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>80 years of age in France used BZDs [<xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The 
10-year trends in the use of sleeping pills in Switzerland found that, overall, 
women, the elderly, and people with a history of anxiety and depression were more 
likely to take sleeping pills. Long-term BZD prescriptions are more common and 
last longer in older women in Australia [<xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Women in the United States are 
about twice as likely as men to be prescribed BZDs, according to a press release 
from the National Institutes of Health on 17 December 2014. The percentage of 
women using BZDs and Z-drugs in this study was 61.8%. Among them, 63.3% were 
women between 50 and 75 years old. The number of BZD and non-BZD prescription 
drug users is much higher in women than in men, based on gender, economic 
factors, and social and family roles.</p></sec><sec id="S6.SS4"><title>5.4 Disease</title><p id="S6.SS4.p1">Considering the above demographic trends, BZDs are the main therapeutic drugs 
for patients with anxiety, insomnia, and epilepsy, and also serve as important 
adjunctive drugs for patients with specific physical and severe mental diseases 
to improve insomnia, anxiety, agitation, and other symptoms. In this study, the 
main disease factors for using BZDs and Z-drugs were anxiety disorder (24.3%), 
insomnia (41.30%), and sleep disorder (17.2%). Statistics showed that the main 
disease factors of BZDs and Z-drugs were also different in different age groups. 
Insomnia and sleep disorders accounted for 71.4%, and anxiety disorders 
accounted for 64.1% of people over 50 years old. Among the 35&#8211;49 age group, 
19.8% had insomnia or sleep disorders, 23.0% had anxiety disorders, and among 
the 18&#8211;34 age group, 8.2% had insomnia or sleep disorders and 18.9% had 
anxiety disorders.</p></sec><sec id="S6.SS5"><title>5.5 Adverse Reactions</title><p id="S6.SS5.p1">With these clinical implications in mind, various adverse events caused by or 
related to the use of BZDs and Z-drugs have been widely reported [<xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. 
Furthermore, there is an increased likelihood of falls and delirium associated 
with the long-term use of BZDs in older adults [<xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and an increased risk of 
cognitive decline, fractures, and episodes of drug dependence in older patients 
[<xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Benzodiazepine users aged 85 and older fall more frequently [<xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="S6.SS6"><title>5.6 The Non-Medical Use of BZDs and Z-Drugs has the Potential for 
Addiction and Dependence</title><p id="S6.SS6.p1">These drugs are controlled under various international drug control treaties, 
according to the Global Drug Report 2018 of the United Nations Office on Drugs 
and Crime [<xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Benzodiazepines are the most commonly abused type of prescription 
drug for non-medical use and have become a growing problem. The non-medical use 
of BZDs is the most prevalent in the UK among illegal stimulants [<xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. 
Non-medical use, including BZDs, is also growing in the Asia&#8211;Pacific region, 
including China [<xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Appropriate interventions are needed to address 
prescription drug abuse, including BZDs.</p></sec><sec id="S6.SS7"><title>5.7 Pandemic</title><p id="S6.SS7.p1">This study includes data before and up to approximately two years following the 
onset of the COVID-19 pandemic. The pandemic may have impacted the study, 
especially since these medications treat many mental health conditions that were 
exacerbated by the psychosocial effects of the pandemic. The authors analysed the 
data, and the histogram from the prescription showed no differences in 2020 
compared with 2019 and a small difference in 2021 compared with 2020.</p></sec><sec id="S6.SS8"><title>5.8 Importance</title><p id="S6.SS8.p1">In synthesising the insights provided by the current research results, this 
study provides critical insights into the prescribing trends of BZDs and Z-drugs 
in China, revealing significant increases in usage that bear implications for 
both clinical practice and public health. Our findings highlight a substantial 
reliance on these medications, particularly among elderly populations, 
underscoring an urgent need for policy interventions. By documenting demographic 
and drug-specific trends, this research contributes to a better understanding of 
the potential risks associated with long-term use, including dependency and 
adverse effects. The data serves as a foundation for developing targeted 
guidelines that can enhance patient safety and optimise prescribing practices. 
This is crucial in settings where ageing populations are particularly vulnerable, 
and where there is a need to balance therapeutic benefits against the risks of 
harm.</p></sec><sec id="S6.SS9"><title>5.9 Conformance with Zhejiang Provincial Hospital&#8217;s Guidelines</title><p id="S6.SS9.p1">Our study aimed to evaluate the prescription patterns of benzodiazepines (BZDs) 
and their alignment with the Zhejiang Provincial Hospital&#8217;s guidelines. The 
findings indicate that prescribed dosages, such as 5 mg/day for diazepam and 1.5 
mg/day for lorazepam, were within recommended ranges. Diagnoses primarily 
included anxiety disorders and insomnia, consistent with the hospital&#8217;s criteria. 
Additionally, 80% of BZD prescriptions adhered to the short-term use guideline 
of 4&#8211;6 weeks, with exceptions clearly documented. These results demonstrate a 
high degree of conformity with the hospital&#8217;s guidelines, reflecting cautious and 
appropriate prescribing practices. Overall, our data underscore the effectiveness 
of these guidelines in ensuring the safe and appropriate use of BZDs, with 
dosages, diagnoses, and treatment durations generally meeting the recommended 
standards.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S7"><title>6. Limitations of this Study</title><p id="S7.p1">This study has a few limitations. The retrospective design may include some data 
inaccuracies, despite our efforts to ensure accuracy. The geographic focus on 
Zhejiang, Jiangsu, and Shanghai limits generalizability to other regions. 
Additionally, excluding over-the-counter and private clinic prescriptions might 
underestimate overall drug use. Lastly, the study period from 2015 to 2021 does 
not capture longer-term trends. Future research should address these areas to 
provide a more comprehensive view. Despite these limitations, our findings offer 
valuable insights into BZD and Z-drug prescription trends in Eastern China.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>7. Conclusions</title><p id="S8.p1">The use of addictive BZDs and non-BZDs showed an increasing trend year by year, 
and the use of addictive BZDs and non-BZDs showed an increasing trend in age. The 
elderly population, notably, the elderly female population, had a higher 
proportion of drug use; accordingly, drug safety measures for this population 
require more attention.</p><p id="S8.p2">Extrapolation: Management of the rational and safe drug use of BZDs and non-BZDs 
should be strengthened to reduce the safety risks caused by long-term irrational 
use. Targeted interventions are needed to reduce the potentially inappropriate 
long-term prescription and use of these drugs.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="S9"><title>Availability of Data and Materials</title><p id="S9.p1">The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="S12"><title>Acknowledgment</title><p id="S12.p1">We would like to thank for Xianzhi Chen who contributed to data statistics and 
English writing.</p></ack><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#8217;s Note:</bold>
IMR Press stays neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional
affiliations.
</p></fn></fn-group><sec id="S10"><title>Author Contributions</title><p id="S10.p1">Conception&#8212;QD, HLC; Design&#8212;QD, HLC; Supervision&#8212;HLC; Data Collection and/or 
Processing&#8212;HLC; Analysis and/or Interpretation&#8212;HLC; Writing&#8212;QD; Critical 
Review&#8212;QD, HLC. All authors read and approved the final manuscript. All authors 
have participated sufficiently in the work and agreed to be accountable for all 
aspects of the work.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Ethics Approval and Consent to Participate</title><p id="S11.p1">This is an observational study with a retrospective prescription analysis. 
Study trends in prescription drug use. This project has been exempted by the local ethics committee. 
All prescriptions are the result of routine medical practice under strict supervision and in accordance with medical ethics. 
No human or animal studies were conducted in this study.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Funding</title><p id="S13.p1">This research received no external funding.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="S14"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p id="S14.p1">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><label>[1]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodchild</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GABA receptors and benzodiazepines</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">British Journal of Anaesthesia</italic></source><year>1993</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bja/71.1.127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8393687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><label>[2]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liebrenz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buadze</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gehring</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dube</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caflisch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-Dose Benzodiazepine Dependence: A Qualitative Study of Patients&#8217; Perceptions on Initiation, Reasons for Use, and Obtainment</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">PloS One</italic></source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0142057</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0142057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26556055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4640837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><label>[3]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jembrek</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vlainic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GABA Receptors: Pharmacological Potential and Pitfalls</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Current Pharmaceutical Design</italic></source><year>2015</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>4943</fpage><lpage>4959</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1381612821666150914121624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26365137</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><label>[4]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abuse of z-drugs and its challenges to the society</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Medical Toxicology &amp; Legal Medicine</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5958/0974-4614.2020.00029.7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><label>[5]</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Drug Report 2018</collab></person-group><year>2018</year><comment>Available at:
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.unodc.org/wdr2018" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.unodc.org/wdr2018</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation content-type="access-date" iso-8601-date="2022-11-07">(Accessed: 7 November 2022)</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><label>[6]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luka&#269;i&#353;inov&#225;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fialov&#225;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peel</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brkic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Onder</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>The prevalence and prescribing patterns of benzodiazepines and Z-drugs in older nursing home residents in different European countries and Israel: retrospective results from the EU SHELTER study</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Geriatrics</italic></source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>277</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12877-021-02213-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33902474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8077828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><label>[7]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres-Bondia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Batlle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galv&#225;n</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barb&#233;</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pi&#241;ol-Ripoll</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trends in the consumption rates of benzodiazepines and benzodiazepine-related drugs in the health region of Lleida from 2002 to 2015</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Public Health</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>818</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-020-08984-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32487058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7268471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><label>[8]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#233;rardin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rousselet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caillet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grall-Bronnec</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lou&#233;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jolliet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>French national health insurance database analysis and field study focusing on the impact of secure prescription pads on zolpidem consumption and sedative drug misuse: ZORRO study protocol</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ Open</italic></source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e027443</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2018-027443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6609064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31256026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><label>[9]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Compton</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and Correlates of Benzodiazepine Use, Misuse, and Use Disorders Among Adults in the United States</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">The Journal of Clinical Psychiatry</italic></source><year>2018</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>12174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4088/JCP.18m12174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10309967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30403446</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><label>[10]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>ZW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Research progress on current situation and preventive measures for the narcotic and psychotropic drugs abuse in the elderly</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Zhonghua Liu Xing Bing Xue Za Zhi</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3760/cma.j.cn112338-20190723-00542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32344492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><label>[11]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of pharmaceutical consumption between urban and suburban catchments in China by wastewater-based epidemiology</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Environmental Research</italic></source><year>2024</year><volume>250</volume><fpage>118544</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2024.118544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38408630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><label>[12]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of the use of benzodiazepines in prescriptions from the outpatient department of the General Hospital of the People&#8217;s Liberation Army</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Epidemiology of Medicines</italic></source><year>1997</year><volume>4</volume><comment>(In Chinese)</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><label>[13]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marra</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazer-Amirshahi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Anker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>May</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pines</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Benzodiazepine Prescribing in Older Adults in U.S. Ambulatory Clinics and Emergency Departments (2001-10)</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of the American Geriatrics Society</italic></source><year>2015</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>2074</fpage><lpage>2081</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgs.13666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26415836</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><label>[14]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonnet</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McAnally</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How prevalent and severe is addiction on GABAmimetic drugs in an elderly German general hospital population? Focus on gabapentinoids, benzodiazepines, and z-hypnotic drugs</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Human Psychopharmacology</italic></source><year>2022</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>e2822</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hup.2822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34687489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><label>[15]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Begum</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez-Chica</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernardo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stocks</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term benzodiazepines and z-drug prescribing in Australian general practice between 2011 and 2018: A national study</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Pharmacology Research &amp; Perspectives</italic></source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e00896</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/prp2.896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34918876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8929365</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><label>[16]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez-Chica</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Begum</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernardo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sweetman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stocks</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trends and patterns of benzodiazepines and Z-drugs prescriptions in Australian general practice: A national study (2011-2018)</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Drug and Alcohol Review</italic></source><year>2023</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/dar.13561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36217261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10092554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><label>[17]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cadogan</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cahir</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Benzodiazepine and Z-drug prescribing in Ireland: analysis of national prescribing trends from 2005 to 2015</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</italic></source><year>2018</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1354</fpage><lpage>1363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bcp.13570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29488252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5980334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><label>[18]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uthayakumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tadrous</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vigod</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitchen</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of COVID-19 on the dispensing rates of antidepressants and benzodiazepines in Canada</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Depression and Anxiety</italic></source><year>2022</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/da.23228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34843627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9015529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><label>[19]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Windle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elliot</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duszynski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Benzodiazepine prescribing in elderly Australian general practice patients</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Australian and New Zealand Journal of Public Health</italic></source><year>2007</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1753-6405.2007.00091.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17725021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><label>[20]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lefebvre-Durel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailly</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunault</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jovic</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Novic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vorspan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Benzodiazepine and Z drug cessation in elderly patients: A qualitative study on the perception of healthcare providers and the place of advanced practice nurses</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Mental Health Nursing</italic></source><year>2021</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>653</fpage><lpage>666</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/inm.12831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33314689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><label>[21]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Benzodiazepines and Z-Drugs: An Updated Review of Major Adverse Outcomes Reported on in Epidemiologic Research</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Drugs in R&amp;D</italic></source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>493</fpage><lpage>507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40268-017-0207-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28865038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5694420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><label>[22]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Necessary evil or systemic failure of care? Use of benzodiazepine and antipsychotic medications in older people seeking emergency department care</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of the American Geriatrics Society</italic></source><year>2022</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>698</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgs.17664</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35080008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><label>[23]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olfson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenbaum</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Benzodiazepine use in the United States</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Psychiatry</italic></source><year>2015</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2014.1763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25517224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><label>[24]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hockenhull</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rockhill</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dargan</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dart</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Nonmedical use of benzodiazepines and Z-drugs in the UK</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</italic></source><year>2021</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>1676</fpage><lpage>1683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bcp.14397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32472941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><label>[25]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dargan</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prescription medicine misuse in the Asia-Pacific region: An evolving issue?</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</italic></source><year>2021</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>1660</fpage><lpage>1667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bcp.14638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33140471</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>