<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Epidemiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur J Epidemiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">365</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">springeropen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>European Journal of Epidemiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0393-2990</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1573-7284</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Springer</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12018500</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12018500.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12018500</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12018500</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39869239</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10654-025-01202-3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1202</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Cohort Profile</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cohort profile: the provincial opioid agonist treatment cohort in Ontario, Canada</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morin</surname><given-names initials="KA">Kristen A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tatangelo</surname><given-names initials="MR">Mark R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names initials="S">Shreedhar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8769-1785</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names initials="DC">David C.</given-names></name><address><email>dmarsh@nosm.ca</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04br0rs05</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.420638.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9741 4533</institution-id><institution>Health Sciences North Research Institute, </institution></institution-wrap>Sudbury, ON Canada </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>ICES North (Institute for Clinical and Evaluative Sciences), Sudbury, ON Canada </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05yb43k62</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.436533.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8658 0974</institution-id><institution>Northern Ontario School of Medicine University, </institution></institution-wrap>Sudbury, ON P3E 2C6 Canada </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>40</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">487129</issue-id><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>27</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>25</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-04-25 00:25:23.703"><day>25</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10654_2025_Article_1202.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Opioid Agonist Treatment (OAT) is the most effective intervention for opioid use disorder (OUD), but retention has decreased due to increasingly potent drugs like fentanyl. This cohort can be used retrospectively to observe trends in service utilization, healthcare integration, healthcare costs and patient outcomes. It also facilitates the design of observational studies to mimic a prospective design.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">This study used linked administrative data from ICES to create a cohort of 137,035 individuals who received at least one prescription of methadone or buprenorphine/naloxone between 2014 and 2022. Data were linked using de-identified personal health numbers. Variables included age, sex, rurality, income, homelessness, and mental health conditions. Regional differences in OAT use, retention, and mortality were analyzed.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Of the cohort, 56.1% began OAT after 2014. Southern Ontario participants more often started on methadone (53.2%), while Northern Ontario patients favored buprenorphine/naloxone (62.7%). Northern patients were younger, more likely to be female, live in rural areas, and face homelessness. The death rate was higher in Southern Ontario (22.1%) than in Northern Ontario (13.2%). Retention declined over time, with 73.4% of patients remaining in treatment at the study's end.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">The findings highlight regional disparities in OAT delivery and emphasize the need for region-specific strategies, particularly in rural areas, to improve retention and reduce mortality.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Observational cohort study</kwd><kwd>Opioid agonist treatment</kwd><kwd>Addiction medicine</kwd><kwd>Longitudinal study</kwd><kwd>Administrative data</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100011251</institution-id><institution>Northern Ontario Academic Medicine Association</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>A-21-10</award-id><award-id>A-21-8</award-id><award-id>C-12-19</award-id><award-id>RR-20-03</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>David C.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; Pietro Paolo Sanna 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Study Setting</title><p id="Par5">Opioid use is a significant public health issue linked to morbidity and mortality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Between 2016 and 2023, Canada faced a severe public health crisis with over 40,000 deaths attributable to the toxic drug supply [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Ontario alone accounted for approximately 25% of these fatalities, with 10,900 deaths reported during this period. Northern Ontario, despite representing less than 10% of the population, experienced about 15% of these deaths, totaling 1411 fatalities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. These regional disparities underscore a troubling trend: areas with smaller populations are experiencing disproportionately high numbers of drug-related deaths [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">People who use opioids (PWUO) experience co-occurring mental disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], and chronic illnesses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], compounded by elevated rates of poverty [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] and homelessness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Despite the issues they face, PWUO encounter significant issues accessing care. As a result, emergency departments (ED) are critical in managing complications related to substance use, often serving as the primary point of contact for individuals in crisis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The high demand for ED services not only contributes to a significant number of costly visits but leads to longer wait times for other medical conditions, exacerbating the overall strain on healthcare resources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">Opioid Agonist Treatment (OAT) is the intervention with the best evidence for OUD. Studies have found that low coverage of OAT leads to higher rates of deaths and overdoses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Moreover, population-level treatment retention has been decreasing due to the potency of the drug supply [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] inhibiting the effectiveness of OAT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Understanding OAT in the era of fentanyl is crucial to continue to improve the system of care for PWUO and to reduce deaths.</p><p id="Par8">Despite the large body of research on people with PWUO, there are limited RCTs and population-level studies to address the high morbidity and mortality unique to the era of fentanyl and its analogs. PWUO are unlikely to participate in conventional randomized control trials (RCT) or complete population-level surveys [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Using observational data fills this gap and allows researchers to replicate the structure of RCTs at a population level. This entails establishing eligibility criteria according to data available at baseline and carefully defining treatment strategies. The emulation of an RCT yields the same effect estimates (except for random variability) as target trials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">This cohort can be used retrospectively to observe trends in service utilization, healthcare integration, healthcare costs and patient outcomes. It also facilitates the design of observational studies to mimic a prospective design. Our approach, built on health administrative database linkages, can deliver exceptional value, with greater external validity than a randomized controlled trial at a fraction of the cost. Additionally, it serves as the groundwork for evaluative studies concerning the costs and benefits of OAT across all regions of Ontario. Our OUD cohort, therefore, presents a pivotal opportunity to assess the impact of these healthcare system changes amidst an unprecedented public health emergency. We secured funding for this cohort from the Northern Ontario Academic Medicine Association (NOAMA) (10). In addition to health care services use, researchers may also use these data using analytic tools that provide more sensitive instruments to detect treatment differences among patients with OUD.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Data collection</title><p id="Par10">The Provincial Opioid Agonist Treatment Cohort in Ontario, Canada was established in 2019 to evaluate treatment and health service outcomes for people with OUD who are engaged in OAT. This cohort is built using linked population-level administrative databases in ICES. ICES is an independent, non-profit organization, that extracts health informatics for population-wide health outcomes research in Ontario, Canada [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. We have on hand several linked provincial databases which include all Ontario residents with an indication of OUD from 01/01/2012 to 08/30/2023 (n&#8201;=&#8201;137,035). ICES has deterministically linked the databases on an individual level using a de-identified personal health number.</p><p id="Par11">In Ontario Canada, a single universal payer of health care system, the Ontario Health Insurance Plan (OHIP) records all health care records in a central secure repository as the payer of health care services<sup>37</sup>. The Discharge Abstract Database (DAD) measuring hospital discharge data<sup>36</sup>, the Narcotics Monitoring System database with all narcotic prescriptions<sup>38</sup> the National Ambulatory Care Reporting System (NACRS)<sup>39</sup> and the Registered Persons (RPDB) database containing vital statistics updated at each health card renewal (every 5 years or each address change) were provided to the study team by ICES. The datasets were deterministically linked based on unique personal health numbers used to record event-level data within the health care system which are recorded in each database. In addition to these datasets, derived standardized tools are available including validated comorbidity instruments for many chronic and acute conditions (citations), standardized health care costing instruments (citation), and socioeconomic data derived from area level census data including the Ontario Marginalization Index, Index of Rurality, and neighborhood income quintile [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Baseline measures</title><p id="Par12">Covariates include demographic and clinical variables. Demographic information included: age, biological sex assigned at birth (male or female), geographical location, rurality, index of remoteness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] and rurality index of Ontario [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]income, and homelessness. Geographical locations as defined by Local Health Integration Network (LHIN) (15). LHINs are regional health authorities responsible for regional administration of public healthcare services in Ontario. Ontario had 14 LHINs which provided hospital and community-based care to all residents within their geographical boundaries, Northern geographic indicators were defined patient residence in LHIN 13 or 14 (15).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Health service use and comorbidities</title><p id="Par13">The DAD contains information on all admitted patient services at all hospitals and the NACRS contains information on all ambulatory care in hospitals including the ED.<sup>42</sup>For acute care, the resource intensity weight, comorbidity code, and the Case Mix Group Plus code<sup>43,44</sup>enable researchers to estimate daily costs per hospital stay or ED visit. The Narcotics Monitoring System (NMS) database includes information on narcotic medications dispensed by the pharmacies in the province; it provides a unique opportunity to estimate the province-wide spending on prescription medications for SUD and co-existing conditions. The NOSM The Ontario Health Insurance Plan (OHIP) database contains information on all billable physician services and diagnosis codes enabling the account of any physician-based service as an outcome or exposure in our models. With these linked databases we can consider key comorbidities among PWOUD including mental disorders, co-occurring substance use disorders, physical comorbidities and infections. We can also a patient&#8217;s health service use journey across the continuum of health services including primary care and psychiatry visits, ED and hospitalizations related and unrelated to substance use.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>OAT prescriber characteristics</title><p id="Par14">The characteristics of OAT prescribers include age, sex, and graduation year. Additionally, whether the prescriber completed their education within Canada, the location of practice and practice size, specialty and if that physician is practicing in a rural or urban area.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Longitudinal follow-up measures</title><p id="Par15">Key measures of longitudinal follow-up of OAT indicators include OAT medication (methadone, buprenorphine/naloxone, extended-release oral morphine or extended-release subcutaneous buprenorphine). The longitudinal follow-up allows for the identification and quantification of OAT services over time, providing critical time-to-event data for patient outcomes with validity and reliability. Study follow-up is observational from clinical interactions; therefore, patients are considered lost to follow-up if they discontinue treatment or die defined as: no clinical visits within 1-year of the last clinical visit. The days of patient follow-up was 1465.84 (1006.45) measured from the initial OAT contact to the conclusion of the study follow-up Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Cohort demographics and OAT engagement</title><p id="Par16">A total of 137,035 people had at least one prescription of methadone or buprenorphine/naloxone in Ontario between 2014 and 2022. 60,140 (43.9%) people started on OAT before 2014 and were still retained in treatment at the end of our follow-up and 76,890 (56.1%) started on OAT after 2014 (incident new user cohort). Of the incident new users, 64,479 (83.4%) resided in Southern Ontario and 12,813 (16.6%) in Northern Ontario. 34,370 (53.2%) of people living in Southern Ontario started on Methadone in their initial OAT episode and 28,647 (46.8%) on Buprenorphine/naloxone. 4573 (37.3%) of people living in Southern Ontario started on Methadone in their initial OAT episode and 7355 (62.7%) on Buprenorphine/naloxone. Results are presented in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Distribution of OAT patients in Ontario</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10654_2025_1202_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par17">The mean age of patients in Southern Ontario was 43.75 (SD = 17.65) compared to 37.41 (SD = 14.38) in Northern Ontario. Females comprised 38.2% of the cohort for Southern Ontario and 44.3% in Northern Ontario. Geographic representation varied significantly, with Erie St. Clair (10.3%) and Hamilton Niagara Hamilton and Brant (14.0%) having the highest number of people on OAT in the province. Rurality was also significantly different, with 52.2% of Northern Ontario patients living in rural areas compared to 10.9% in Southern Ontario. Overall, 26.6% of patients&#160;reported being homeless, and the death rate was higher in Southern Ontario (22.1%) compared to Northern Ontario (13.2%). The cohort experienced a 6.0% loss to follow-up, with 73.4% still retained at the end of the study period. The results are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic characteristics in the calendar year of cohort entry</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ontario Total</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Southern Ontario</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Northern Ontario</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SMD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N = 76,890</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N = 64,623 (84.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N = 12,267 (16.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77,292</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64,479 (83.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,813 (16.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (mean (SD))</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.7 (17.32)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.75 (17.65)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.41 (14.38)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Sex (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.182</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;F</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30,327 (39.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24,652 (38.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5675 (44.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;M</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46,338 (60.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39,200 (60.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7138 (55.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;X</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">627 (0.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">627 (1.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Location of residence (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.751</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Erie St. Clair</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7687 (10.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7687 (12.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;South West</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5885 (7.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5885 (9.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Waterloo Wellington</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3710 (5.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3710 (6.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hamilton Niagara Hamilton and Brant</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,453 (14.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,453 (16.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Central West</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3117 (4.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3117 (5.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Mississauga</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3292 (4.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3292 (5.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Toronto Central</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4577 (6.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4577 (7.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Central</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4542 (6.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4542 (7.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Central East</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7068 (9.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7068 (11.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;South East</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3448 (4.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3448 (5.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Champlain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4762 (6.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4762 (7.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;North Simcoe Muskoka</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3156 (4.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3156 (5.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;North East</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6957 (9.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6957 (54.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;North West</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5856 (7.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5856 (45.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Income quintile (mean (SD))</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.46 (1.49)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.53 (1.48)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.13 (1.45)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.272</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Rural (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0/925</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61,332 (79.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54,644 (84.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6688 (52.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,163 (17.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7038 (10.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6125 (47.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">missing</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66,803 (82.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59,632 (87.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7171 (54.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rurality Index of Ontario (mean (SD))</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.67 (18.46)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.73 (14.11)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.43 (30.67)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Index of Remoteness (mean (SD))</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15 (0.16)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.10 (0.07)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.43 (0.19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.342</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Homeless (mean (SD))</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20,593 (26.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17,216 (26.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3377 (26.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.008</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Death (mean (SD))</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,958 (20.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,267 (22.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1691 (13.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.238</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lost to follow up (mean (SD))</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4634 (6.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3999 (6.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">635 (5.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.024</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Still retained at the end of study period (mean (SD))</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56,700 (73.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46,213 (71.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,487 (81.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.228</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*n = number</p><p>*mean = mean per year</p><p>*SD = standard deviation</p><p>*SMD = standardized mean difference</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par18">Overall, 42.1% of patients were on buprenorphine/naloxone as a first-time medication, with a statistically significantly higher proportion in Northern Ontario (57.0%) compared to Southern Ontario (39.1%). Methadone was prescribed to 44.8% of the cohort as a first time OAT, with statistically significantly higher use in Southern Ontario (46.6%) compared to Northern Ontario (35.7%). The mean days retained during the first OAT attempt was 166.04 days (SD 297.25), with Northern Ontario exhibiting lower retention (133.77 days) compared to Southern Ontario (172.45 days). Buprenorphine/naloxone retention was significantly higher in Northern Ontario (206.57 days) than in Southern Ontario (94.25 days). For methadone, Southern Ontario saw longer retention (243.05 days) compared to Northern Ontario (173.35 days).</p><p id="Par19">The mean follow-up time across the cohort was 1465.84 days (SD 1006.45), with Northern Ontario patients followed for longer periods (1671.75 days) than those in Southern Ontario (1424.93 days). The percent of days covered (PDC) was similar across regions, with a mean of 48.47% (SD 36.49), slightly higher in Southern Ontario (48.86%) than in Northern Ontario (46.50%). Buprenorphine/naloxone PDC was higher in Northern Ontario (448.90 days) than in Southern Ontario (262.35 days), with an SMD of 0.301. Methadone PDC was greater in Southern Ontario (243.17 days) than in Northern Ontario (153.95 days). The results are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>OAT, comorbidities and health service use among cohort patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ontario total</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Southern Ontario</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Northern Ontario</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SMD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N = 76,890</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n = 64,623 (84.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n = 12,267 (16.0%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">OAT starting medications, <italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.400</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Buprenorphine/naloxone</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36,002 (42.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28,647 (45.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7355 (61.9)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Methadone</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38,943 (44.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34,370 (54.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4573 (38.1)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1945</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1606</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">339</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Frist OAT Attempt days retained, <italic toggle="yes">mean (SD)</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">166.04 (297.25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">172.45 (301.37)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">133.77 (273.32)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.134</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Buprenorphine/naloxone</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">112.87 (248.91)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94.25 (208.07)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">206.57 (381.24)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.366</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Methadone</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">231.50 (416.64)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">243.05 (428.96)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">173.35 (342.28)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Follow up time in days<italic toggle="yes">, mean (SD)</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1465.84 (1006.45)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1424.93 (1008.08)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1671.75 (972.49)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.249</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Percent of days covered, <italic toggle="yes">mean (SD)</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.47 (36.49)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.86 (36.48)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.50 (36.51)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.070</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Buprenorphine/naloxone</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">293.28 (574.14)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">262.35 (543.01)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">448.90 (689.66)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.301</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Methadone</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">228.38 (396.97)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">243.17 (410.86)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">153.95 (307.35)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.246</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mental Disorder <italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34,051 (68.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29,458 (70.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4593 (54.4)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.343</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Schizophrenia <italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4305 (5.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3688 (5.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">617 (5.0)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.035</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bipolar disorder <italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3987 (8.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3525 (8.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">462 (5.5)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.336</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alcohol Use Disorder, <italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6879 (9.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5353 (8.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1526 (12.7)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.144</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chronic Pain n (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56,657 (73.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48,430 (75.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8227 (64.2)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.239</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HIV n (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">606 (0.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">505 (0.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101 (0.8)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.016</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">All -cause ED visits</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">12.82 (35.11)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">12.65 (35.41)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">13.71 (33.45)</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.031</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">mean per patient per year (SD)</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mental Health and Substance-related ED visits</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">8.53 (16.36)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">8.25 (16.38)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">10.00 (16.17)</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.107</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">mean per patient per year (SD)</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">All cause Hospital admissions</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.38 (2.93)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.35 (2.90)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.53 (3.10)</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.060</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">mean per patient per year (SD)</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mental Health and Substance-related Hospital Admissions</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.27 (2.91)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.24 (2.88)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.43 (3.06)</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.065</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">mean per patient per year (SD)</italic></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*n = number</p><p>*mean = mean per year</p><p>*SD = standard deviation</p><p>*SMD = standardized mean difference</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par20">The prevalence of mental health disorders varied significantly between the regions. Overall, 70.8% of people living in Southern Ontario had a diagnosed mental disorder and 54.4% in northern Ontario. 5.6% were diagnosed with schizophrenia, with a slightly higher proportion in Southern Ontario (5.7%) compared to Northern Ontario (5.0%). Bipolar disorder was reported in 3987 people (8.0%), notably more prevalent in Southern Ontario (8.5%) than in Northern Ontario (5.5%). Alcohol use disorder was present in 6879 (9.0%) with differences across both regions (8.3% in Southern Ontario and 12.7% in Northern Ontario). Chronic pain was more common in Southern Ontario 75.1% than Northern Ontario 64.2%. 0.8% of the cohort is diagnosed with HIV and there were no regional differences. The mean all-cause emergency department (ED) visits per patient per year was 12.65 (standard deviation (SD) 35.41) in Southern Ontario versus 13.71 (33.45) in Northern Ontario. The mean ED visits per patient per year for reasons mental health and substance use was 8.25 (SD 16.38) in Southern Ontario and 10.00 (SD 16.71) in Northern Ontario. The mean of all-cause hospital admissions per patient per year was 1.35 (SD 2.90) in Southern Ontario and 1.53 (SD 3.10) in Northern Ontario. The mean hospital admissions per patient per year for reasons mental health and substance use was 1.24 (SD 2.88) in Southern Ontario and 1.43 (SD 3.06) in Northern Ontario. Results are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.</p><sec id="Sec8"><title>OAT engagement in Ontario</title><p id="Par21">The majority (56.1%) of people in OAT began treatment after 2014, however, a substantial proportion (43.9%) were long-term users who started before 2014 and remained in treatment throughout the follow-up period. We also found that in Southern Ontario, methadone was the more common initial treatment, with 53.2% starting on it. Conversely, Northern Ontario buprenorphine/naloxone was the more common starting medication (62.7%). These differences may reflect varying prescribing practices, healthcare access, or patient preferences across regions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Demographic differences in Ontario</title><p id="Par22">The data highlights key demographic, geographic, and socioeconomic differences between OAT patients in Northern and Southern Ontario. The patients in the North were significantly younger, with a slightly higher proportion of females in Northern Ontario (44.3%), had a lower average quintile and live in rural and remote all factors creating additional barriers to healthcare access. Homelessness affected 26.6% of the cohort, which reflects a vulnerable population in need of integrated social and healthcare services. Our cohort demonstrates significant geographic, demographic, and socioeconomic disparities between Northern and Southern Ontario, highlighting the need for region-specific approaches to OAT delivery, particularly in rural and remote areas (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Cohort follow-up</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10654_2025_1202_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>OAT retention</title><p id="Par23">We found that the probability of OAT retention at 30 the day mark in this cohort is approximately 50%, at 90 days it&#8217;s about 45 and at one year, it&#8217;s approximately 25%. Results are displayed in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>.<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Probability of patient retention in days</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10654_2025_1202_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Strengths and limitations</title><p id="Par24">The main strengths are event-level data for patient medication use, health care services resource use and physician and geographic variation in practice patterns at a population-level across different regions of Ontario. The use of multiple health administrative databases linked through unique identifiers provides a comprehensive view of individuals' healthcare utilization. Such linkage enables a detailed analysis of health service use and treatment patterns. The cohort allows for observational studies that mimic randomized controlled trials (RCTs) at a population level. By using existing data and applying careful eligibility criteria and treatment definitions, researchers can assess the effectiveness of interventions and healthcare system changes in a real-world setting. The cohort covers both Southern and Northern Ontario, offering insights into regional disparities in healthcare access and treatment. The north-south comparison in Ontario is particularly valuable for other jurisdictions because southern Ontario has a high concentration of densely populated urban areas, while northern Ontario is characterized by less populated and more rural regions. These distinctions are crucial for countries with a mix of highly dense urban centers and lower-density rural areas, as they highlight how OAT access, delivery, and outcomes may vary depending on population density and geographic context. The inclusion of socioeconomic data, allows for a nuanced understanding of how socio-economic factors impact treatment outcomes and healthcare utilization.</p><p id="Par25">While the cohort provides detailed data for Ontario, the findings may not be directly generalizable to other regions with different healthcare systems or population characteristics. Additionally, although the observational approach can emulate RCTs, it still has limitations such as potential biases in treatment allocation and confounding factors that are not always fully controlled. The reliance on existing data may also limit the ability to address all potential variables influencing outcomes. The accuracy of the results also depends on the completeness and correctness of the data within the administrative databases. While the cohort covers diverse regions, the concentration of OAT services and interventions in Southern and urban areas may result in less detailed information about rural and Northern regions. This uneven distribution could affect the interpretation of findings. The cohort&#8217;s reliance on administrative data may limit the depth of understanding of patient experiences.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Collaboration and data sharing</title><p id="Par26">The dataset from this study is held securely in coded form at ICES. While legal data sharing agreements between ICES and data providers (e.g., healthcare organizations and government) prohibit ICES from making the dataset publicly available, access may be granted to those who meet pre-specified criteria for confidential access, available at www.ices.on.ca/DAS (email: das@ices.on.ca). The full dataset creation plan and underlying analytic code are available from the authors upon request, understanding that the computer programs may rely upon coding templates or macros that are unique to ICES and are therefore either inaccessible or may require modification.&#160;Any inquiries or clarifications regarding the project&#160;can be directed via email to Dr. David Marsh at dmarsh@nosm.ca.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par27">The OAT cohort in Ontario, Canada, provides valuable insights into OAT at a population level. It is a unique resource for evaluating health system patterns and outcomes for PWOUD over time. With a set of clinical, social, and demographic variables, the cohort allows for a comprehensive evaluation of various exposures and outcomes, making it a high-priority area of interest in the field of health and social policy and services at all levels of government.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>We thank the Marsh research lab as well as our funders. This study was supported by ICES, which is funded by an annual grant from the Ontario Ministry of Health (MOH) and the Ministry of Long-Term Care (MLTC). This study also received funding from: Northern Ontario Medicine Associaion (NOAMA). This document used data adapted from the Statistics Canada Postal CodeOM Conversion File, which is based on data licensed from Canada Post Corporation, and/or data adapted from the Ontario Ministry of Health Postal Code Conversion File, which contains data copied under license from &#169;Canada Post Corporation and Statistics Canada. Parts of this material are based on data and/or information compiled and provided by: Canadian institute for health information (CIHI). The analyses, conclusions, opinions and statements expressed herein are solely those of the authors and do not reflect those of the funding or data sources; no endorsement is intended or should be inferred.&#160;This study was supported by the Ontario Health Data Platform (OHDP), a Province of Ontario initiative to support Ontario&#8217;s ongoing response to COVID-19 and its related impacts. The opinions, results and conclusions reported in this paper are those of the authors and are independent from the funding sources. No endorsement by the OHDP, its partners, or the Province of Ontario is intended or should be inferred.&#160;Parts of this material are based on data and information compiled and provided by the Ontario Ministry of Health. The analyses, conclusions, opinions and statements expressed herein are solely those of the authors and do not reflect those of the funding or data sources; no endorsement is intended or should be inferred.&#160;Parts of this material are based on data and/or information compiled and provided by CIHI and the Ontario Ministry of Health. The analyses, conclusions, opinions and statements expressed herein are solely those of the authors and do not reflect those of the funding or data sources; no endorsement is intended or should be inferred.&#160;We thank IQVIA Solutions Canada Inc. for use of their Drug Information File. Parts of this material are based on data and information compiled and provided by the Ontario Ministry of Health. The analyses, conclusions, opinions and statements expressed herein are solely those of the authors and do not reflect those of the funding or data sources; no endorsement is intended or should be inferred.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>KAM oversaw the project, helped to interpret the findings, prepared, and revised the final manuscript. MT designed the analytical strategy and helped to interpret the findings, prepared, and revised the final manuscript. SA analyzed the data and prepared and revised the final manuscript. DCM plays a supervisory role in the design and interpretation analysis and DCM revised the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by NOAMA A-23. This study was also supported by ICES, which is funded in part by an annual grant from the Ontario Ministry of Health (MOH) and the Ministry of Long-Term Care (MLTC). This study was based on data compiled by ICES. However, the analyses, conclusions, opinions and statements expressed herein are those of the author(s), and not necessarily those of ICES.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par28">The authors have no relevant financial or non-financial interests to disclose.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Ethical approval</title><p id="Par29">This study was performed in line with the principles of the Tri-Council Policy Statement 2 (TCPS2).. Approval was granted by the Laurentian University Research and Ethics Board number 6020852.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Consent to participate and publish</title><p id="Par30">Consent to participate and publish was not obtained for this study. We utilized secondary data from ICES (Institute for Clinical Evaluative Sciences). As a prescribed entity under Personal Health Information Protection Act (PHIPA), ICES is authorized to collect personal health information from health organizations without consent, specifically for the purpose of evaluating and monitoring Ontario&#8217;s health system. Access to this research data is granted only after approval by ICES&#8217; Privacy Office and a Research Ethics Board (REB). Once approved, ICES provides research-ready, linked, and de-identified data. All personal identifiers are irrevocably removed before the data is made available to researchers, making written consent unattainable.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extent of illicit drug use and dependence, and their contribution to the global burden of disease</article-title><source>Lancet.</source><year>2012</year><volume>379</volume><issue>9810</issue><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(11)61138-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22225671</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Degenhardt L, Hall W. Extent of illicit drug use and dependence, and their contribution to the global burden of disease. Lancet. 2012;379(9810):55&#8211;70.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22225671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(11)61138-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Federal, provincial, and territorial Special Advisory Committee on the Epidemic of Opioid Overdoses. Opioid- and Stimulant-related Harms in Canada. Ottawa:: Public Health Agency of Canada; 2023 [Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://health-infobase.canada.ca/substance-related-harms/opioids-stimulants/">https://health-infobase.canada.ca/substance-related-harms/opioids-stimulants/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ontario Drug Policy Research Network. Ontario Opioid Indicator Tool Toronto, ON: ODPRN; 2023</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">[updated March 2023. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://odprn.ca/ontario-opioid-indicator-tool/">https://odprn.ca/ontario-opioid-indicator-tool/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pear</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ponicki</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaidus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keyes</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Urban-rural variation in the socioeconomic determinants of opioid overdose</article-title><source>Drug and Alcohol Dependence.</source><year>2019</year><volume>195</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2018.11.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30592998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6375680</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Pear VA, Ponicki WR, Gaidus A, Keyes KM, Martins SS, Fink DS, et al. Urban-rural variation in the socioeconomic determinants of opioid overdose. Drug and Alcohol Dependence. 2019;195:66&#8211;73.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30592998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2018.11.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6375680</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrero</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Opioid use disorder treatment for people experiencing homelessness: A scoping review</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend.</source><year>2021</year><volume>224</volume><fpage>108717</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2021.108717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33985863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9758007</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">McLaughlin MF, Li R, Carrero ND, Bain PA, Chatterjee A. Opioid use disorder treatment for people experiencing homelessness: A scoping review. Drug Alcohol Depend. 2021;224: 108717.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33985863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2021.108717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9758007</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Morin KA, Eibl, JK, Gauthier G, Rush B, Mushquash C, Lightfoot NE, Marsh DC. A cohort study evaluating the association between concurrent mental disorders, mortality, morbidity, and continuous treatment retention for patients in opioid agonist treatment (OAT) across Ontario, Canada using administrative health data [pre-print]. Harm Reduction Journal. 2020.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12954-020-00396-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7376938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32703310</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bogdanowicz</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Broadbent</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatch</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hotopf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Double trouble: Psychiatric comorbidity and opioid addiction-all-cause and cause-specific mortality</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend.</source><year>2015</year><volume>148</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2014.12.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25578253</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Bogdanowicz KM, Stewart R, Broadbent M, Hatch SL, Hotopf M, Strang J, et al. Double trouble: Psychiatric comorbidity and opioid addiction-all-cause and cause-specific mortality. Drug Alcohol Depend. 2015;148:85&#8211;92.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25578253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2014.12.025</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Astals</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Domingo-Salvany</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buenaventura</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tato</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vazquez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin-Santos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of substance dependence and dual diagnosis on the quality of life of heroin users seeking treatment</article-title><source>Subst Use Misuse.</source><year>2008</year><volume>43</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>612</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10826080701204813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18393080</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Astals M, Domingo-Salvany A, Buenaventura CC, Tato J, Vazquez JM, Martin-Santos R, et al. Impact of substance dependence and dual diagnosis on the quality of life of heroin users seeking treatment. Subst Use Misuse. 2008;43(5):612&#8211;32.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18393080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/10826080701204813</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prevost</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eibl</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oghene</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franklyn</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moise</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A retrospective cohort study evaluating correlates of deep tissue infections among patients enrolled in opioid agonist treatment using administrative data in Ontario, Canada</article-title><source>PLoS One.</source><year>2020</year><volume>15</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e0232191</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0232191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32330184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7182261</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Morin KA, Prevost CR, Eibl JK, Oghene P, Franklyn MT, Moise AR, Marsh DC. A retrospective cohort study evaluating correlates of deep tissue infections among patients enrolled in opioid agonist treatment using administrative data in Ontario, Canada. PLoS One. 2020;15(4):e0232191.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32330184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0232191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7182261</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kak</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandrasekar</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bone and joint infections in injection drug users</article-title><source>Infect Dis Clin North Am.</source><year>2002</year><volume>16</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>681</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0891-5520(02)00016-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12371122</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Kak V, Chandrasekar PH. Bone and joint infections in injection drug users. Infect Dis Clin North Am. 2002;16(3):681&#8211;95.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12371122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0891-5520(02)00016-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bachmeyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Landgraf</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daumas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soft tissue infection caused by Gemella morbillorum in two intravenous drug users</article-title><source>J Am Acad Dermatol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>52</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>704</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2004.11.045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15793530</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Bachmeyer C, Landgraf N, Daumas L. Soft tissue infection caused by Gemella morbillorum in two intravenous drug users. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2005;52(4):704&#8211;5.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15793530</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jaad.2004.11.045</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shei</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirson</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bodnar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Enloe</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Birnbaum</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of high-cost patients diagnosed with opioid abuse</article-title><source>J Manag Care Spec Pharm.</source><year>2015</year><volume>21</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>902</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26402390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18553/jmcp.2015.21.10.902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10397972</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Shei A, Rice JB, Kirson NY, Bodnar K, Enloe CJ, Birnbaum HG, et al. Characteristics of high-cost patients diagnosed with opioid abuse. J Manag Care Spec Pharm. 2015;21(10):902&#8211;12.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26402390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18553/jmcp.2015.21.10.902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10397972</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Showstack</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colby</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callaham</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of frequent users of emergency departments</article-title><source>Ann Emerg Med.</source><year>2006</year><volume>48</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annemergmed.2005.12.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16781914</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Hunt KA, Weber EJ, Showstack JA, Colby DC, Callaham ML. Characteristics of frequent users of emergency departments. Ann Emerg Med. 2006;48(1):1&#8211;8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16781914</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.annemergmed.2005.12.030</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forchuk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nisenbaum</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clemens</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiens</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Validation study of health administrative data algorithms to identify individuals experiencing homelessness and estimate population prevalence of homelessness in Ontario, Canada</article-title><source>BMJ Open.</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e030221</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2019-030221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31594882</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6797366</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Richard L, Hwang SW, Forchuk C, Nisenbaum R, Clemens K, Wiens K, et al. Validation study of health administrative data algorithms to identify individuals experiencing homelessness and estimate population prevalence of homelessness in Ontario, Canada. BMJ Open. 2019;9(10): e030221.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31594882</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2019-030221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6797366</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pear</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ponicki</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaidus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keyes</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Urban-rural variation in the socioeconomic determinants of opioid overdose</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend.</source><year>2019</year><volume>195</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2018.11.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30592998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6375680</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Pear VA, Ponicki WR, Gaidus A, Keyes KM, Martins SS, Fink DS, et al. Urban-rural variation in the socioeconomic determinants of opioid overdose. Drug Alcohol Depend. 2019;195:66&#8211;73.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30592998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2018.11.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6375680</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelleher</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Famelia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yilmazer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mallory</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chavez</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevention of opioid use disorder: the HOME (housing, opportunities, motivation and engagement) feasibility study</article-title><source>Harm Reduct J.</source><year>2021</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>112</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12954-021-00560-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34749744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8576969</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Kelleher KJ, Famelia R, Yilmazer T, Mallory A, Ford J, Chavez LJ, et al. Prevention of opioid use disorder: the HOME (housing, opportunities, motivation and engagement) feasibility study. Harm Reduct J. 2021;18(1):112.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34749744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12954-021-00560-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8576969</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atzema</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schull</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurdyak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilton</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vermuelen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Wait times in the emergency department for patients with mental illness</article-title><source>CMAJ.</source><year>2012</year><volume>184</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>E969</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1503/cmaj.111043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23148052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3519154</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Atzema CL, Schull MJ, Kurdyak P, Menezes NM, Wilton AS, Vermuelen MJ, et al. Wait times in the emergency department for patients with mental illness. CMAJ. 2012;184(18):E969-76.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23148052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1503/cmaj.111043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3519154</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansagi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sjoberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomson</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goransson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Frequent use of the hospital emergency department is indicative of high use of other health care services</article-title><source>Ann Emerg Med.</source><year>2001</year><volume>37</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>561</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mem.2001.111762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11385324</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Hansagi H, Olsson M, Sjoberg S, Tomson Y, Goransson S. Frequent use of the hospital emergency department is indicative of high use of other health care services. Ann Emerg Med. 2001;37(6):561&#8211;7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11385324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1067/mem.2001.111762</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Min</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nosyk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing the determinants of completing OAT induction and long-term retention: A population-based study in British Columbia Canada</article-title><source>J Subst Abuse Treat.</source><year>2022</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>108647</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2021.108647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34740484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9833672</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Kurz M, Min JE, Dale LM, Nosyk B. Assessing the determinants of completing OAT induction and long-term retention: A population-based study in British Columbia Canada. J Subst Abuse Treat. 2022;133: 108647.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34740484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jsat.2021.108647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9833672</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tahsin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vojtesek</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measuring treatment attrition at various stages of engagement in Opioid Agonist Treatment in Ontario Canada using a cascade of care framework</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res.</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>490</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12913-022-07877-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35413980</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9004214</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Tahsin F, Morin KA, Vojtesek F, Marsh DC. Measuring treatment attrition at various stages of engagement in Opioid Agonist Treatment in Ontario Canada using a cascade of care framework. BMC Health Serv Res. 2022;22(1):490.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35413980</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12913-022-07877-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9004214</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Viera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bromberg</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Refsland</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanojlovi&#263;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyhan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adherence to and retention in medications for opioid use disorder among adolescents and young adults</article-title><source>Epidemiologic Reviews.</source><year>2020</year><volume>42</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/epirev/mxaa001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32239206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8087870</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Viera A, Bromberg DJ, Whittaker S, Refsland BM, Stanojlovi&#263; M, Nyhan K, et al. Adherence to and retention in medications for opioid use disorder among adolescents and young adults. Epidemiologic Reviews. 2020;42(1):41&#8211;56.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32239206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/epirev/mxaa001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8087870</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pani</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vacca</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trogu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amato</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>2010 Pharmacological treatment for depression during opioid agonist treatment for opioid dependence</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev.</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>cd008373</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD008373.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20824876</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Pani PP, Vacca R, Trogu E, Amato L, Davoli M. 2010 Pharmacological treatment for depression during opioid agonist treatment for opioid dependence. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2010;9:cd008373.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD008373.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20824876</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Homayra</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Enns</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Min</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruneau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative analysis of instrumental variables on the assignment of buprenorphine/naloxone or methadone for the treatment of opioid use disorder</article-title><source>Epidemiology.</source><year>2024</year><volume>35</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/EDE.0000000000001697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38290142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10833049</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Homayra F, Enns B, Min JE, Kurz M, Bach P, Bruneau J, et al. Comparative analysis of instrumental variables on the assignment of buprenorphine/naloxone or methadone for the treatment of opioid use disorder. Epidemiology. 2024;35(2):218&#8211;31.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38290142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/EDE.0000000000001697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10833049</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerra-Alejos</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Min</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urbanoski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Influence of physician networks on the implementation of pharmaceutical alternatives to a toxic drug supply in British Columbia</article-title><source>Implement Sci.</source><year>2024</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13012-023-01331-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38184548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10771688</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Kurz M, Guerra-Alejos BC, Min JE, Barker B, Pauly B, Urbanoski K, et al. Influence of physician networks on the implementation of pharmaceutical alternatives to a toxic drug supply in British Columbia. Implement Sci. 2024;19(1):3.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38184548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13012-023-01331-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10771688</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerra-Alejos</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Min</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piske</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative effectiveness of urine drug screening strategies alongside opioid agonist treatment in British Columbia, Canada: A population-based observational study protocol</article-title><source>BMJ Open.</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e068729</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2022-068729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37258082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10255039</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Guerra-Alejos BC, Kurz M, Min JE, Dale LM, Piske M, Bach P, et al. Comparative effectiveness of urine drug screening strategies alongside opioid agonist treatment in British Columbia, Canada: A population-based observational study protocol. BMJ Open. 2023;13(5): e068729.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37258082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2022-068729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10255039</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ICES Mission, Vision, Values Toronto, ON: ICES; [Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ices.on.ca/About-ICES/Mission-vision-and-values">https://www.ices.on.ca/About-ICES/Mission-vision-and-values</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Matheson FI MG, van Ingen T. 2021 J. Ontario marginalization index: user guide. . Toronto, ON:: St. Michael&#8217;s Hospital (Unity Health Toronto); 2021.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Alessandro A BF, B&#233;langer J, Guimond E, and Penney C. 2017 Measuring remoteness and accessibility: A set of indices for Canadian communities. Reports on Special Business Projects. Ottawa ON: Statistics Canada; 2017.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aird</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors affecting rural medicine: An improvement on the rurality index of Ontario</article-title><source>Can J Rural Med.</source><year>2007</year><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18076819</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Aird P, Kerr J. Factors affecting rural medicine: An improvement on the rurality index of Ontario. Can J Rural Med. 2007;12(4):245&#8211;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18076819</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>