<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Subst Abuse Rehabil</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Subst Abuse Rehabil</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2178</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">sar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">sar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Substance Abuse and Rehabilitation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-8467</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11409926</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11409926.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11409926</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11409926</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39295965</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/SAR.S475807</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">475807</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Community-Based Medications First for Opioid Use Disorder - Care Utilization and Mortality Outcomes</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Banta-Green et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Banta-Green et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4084-6943</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Banta-Green</surname><given-names initials="CJ">Caleb J</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Owens</surname><given-names initials="MD">Mandy D</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5355-3210</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names initials="JR">Jason R</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Floyd</surname><given-names initials="AS">Anthony S</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams-Gilbert</surname><given-names initials="W">Wendy</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kingston</surname><given-names initials="S">Susan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Addictions, Drug &amp; Alcohol Institute, Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, School of Medicine, University of Washington Seattle</institution>, <addr-line>Seattle</addr-line>, <addr-line>WA</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Health Systems and Population Health, School of Public Health, University of Washington Seattle</institution>, <addr-line>Seattle</addr-line>, <addr-line>WA</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Epidemiology, School of Public Health, University of Washington Seattle</institution>, <addr-line>Seattle</addr-line>, <addr-line>WA</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Psychology, University of Washington</institution>, <addr-line>Seattle</addr-line>, <addr-line>WA</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Caleb J Banta-Green, <institution>Addictions, Drug &amp; Alcohol Institute, Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, School of Medicine, University of Washington</institution>, <addr-line>NE Pacific St Box 356560</addr-line>, <addr-line>Seattle</addr-line>, <addr-line>WA</addr-line>, <addr-line>98195</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>, Email calebbg@uw.edu</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">452758</issue-id><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>04</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>14</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>18</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-09-19 10:25:40.533"><day>19</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2024 Banta-Green et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Banta-Green et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution &#8211; Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="sar-15-173.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>A large treatment gap exists for people who could benefit from medications for opioid use disorder (MOUD). People OUD accessing services in harm reduction and community-based organizations often have difficulty engaging in MOUD at opioid treatment programs and traditional health care settings. We conducted a study to test the impacts of a community-based medications first model of care in six Washington (WA) State communities that provided drop-in MOUD access.</p></sec><sec><title>Participants and Methods</title><p>Participants included people newly prescribed MOUD. Settings included harm reduction and homeless services programs. A prospective cohort analysis tested the impacts of the intervention on MOUD and care utilization. Intervention impacts on mortality were tested via a synthetic comparison group analysis matching on demographics, MOUD history, and geography using WA State agency administrative data.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>825 people were enrolled in the study of whom 813 were matched to state records for care utilization and outcomes. Cohort analyses indicated significant increases for days&#8217; supply of buprenorphine, months with any MOUD, and months with any buprenorphine for people previously on buprenorphine (all results p&lt;0.05). Months with an emergency department overdose did not change. Months with an inpatient hospital stay increased (p&lt;0.05). The annual death rate in the first year for the intervention group was 0.45% (3 out of 664) versus 2.2% (222 out of 9893) in the comparison group in the 12 months; a relative risk of 0.323 (95% CI 0.11&#8211;0.94).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Findings indicated a significant increase in MOUD for the intervention group and a lower mortality rate relative to the comparison group. The COVID-19 epidemic and rapid increase in non-pharmaceutical-fentanyl may have lessened the intervention impact as measured in the cohort analysis. Study findings support expanding access to a third model of low barrier MOUD care alongside opioid treatment programs and traditional health care settings.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="video"><title>Video Abstract</title><p>
<fig position="anchor" id="uf0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="SAR-15-173-g0001.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p>Point your SmartPhone at the code above. If you have a QR code reader the video abstract will appear. Or use:<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://youtu.be/ReYtOx-0SQE" ext-link-type="uri">https://youtu.be/ReYtOx-0SQE</ext-link></underline></p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>opioid use disorder</kwd><kwd>medications for opioid use disorder</kwd><kwd>multi-site study</kwd><kwd>low-barrier care</kwd><kwd>harm reduction</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Paul G. Allen Family Foundation</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/100000952</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>Funding for this research was provided by the Paul G. Allen Family Foundation which had no role in the design of the study and collection, analysis, and interpretation of data.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="3"/><ref-count count="51"/><page-count count="11"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0001"><title>Background and Aims</title><p>A large treatment gap exists between those who have opioid use disorder (OUD) and the proportion receiving medications for OUD (MOUD), which are the most effective and evidence-based treatment for OUD.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Methadone and buprenorphine also significantly reduce opioid and all-cause mortality providing substantial harm reduction benefit in addition to supporting recovery according to findings from multiple large studies in diverse populations.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Most people with OUD want to stop or reduce their use and are interested in MOUD.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> While many people with OUD access an array of services in harm reduction and other community-based organizations, many also have difficulty starting or engaging in care at traditional substance use disorder (SUD) treatment clinics or primary care clinics.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></p><p>In recent years clinical efforts to increase low-barrier, rapid access to buprenorphine have expanded. Some programs initiate medications at harm reduction programs and transition quickly to primary care.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Hospital infrastructure and proximity to emergency departments (ED) and primary care clinics have been leveraged to create &#8220;bridge clinics&#8221;.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Rapid Access Addiction Medicine clinics are being scaled up in parts of Canada showing positive outcomes on care utilization and mortality.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Care models are sometimes focused on specific populations, such as those who are unhoused. One such model is the Boston Roundhouse, which utilized buprenorphine and also made substantial use of methadone via the 72-hour rule in preparation for continuing care at an opioid treatment program.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Some existing SUD treatment programs have lowered barriers to initiating and continuing care.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Telemedicine has been shown to improve access and reduce costs for MOUD.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></p><p>Policy changes have been enacted to expand buprenorphine prescriber types, patient capacity, and tele-medicine access, but it is not clear that they are increasing access in general let alone for marginalized populations who may be at particular risk for overdose and face additional challenges accessing health care systems.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14&#8211;16</xref> The Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration indicated their support for low-barrier access to buprenorphine in a &#8220;Dear Colleague&#8221; letter about the medication first model in 2023.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> The United States Department of Health and Human Services and the Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) have published rules to continue COVID-19 era temporary policies to lessen barriers to starting and staying on methadone; these include options to reduce clinic-observed dosing frequency and to start at higher initial doses, which helps address higher tolerances associated with non-pharmaceutical fentanyl (NPF) use.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></p><p>Recent efforts have expanded the utilization of MOUD, typically buprenorphine, in emergency departments, jails, and even by emergency medical services in the field.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19&#8211;21</xref> These inductions likely significantly reduce mortality risk in the short-term, but given that these patients are often marginalized and/or unhoused, connection to ongoing care can be a challenge for the patient to initiate and maintain.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> In many areas of the United States homelessness has increased in recent years just as NPF availability has increased, a dangerous combination given that being unhoused has been shown to significantly increase fatal overdose risk.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Unfortunately, some prescribers may be more reluctant to accept these unhoused patients who may be seen as less &#8220;motivated&#8221; to stop using opioids (and other substances) or less likely to &#8220;embrace recovery&#8221;.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></p><p>Staffing models that incorporate nurse care managers in office-based opioid treatment, primarily utilizing buprenorphine, have been shown to increase the number of providers who prescribe buprenorphine as well as the number of patients to whom they prescribe; nurse care managers provide structured clinical support to prescribers utilizing MOUD.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> More recently, other supportive staff have been added to the care team with roles and titles such as care navigators, peer support specialists, and community health workers; research is ongoing on the potential additive impact of these support staff.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></p><p>A low-barrier buprenorphine clinic at a downtown Seattle, WA syringe services program located at a public health department was implemented in 2017 utilizing a nurse care manager model. Research on this clinic found that the care model was feasible, in high demand by clients, had good retention, and significantly reduced illicit opioid use.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> The current study adapted that care model by adding care navigators and implementing it in multiple, diverse sites across WA State, in a community-based medications first (CBMF) model of care delivery.</p><p>In this context, community-based means care is located at community-based agencies that have a harm reduction philosophy and are either primarily a harm reduction organization that provides safer use supplies, among other supplies and services, or provides services to unhoused people. Said another way, community-based sites are not located in traditional health care or SUD treatment programs, thus providing a potential third model of care. Medications &#8220;first&#8221; does not necessarily mean medications &#8220;only&#8221;. Medications first is predicated upon buprenorphine and methadone being strongly preventative of fatal overdose<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> and therefore trying to induce and stabilize people on medications as the first step in the care process. It is also in response to the predominant models for accessing buprenorphine in the traditional health care system and specialty addiction treatment that are appointment-based with multiple requirements and appointments prior to receiving MOUD. Counseling, while clearly beneficial to some, has not been proven to have significant additive benefit to medications.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> CBMF also acknowledges that substance use often persists throughout treatment and recovery and that this is, in fact, a manifestation of opioid use disorder and a reason to continue to engage people in care, not discharge them from it.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Ongoing engagement in care is a primary goal of CBMF, and harm reduction services and supplies can provide a reason for initially engaging in a care relationship and a reason to stay engaged if substance use continues, with or without continuation of MOUD. An engagement-oriented, harm reduction-supportive care model and philosophy is integral. Parallel to our work, others have used similar medications first terminology in the context of reducing barriers and supporting engagement in specialty addiction treatment (eg, outpatient and inpatient OUD treatment services that may or may not utilize MOUD). The rationale for a medications first approach and elements of the various barriers have been well articulated.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Further details on the rationale, staffing model, and evolution of this care model are available in our protocol paper for this study.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></p><p>Our primary aim is to test the impact of the CBMF intervention on emergency department utilization, hospitalization, and mortality outcomes. Other aims include testing whether housing status modifies the impact of the intervention and the impact of the intervention on MOUD utilization.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Methods</title><p>Study methods are described here, with additional details about the clinical intervention and study design available in our protocol paper.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></p><sec id="s0002-s2001"><title>Clinical Intervention</title><p>The CBMF intervention is rapid, typically same-day, access to medications; convenient, non-appointment-based care; no exclusions for polysubstance use; no counseling mandates (but services readily available); ongoing, easy-to-access care. The model is intended for people who may have barriers to appointment-based care, including those who are unhoused. Staffing for CBMF utilized project-funded care teams comprised a nurse care manager and care navigators, as well as a prescriber&#8217;s time to oversee clinical activities. CBMF staff were often co-located at syringe services programs to facilitate linkage. COVID-19 precautions necessitated some clinics to move to appointment-based care for portions of the study period.</p><p>Ongoing implementation support was provided by the study team to clinic sites. The study&#8217;s clinical intervention support team (CBG, MDO, WWG, SK) provided initial training and ongoing, twice-monthly and ad hoc technical assistance and clinical consultation for nurse care managers and care navigators. Clinical support was provided to prescribers in monthly video conference calls. Site administrators met with the study team twice monthly to discuss administrative, clinical, and research issues (the clinical support team along with ASF).</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002"><title>Settings</title><p>Settings included syringe services programs, health departments, a federally qualified health center with a small primary care office on a highway adjacent to mobile harm reduction services, and programs for unhoused people. <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> provides an overview of each of the sites. The goal of this project was to provide care where people with OUD already receive other services and often have established trusting relationships with staff and volunteers. The six sites were purposefully selected to represent different types of organizations and provide geographic variability. Three of the sites were in Eastern Washington (Spokane, Walla Walla, Kennewick) and three in Western Washington (Tacoma, Seattle, Centralia).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Site Locations and Characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Service Providers</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSP Services Located:</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OUD Services Located:</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care Navigator Located:</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>Tacoma</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-Tacoma Needle Exchange/ Dave Purchase Project</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Parked van outside health department. Later inside an adjacent building</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Inside health department</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Van, inside SSP, inside health department</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-Tacoma Pierce County Health Department</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>Spokane</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-Spokane Regional Health District syringe services program (SSP)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Inside health department and CAT</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Inside health department and CAT</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Inside all locations. Provided by Frontier Behavioral Health.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-Frontier Behavioral Health</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;Compassionate Addiction Treatment (CAT)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Centralia</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;Gather Church</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mobile van</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inside agency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSP van and inside agency</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Walla Walla</bold></td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">&#8211;Blue Mountain Heart to Heart*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inside agency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inside agency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inside agency</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Kennewick*</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inside agency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inside agency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inside agency</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>North Seattle</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;Neighborcare Health</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Nearby street outreach, mobile delivery</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Inside adjacent primary care clinic and later also at community drop-in center</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">At both indoor locations</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;Aurora Commons</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;SSP outreach/delivery by The People&#8217;s Harm Reduction Alliance</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: *also operated a mobile SSP van with referrals into CBMF.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003"><title>Study Participants</title><p>People with OUD, per clinician assessment, who were interested in starting on an FDA-approved medication for OUD were eligible for the study if they were also between the ages of 18&#8211;70 and willing to provide access to state records data including substance use treatment records along with identifiers needed to link to records data. Potential participants were approached about study involvement and provided consent to participate in the study <italic toggle="yes">after</italic> their initial CBMF service encounter when they had already been informed and been prescribed MOUD. The clinical intervention, study recruitment, and enrollment began August 2019. The last month of new client enrollment was September 2021. At least 12 months of follow-up data from the date of beginning the clinical intervention were utilized.</p><p>A potential comparison group derived from state records was identified via a variable indicating a history of OUD based on documented history of a diagnosis for OUD or diagnoses indicating health complications attributed to opioid use in state Medicaid data.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004"><title>Data Sources</title><p>At the time of study enrollment personal identifiers (for data linkage), demographics, and housing status were collected from participants. Secondary, administrative data were obtained from the WA State Department of Social and Health Services&#8217; Research and Data Analysis (RDA) office including: health care, buprenorphine, and naltrexone utilization documented in state Medicaid data, monthly Medicaid eligibility, mortality data (indicating that a death from any cause occurred in a specific month), county of residence in a given month, arrests, Prescription Monitoring Program data for buprenorphine prescriptions, and methadone provided by publicly-funded opioid treatment programs.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2005"><title>Study Design</title><p>A prospective cohort study design was conducted to test the impacts of the intervention on subsequent MOUD and emergency department utilization and hospitalization. For care utilization outcomes we restricted analyses to those with complete Medicaid eligibility in the 12 months prior to and following receiving CBMF to maximize complete data.</p><p>To test the impact of the intervention on mortality, a synthetic comparison group analysis, based upon a statistically matched group from WA State agency administrative data sources, was conducted. In the first stage of creating a comparison group, members of the large comparison data pool were assigned the treatment group member&#8217;s start date and matched on key broad indicators of OUD history and county of residence. In the second stage, propensity score matching was implemented with more fine-grained history variables, including MOUD utilization, opioid poisonings, all-cause hospital emergency department visits and inpatient hospitalizations, and arrest history, to match and balance the samples; details are provided in the <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=475807.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplement</ext-link></underline>.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2006"><title>Analyses</title><p>Descriptive statistics for demographics, MOUD utilization, arrests, and emergency department and inpatient hospitalization are presented for all study participants enrolled and matched to state data, the subset of study participants included in the synthetic comparison group analysis for mortality, and those with complete Medicaid data. Propensity score matching for the comparison analysis was conducted with a 24-month pre-period, for a slightly different set of characteristics (see <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=475807.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplement</ext-link></underline>) and resulted in all weighted standardized mean differences being less than 0.06 standard deviations (data not shown).</p><p>For the prospective cohort study analyses, pre-post comparison of rates of care utilization based on days&#8217; supply of buprenorphine or number of months within which an event occurred was tested with an unadjusted model regressing change score on housing status. Specifically, the value for the 12 months before induction into CBMF was subtracted from the value for the 12-month follow-up period, and this change score regressed on whether the participant reported having stable housing at induction. For example, a client who had 2 opioid poisonings treated at an emergency department in the post period and 3 in the pre period would have a change score of &#8722;1. Post-hoc contrasts determined significant change scores (whether the model intercept differs from 0) or whether this depends on housing status.</p><p>For the synthetic comparison group analysis, the all-cause mortality rate difference between the intervention and comparison groups was tested in a logistic regression model that accounted for propensity score weighting and included history variables used in estimating the propensity score as covariates, followed by marginal effects estimation to calculate an average risk ratio. Details are provided in the <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=475807.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplement</ext-link></underline>. All analyses were conducted in R statistical software, using the MatchIt package for propensity score matching and weighting and the marginaleffects package for g-computation of the marginal risk ratio.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37&#8211;39</xref></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 1325 people received the CMBF clinical intervention. 825 people were enrolled in the study, of whom 813 were matched to state records by RDA. Those who received CBMF services had generally similar age and gender as those enrolled in the study and whose data were analyzed (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Data indicated that those with complete Medicaid eligibility were similar to all of those enrolled in the CBMF study except they had higher rates of each care measure, likely because they had more time with complete data. The group with complete eligibility for Medicaid had lower rates of arrest, which is likely due at least in part to the fact that people lose Medicaid eligibility if they are incarcerated. The group with complete Medicaid data had a somewhat smaller proportion who were unstably housed/unhoused, 41% versus 44%.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Participant Characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All Clients Served</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enrolled and Matched to State Data</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-post Cohort Analysis with Complete Medicaid Data</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matched Comparison Mortality Analysis</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1325</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">813</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">463</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">664</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold>Demographics</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age- mean</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#8211;29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.90%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.40%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.30%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.00%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30&#8211;39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.60%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.90%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.70%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.90%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#8211;49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.40%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.70%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#8211;59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.70%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.10%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.40%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.10%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.10%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unstably housed/unhoused</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.10%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.60%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.90%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold>Medications for opioid use disorder utilization</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buprenorphine - day&#8217;s supply</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;38.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buprenorphine - any</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.30%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;63.3%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buprenorphine - months with</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.83</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methadone - any</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.20%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;7.4%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methadone - months with</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Naltrexone - any</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;3.3%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Naltrexone - months with</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any OUD medication - months with</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any OUD medication</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.70%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;67.8%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold>Arrests</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arrests - any</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.60%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;43.4%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arrests - month with</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold>Emergency department and inpatient hospital utilization</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ED poisoning - any</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.80%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.10%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;4.2%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ED poisoning - months with</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.048&#160;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ED non-poisoning - any</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.70%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;59.5%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ED non-poisoning - months with</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55&#160;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitalization - any</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.70%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;27.6%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitalization - months with</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><sec id="s0003-s2001"><title>Impact of CBMF on MOUD Utilization and Health Care Utilization</title><p>For care utilization outcomes, we restricted analyses to those with complete Medicaid eligibility in the 12 months prior to and following receiving CBMF and complete housing data (n=446). <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> compares the year before and after starting CBMF. Not all measures depended on Medicaid eligibility; however, we narrowed analyses to this group as health care and some MOUD utilization data elements were constructed from Medicaid health system data.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Changes Pre-Post Among Intervention Participants</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Fully Medicaid Eligible<sup>+</sup></th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Fully Medicaid Eligible w/ Housing Data</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Stably Housed at Baseline&#160;</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Unstably Housed/ Unhoused at Baseline&#160;</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Change by Housing Status</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=</td><td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">463</td><td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">446</td><td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">265</td><td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">181&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p&lt;0.05*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p&lt;0.05*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p&lt;0.05*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p&lt;0.05*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="13" rowspan="1"><bold>Medications for opioid use disorder utilization</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buprenorphine days&#8217; supply</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">121.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OUD medication- months with any</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buprenorphine- months with any</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="13" rowspan="1"><bold>Acute care utilization</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ED poisoning visit- months with any</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ED non-poisoning visit- months with any</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any hospital stay- months with any</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: +Noted as Medicaid eligible in all 12 months before and after the start month. *Significance tested in an unadjusted model regressing change score on housing status.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Analyses indicated significant increases for days&#8217; supply of buprenorphine, months with any OUD medication, and months with any buprenorphine overall (n=446) and for both housed and unhoused people. Those housed had a significantly greater increase than those unhoused. Both months with an emergency department poisoning visit (eg, opioid overdose) and with a non-poisoning-related emergency department visit did not change. The months with an inpatient hospitalization stay increased significantly, with no difference by housing status. Among those who had any buprenorphine in the pre-period (n=243), the change in buprenorphine days&#8217; supply increased significantly from a mean of 81.5 days to 136.5 days (p&lt;0.05).</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002"><title>Mortality Analyses</title><p>The mortality analyses utilized a matched comparison group drawn from state records data. For the matched comparison analyses, intervention participants were included if they had an indication of a history of OUD based upon the presence of an OUD or opioid poisoning diagnosis and/or a previous indication of having received a medication for the treatment of OUD (n=670). (For the other 143, no indication of needing MOUD could be found in state records). The final comparison group was matched based upon multiple variables including geography/county, demographics, care utilization, and arrest history (n=664).</p><p>The observed annual death rate in the first year for the intervention group was 0.45% (3 out of 664) compared to 2.2% (222 out of 9893) in the comparison group in the 12 months, with a regression adjusted relative risk of 0.323 (95% CI 0.11&#8211;0.94). This can be interpreted as the CBMF intervention was associated with a significant reduction in the mortality rate with an estimated 68% reduction (95% CI 6%-89%) relative to the comparison group. Had the comparison group experienced mortality at the same rate as the intervention group, there would have been an estimated 45 deaths, or 177 potential deaths avoided.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our findings indicated a statistically and clinically significant increase in medications for OUD after receiving CBMF and a significant decrease in mortality relative to the comparison group. We did not see a change in emergency department poisoning visits, but it is important to note that the rate of these visits is very low and that previous research indicated that many people who have an overdose do not seek medical care.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> Not seeking care for an overdose was perhaps even more likely given the high rates of naloxone availability in the community (approximately 80% of people who use opioids reported having naloxone according to a WA State syringe services program survey) and the reluctance of people to go to the emergency department or hospital during COVID-19.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> Conversely, there was a significant increase in inpatient hospitalizations which did not align with emergency department poisoning findings, perhaps due to COVID-19 or other unmeasured co-morbidities.</p><p>We aimed to provide services to housing-insecure people and at least 40% of participants studied were housing insecure. It is important to see that those who were unhoused also had a substantial and statistically significant increase in time on medications. We also wanted to test this model of care in multiple diverse communities, urban and rural, small and large, and the intervention was feasible in all settings. This study is not generalizable to all of WA State nor nationally due to purposeful community recruitment. However, findings suggest that the CBMF model is feasible outside of a large urban setting, such as Seattle, which was the forerunner of this model, which is important for ensuring broad accessibility. We believe that feasibility was increased by the relationship building and ongoing communication between CBMF sites and upstream and downstream referral partners as program successes and challenges were shared. These communication processes should be strongly considered by those planning to implement CBMF in the future.</p><p>CBMF added care navigators to the original Seattle-based model. Care navigators averaged 10 contacts/encounters per client during the first six months of care for the 1325 people who received services.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Even during COVID-19 restrictions the most common mode of communication was in-person, speaking to the dedication of staff and the significance of these encounters to clients. The most common topic of encounters was program retention, followed by clients&#8217; ongoing substance use. As one client said,
<disp-quote><p>You can&#8217;t imagine how it feels to finally not have to lie or cheat to hide my drug use just to get some help. Here, they actually want to know about it! That seemed crazy to me at first but that&#8217;s just really how it ought to be, isn&#8217;t it?</p></disp-quote></p><p>Future research on CBMF would benefit from studying the potential impacts of different staffing models involving nurse care managers and care navigators, though the existing literature has shown that each can provide significant improvements in outcomes for people on buprenorphine.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Cost-effectiveness of the model will be important to analyze in the future. Roughly in the middle of the study period, NPF overtook heroin as the predominant opioid. The utility of the CBMF model for those with OUD and dependent on NPF is important to understand, particularly given greater medication induction challenges and some perceptions among people who use NPF of lower effectiveness of buprenorphine for NPF compared to heroin or pharmaceutical opioids such as oxycodone. Lastly, given the promise of long-acting injectable buprenorphine products for NPF, including growing uptake at several of our sites that continued services after the study ended, future research should incorporate these newer MOUD products.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> There is also the possibility of rapid starts with long-acting injectable products.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> For regions with geographic access to opioid treatment programs there is the potential for future CBMF programs to utilize the 72-hour rule for methadone to get a person quickly started on methadone, which, as a full agonist medication, may ease induction from fentanyl and help match new higher opioid tolerance levels seen with use of non-pharmaceutical fentanyl.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></p><sec id="s0004-s2001"><title>Rationale for Study Design Modifications</title><p>We originally proposed a &#8220;6-month, induction-stabilization-transition&#8221; model, such that after 6 months of CBMF care clients would be transferred to ongoing care elsewhere, ideally primary care in traditional health care settings. However, this was difficult for many participants, and we did not enforce this 6-month limit as it would have potentially meant discontinuing buprenorphine for people with no other option. Therefore, the model of care we tested did not have a strict 6-month duration. When recruiting sites for the study, we asked them to identify a primary care provider willing to take clients stabilized on MOUD and all sites identified at least one provider. However, when it came time to refer clients from CBMF many community providers would not accept clients or quickly discharged them. This lack of referral acceptance or rapid care discontinuation was often explained as being due to ongoing substance use such as methamphetamine or benzodiazepines, even when clients were stable on buprenorphine and regularly attended their medical appointments. Some CBMF site administrators noted that community prescribers became more willing over time to accept referrals from CBMF programs. In addition, according to clinic staff, many unhoused clients found it difficult to get to an appointment with a primary care provider due to lack of transportation.</p><p>Arrest outcomes were not explored due to two major events: 1) the COVID-19 pandemic led to rapid and dramatic reductions in jail censuses beginning in March 2020 and 2) major legal changes to state drug possession laws. In February 2021 the WA State Supreme Court decided a case with the result that state drug possession laws were invalidated, the legislature subsequently passed ESB5476 making drug possession a misdemeanor with the first two arrests subject to diversion.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> The net impact was that arrests and incarceration for possession virtually stopped until the law was changed in 2023 to make drug possession a gross misdemeanor.<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></p><p>We also originally planned to use a comparison group approach for all analyses. However, we could not obtain housing management information system data from WA State as planned and thus had no measure of housing stability for the comparison group. Given that the intervention group was at least 40% unstably housed, we felt this could result in an unfair comparison such that the intervention may have outcomes that appeared worse due to their housing instability. Thus, we used a cohort pre-post analysis for MOUD and care utilization so that participants served as their own comparison to reduce confounding. We chose to use the comparison group approach for the mortality analysis as we felt this would result in conservative bias, with the intervention group likely having worse outcomes and elevated mortality if not for the intervention.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> The actual results indicated the intervention group had lower mortality, with the degree of mortality reduction associated with the intervention likely underestimated.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0005"><title>Limitations</title><p>For our pre-post cohort analyses we utilized data for clients who had continuous Medicaid eligibility for 24 months (12 months pre- and post-CBMF enrollment). The data indicated that this subset had somewhat lower rates of housing instability and arrests. It is likely, therefore, that the findings somewhat overestimated the impact of CBMF in these analyses relative to the entire population enrolled in the study.</p><p>Due to COVID-19 infection concerns beginning in March 2020 (8 months after the start of the study), some programs temporarily instituted appointment-based care to minimize the number of clients in clinic spaces; this had a substantial negative impact on study enrollment. However, the demographics of those who received services were generally very similar to those included in analyses (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Switching to appointment-based care for some intervention participants likely made the care model more similar to those in the comparison group. This conservative bias would most likely result in an underestimate of the impact of the intervention.</p><p>In preparing for this study, we estimated an annual mortality rate of 6%, based upon our previous research with those with opioid use seen for care in Seattle emergency departments as well as very similar findings in Boston.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> In this case, it appears that the matched comparison, which had an extensive history of medication use for OUD, had a lower mortality rate than we anticipated, and yet the intervention group still had a significantly reduced mortality rate. We were only able to obtain all-cause mortality data, not opioid involved overdose specific mortality data from WA State. While it is possible that the intervention did not impact opioid involved mortality specifically, multiple studies have found consistent impacts of MOUD on reducing both all-cause and opioid specific mortality.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Further, one of the goals of the intervention was to reduce mortality, regardless of the cause.</p><p>We used an observational study design rather than a randomized controlled trial. Based on previous experience implementing a randomized controlled trial with a similar, high acuity population receiving care in fast paced, non-appointment-based care setting, we chose to emphasize including as many participants as possible by removing research burden on staff and clients.<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> The net result, we believe, is study findings that are likely representative of real-world care and a broad spectrum of clients and are less biased than a randomized controlled trial might have been.<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0006"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Given the persistent unmet need for MOUD and increasing challenges presented by NPF, the positive findings for CBMF warrant its inclusion among a growing third model of community-based care. This third care model is evolving across the United State and Canada to provide a medication-first, low-barrier model of care to provide access to buprenorphine alongside existing models in traditional health care settings and opioid treatment programs.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors acknowledge the kind, ethical, high-quality care provided by community-based providers during the COVID-19 pandemic. Their dedication and passion is greatly appreciated. Tremendous thanks to the clients who agreed to share their data for this study. We also thank Jeanne Sears PhD RN who provided expert consultation on statistical methods. A preliminary version of the study findings was presented as a poster at the College on Problems of Drug Dependence on June 20, 2023 and a copy is available online at: <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://adai.uw.edu/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/community-based-meds-poster-2023.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://adai.uw.edu/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/community-based-meds-poster-2023.pdf</ext-link></underline></p></ack><sec id="s0007"><title>Ethics/Human Subjects Review</title><p>The University of Washington IRB determined that the application qualified for expedited review and approved it (IRB ID# STUDY00006623). The WA State IRB reviewed and approved the use of state&#8209;held secondary data records (Project # 2019&#8209;032). This study complies with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests in this work.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Krawczyk</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jent</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Keyes</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cerd&#225;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Has the treatment gap for opioid use disorder narrowed in the U.S.?: a yearly assessment from 2010 to 2019&#8221;</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Drug Policy</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>103786</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugpo.2022.103786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35934583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10976290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hser</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long-term follow-up assessment of opioid use outcomes among individuals with comorbid mental disorders and opioid use disorder treated with buprenorphine or methadone in a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Addiction</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>117</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>151</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>161</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/add.15594</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34105213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8710136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of treatment for opioid dependence on fatal drug-related poisoning: a national cohort study in England</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Addiction</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>298</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>308</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/add.13193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26452239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4950033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Larochelle</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bernson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Land</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Medication for opioid use disorder after nonfatal opioid overdose and association with mortality</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Internal Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>169</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>137</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M17-3107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29913516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6387681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McMahan</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kingston</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stekler</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Glick</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Banta-Green</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Interest in reducing methamphetamine and opioid use among syringe services program participants in Washington State</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Drug Alcohol Depend</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<fpage>216</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.108243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9632690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32911134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Banta-Green</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kingston</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>University of Washington. Washinton State Syringe Exchange Health Survey: 2017 Results</article-title>. <comment>Available from:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://adai.uw.edu/pubs/pdf/2017syringeexchangehealthsurvey.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://adai.uw.edu/pubs/pdf/2017syringeexchangehealthsurvey.pdf</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed<day>10</day><month>May</month> 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tsui</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Merrill</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adwell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tamru</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Linking patients with buprenorphine treatment in primary care: predictors of engagement</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Drug Alcohol Depend</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>181</volume>:<fpage>58</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2017.09.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29035705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Perez-Correa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Riback</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Onsite buprenorphine inductions at harm reduction agencies to increase treatment engagement and reduce HIV risk: design and rationale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Contemp Clin Trials</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>114</volume>:<fpage>106674</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cct.2021.106674</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34990854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10123766</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wakeman</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Walley</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kehoe</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Substance use disorder bridge clinics: models, evidence, and future directions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Addict Sci Clin Pract</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>23</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13722-023-00365-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37055851</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10101823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Corace</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thavorn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Suschinsky</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Rapid access addiction medicine clinics for people with problematic opioid use</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e2344528</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.44528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37991762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10665968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Komaromy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gott</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Facilitating exit from encampments: combining low-barrier transitional housing with stabilizing treatment for substance related problems</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Addict Sci Clin Pract</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>66</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13722-023-00420-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37884986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10601141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Winograd</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stringfellow</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Implementation and evaluation of Missouri&#8217;s medication first treatment approach for opioid use disorder in publicly-funded substance use treatment programs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Substance Abuse Treatm</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>108</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2019.06.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31277891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Winger</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A telemedicine bridge clinic improves access and reduces cost for opioid use disorder care</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Drug Alcohol Depend Rep</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>100227</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dadr.2024.100227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38550513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10972833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Suda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Buprenorphine dispensing before and after the April 2021 X-Waiver exemptions: an interrupted time series analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Drug Policy</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>104381</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugpo.2024.104381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38457960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Krawczyk</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dooling</surname><given-names>BCE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pandemic telehealth flexibilities for buprenorphine treatment: a synthesis of evidence and policy implications for expanding opioid use disorder care in the United States</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Health Aff Sch</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>qxad013</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/haschl/qxad013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38145115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10734906</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khatiwada</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Did the 2021 federal change in the practice guidelines for the administration of buprenorphine for treating opioid use disorder increase buprenorphine prescription dispensing in medicaid population?</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Addict</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>335</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>338</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ajad.13505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38069608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="newspaper"><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Dear colleague letter- medication first model</italic>. food and drug administration and substance abuse and mental health services administration</article-title>; <year>2023</year>. <comment>Available from:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.samhsa.gov/sites/default/files/dear-colleague-letter-fda-samhsa.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.samhsa.gov/sites/default/files/dear-colleague-letter-fda-samhsa.pdf</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>September</month><day>05</day>, 2024</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><source><italic toggle="yes">Medications for the Treatment of Opioid Use Disorder a Rule by the Health and Human Services Department</italic></source>. <publisher-name>U.S. Health and Human Services</publisher-name>; <year>2024</year>. <comment>Available from:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2024/02/02/2024-01693/medications-for-the-treatment-of-opioid-use-disorder" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2024/02/02/2024-01693/medications-for-the-treatment-of-opioid-use-disorder</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>September</month><day>05</day>, 2024</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>D&#8217;Onofrio</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chawarski</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Connor</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Emergency department-initiated buprenorphine for opioid dependence with continuation in primary care: outcomes during and after intervention</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Gen Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>660</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>666</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-017-3993-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28194688</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5442013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Herring</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Samuels</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Emergency department access to buprenorphine for opioid use disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e2353771</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.53771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38285444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10825722</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heil</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of administering buprenorphine to overdose survivors using emergency medical services</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Emerg Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>165</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>175</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annemergmed.2022.07.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36192278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pourtaher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gelberg</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fallico</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ellendon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Expanding access to Medication for Opioid Use Disorder (MOUD) in jails: a comprehensive program evaluation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Subst Use Addict Treat</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>161</volume>:<fpage>209248</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.josat.2023.209248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38081540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lozano-Rojas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Higher rates of homelessness are associated with increases in mortality from accidental drug and alcohol poisonings</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Health Aff</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>242</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>249</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2023.00951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38315926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fowle</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Routhier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mortal systemic exclusion yielded steep mortality-rate increases in people experiencing homelessness, 2011&#8211;20</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Health Aff</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>226</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>233</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2023.01039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38315931</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lofwall</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Havens</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Studts</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Physicians&#8217; decision-making when implementing buprenorphine with new patients: conjoint analyses of data from a cohort of current prescribers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Addict Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>31</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>39</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ADM.0000000000000360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28914663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5786469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>LaBelle</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bergeron</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Samet</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Office-Based Opioid Treatment with Buprenorphine (OBOT-B): statewide implementation of the Massachusetts collaborative care model in community health centers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Substance Abuse Treatm</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2015.06.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4682362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26233698</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alford</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>LaBelle</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kretsch</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Collaborative care of opioid-addicted patients in primary care using buprenorphine: five-year experience</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Archives Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>171</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>425</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>431</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinternmed.2010.541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3059544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21403039</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ramdin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Becceril</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Al Kik</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jefri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The impact of an emergency department peer navigator (EDPN) program in improving clinical outcomes and healthcare utilization in an urban setting</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Emerg Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajem.2023.02.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36905880</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lawdahl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Characterization of peer support services for substance use disorders in 11 US emergency departments in 2020: findings from a NIDA clinical trials network site selection process</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Addict Sci Clin Pract</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>26</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13722-024-00453-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38589934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11003047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hood</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Banta-Green</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Duchin</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Engaging an unstably housed population with low-barrier buprenorphine treatment at a syringe services program: lessons learned from Seattle, Washington</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Substance Abuse</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>356</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>364</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08897077.2019.1635557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31403907</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;grady</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jaffe</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gandhi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Improvements in outcomes in methadone patients on probation/parole regardless of counseling early in treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Addict Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>133</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>138</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ADM.0b013e318284a0c1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23455877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3618548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The role of behavioral interventions in buprenorphine maintenance treatment: a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2016.16070792</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5474206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27978771</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Beyond abstinence: changes in indices of quality of life with time in recovery in a nationally representative sample of U.S. adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Alcohol Clin Exp Res</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>770</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>780</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/acer.13604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29473966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5880708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Winograd</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Presnall</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stringfellow</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The case for a medication first approach to the treatment of opioid use disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Drug Alcohol Abuse</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>333</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>340</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00952990.2019.1605372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31084515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kourounis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>BDW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kyprianou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Symeonidou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Malliori</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Samartzis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Opioid substitution therapy: lowering the treatment thresholds</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Drug Alcohol Depend</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>161</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2015.12.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26832931</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0036"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Banta-Green</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The community-based medication-first program for opioid use disorder: a hybrid implementation study protocol of a rapid access to buprenorphine program in Washington State</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Addict Sci Clin Pract</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>34</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13722-022-00315-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35799210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9261214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0037"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Team</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc>. <year>2020</year></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0038"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>MatchIt: nonparametric preprocessing for parametric causal inference</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Statis Softw</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>28</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v042.i08</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0039"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Arel-Bundock</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>marginal effects: Predictions, Comparisons, Slopes, Marginal Means, and Hypothesis Tests. R package version 0.11.1</article-title>. <year>2023</year></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0040"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karamouzian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Crabtree</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Buxton</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Correlates of seeking emergency medical help in the event of an overdose in British Columbia, Canada: findings from the take home Naloxone program</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Drug Policy</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>163</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugpo.2019.01.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30691944</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0041"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Banta-Green</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kingston</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Glick</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tinsely</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Washington State Syringe Exchange Health Survey, 2019 Results</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Alcohol &amp; Drug Abust Institute, University of Washington</publisher-name>; <year>2020</year>. <comment>Available from:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://adai.uw.edu/wa-state-syringe-exchange-health-survey-2019-results" ext-link-type="uri">https://adai.uw.edu/wa-state-syringe-exchange-health-survey-2019-results</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0042"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Salvia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Worse cardiac arrest outcomes during the COVID-19 pandemic in Boston can be attributed to patient reluctance to seek care</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Health Aff</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>886</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>895</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2021.00250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34038193</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0043"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kingston</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Banta-Green</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Care Navigation at Harm Reduction Programs: Community-Based</italic> &#8220;Meds First&#8221; <italic toggle="yes">Buprenorphine Program Preliminary Dat</italic></article-title>. <publisher-name>Addictions, Drug &amp; Alcohol Institute, Department of Psychiatry &amp; Behavioral Sciences, School of Medicine, University of Washington</publisher-name>; <year>2022</year>. <comment>Available from:</comment>: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://adai.uw.edu/care-navigation-2022" ext-link-type="uri">https://adai.uw.edu/care-navigation-2022</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0044"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Malone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Comparison of treatment retention of adults with opioid addiction managed with extended-release buprenorphine vs daily sublingual buprenorphine-naloxone at time of release from jail</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e2123032</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.23032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34495340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8427378</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0045"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mariani</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mahony</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Podell</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Open-label trial of a single-day induction onto buprenorphine extended-release injection for users of heroin and fentanyl</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Addict</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>470</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>476</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ajad.13193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34223681</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8459386</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0046"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Laks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Christine</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Bridge clinic implementation of &#8220;72-hour rule&#8221; methadone for opioid withdrawal management: impact on opioid treatment program linkage and retention in care</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Drug Alcohol Depend</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>236</volume>:<fpage>109497</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2022.109497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35607834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0047"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dhingra</surname></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">ESB5476</italic></source>. <comment>Available from:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://app.leg.wa.gov/billsummary?BillNumber=5476%2526Year=2021" ext-link-type="uri">https://app.leg.wa.gov/billsummary?BillNumber=5476&amp;Year=2021</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>September</month><day>05</day>, 2024</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0048"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">ESB5536</italic></source>. <comment>Available from:</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://app.leg.wa.gov/billsummary?BillNumber=5536%2526Year=2023" ext-link-type="uri">https://app.leg.wa.gov/billsummary?BillNumber=5536&amp;Year=2023</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>September</month><day>05</day>, 2024</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0049"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Roussos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Angelopoulos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cholongitas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>High levels of all-cause mortality among people who inject drugs from 2018 to 2022</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Drug Policy</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>104356</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugpo.2024.104356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38394950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0050"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Banta-Green</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Coffin</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Merrill</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impacts of an opioid overdose prevention intervention delivered subsequent to acute care</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Inj Prev</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>191</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>198</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/injuryprev-2017-042676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29436397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6800078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0051"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Why all randomised controlled trials produce biased results</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>312</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>322</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07853890.2018.1453233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29616838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>