<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="editorial" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Prev Pract</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Infect Prev Pract</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4083</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">infpip</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Infection Prevention in Practice</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2590-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12167906</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12167906.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12167906</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12167906</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40525117</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.infpip.2025.100459</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2590-0889(25)00023-X</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100459</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>MRSA: the enduring foe</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names initials="S">Siobhain</given-names></name><email>siobhain.kelly@outlook.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#8270;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winzor</surname><given-names initials="G">Gemma</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names initials="SC">Simon Ching</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Graham Ayliffe Fellow, Healthcare Infection Society, London, UK</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Microbiology, Connolly Hospital, Dublin, Ireland</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Microbiology, Worcestershire Acute Hospitals NHS Trust, Worcester, UK</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>School of Nursing, Tung Wah College, Hong Kong, Hong Kong Special Administrative Region of China</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#8270;</label>Corresponding author. Address: Graham Ayliffe Fellow, Healthcare Infection Society, London, UK. <email>siobhain.kelly@outlook.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">483508</issue-id><elocation-id>100459</elocation-id><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>25</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>16</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-06-17 13:25:40.067"><day>17</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Crown Copyright &#169; 2025 Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of The Healthcare Infection Society.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0010">It has been six decades since Professor Patricia Jevons first identified a methicillin-resistant strain of <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA). Since then, our understanding of MRSA's pathogenicity and virulence has expanded significantly and has been accompanied by advances in diagnostics and treatment options. Yet, as the articles in this special edition demonstrate, MRSA remains a significant global public health concern.</p><p id="p0015">MRSA is widely regarded as the &#8220;original superbug&#8221;, and over the years it has continued to evolve. Toxin producing strains and resistance to additional classes of antibiotics present further challenges. Although other superbugs have emerged, MRSA remains a significant burden. A systematic review by Murray <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> identified MRSA as the pathogen-drug combination responsible for the highest attributable death rate globally [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. MRSA remains a leading cause of nosocomial infections in healthcare settings. The papers in this special edition, spanning four continents, highlight the persistent threat of MRSA internationally and the challenges imposed by differing resource limitations in its detection and management.</p><p id="p0020">High quality, up-to-date data on the prevalence of multi-drug resistant organisms (MDROs) is often limited in low-income settings. Abebe <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> attempt to address this gap by detailing MRSA colonisation rates among a subset of Ethiopian patients with wound infections [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Similarly, Sagiraju <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> investigated MRSA colonisation rates in their diabetic population, finding nearly double the prevalence compared to non-diabetic individuals [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Both studies also report significant rates of vancomycin resistant Staphylococcus aureus (VRSA). Vancomycin remains a standard treatment for MRSA, but in regions where VRSA is prevalent, the lack of access to microbiological testing to guide treatment poses significant risks to patient outcomes. Fortunately, as antimicrobial resistance has progressed, our treatment options for Gram-positive organisms have expanded &#8211; ranging from vancomycin to linezolid, daptomycin, and most recently, dalbavancin. These newer agents have significantly enhanced our treatment arsenal for MRSA in high-income settings, offering advantages such as linezolid's oral formulation and dalbavancin's extended half life, while also eliminating the need for therapeutic drug monitoring. Studies consistently demonstrate that these agents are as effective as vancomycin in treating MRSA [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>].</p><p id="p0025">Exposure to healthcare settings is a well-recognised risk factor for MRSA colonisation, disproportionately impacting the most vulnerable patient groups. Sigakis <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> reviewed seven years of data, demonstrating that patients colonised with MRSA experience higher mortality rates compared to their MRSA-negative counterparts [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Numerous studies have highlighted the association between MRSA colonisation and poorer outcomes across a wide range of specialties [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>].</p><p id="p0030">Advances in technology have facilitated the rapid detection of MRSA isolates, the identification of toxin-producing strains, and enhanced the management of outbreaks. For instance, MRSA strains producing virulence factors like Panton-Valentine Leucocidin (PVL) present additional challenges in managing cases and outbreaks in the healthcare setting. However, as these studies highlight, access to such technology remains limited in many regions, highlighting global disparities in MRSA management.</p><p id="p0035">Traynor <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> describe a protracted 16-month outbreak of PVL-positive MRSA in a National Burns Unit [<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Outbreaks of PVL-positive MRSA have also been reported in other high-risk settings, including maternity and neonatal units [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Traynor <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> highlight the important role that whole genome sequencing (WGS) played in bringing this outbreak to a conclusion. Advances in sequencing technology have transformed MRSA outbreak management by enabling precise discrimination between isolates and improving our ability to trace transmission pathways. In the absence of genomic tools, there is often a reliance on antibiograms for strain differentiation. Yet, as shown by Cerezo <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, this approach can lead to inaccurate conclusions, and in turn complicate outbreak investigations even further [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p id="p0040">A recurring theme across the eight papers is the emphasis on screening high-risk patients, such as those in critical care units. However, there is no universally adopted guideline on screening and decolonisation protocols. The lack of international consensus on MRSA screening practices may stem from insufficient scientific evidence regarding the clinical utility and cost-effectiveness of different policies, whether targeted or universal [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Brady et al.</italic> describe a prolonged MRSA outbreak in their cardiothoracic high-dependency unit. Despite national guidelines in Ireland not recommending routine screening of healthcare workers, it was implemented in this case, ultimately revealing that the outbreak was linked to a staff member who was subsequently recolonised [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Advances in diagnostic capabilities now allow for point of care testing (POCT) for MRSA, offering real-time results as an alternative to traditional culture methods. This rapid turnaround time is particularly valuable when results influence isolation precautions and pre-operative antibiotic prophylaxis regimes. However, it's imperative to recognise that its availability depends on local resources, underscoring the inequalities in MRSA management worldwide.</p><p id="p0045">Healthcare settings face daily challenges from competing infection prevention and control (IPC) demands. As new MDROs have emerged, the prioritisation of MRSA-specific measures has declined in some settings. These challenges have been compounded by pressures from infectious diseases like COVID-19 and Mpox alongside a resurgence of vaccine-preventable diseases such as pertussis and measles. Due to the highly communicable nature of these diseases, they take precedence when it comes to IPC efforts. This is also often in the context of healthcare facilities that lack sufficient isolation resources to meet the growing demands of effective infection control.</p><p id="p0050">In 2021, the Healthcare Infection Society and Infection Prevention Society published joint guidelines for the prevention and control of MRSA in healthcare facilities [<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. These guidelines offer a pragmatic approach and acknowledge the variations in local resources and policies that exist. Acknowledging that screening, isolation and IPC measures are not universally accessible, the guidelines provide practical recommendations and offer adaptable advice for resource-limited settings. Importantly, they reinforce key principles such as ensuring that patients receive clear information, advising visitors on hand hygiene practises, and minimising patient transfers to reduce spread. It is crucial for all healthcare workers to be knowledgeable about MRSA, its transmission routes, and effective strategies to mitigate risk for the patients they interact with - a point emphasised by <italic toggle="yes">Roz et al.</italic> in their study conducted in Lebanon [<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Ultimately, these measures emphasise the timeless message that prevention is better than cure and serve as a reminder of the crucial role we all play in safeguarding those under our care. The valuable insights and experiences shared by our colleagues further highlight the importance of continuing to invest in IPC measures, leveraging genomic technologies, and addressing global disparities in MRSA management.</p><sec id="sec1"><title>Funding</title><p id="p0055">SK is supported by the Graham Ayliffe Fellowship of the Healthcare Infection Society. No direct funding was received for this editorial.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0010"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p id="p0060">GW is the Editor in Chief of <italic toggle="yes">Infection Prevention in Practice</italic>. SK is a trainee editor for <italic toggle="yes">Infection Prevention in Practice</italic>. SCL is an Editor of <italic toggle="yes">Infection Prevention in Practice</italic>.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>Christopher JL.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikuta</surname><given-names>Kevin Shunji</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharara</surname><given-names>Fablina</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swetschinski</surname><given-names>Lucien</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>Gisela Robles</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>Authia</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global burden of bacterial antimicrobial resistance in 2019: a systematic analysis</article-title><source>The lancet</source><volume>399</volume><issue>10325</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>655</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)02724-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8841637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35065702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abebe</surname><given-names>Milkias</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alemkere</surname><given-names>Getachew</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayele</surname><given-names>Gizachew</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methicillin and vancomycin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus and associated risk factors among patients with wound infection in East Wallaga Zone, Western Ethiopia</article-title><source>Infection Prevention in Practice</source><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100409</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.infpip.2024.100409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11582734</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39583882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sagiraju</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gopi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diabetes and MRSA Infections: A comparative analysis in an Indian tertiary healthcare setting</article-title><source>Infection Prevention in Practice</source><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.infpip.2024.100372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11176644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38882195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boucher</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>G.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puttagunta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Once-weekly dalbavancin versus daily conventional therapy for skin infection</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>370</volume><issue>23</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>2169</fpage><lpage>2179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24897082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMoa1310480</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harry</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname><given-names>L.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donald</surname><given-names>H.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><collab>Linezolid MRSA Study Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Linezolid versus vancomycin for the treatment of methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus infections</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><volume>34</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>1481</fpage><lpage>1490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12015695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1086/340353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajabi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Afifirad</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omidi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kouhsari</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity of recently approved antibiotics against methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) strains: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Ann Clin Microbiol Antimicrob</source><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>37</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35978400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12941-022-00529-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9382732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maraolo</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giaccone</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gentile</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saracino</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bavaro</surname><given-names>D.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Daptomycin versus vancomycin for the treatment of methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus bloodstream infection with or without endocarditis: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><volume>10</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>1014</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34439067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antibiotics10081014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8389004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sigakis</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Posluszny</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maile</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jewell</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engoren</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is There an Association Between Colonisation of Vancomycin Resistant Enterococci, Methicillin Resistant Staphylococcus Aureus, or Clostridiodes Difficile and Mortality in Sepsis?</article-title><source>Infection Prevention in Practice</source><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100413</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.infpip.2024.100413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11609449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39624778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dewan</surname><given-names>K.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dewan</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Navale</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Svensson</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillinov</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Implications of methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus carriage on cardiac surgical outcomes</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><volume>110</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>776</fpage><lpage>782</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32387036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.athoracsur.2020.03.088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marzec</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bessesen</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk and outcomes of methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) bacteremia among patients admitted with and without MRSA nares colonization</article-title><source>Am J Infect Control</source><volume>44</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27038392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajic.2015.11.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>Holger</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romanos</surname><given-names>Andre</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schiffl</surname><given-names>Helmut</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lederer</surname><given-names>Stephan R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Persistent nasal methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus carriage in hemodialysis outpatients: a predictor of worse outcome</article-title><source>BMC Nephrol</source><volume>14</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23617360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2369-14-93</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3651301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Traynor</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>G.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoban</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Connell</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Successful control of an outbreak of Panton&#8211;Valentine leucocidin positive meticillin resistant Staphylococcus aureus in a National Burns Unit through early detection by whole genome sequencing</article-title><source>Infection Prevention in Practice</source><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100400</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.infpip.2024.100400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11526057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39483423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnsley</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McFall</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suleman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pichon</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emergence and control of an outbreak of PVL-positive MRSA in a UK-based maternity setting</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><volume>149</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38145811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jhin.2023.10.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seth</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tallon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dempsey</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tracy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Emergence and control of an outbreak of infections due to Panton-Valentine leukocidin positive, ST22 methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus in a neonatal intensive care unit</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infection</source><volume>19</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>620</fpage><lpage>627</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2012.03987.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22900572</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coll</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toleman</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blane</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jamrozy</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>N.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic evaluation of phenotypic antibiotic susceptibility patterns as a surrogate for MRSA relatedness and putative transmission during outbreak investigations</article-title><source>Infection Prevention in Practice</source><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100435</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.infpip.2024.100435</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11772957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39877244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borg</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suda</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scicluna</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brincat</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zarb</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Universal admission screening: a potential game-changer in hospitals with high prevalence of MRSA</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><volume>113</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33811962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jhin.2021.03.024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Septimus</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleinman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moody</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hickok</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avery</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Targeted versus universal decolonization to prevent ICU infection</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>368</volume><issue>24</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>2255</fpage><lpage>2265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23718152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMoa1207290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10853913</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>F&#228;tkenheuer</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirschel</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harbarth</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening and isolation to control meticillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus: sense, nonsense, and evidence</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>385</volume><issue>9973</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1146</fpage><lpage>1149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25150745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(14)60660-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Connell</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lenehan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A 4-year outbreak of MRSA ST72-MRSA-IV spa type t1597 in a surgical high dependency unit in Ireland linked to repeated healthcare worker recolonisation</article-title><source>Infection Prevention in Practice</source><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2025</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100421</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.infpip.2024.100421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11647124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39687552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coia</surname><given-names>John E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Jennie A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bak</surname><given-names>Aggie</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsden</surname><given-names>Gemma L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimonovich</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loveday</surname><given-names>H.P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Joint Healthcare Infection Society (HIS) and Infection Prevention Society (IPS) guidelines for the prevention and control of meticillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) in healthcare facilities</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><volume>118</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>S1</fpage><lpage>S39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jhin.2021.09.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34757174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El Roz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaaban</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Issa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ezzeddine</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghssein</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of Methicillin-Resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) knowledge and awareness among healthcare workers in South-Lebanon</article-title><source>Infection Prevention in Practice</source><year>2025</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100451</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.infpip.2025.100451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11907437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40092510</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>