<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">62</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcpsyc</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-244X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11841265</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11841265.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11841265</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11841265</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39972295</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12888-025-06576-y</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">6576</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Association between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms in adults with diagnosed sleep disorders: an analysis of NHANES 2007&#8211;2018 data</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="ZX">Zhong-Xin</given-names></name><address><email>zhangzx7772024@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/032xf8h46</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411203.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0691 2332</institution-id><institution>College of Sports Science, </institution><institution>Kyonggi University, </institution></institution-wrap>Suwon, Gyeonggi Province South Korea </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01thhk923</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412069.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1770 4266</institution-id><institution>College of Sports Science, </institution><institution>Dongshin University, </institution></institution-wrap>Naju, Jeollanam Province South Korea </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>College of Martial Arts, Hebei Sports University, Shijiazhuang, China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478311</issue-id><elocation-id>150</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>19</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>20</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-02-24 09:25:16.247"><day>24</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12888_2025_Article_6576.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Objective</title><p id="Par1">This study aimed to examine the relationship between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms in adults diagnosed with sleep disorders, and to explore the potential of recreational physical activity as a practical intervention to alleviate depressive symptoms.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Data were drawn from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES) between 2007 and 2018, including a cohort of 3,164 adults with diagnosed sleep disorders. Depressive symptoms were measured using the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9), while recreational physical activity was assessed via metabolic equivalents (METs). The association between physical activity and depressive symptoms was evaluated using multiple linear regression and breakpoint regression models, adjusting for covariates such as sex, age, ethnicity, smoking status, and alcohol consumption.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">In the fully adjusted model, participants in the highest quartile of recreational physical activity (Q4) exhibited significantly lower depressive symptom scores (Q4: &#946; = -1.01, 95% CI: -1.58 to -0.44, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0005), indicating that greater physical activity was linked to fewer depressive symptoms. Additional analyses revealed that this inverse relationship was most pronounced for activity levels below 840 MET, which corresponds to approximately 105&#160;min of vigorous recreational physical activity per day or 210&#160;min of moderate-intensity activity per day. The association weakened for activity levels exceeding 840 MET. Subgroup analyses further indicated that the benefits of recreational physical activity were more pronounced in men, individuals aged 40&#8211;60 years, and former smokers.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Higher levels of recreational physical activity were associated with significantly reduced depressive symptoms in adults with sleep disorders. The greatest reductions in depressive symptoms were observed at activity levels below 840 MET, which corresponds to approximately 105&#160;min of vigorous recreational physical activity per day or 210&#160;min of moderate-intensity activity per day. Men, individuals aged 40&#8211;60 years, and former smokers derived the most benefit from these activity levels.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Recreational physical activities</kwd><kwd>Sleep disorder</kwd><kwd>Depressive symptoms</kwd><kwd>NHANES</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par5">Depression is a prevalent mental health condition affecting hundreds of millions globally [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. It profoundly impacts mood, quality of life, and social functioning, and increases the risk of numerous physiological conditions, including cardiovascular disease and metabolic syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The pathogenesis of depression is complex, involving genetic, environmental, and psychological factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].Although current pharmacological and psychotherapeutic interventions have demonstrated efficacy in alleviating depressive symptoms, they often face challenges such as side effects, variability in effectiveness, and high relapse rates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Consequently, the search for alternative, effective, and cost-efficient interventions is of critical importance.</p><p id="Par6">Recreational physical activity has emerged as a promising non-pharmacological intervention, garnering significant attention in recent year. Encompassing activities like walking, jogging, cycling, and swimming [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], recreational physical activity is highly valued for its accessibility and potential mental health benefits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Numerous studies have highlighted its positive impact on depressive symptoms, mediated through mechanisms such as promoting endorphin release, reducing inflammation, and improving sleep quality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Furthermore, recreational physical activity can alleviate depression by reducing anxiety and enhancing overall well-being [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Despite these promising findings, the effectiveness of recreational physical activity in mitigating depressive symptoms specifically in adults with sleep disorders remains unclear.</p><p id="Par7">Individuals with sleep disorders are at an elevated risk for depression, given the significant bidirectional relationship between sleep disturbances and depressive symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Sleep problems not only increase the risk of depression but are also exacerbated by existing depressive symptoms, creating a complex cycle that complicates intervention strategies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Given this interplay, addressing depression in those with sleep disorders presents unique challenges. Recreational physical activity, through its potential to improve sleep quality, regulate physiological rhythms, and promote enjoyment, may offer a beneficial avenue for these individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. However, the specific impact of recreational physical activity on depression in this population remains underexplored, leaving a critical gap in understanding the underlying mechanisms.</p><p id="Par8">This study aims to evaluate the association between recreational physical activity and depression in adults with clinically diagnosed sleep disorders. Through this cross-sectional analysis, we seek to address the existing research gap, provide a scientific basis for mental health intervention strategies targeting this population, and explore the potential of recreational physical activity as an accessible intervention to alleviate depressive symptoms.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Method</title><sec id="FPar1"><title>Ethical approval statement</title><p id="Par9">This study uses data from the NHANES database. All data in this database is fully anonymized before access, and therefore, no additional ethical approval was required. The use of the data complies with the ethical guidelines of the database.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Informed consent statement</title><p id="Par10">As the data used in this study is fully anonymized and no personal identifiers are available, informed consent from participants was not necessary. According to the ethical guidelines of the relevant institutional review board, informed consent was waived for this study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study population</title><p id="Par11">The study utilized data from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES), collected between 2007 and 2018. Initially, a total of 59,842 participants were included. Depressive symptoms were assessed using the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9), and recreational physical activity was quantified using metabolic equivalent (MET) scores. Participants with incomplete data were systematically excluded to optimize the study population. Specifically, 28,383 participants with missing PHQ-9 scores were excluded first, followed by 16,298 participants with missing data on recreational physical activity. Additionally, 11,997 participants without a diagnosis of a sleep disorder were excluded. After applying these exclusion criteria, a total of 3,164 participants were included in the final analyses (see Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> flowchart).</p><p id="Par12">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Flowchart</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e270" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12888_2025_6576_Figa_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Measurement of depression levels</title><p id="Par13">Depression levels were assessed using the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9), a widely used self-report instrument consisting of nine items that evaluate the frequency of depressive symptoms over the past two weeks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Each item is scored from 0 to 3, with 0 representing &#8216;not at all&#8217; and 3 representing &#8216;nearly every day.&#8217; The total score ranges from 0 to 27, with higher scores indicating more severe depressive symptoms. Depression severity was categorized based on the total score as follows: no depression (0&#8211;4), mild depression (5&#8211;9), moderate depression (10&#8211;14), moderately severe depression (15&#8211;19), and severe depression (20&#8211;27). The PHQ-9 has been extensively validated and demonstrates strong reliability and validity for assessing depressive symptoms across diverse populations. In this study, PHQ-9 scores were used to quantify and analyze participants&#8217; depression levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Sleep disorders assessment</title><p id="Par14">Sleep disorders were assessed based on whether participants had ever been informed by a physician that they had sleep problems. Specifically, participants were asked during the NHANES survey if they had ever been told by a doctor that they had trouble sleeping. Those who answered affirmatively were classified as having a diagnosed sleep disorder. In this study, only participants with a physician-confirmed diagnosis of a sleep disorder were included to enable a more focused analysis of the relationship between depressive symptoms and recreational physical activity.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Recreational physical activities Assessment</title><p id="Par15">Recreational physical activity was assessed based on the time participants spent engaging in vigorous and moderate-intensity recreational physical activities. In the NHANES survey, participants were asked to report the number of minutes they engaged in vigorous and moderate-intensity recreational physical activities over the previous 30 days. To calculate the metabolic equivalents (MET) of total recreational physical activity, the time spent in vigorous activity was multiplied by 8 METs, and the time spent in moderate-intensity activity was multiplied by 4 METs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. The metabolic equivalent of 8 METs for vigorous activity reflects the higher energy and oxygen demands of such activities, equivalent to eight times the resting metabolic rate. Similarly, a metabolic equivalent of 4 METs for moderate-intensity activity corresponds to four times the resting metabolic rate, indicating a relatively lower energy expenditure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. This composite MET score was used to quantify participants&#8217; levels of recreational physical activity, facilitating the analysis of its association with depressive symptoms and sleep disturbances.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Assessment of covariates</title><p id="Par16">The following covariates were included in this study to control for their potential confounding effects on the relationship between depressive symptoms and recreational physical activity: gender, age, race, smoking status, alcohol use status, diabetes, hypertension, and body mass index (BMI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p><p id="Par17">Gender was recorded as male or female based on participant self-report. Age was recorded as the participant&#8217;s actual age at the time of the survey. Race was categorized based on participant self-identification as one of five groups: Mexican American, Other Hispanic, Non-Hispanic White, Non-Hispanic Black, and Other Race (including multi-racial). Smoking status was categorized as never smoker, former smoker, or current smoker, based on participants&#8217; self-reports. Alcohol use status was similarly assessed by self-report and categorized as never drinker, former drinker, or current drinker. Diabetes and hypertension were assessed based on whether participants had ever received a physician&#8217;s diagnosis of either condition. Body mass index (BMI) was calculated from participants&#8217; height and weight using the formula BMI&#8201;=&#8201;weight (kg) / height (m)<sup>2</sup>, and used to assess participants&#8217; weight status. Detailed measurement procedures for all variables are available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhanes/">www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhanes/</ext-link>. By adjusting for these covariates, the study aimed to minimize the impact of confounding factors and enhance the accuracy and reliability of the results.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par18">R software was used for all statistical analyses. The study began with a descriptive analysis of the baseline characteristics of the study population. Frequencies and percentages were calculated for categorical variables, while means and standard deviations were reported for continuous variables. To assess the relationship between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms, a multiple linear regression model adjusted for covariates was employed. PHQ-9 scores for depressive symptoms were quartile-transformed prior to analysis to address potential non-normality in the distribution.</p><p id="Par19">To further explore the effects of recreational physical activity, stratified analyses were conducted by gender, age, and ethnicity to evaluate subgroup-specific associations. Additionally, sensitivity analyses were performed to assess the robustness of the results with respect to different covariates. All statistical tests were two-sided, with a significance level set at 0.05.</p><p id="Par20">The study also examined the dose-response relationship between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms using generalized additive modeling (GAM) to capture potential non-linear associations. This approach allowed for a more nuanced understanding of complex relationships between variables. All analyses accounted for the NHANES complex sampling design through appropriate weighting, ensuring the representativeness and accuracy of the findings.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Result</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Baseline situation</title><p id="Par21">A total of 3,164 participants were enrolled in this study, divided into four quartile groups (Q1-Q4) based on their metabolic equivalent of recreational physical activity (MET) scores. Demographic and health characteristics across quartile groups are presented in Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The baseline characteristics indicated a gradual decrease in participants&#8217; age with increasing MET scores (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001), with mean ages of 56.11, 53.16, 48.89, and 43.49 years for quartiles Q1 to Q4, respectively. The poverty income ratio (PIR) also increased with rising MET levels, with PIR values of 2.39, 2.94, 2.90, and 2.94 for Q1 to Q4, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001). Body mass index (BMI) progressively decreased across quartile groups, from 30.85&#160;kg/m&#178; in Q1 to 28.68&#160;kg/m&#178; in Q4 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001). The proportion of males increased significantly with higher levels of recreational physical activity, from 35.81% in Q1 to 59.20% in Q4 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001). The racial distribution remained relatively consistent across quartile groups, predominantly composed of non-Hispanic White participants, with proportions of 50.13%, 56.26%, 52.08%, and 49.09% in Q1 to Q4, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.181).</p><p id="Par22">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of study population</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MET</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q1</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q2</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q3</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q4</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">391</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">727</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1225</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">821</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age(years)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.11&#8201;&#177;&#8201;16.48</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.16&#8201;&#177;&#8201;16.32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.89&#8201;&#177;&#8201;16.77</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.49&#8201;&#177;&#8201;17.24</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PIR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.39&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.94&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.62</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.90&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.69</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.94&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.72</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BMI, (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.85&#8201;&#177;&#8201;7.67</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.21&#8201;&#177;&#8201;7.64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.65&#8201;&#177;&#8201;7.32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.68&#8201;&#177;&#8201;6.99</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gender</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">140 (35.81%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">257 (35.35%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">542 (44.24%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">486 (59.20%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">251 (64.19%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">470 (64.65%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">683 (55.76%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">335 (40.80%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.181</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Mexican American</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41 (10.49%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56 (7.70%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">126 (10.29%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84 (10.23%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Other Hispanic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (10.74%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54 (7.43%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92 (7.51%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75 (9.14%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Non-Hispanic White</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">196 (50.13%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">409 (56.26%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">638 (52.08%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">403 (49.09%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Non-Hispanic Black</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74 (18.93%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">134 (18.43%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">250 (20.41%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">163 (19.85%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other Race - Including Multi-Racial</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38 (9.72%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74 (10.18%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">119 (9.71%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96 (11.69%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Education level</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Less than 9th grade</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36 (9.38%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (4.36%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (4.09%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (2.84%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;9-11th grade</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46 (11.98%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 (6.61%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 (7.34%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68 (8.79%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High school graduate/GED or equivalent</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92 (23.96%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">137 (19.27%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">242 (20.18%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">149 (19.25%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Some college or AA degree</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">132 (34.38%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">273 (38.40%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">412 (34.36%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">273 (35.27%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;College graduate or above</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78 (20.31%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">223 (31.36%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">408 (34.03%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">262 (33.85%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Marital status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Married</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">176 (45.83%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">372 (52.32%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">594 (49.54%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">356 (45.99%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Widowed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59 (15.36%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63 (8.86%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69 (5.75%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 (4.52%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Divorced</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60 (15.62%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96 (13.50%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">190 (15.85%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91 (11.76%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Separated</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (4.43%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38 (5.34%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36 (3.00%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (2.45%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Never married</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (12.76%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98 (13.78%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">208 (17.35%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">201 (25.97%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Living with partner</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (5.99%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (5.91%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102 (8.51%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71 (9.17%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Never smoking</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">183 (46.80%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">377 (51.86%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">640 (52.24%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">418 (50.91%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Former smoking</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">122 (31.20%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">223 (30.67%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">336 (27.43%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">190 (23.14%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Current smoking</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86 (21.99%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">127 (17.47%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">249 (20.33%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">213 (25.94%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alcohol status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Never drinking</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (12.53%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81 (11.14%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102 (8.33%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48 (5.85%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Former drinker</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46 (11.76%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66 (9.08%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100 (8.16%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (5.12%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Current drinker</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">296 (75.70%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">580 (79.78%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1023 (83.51%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">731 (89.04%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cardiovascular disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.877</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78 (19.95%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100 (13.76%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">133 (10.86%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71 (8.65%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">313 (80.05%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">627 (86.24%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1092 (89.14%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">750 (91.35%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High blood pressure</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">214 (54.73%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">341 (46.91%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">496 (40.49%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">283 (34.47%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">176 (45.01%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">386 (53.09%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">727 (59.35%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">537 (65.41%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diabetes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81 (20.72%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">124 (17.06%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">155 (12.65%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61 (7.43%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">294 (75.19%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">582 (80.06%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1025 (83.67%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">740 (90.13%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviations: BMI, body mass index; PHQ-9, Patient Health Questionnaire-9</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par23">There was a trend towards higher educational attainment across quartile groups, with the proportion of participants holding a university degree or higher increasing from 20.31% in Q1 to 33.85% in Q4 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001). The proportion of unmarried participants varied slightly across quartiles, with 25.97% in Q4 compared to 12.76% in Q1 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001). The proportion of never smokers increased with rising MET levels, with 46.80%, 51.86%, 52.24%, and 50.91% in Q1 to Q4, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001). Similarly, the proportion of current drinkers rose from 75.70% in Q1 to 89.04% in Q4 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001).The prevalence of cardiovascular disease decreased gradually from 19.95% in Q1 to 8.65% in Q4 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.877). The prevalence of hypertension and diabetes mellitus also showed significant declines with increasing MET levels, with hypertension decreasing from 54.73% in Q1 to 34.47% in Q4 and diabetes mellitus from 20.72% in Q1 to 7.43% in Q4 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001).</p><p id="Par24">Overall, baseline characteristics revealed notable improvements in health indicators with increasing levels of recreational physical activity, including lower age, reduced BMI, and decreased prevalence of cardiovascular disease, hypertension, and diabetes. These findings suggest that higher levels of recreational physical activity may be associated with multiple health benefits.</p></sec><sec id="Sec901"><title>Association between recreational activities and Depressive symptoms in adults with diagnosed sleep disorders</title><p id="Par25">The present study further analyzed the relationship between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms in adults diagnosed with sleep disorders. Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> presents the effects of different levels of recreational physical activity (Q1-Q4) on depressive symptoms across the unadjusted, adjusted I, and adjusted II models.</p><p id="Par26">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The association between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms in adults with diagnosed Sleep disorders</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q1</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q2&#946; (95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q3&#946; (95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q4&#946; (95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-adjusted</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.51 (-1.08, 0.07) <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0869</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.86 (-1.40, -0.31) <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0020</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-1.01 (-1.57, -0.44) <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adjust I</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.50 (-1.07, 0.07) <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0854</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-1.07 (-1.61, -0.53) <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-1.36 (-1.93, -0.79) <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adjust II</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.19 (-0.75, 0.37) <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.5043</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.73 (-1.27, -0.20) <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0073</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-1.01 (-1.58, -0.44) <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0005</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Adjust I, Adjusted for Gender, Age and Race;</p><p>Adjust II, Adjusted for Gender, Age, Race, High blood pressure, Diabetes, BMI, Smoking status, Alcohol status</p><p>Note: &#8220;Ref&#8221; refers to Q1 (first quartile) group, with Q2, Q3, and Q4 representing second, third, and fourth quartiles, respectively. These quartiles are used as reference categories for comparison in the analysis</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par27">In the unadjusted model, higher quartiles of recreational physical activity (Q3 and Q4) were significantly associated with lower depressive symptom scores compared to the lowest quartile (Q1) (Q3: &#946; = -0.86, 95% CI: -1.40, -0.31, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0020; Q4: &#946; = -1.01, 95% CI: -1.57, -0.44, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0005), suggesting that greater engagement in recreational physical activity was linked to fewer depressive symptoms. The association between the second quartile (Q2) and depressive symptoms did not reach statistical significance (&#946; = -0.51, 95% CI: -1.08, 0.07, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0869). The association between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms remained significant in quartiles Q3 and Q4 in the adjusted I model (adjusted for gender, age, and ethnicity) (Q3: &#946; = -1.07, 95% CI: -1.61, -0.53, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0001; Q4: &#946; = -1.36, 95% CI: -1.93, -0.79, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), while the association for Q2 did not reach statistical significance (&#946; = -0.50, 95% CI: -1.07, 0.07, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0854).</p><p id="Par28">In the adjusted II model (further adjusted for hypertension, diabetes, BMI, smoking status, and alcohol consumption), the negative associations between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms remained significant for Q3 and Q4 (Q3: &#946; = -0.73, 95% CI: -1.27, -0.20, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0073; Q4: &#946; = -1.01, 95% CI: -1.58, -0.44, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0005), while the association for Q2 remained non-significant (&#946; = -0.19, 95% CI: -0.75, 0.37, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.5043)</p><p id="Par29">Overall, the findings indicate that higher levels of recreational physical activity, particularly in the third and fourth quartiles, were significantly associated with lower depressive symptom scores among adults with sleep disorders, even after adjusting for multiple covariates. This suggests a robust relationship between recreational physical activity and reduced depressive symptoms in this population.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Analysis of the non-linear relationship between MET and PHQ-9 depressive symptoms</title><p id="Par30">To further understand the non-linear relationship between recreational physical activity (measured in metabolic equivalents, MET) and depressive symptoms (PHQ-9 scores), breakpoint regression analyses were conducted. Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> presents the results of the breakpoint regression model for MET on PHQ-9 scores, and the fitted curve between MET and PHQ-9 scores is shown in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.</p><p id="Par31">In Model I, the linear effect of recreational physical activity was significant (&#946; = -0.00, 95% CI: -0.00, -0.00, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0046), indicating that recreational physical activity was significantly associated with lower depressive symptoms, albeit with a modest effect size. In Model II, a breakpoint was identified (K&#8201;=&#8201;840), before and after which the effect of recreational physical activity on depressive symptoms differed significantly.</p><p id="Par32">
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Breakpoint regression analysis of MET on PHQ-9</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#946; (95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model I: Linear Effect</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.00 (-0.00, -0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0046</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model II: Breakpoint (K)</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">840</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; K Segment Effect</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.00 (-0.00, -0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt; K Segment Effect</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00 (-0.00, 0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0849</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Difference between 2 segments</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00 (0.00, 0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Log-likelihood test for the</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">3.67 (3.30, 4.03)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par33">
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>The fitted curve between MET and PHQ-9 scores</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1135" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12888_2025_6576_Figb_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par34">Specifically, when MET was below the breakpoint (K&#8201;=&#8201;840), there was a significant negative association between recreational physical activity and PHQ-9 scores (&#946; = -0.00, 95% CI: -0.00, -0.00, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), In contrast, this negative association was significantly attenuated once MET exceeded the breakpoint (&#946;&#8201;=&#8201;0.00, 95% CI: -0.00, 0.00, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0849) and did not reach statistical significance. The difference between the two zones, before and after the breakpoint, was significant (difference &#946;&#8201;=&#8201;0.00, 95% CI: 0.00, 0.00, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0003). This finding further supports the non-linear relationship between MET and PHQ-9 scores. The log-likelihood ratio test results (3.67, 95% CI: 3.30, 4.03, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001) indicated that the breakpoint model provided a better fit for explaining the relationship between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms compared to a simple linear model.</p><p id="Par35">The phenomenon of &#946;&#8201;=&#8201;0 but statistically significant warrants further clarification, as several factors contribute to this observation. In large datasets such as NHANES, even very small effects can become statistically significant due to the increased statistical power derived from the large sample size. While the effect size may appear negligible, the high power of the analysis allows for the detection of small effects. Additionally, the breakpoint regression analysis reveals a non-linear relationship between physical activity and depressive symptoms. At lower levels of activity, there is a measurable effect, but once the activity level surpasses a certain threshold, the effect diminishes, likely due to diminishing returns at higher activity levels. The log-likelihood ratio test (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001) further confirms that the breakpoint model fits the data better than a linear model, reinforcing the non-linear nature of the relationship between physical activity and depressive symptoms. In summary, although the regression coefficients may seem small or even close to zero, their statistical significance should not be overlooked. These findings underscore the complexity of the relationship between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms, with the breakpoint model offering a more nuanced understanding of how different levels of activity influence mental health outcomes.</p><p id="Par36">In summary, the relationship between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms exhibits a complex, non-linear pattern. At activity levels below 840 MET, increases in recreational physical activity appear to be effective in alleviating depressive symptoms. However, when activity levels exceed 840 MET, the marginal benefits diminish significantly. These findings suggest that moderate levels of recreational physical activity may represent the most effective strategy for reducing depressive symptoms.</p></sec><sec id="Sec908"><title>Subgroup analyses and interaction tests</title><p id="Par37">Subgroup analyses and interaction tests were conducted to assess the impact of demographic and health characteristics on the association between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p><p id="Par38">
<table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Subgroup analysis of the association between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms in Diagnosed Sleep disorders</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Character</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Crude</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model II</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<sub>interaction</sub>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gender</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0841</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.0006 (-0.0011, -0.0001)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0105</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0000 (-0.0005, 0.0006)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8769</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5074</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Mexican American</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0005 (-0.0013, 0.0023)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6203</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Other Hispanic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.0002 (-0.0020, 0.0017)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8687</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Non-Hispanic White</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.0007 (-0.0011, -0.0002)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0020</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Non-Hispanic Black</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.0007 (-0.0019, 0.0005)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2520</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other Race - Including Multi-Racial</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0004 (-0.0011, 0.0018)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6256</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1052</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;&lt;&#8201;40</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.0002 (-0.0007, 0.0004)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5790</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;&gt;=40, &lt;&#8201;60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.0010 (-0.0017, -0.0004)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0013</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;&gt;=60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.0005 (-0.0012, 0.0003)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2055</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alcohol status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6010</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Never drinking</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0001 (-0.0021, 0.0022)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9559</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Former drinker</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0001 (-0.0015, 0.0018)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8609</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Current drinker</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.0006 (-0.0010, -0.0002)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0030</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.0442</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Never smoking</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.0001 (-0.0006, 0.0005)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7690</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Former smoking</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.0012 (-0.0018, -0.0005)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Current smoking</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.0005 (-0.0012, 0.0003)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2095</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BMI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3652</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;&lt;&#8201;25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.0006 (-0.0012, 0.0001)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0785</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;&gt;=25, &lt;&#8201;30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.0002 (-0.0008, 0.0005)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6079</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;&gt;=30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.0008 (-0.0014, -0.0002)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0092</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diabetes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8111</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.0005 (-0.0018, 0.0008)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4409</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.0005 (-0.0009, -0.0001)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0116</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High blood pressure</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7306</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.0004 (-0.0011, 0.0002)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1735</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.0006 (-0.0010, -0.0001)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0140</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Adjust II, Adjusted for Gender, Age, Race, High blood pressure, Diabetes, BMI, Smoking status, Alcohol status</p><p>Note: &#8220;Ref&#8221; refers to the reference group in the Crude model, with all other subgroups being compared to this group in the analysis</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par39">In terms of gender, the inverse relationship between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms was statistically significant in men (&#946; = -0.0006, 95% CI: -0.0011, -0.0001, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0105), but not in women (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.8769). The interaction <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value for gender was 0.0841, suggesting that gender differences may carry some statistical significance. When examining race, the strongest negative association was observed among non-Hispanic whites (&#946; = -0.0007, 95% CI: -0.0011, -0.0002, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0020), with no significant associations detected in other racial groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05). The interaction <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value of 0.5074 indicates a non-significant difference between races. Age-related analyses revealed that recreational physical activity was most strongly associated with a reduction in depressive symptoms in participants aged 40&#8211;60 years (&#946; = -0.0010, 95% CI: -0.0017, -0.0004, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0013). No significant associations were found in other age groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05), with the interaction <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value for age standing at 0.1052.</p><p id="Par40">Regarding alcohol consumption, current drinkers showed a significant inverse association between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms (&#946; = -0.0006, 95% CI: -0.0010, -0.0002, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0030), although the interaction <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value of 0.6010 suggests that drinking status did not significantly modulate this relationship. In terms of smoking status, the strongest negative association was seen in former smokers (&#946; = -0.0012, 95% CI: -0.0018, -0.0005, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0005), with no significant effects observed in never smokers or current smokers (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05). The interaction <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value for smoking status was 0.0442, indicating a statistically significant moderating effect. With respect to BMI, recreational physical activity was significantly associated with lower depressive symptoms in individuals with a BMI&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;30 (&#946; = -0.0008, 95% CI: -0.0014, -0.0002, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0092), while no significant associations were detected in participants with lower BMI values (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05). The interaction <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value for BMI was 0.3652.</p><p id="Par41">Overall, these subgroup analyses demonstrate that the effects of recreational physical activity on depressive symptoms vary across populations with different characteristics. In particular, more significant associations were observed in men, individuals aged 40&#8211;60, and former smokers. Interaction tests further suggest that sex, age, and smoking status may influence the relationship between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms to a certain degree.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par42">The findings of this study reveal a significant negative association between higher levels of recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms, characterized by complex nonlinear dynamics. Increases in recreational physical activity were significantly linked to reductions in depressive symptoms at activity levels below 840 MET, while this negative association was notably attenuated at levels exceeding 840 MET. Subgroup analyses further highlighted heterogeneity in this relationship across sex, age, ethnicity, alcohol consumption, and smoking status, suggesting that certain populations&#8212;particularly men, individuals aged 40&#8211;60 years, and former smokers&#8212;may derive greater benefits from recreational physical activity.</p><p id="Par43">In comparison to previous research on the relationship between recreational physical activity and mental health, this study uniquely focuses on adults with sleep disorders. This aligns with prior work, including meta-analysis by Matthew Pearce and Francesco Recchia, which reported that regular physical activity significantly alleviated depressive symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. However, the present study extends these findings by identifying a differential impact of activity levels on depressive symptoms using a breakpoint regression model. This non-linear effect suggests that moderate levels of recreational activity may offer the most benefit in reducing depressive symptoms, while higher activity levels may confer diminishing returns, consistent with the observations of Paluska and Paolucci regarding the relationship between physical activity and mental health outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p><p id="Par44">Consistent with the findings of Eunjung Lim and Laia Maynou on the influence of demographic characteristics, the present study&#8217;s subgroup analyses revealed that recreational physical activity has varying effects across specific populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. In particular, males, individuals aged 40&#8211;60, and those with a history of smoking appeared to benefit more significantly from recreational physical activity. This aligns with previous research highlighting the role of lifestyle factors in physical activity outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], particularly among middle-aged men. Notably, the mental health benefits of physical activity were more pronounced in individuals with sleep disturbances, further emphasizing the relevance and applicability of recreational physical activity in these populations.</p><p id="Par45">In summary, by examining both the non-linear relationship between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms and its differential effects across subgroups, this study offers new insights into developing targeted mental health interventions for adults with sleep disorders. To maximize the positive impact on mental health, future interventions should focus on promoting moderate levels of activity while accounting for individual factors such as gender, age, and lifestyle.</p><p id="Par46">The mechanisms by which recreational physical activity alleviates depressive symptoms in adults with sleep disorders are not yet fully understood, though several physiological and psychological pathways may contribute to this association. First, recreational physical activity may enhance mood and alleviate depressive symptoms by increasing levels of endorphins and dopamine&#8212;neurotransmitters critical to feelings of pleasure and reward [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Moderate physical activity is known to stimulate the release of these neurotransmitters, resulting in an antidepressant effect.</p><p id="Par47">Second, physical activity may indirectly reduce depressive symptoms by improving sleep quality. Research highlights a significant bidirectional relationship between sleep disturbances and depressive symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Recreational physical activity can help regulate physiological rhythms, shorten sleep onset latency, and increase the duration of deep sleep. These improvements in sleep quality are particularly valuable for individuals with sleep disorders, as better sleep can mitigate depressive symptoms driven by chronic sleep deprivation. Additionally, recreational physical activity may exert its beneficial effects by reducing inflammation and modulating the stress response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Sleep disorders are often associated with chronic inflammation and heightened stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], and physical activity has been shown to lower pro-inflammatory markers and reduce cortisol levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. These anti-inflammatory and stress-reducing effects can contribute to improved mental health.</p><p id="Par48">Finally, the social and psychological aspects of recreational physical activity should not be overlooked [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Participation in such activities often involves social interaction, which can provide valuable psychological support and emotional connection for individuals with sleep disorders. This social engagement helps reduce feelings of isolation and depression, fostering psychological resilience. Thus, recreational physical activity is not only a means of exercise but also a pathway to social support and mental well-being.</p><p id="Par49">This study possesses several notable strengths. First, the large sample size derived from the nationally representative NHANES database enhances the generalizability and representativeness of the findings. Second, the use of a breakpoint regression model offers a novel approach to capturing the nonlinear relationship between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms, allowing for a more nuanced understanding of how different activity levels influence mental health outcomes. Additionally, the detailed subgroup analyses provide valuable insights into the heterogeneity of this relationship across various demographic characteristics, laying the groundwork for the development of individualized intervention strategies.</p><p id="Par50">This study has several limitations. First, both depressive symptoms and recreational physical activity were self-reported, which may introduce recall and social desirability biases, potentially affecting the accuracy of the data. While self-reported measures are commonly used in large-scale epidemiological studies like NHANES and have been validated in similar cohorts, these biases could either underestimate or overestimate the observed associations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. To strengthen the findings, future research could incorporate more objective measures, such as activity trackers or clinical assessments. Additionally, as a secondary analysis of the NHANES dataset, this study is susceptible to the risk of false positives due to multiple testing. The large number of statistical comparisons increases the likelihood of Type I errors, and although confounders were adjusted for, no formal correction for multiple testing was applied. Future research should address this limitation by applying appropriate statistical corrections or adopting prospective study designs to further validate the results. Furthermore, the cross-sectional nature of the study prevents causal inferences. Although the study suggests an association between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms, it cannot establish causality, and the observed relationship may be influenced by reverse causality. The lack of longitudinal data limits the ability to assess the directionality of this relationship. To better understand causal pathways, future studies should employ longitudinal designs and aim to identify whether increasing physical activity can serve as a preventive or therapeutic intervention for depressive symptoms, particularly in individuals with sleep disorders.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par51">This study demonstrates a significant inverse association between recreational physical activity and depressive symptoms in adults with sleep disorders, with the effect being particularly strong at higher levels of activity. Recreational physical activity shows promise as a non-pharmacological intervention for alleviating depressive symptoms in this population. By leveraging the large NHANES database and employing innovative methods such as breakpoint regression and smoothed curve analyses, we quantified the non-linear relationship between physical activity and depressive symptoms. Our findings suggest that higher levels of recreational physical activity, up to approximately 105&#160;min of vigorous activity per day (or 210&#160;min of moderate-intensity activity per day), are associated with reduced depressive symptoms, offering preliminary recommendations for moderate activity levels. This insight paves the way for developing interventions tailored to the needs of different demographic groups.</p><p id="Par52">Subgroup analyses further revealed that the benefits of recreational physical activity were more pronounced among men, middle-aged adults (aged 40&#8211;60), and former smokers. These findings highlight the importance of personalizing interventions based on gender, age, and lifestyle to enhance the effectiveness of mental health strategies. In addition to mitigating depressive symptoms, recreational physical activity may enhance overall mental health in patients with sleep disorders by improving sleep quality, reducing inflammation, and modulating stress responses.</p><p id="Par53">However, due to the cross-sectional nature of this study, a causal relationship could not be definitively established. Future research should adopt longitudinal designs to explore the long-term effects of recreational physical activity on depressive symptoms while accounting for potential confounders, such as diet and life stress. Moreover, as this study relied on self-reported data, future studies should aim to validate these findings using more objective measures.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#8217;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Zheng Zhang: Conceptualization, Data Collection, Writing &#8211; Original Draft. Zheng Tang: Methodology, Data Analysis, Writing &#8211; Review &amp; Editing. Zhong-Xin Zhang: Supervision, Writing &#8211; Review &amp; Editing.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>No Funding.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets used in this study are publicly available from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES) database. The data can be accessed at: https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhanes/index.htm.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par54">Not Applicable. No identifiable personal data or images are presented in this study.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par55">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><notes id="FPar7"><title>Clinical trial number</title><p id="Par56">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar8"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par57">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar9" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par58">We declare that we have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The costs of depression</article-title><source>Psychiatr Clin North Am</source><year>2012</year><volume>35</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psc.2011.11.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22370487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3292769</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Kessler RC. The costs of depression. Psychiatr Clin North Am. 2012;35(1):1&#8211;14.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22370487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.psc.2011.11.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3292769</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Depression and cardiovascular disease in elderly: current understanding</article-title><source>J Clin Neurosci</source><year>2018</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jocn.2017.09.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29066229</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Zhang Y, Chen Y, Ma L. Depression and cardiovascular disease in elderly: current understanding. J Clin Neurosci. 2018;47:1&#8211;5.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29066229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jocn.2017.09.022</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kessing LV. Epidemiology of subtypes of depression. Acta Psychiatr Scand Suppl 2007(433):85&#8211;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1600-0447.2007.00966.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17280574</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seiffge-Krenke</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[Depression in children and adolescents: prevalence, diagnosis, etiology, gender differences and therapeutic approaches]</article-title><source>Prax Kinderpsychol Kinderpsychiatr</source><year>2007</year><volume>56</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.13109/prkk.2007.56.3.185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17451150</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Seiffge-Krenke I. [Depression in children and adolescents: prevalence, diagnosis, etiology, gender differences and therapeutic approaches]. Prax Kinderpsychol Kinderpsychiatr. 2007;56(3):185&#8211;205.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17451150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.13109/prkk.2007.56.3.185</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dudek</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dion-Albert</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuck</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lebel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurobiology of resilience in depression: immune and vascular insights from human and animal studies</article-title><source>Eur J Neurosci</source><year>2021</year><volume>53</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ejn.14547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31421056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7891571</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Dudek KA, Dion-Albert L, Kaufmann FN, Tuck E, Lebel M, Menard C. Neurobiology of resilience in depression: immune and vascular insights from human and animal studies. Eur J Neurosci. 2021;53(1):183&#8211;221.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31421056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/ejn.14547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7891571</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Card&#243; Vila</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez Gonz&#225;lez</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sumalla G&#243;mez EC: [Depression. 2. Treatment and nursing interventions]</article-title><source>Rev Enferm</source><year>2000</year><volume>23</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10909363</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Card&#243; Vila G, Gonz&#225;lez Gonz&#225;lez MC. Sumalla G&#243;mez EC: [Depression. 2. Treatment and nursing interventions]. Rev Enferm. 2000;23(5):337&#8211;42.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10909363</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McQuillan</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[Psychotherapy of the child and adolescent with depression]</article-title><source>Bol Asoc Med P R</source><year>2003</year><volume>95</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14584456</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">McQuillan CT. [Psychotherapy of the child and adolescent with depression]. Bol Asoc Med P R. 2003;95(3):21&#8211;8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14584456</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Watt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laugharne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complementary and alternative medicine in the treatment of anxiety and depression</article-title><source>Curr Opin Psychiatry</source><year>2008</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/YCO.0b013e3282f2d814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18281839</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">van der Watt G, Laugharne J, Janca A. Complementary and alternative medicine in the treatment of anxiety and depression. Curr Opin Psychiatry. 2008;21(1):37&#8211;42.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18281839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/YCO.0b013e3282f2d814</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Epel</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stress, eating and the reward system</article-title><source>Physiol Behav</source><year>2007</year><volume>91</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physbeh.2007.04.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17543357</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Adam TC, Epel ES. Stress, eating and the reward system. Physiol Behav. 2007;91(4):449&#8211;58.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17543357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.physbeh.2007.04.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Depledge</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recreational physical activity in natural environments and implications for health: a population based cross-sectional study in England</article-title><source>Prev Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ypmed.2016.08.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27658650</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">White MP, Elliott LR, Taylor T, Wheeler BW, Spencer A, Bone A, Depledge MH, Fleming LE. Recreational physical activity in natural environments and implications for health: a population based cross-sectional study in England. Prev Med. 2016;91:383&#8211;8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27658650</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ypmed.2016.08.023</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>FTT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwan</surname><given-names>JLY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeoh</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sport and recreational physical activities attenuate the Predictive Association of Multimorbidity with increased geriatric depressive symptoms: a 14-Year Follow-Up study of Community-Dwelling older adults</article-title><source>J Aging Phys Act</source><year>2022</year><volume>30</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>252</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/japa.2021-0070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34294608</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Liang Y, Lai FTT, Kwan JLY, Chan W, Yeoh EK. Sport and recreational physical activities attenuate the Predictive Association of Multimorbidity with increased geriatric depressive symptoms: a 14-Year Follow-Up study of Community-Dwelling older adults. J Aging Phys Act. 2022;30(2):252&#8211;60.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34294608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1123/japa.2021-0070</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleppang</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thurston</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagquist</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The association between physical activity and symptoms of depression in different contexts - a cross-sectional study of Norwegian adolescents</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1368</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-018-6257-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30541522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6292029</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Kleppang AL, Hartz I, Thurston M, Hagquist C. The association between physical activity and symptoms of depression in different contexts - a cross-sectional study of Norwegian adolescents. BMC Public Health. 2018;18(1):1368.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30541522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12889-018-6257-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6292029</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Neil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coulson</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schweitzer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lifestyle medicine for depression</article-title><source>BMC Psychiatry</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>107</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-244X-14-107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24721040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3998225</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Sarris J, O&#8217;Neil A, Coulson CE, Schweitzer I, Berk M. Lifestyle medicine for depression. BMC Psychiatry. 2014;14:107.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24721040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-244X-14-107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3998225</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corcoran</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Regan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keeley</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wasserman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadlaczky</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarchiapone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Physical activity in European adolescents and associations with anxiety, depression and well-being</article-title><source>Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source><year>2017</year><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00787-016-0875-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27277894</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">McMahon EM, Corcoran P, O&#8217;Regan G, Keeley H, Cannon M, Carli V, Wasserman C, Hadlaczky G, Sarchiapone M, Apter A, et al. Physical activity in European adolescents and associations with anxiety, depression and well-being. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2017;26(1):111&#8211;22.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27277894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00787-016-0875-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Depression in sleep disturbance: a review on a bidirectional relationship, mechanisms and treatment</article-title><source>J Cell Mol Med</source><year>2019</year><volume>23</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>2324</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcmm.14170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30734486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6433686</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Fang H, Tu S, Sheng J, Shao A. Depression in sleep disturbance: a review on a bidirectional relationship, mechanisms and treatment. J Cell Mol Med. 2019;23(4):2324&#8211;32.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30734486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jcmm.14170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6433686</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandi-Perumal</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monti</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karthikeyan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>BaHammam</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Narashimhan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clarifying the role of sleep in depression: a narrative review</article-title><source>Psychiatry Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>291</volume><fpage>113239</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32593854</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Pandi-Perumal SR, Monti JM, Burman D, Karthikeyan R, BaHammam AS, Spence DW, Brown GM, Narashimhan M. Clarifying the role of sleep in depression: a narrative review. Psychiatry Res. 2020;291:113239.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32593854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113239</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sejbuk M, Miro&#324;czuk-Chodakowska I, Witkowska AM. Sleep quality: a narrative review on Nutrition, stimulants, and physical activity as important factors. Nutrients 2022, 14(9).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/nu14091912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9103473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35565879</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kredlow</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Capozzoli</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hearon</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calkins</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of physical activity on sleep: a meta-analytic review</article-title><source>J Behav Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>38</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10865-015-9617-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25596964</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Kredlow MA, Capozzoli MC, Hearon BA, Calkins AW, Otto MW. The effects of physical activity on sleep: a meta-analytic review. J Behav Med. 2015;38(3):427&#8211;49.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25596964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10865-015-9617-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strain</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuch</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Golubic</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Utukuri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association between Physical Activity and Risk of Depression: a systematic review and Meta-analysis</article-title><source>JAMA Psychiatry</source><year>2022</year><volume>79</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>550</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2022.0609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35416941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9008579</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Pearce M, Garcia L, Abbas A, Strain T, Schuch FB, Golubic R, Kelly P, Khan S, Utukuri M, Laird Y, et al. Association between Physical Activity and Risk of Depression: a systematic review and Meta-analysis. JAMA Psychiatry. 2022;79(6):550&#8211;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35416941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2022.0609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9008579</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Recchia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernal</surname><given-names>JDK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>SHS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>DKC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Capio</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>CCW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>SWS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sit</surname><given-names>CHP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Physical activity interventions to alleviate depressive symptoms in children and adolescents: a systematic review and Meta-analysis</article-title><source>JAMA Pediatr</source><year>2023</year><volume>177</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2022.5090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36595284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9857695</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Recchia F, Bernal JDK, Fong DY, Wong SHS, Chung PK, Chan DKC, Capio CM, Yu CCW, Wong SWS, Sit CHP, et al. Physical activity interventions to alleviate depressive symptoms in children and adolescents: a systematic review and Meta-analysis. JAMA Pediatr. 2023;177(2):132&#8211;40.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36595284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2022.5090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9857695</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paolucci</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loukov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowdish</surname><given-names>DME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heisz</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exercise reduces depression and inflammation but intensity matters</article-title><source>Biol Psychol</source><year>2018</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsycho.2018.01.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29408464</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Paolucci EM, Loukov D, Bowdish DME, Heisz JJ. Exercise reduces depression and inflammation but intensity matters. Biol Psychol. 2018;133:79&#8211;84.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29408464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biopsycho.2018.01.015</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paluska</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwenk</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physical activity and mental health: current concepts</article-title><source>Sports Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>29</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00007256-200029030-00003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10739267</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Paluska SA, Schwenk TL. Physical activity and mental health: current concepts. Sports Med. 2000;29(3):167&#8211;80.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10739267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2165/00007256-200029030-00003</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Association of Race/Ethnicity, Dietary Intake, and physical activity with Depression</article-title><source>J Racial Ethn Health Disparities</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40615-020-00784-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32488824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7708411</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Lim E, Davis J, Chen JJ. The Association of Race/Ethnicity, Dietary Intake, and physical activity with Depression. J Racial Ethn Health Disparities. 2021;8(2):315&#8211;31.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32488824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40615-020-00784-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7708411</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Maynou L, Hern&#225;ndez-Pizarro HM, Errea Rodr&#237;guez M. The Association of Physical (in)activity with Mental Health. Differences between elder and younger populations: a systematic literature review. Int J Environ Res Public Health 2021, 18(9).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph18094771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8124550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33947122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kandola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashdown-Franks</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hendrikse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabiston</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stubbs</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physical activity and depression: towards understanding the antidepressant mechanisms of physical activity</article-title><source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source><year>2019</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2019.09.040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31586447</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Kandola A, Ashdown-Franks G, Hendrikse J, Sabiston CM, Stubbs B. Physical activity and depression: towards understanding the antidepressant mechanisms of physical activity. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 2019;107:525&#8211;39.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31586447</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2019.09.040</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gyasi</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quansah</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boateng</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akomeah</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yakubu</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahiabli</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aikins</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Owusu-Sarpong</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dumbe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nimoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Meeting the WHO Physical Activity guidelines is Associated with Lower odds of Depression in older adults: potential psychosomatic mechanisms</article-title><source>Am J Geriatr Psychiatry</source><year>2024</year><volume>32</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1105</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jagp.2024.04.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38641509</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Gyasi RM, Quansah N, Boateng PA, Akomeah E, Yakubu AF, Ahiabli PA, Aikins E, Owusu-Sarpong OJ, Dumbe Y, Nimoh M, et al. Meeting the WHO Physical Activity guidelines is Associated with Lower odds of Depression in older adults: potential psychosomatic mechanisms. Am J Geriatr Psychiatry. 2024;32(9):1105&#8211;18.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38641509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jagp.2024.04.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sleep disturbances in Depression</article-title><source>Sleep Med Clin</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsmc.2014.11.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26055669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5678925</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Murphy MJ, Peterson MJ. Sleep disturbances in Depression. Sleep Med Clin. 2015;10(1):17&#8211;23.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26055669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jsmc.2014.11.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5678925</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">El Assar M, &#193;lvarez-Bustos A, Sosa P, Angulo J, Rodr&#237;guez-Ma&#241;as L. Effect of Physical Activity/Exercise on oxidative stress and inflammation in muscle and vascular aging. Int J Mol Sci 2022, 23(15).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms23158713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9369066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35955849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olmstead</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sleep disturbance, Sleep Duration, and inflammation: a systematic review and Meta-analysis of Cohort studies and experimental sleep deprivation</article-title><source>Biol Psychiatry</source><year>2016</year><volume>80</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.05.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26140821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4666828</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Irwin MR, Olmstead R, Carroll JE. Sleep disturbance, Sleep Duration, and inflammation: a systematic review and Meta-analysis of Cohort studies and experimental sleep deprivation. Biol Psychiatry. 2016;80(1):40&#8211;52.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26140821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.05.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4666828</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Calcaterra V, Vandoni M, Rossi V, Berardo C, Grazi R, Cordaro E, Tranfaglia V, Carnevale Pellino V, Cereda C, Zuccotti G. Use of Physical Activity and Exercise to reduce inflammation in children and adolescents with obesity. Int J Environ Res Public Health 2022, 19(11).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph19116908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9180584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35682490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sallis</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Needle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relation of physical activity and exercise to mental health</article-title><source>Public Health Rep</source><year>1985</year><volume>100</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3920718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1424736</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Taylor CB, Sallis JF, Needle R. The relation of physical activity and exercise to mental health. Public Health Rep. 1985;100(2):195&#8211;202.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3920718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1424736</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandborg</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skjerning</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physical activity through social prescribing: an interview-based study of Danish general practitioners&#8217; opinions</article-title><source>Health Soc Care Community</source><year>2022</year><volume>30</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1969</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/hsc.13577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34587342</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Brandborg CE, Skjerning HT, Nielsen RO. Physical activity through social prescribing: an interview-based study of Danish general practitioners&#8217; opinions. Health Soc Care Community. 2022;30(5):1969&#8211;78.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34587342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/hsc.13577</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stommel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenborn</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accuracy and usefulness of BMI measures based on self-reported weight and height: findings from the NHANES &amp; NHIS 2001&#8211;2006</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-9-421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19922675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2784464</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Stommel M, Schoenborn CA. Accuracy and usefulness of BMI measures based on self-reported weight and height: findings from the NHANES &amp; NHIS 2001&#8211;2006. BMC Public Health. 2009;9:1&#8211;10.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19922675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2458-9-421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2784464</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kroenke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spitzer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The PHQ-9: validity of a brief depression severity measure</article-title><source>J Gen Intern Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>16</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>606</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1525-1497.2001.016009606.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11556941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1495268</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Kroenke K, Spitzer RL, Williams JB. The PHQ-9: validity of a brief depression severity measure. J Gen Intern Med. 2001;16(9):606&#8211;13.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11556941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1525-1497.2001.016009606.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1495268</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levis</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benedetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thombs</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accuracy of Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9) for screening to detect major depression: individual participant data meta-analysis</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2019</year><volume>365</volume><fpage>l1476</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.l1476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30967483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6454318</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Levis B, Benedetti A, Thombs BD. Accuracy of Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9) for screening to detect major depression: individual participant data meta-analysis. BMJ. 2019;365:l1476.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30967483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.l1476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6454318</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physical activity (PA) influences the risk of depression associated with long working hours</article-title><source>J Affect Disord</source><year>2023</year><volume>321</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2022.10.043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36334760</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Yan T, Ding X, Xie T, Lan T, Niu D, Li J, Guo D, Wang M, Wang M. Physical activity (PA) influences the risk of depression associated with long working hours. J Affect Disord. 2023;321:227&#8211;33.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36334760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jad.2022.10.043</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kakaer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association between Joint Physical Activity and Dietary Quality and Lower Risk of Depression symptoms in US Adults: cross-sectional NHANES Study</article-title><source>JMIR Public Health Surveill</source><year>2023</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e45776</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/45776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37163324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10209797</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Liang J, Huang S, Jiang N, Kakaer A, Chen Y, Liu M, Pu Y, Huang S, Pu X, Zhao Y, et al. Association between Joint Physical Activity and Dietary Quality and Lower Risk of Depression symptoms in US Adults: cross-sectional NHANES Study. JMIR Public Health Surveill. 2023;9:e45776.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37163324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2196/45776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10209797</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shokeen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sokal-Gutierrez</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between cardio-metabolic risks and depressive symptoms among US adults (NHANES 2013&#8211;2018)</article-title><source>J Affect Disord</source><year>2022</year><volume>299</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2021.11.065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34856304</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Shokeen D, Sokal-Gutierrez K. Association between cardio-metabolic risks and depressive symptoms among US adults (NHANES 2013&#8211;2018). J Affect Disord. 2022;299:166&#8211;73.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34856304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jad.2021.11.065</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leisure-time physical activity is associated with depressive symptoms in cancer patients: data from the NHANES 2007&#8211;2018</article-title><source>J Affect Disord</source><year>2024</year><volume>358</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2024.05.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38705529</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Lai Q, Li W, He X, Wang H, He Q, Hao C, Deng Z. Leisure-time physical activity is associated with depressive symptoms in cancer patients: data from the NHANES 2007&#8211;2018. J Affect Disord. 2024;358:35&#8211;41.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38705529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jad.2024.05.023</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>