<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nicotine Tob Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nicotine Tob Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">768</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">nictob</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nictob</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nicotine &amp; Tobacco Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1462-2203</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1469-994X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10077936</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10077936.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10077936</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10077936</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36394282</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntac262</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ntac262</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-oup-series"><subject>Editor's Choice</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00010</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SOC02541</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Proactive Referral to Behavioral Smoking Cessation Programs by Healthcare Staff: A Systematic Review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2470-1763</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>van Westen-Lagerweij</surname><given-names initials="NA">Naomi A</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><aff>
<institution>The Netherlands Expertise Centre for Tobacco Control, Trimbos Institute</institution>, <addr-line>Utrecht</addr-line>, <country country="NL">The Netherlands</country></aff><aff>
<institution>Department of Health Promotion, Maastricht University</institution>, <addr-line>Maastricht</addr-line>, <country country="NL">The Netherlands</country></aff><xref rid="c1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hipple Walters</surname><given-names initials="BJ">Bethany J</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><aff>
<institution>The Netherlands Expertise Centre for Tobacco Control, Trimbos Institute</institution>, <addr-line>Utrecht</addr-line>, <country country="NL">The Netherlands</country></aff><aff>
<institution>Tobacco Research and Treatment Center, Massachusetts General Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Boston, MA</addr-line>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Potyka</surname><given-names initials="F">Franziska</given-names></name><degrees>BSc</degrees><aff>
<institution>The Netherlands Expertise Centre for Tobacco Control, Trimbos Institute</institution>, <addr-line>Utrecht</addr-line>, <country country="NL">The Netherlands</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Croes</surname><given-names initials="EA">Esther A</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><aff>
<institution>The Netherlands Expertise Centre for Tobacco Control, Trimbos Institute</institution>, <addr-line>Utrecht</addr-line>, <country country="NL">The Netherlands</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Willemsen</surname><given-names initials="MC">Marc C</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><aff>
<institution>The Netherlands Expertise Centre for Tobacco Control, Trimbos Institute</institution>, <addr-line>Utrecht</addr-line>, <country country="NL">The Netherlands</country></aff><aff>
<institution>Department of Health Promotion, Maastricht University</institution>, <addr-line>Maastricht</addr-line>, <country country="NL">The Netherlands</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Corresponding Author: Naomi A. van Westen-Lagerweij, MSc, The Netherlands Expertise Centre for Tobacco Control, Trimbos Institute, PO Box 725, 3500 AS, Utrecht, The Netherlands. Telephone: +31302971100; E-mail: <email>NLagerweij@trimbos.nl</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2022-11-17"><day>17</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">432947</issue-id><fpage>849</fpage><lpage>858</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>6</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>16</day><month>9</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="corrected-typeset"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>17</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>07</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-04-11 06:10:14.553"><day>11</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2022. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Research on Nicotine and Tobacco.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs licence (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial reproduction and distribution of the work, in any medium, provided the original work is not altered or transformed in any way, and that the work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="ntac262.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ntac262.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Behavioral smoking cessation programs are an effective tool for quitting smoking, yet remain underused by smokers. Proactive referral may be a promising strategy for healthcare staff to connect smokers to such programs.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Aims and Methods</title><p>The aim of this study was to gain insight into the effectiveness and implementability of proactive referral of smokers to behavioral smoking cessation programs by healthcare staff. A systematic review was conducted using five databases. Effectiveness of proactive referral was defined as the proportion of referred smokers who enrolled in a behavioral smoking cessation program. To determine the implementability of proactive referral, measures of feasibility, acceptability, adoption, and referral rates were included as variables of interest. Out of 6686 screened records, 34 articles were eligible for review. A narrative synthesis approach was used.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>The majority of the included studies investigated proactive referral within an e-referral system, combined with one or more intervention components that enhance implementation. Overall, proactive referral resulted in higher enrollment rates, especially among low-income smokers, and was found to be feasible, adoptable, and acceptable to healthcare staff. E-referral systems performed better in terms of implementability compared to fax referral systems. About half of the studies were of good quality. Many studies lacked information which resulted in lower-quality scores.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The literature provides evidence that the proactive referral of smokers to behavioral smoking cessation programs by healthcare staff is effective and implementable across different settings. Based on the results, e-referral systems may be preferable to fax referral systems in terms of implementability.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Implications</title><p>This systematic review demonstrated that proactive referral has the potential to increase the reach of smoking cessation programs and reduce inequalities in access to such programs. In the selection and implementation of behavioral smoking cessation programs with a proactive referral component, stakeholders (eg, policymakers, healthcare funders, and healthcare professionals) may benefit from taking different aspects of proactive referral systems into account, such as the type of proactive referral system used and additional strategies which can enhance the implementability of the system.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>ZonMw</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100001826</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>531003017</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s6"><title>Introduction</title><p>Smoking tobacco is a major public health issue with over 1.14 billion smokers worldwide.<sup><xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> It is a significant cause of morbidity and mortality, causing more than 7 million deaths and 200 million disability-adjusted life-years each year.<sup><xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Smoking cigarettes has been shown to increase a person&#8217;s risk of acquiring many different diseases and disorders, including cancer, respiratory disease, and cardiovascular disease.<sup><xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Secondhand tobacco smoke exposure also poses a great risk to the health and lives of nonsmokers.<sup><xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Based on global data, previous research found that the secondhand tobacco smoke exposure produced by an equivalent of 52 smokers is associated with the death of one nonsmoker.<sup><xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Tobacco use and exposure to tobacco smoke harm health.</p><p>Quitting smoking is one of the most effective ways of reducing the harms of tobacco use and exposure.<sup><xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Behavioral health programs have been shown to be the most effective method of providing smoking cessation assistance.<sup><xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Behavioral health programs are programs that provide education, guidance, and support to help individuals improve their health behavior.<sup><xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Evidence-based behavioral health programs for smoking cessation include one-on-one counseling delivered by a smoking cessation counselor or a healthcare provider, group counseling, telephone-based counseling provided by coaches or counselors at telephone quitlines, and internet-based and mobile-based smoking cessation resources and tools.<sup><xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9&#8211;13</xref></sup> The primary aim of such programs is to help people to quit smoking through behavior change techniques. Research conducted on the tobacco treatment guidelines in 61 countries shows that the majority of clinical treatment guidelines recommend smoking cessation medications in combination with intensive specialist support, such as the support provided through a behavioral smoking cessation program, for those who want to quit smoking.<sup><xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup></p><p>While behavioral smoking cessation programs, with or without medication, can be an effective tool for quitting smoking, they are generally underused.<sup><xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> Most smokers try to quit smoking unaided, which is associated with success rates as low as 3%&#8211;5% per quit attempt.<sup><xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> Though not everyone may need intensive specialist support to quit (eg, in many cases the use of self-help material is sufficient), behavioral smoking cessation programs may be especially beneficial for those who need extra help to overcome their tobacco addiction. People who want to quit smoking may not know of effective tools and programs to help them quit smoking or may not believe that such interventions may increase their chance of success substantially.<sup><xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> Increasing smokers&#8217; use of behavioral smoking cessation programs could result in a higher number of people who quit smoking and stay quit.</p><p>Different strategies exist to increase the usage of behavioral smoking cessation programs among smokers, such as informing smokers about such programs through mass media campaigns, or inviting smokers to participate in behavioral smoking cessation programs.<sup><xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> Healthcare staff, such as clinicians, administrators, volunteers, and students in healthcare-related fields, can play an important role in stimulating the use of behavioral smoking cessation programs. First, they can do this by discussing program options with smokers.<sup><xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> Second, healthcare staff may actively refer patients who smoke to cessation programs. Identifying patients who smoke and actively referring patients to existing programs is a crucial step in ensuring that smokers receive effective, evidence-based smoking cessation support. In many cases, this may need to be facilitated by system changes in the clinic setting, such as implementing tobacco-user identification and referral systems.<sup><xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> Implementation strategies can support the implementation and adoption of such systems,<sup><xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> for example, by providing training, reminders, and feedback to healthcare staff.<sup><xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup></p><p>The way in which healthcare staff refer smokers to behavioral smoking cessation programs may have an impact on &#173;enrollment rates. Healthcare staff may refer smokers to smoking cessation programs either through passive referral (ie, patients who smoke contact a behavioral smoking cessation provider themselves after being referred by healthcare staff), or through proactive referral (ie, healthcare staff actively connects a smoker to a behavioral smoking cessation program). Research has shown that smokers who are passively referred to behavioral smoking cessation programs often fail to enroll in treatment. A study conducted in the United States found that only 9 out of 564 smokers who received a quitline referral card from a family-practice nurse or medical assistant and were instructed to contact the quitline themselves eventually enrolled in the quitline.<sup><xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> In contrast, the same study found that 160 out of 567 smokers who were proactively referred to the quitline enrolled.<sup><xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Proactive referral may be a promising and potentially more effective strategy for healthcare staff to connect smokers to behavioral smoking cessation programs. Proactive referral by healthcare staff, however, remains understudied in systematic reviews.</p><sec id="s7"><title>Research Questions</title><p>We conducted a systematic literature review to gain insight into the proactive referral of smokers to behavioral smoking cessation programs by healthcare staff. Specifically, we sought to answer six research questions. The first research question was related to the effectiveness of proactive referral:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Does proactively referring smokers to behavioral smoking cessation programs by healthcare staff result in higher enrollment rates compared to passively referring smokers?</p></list-item></list><p>The remaining questions were related to four aspects of the implementability of proactive referral: feasibility, adoption, acceptability, and referral rates.</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>To what extent is proactively referring smokers to behavioral smoking cessation programs <italic toggle="yes">feasible</italic> for healthcare staff?</p></list-item><list-item><p>To what extent is proactively referring smokers to behavioral smoking cessation programs <italic toggle="yes">adoptable</italic> by healthcare staff?</p></list-item><list-item><p>To what extent is proactively referring smokers to behavioral smoking cessation programs <italic toggle="yes">acceptable</italic> to healthcare staff?</p></list-item><list-item><p>To what extent is proactively referring smokers to behavioral smoking cessation programs <italic toggle="yes">acceptable</italic> to smokers?</p></list-item><list-item><p>Do referral rates improve after informing healthcare staff about proactive referral options?</p></list-item></list><p>Information about the effectiveness, feasibility, adoption, acceptability, and rates of proactive referral provides insight into whether proactive referral &#8220;works&#8221; as a tool for healthcare staff to use when helping people to quit smoking. The findings of this systematic literature review can help policymakers, healthcare funders, and healthcare professionals to decide on implementing a proactive referral component within their smoking cessation care.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials" id="s8"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s9"><title>Search Strategy and Criteria</title><p>A systematic search of relevant literature was performed using five databases: PubMed, Embase (OVID), Web of Science, CINAHL, and PsycINFO. The search was conducted in January 2021 by NvWL and included keywords related to smoking cessation, referral, and healthcare staff. The complete search string can be found in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary File 1</xref>. The identified records were exported into EndNote. Before screening, we defined several inclusion and exclusion criteria.</p><sec id="s10"><title>Types of Studies</title><p>We included peer-reviewed primary research studies written in English and published after the year 2000. We excluded reviews, conference abstracts, letters, editorials, and study protocols. To answer the first research question regarding effectiveness, only (cluster) randomized controlled trials (RCTs) and quasi-RCTs were included. For the remaining five research questions, we also accepted non-randomized studies, quantitative descriptive studies, qualitative studies, and mixed-methods studies.</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Types of Participants of Published Studies</title><p>We included studies of adult smokers, with adults defined as 18 years or older. Articles that specifically focused on adolescents were excluded. We also excluded articles in which the number of smokers was unclear, for example, studies in which smokers and alcohol users were grouped together.</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Types of Interventions</title><p>Articles were included if they described a study that investigated, at least in part, proactive referral by healthcare staff to a behavioral smoking cessation program, defined as any type of evidence-based program with the primary aim of helping people to quit smoking through behavior change techniques. We included studies in which healthcare staff were involved in referring smokers to a behavioral smoking cessation program; we excluded studies in which the study personnel was responsible for delivering the intervention. Healthcare staff were defined as any type of employed healthcare worker, volunteer, or student studying in a healthcare-related field.</p><p>A referral qualified as &#8220;proactive&#8221; if the healthcare staff was responsible for connecting patients to a behavioral smoking cessation program. Examples of proactive referral included:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Forwarding the patient&#8217;s contact details to a smoking cessation program, for example, by using a fax machine or by placing a referral order in the electronic health record system (ie, an e-referral). Staff from the smoking cessation program then contacts the patient to enroll.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Scheduling an appointment directly with a counselor of a smoking cessation service during the patient&#8217;s visit.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Providing any practical assistance to the smoker to make contact with and enroll in a behavioral smoking cessation program. Practical assistance can include handing a computer tablet to the patient which assesses the patient&#8217;s interest in quitting smoking and then sends the patient&#8217;s contact details to a smoking cessation program (ie, an e-referral). It may also include calling a smoking cessation counselor while the patient is in-patient at a hospital, and then transferring the call to the bedside hospital phone for the patient to pick up (ie, a bedside warm transfer call).</p></list-item></list><p>We included opt-in as well as opt-out referrals. &#8220;Opt-in&#8221; means that patients explicitly give consent for the referral; &#8220;opt-out&#8221; means that patients are always referred unless they explicitly decline the referral.</p><p>To answer the effectiveness research question, we excluded studies in which the effect of proactive referral could not be independently evaluated from additional components of an intervention which may also influence enrollment rates. For example, studies that investigated a combination of proactive referral and reminders for the patient to enroll in a program and compared this to passive referral without reminders for the patient to enroll were excluded. We also excluded studies that did not investigate passive referral by healthcare staff in the comparison condition. Referrals were considered to be passive when patients were asked or expected to contact a behavioral smoking cessation program themselves. Regarding the implementability research questions, we did not specify necessary comparison conditions except for one outcome (ie, referral rates) described below.</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Types of Outcome Measures</title><p>
<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> provides an overview of the different included outcome measures per research question.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Included Outcome Measures Per Research Question</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Research question</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Included outcome measures</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Our definition</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">If relevant: based on definition from literature</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. Effectiveness</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enrollment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The proportion of referred smokers who enrolled in a behavioral smoking cessation program, compared between the proactive referral group and the passive referral group.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2. Feasibility</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any assessment of &#173;feasibility from the perspective of healthcare staff</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The extent to which proactively referring smokers to behavioral smoking cessation programs can be successfully carried out by healthcare staff.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proctor et al.: &#8220;Feasibility is defined as the extent to which a new treatment, or an innovation, can be successfully used or carried out within a given agency or setting.&#8221;<sup><xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3. Adoption</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adoption of proactive referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The proportion of healthcare staff individuals who proactively referred smokers to behavioral smoking cessation programs.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proctor et al.: &#8220;Adoption is defined as the intention, initial decision, or action to try or employ an innovation or evidence-based practice.&#8221;<sup><xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">4. Acceptance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any measure of perceived acceptability of proactive referral from the perspective of &#173;healthcare staff and smokers</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The extent to which proactively referring smokers to behavioral smoking cessation programs is perceived to be agreeable or satisfactory by healthcare staff and smokers.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proctor et al.: &#8220;Acceptability is the &#173;perception among implementation stakeholders that a given treatment, &#173;service, practice, or innovation is agreeable, &#173;palatable, or satisfactory.&#8221;<sup><xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smokers&#8217; acceptance of referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The proportion of smokers that agreed to be proactively referred to a behavioral smoking cessation program.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5. Referral rates</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Referral rates after the introduction of proactive referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">- The proportion of referred smokers before and after implementation of proactive referral.<break/>- The proportion of referred smokers between a proactive referral group and a comparison group, with the comparison group being either usual care or passive referral.<break/>- The proportion of referred smokers between different types of proactive referral groups.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Study Selection</title><p>Before screening, duplicates were automatically removed. We also removed records published before the year 2000. Any remaining duplicates were manually removed during the screening process. NvWL and FP screened titles and abstracts of the records using a screening sheet which was tested beforehand on 10 records. Based on the inclusion criteria, we determined whether the records were eligible for full-text assessment. NvWL screened 30% of the records, FP screened 70%. Of all records, 10% were randomly selected and screened by a third reviewer (BJHW) to check for interrater reliability. Full texts of all potentially relevant studies were obtained and reviewed by NvWL and FP for eligibility using a screening sheet which was tested beforehand. We excluded studies that did not meet the inclusion criteria. The remaining studies were included in the data extraction and analysis.</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Data Extraction and Analysis</title><p>Data were extracted using a form that was adapted from the data extraction template developed by the Cochrane Collaboration. The adapted form was first tested by FP and NvWL on three articles with different study designs: an RCT, a non-randomized study, and a qualitative study. The data extraction form included details of publication (eg, title, authors, journal, country, year), study characteristics (eg, study design, setting, type of behavioral smoking cessation program referred to, type of referring healthcare staff), patient characteristics (eg, number of smokers, age, gender, socioeconomic status, motivation to quit), intervention and comparison characteristics (eg, description of proactive referral, description of passive referral), outcomes (eg, outcome definitions, results), discussion (eg, limitations), and key conclusions. Data were extracted independently by FP, and checked for accuracy by NvWL. Any disagreements between the authors were resolved through discussion.</p><p>The extracted data was used for the analysis. The included studies varied greatly in setting, patient population, type of proactive referral, type of referring healthcare staff, and outcome definitions. Due to this heterogeneity, we took a narrative synthesis approach in describing the results.</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Quality Assessment</title><p>The methodological quality of the included studies was assessed using the Mixed Methods Appraisal Tool (MMAT).<sup><xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> The MMAT is an appraisal tool for systematic reviews which include quantitative, qualitative, and mixed methods studies. For each study design, the MMAT provides five criteria that must be rated with &#8220;yes&#8221;, &#8220;no&#8221;, or &#8220;can&#8217;t tell&#8221;. <xref rid="sup2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary File 2</xref> briefly describes how each criterion was defined for our review. In addition, we added the rating &#8220;not applicable&#8221; to the criterion &#8220;Are the confounders accounted for in the design and analysis?&#8221;. NvWL and BJHW independently rated the included studies. Any disagreements between the authors were resolved through discussion. We scored each criterion depending on the rating it received: &#8220;yes&#8221; corresponded with 1 point, &#8220;no&#8221; corresponded with &#8722;1 points, and &#8220;can&#8217;t tell&#8221; and &#8220;not applicable&#8221; corresponded with 0 points. For each included study an overall score was calculated based on the ratings of the five criteria. We considered studies with an overall score of at least 3 points to be of good quality.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Results</title><p>In total 6686 records were screened, resulting in 34 included articles. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> illustrates the screening process. While the search criteria included articles published from 2000 onwards, the 34 included articles were published between 2008 and 2020. A brief overview of the study characteristics and findings are presented in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>; the full overview can be found in <xref rid="sup3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 1</xref>. The articles included 11 RCTs (3 parallel RCTs and 8 cluster RCTs),<sup><xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29&#8211;38</xref></sup> 18 non-randomized studies,<sup><xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39&#8211;56</xref></sup> 2 qualitative studies,<sup><xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></sup> and 3 mixed-methods studies.<sup><xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59&#8211;61</xref></sup> The majority of the &#173;studies were conducted in the United States (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;24).<sup><xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29&#8211;34</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40&#8211;46</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52&#8211;55</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup> Six studies were conducted in the United Kingdom,<sup><xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></sup> two in Canada,<sup><xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> one in Australia,<sup><xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> and one in Hong Kong.<sup><xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup></p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Brief Overview of the Study Characteristics and Findings</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First author, year</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Design</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of proactive referral</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Main findings</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abdelmutti, 2019<sup><xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptance rate: 20%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adsit, 2014<sup><xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Referral rates: 13.9% (e-referral) vs. 0.3% (fax referral)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boykan, 2016<sup><xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptance rates: 62%, 36%, and 34%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Campbell, 2017<sup><xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Referral rates: 61.9% (opt-out&#8197;+&#8197;opt-in) vs. 54.1% (opt-in)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Campbell, 2016<sup><xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qualitative</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive with regard to feasibility and acceptability</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Campbell, 2019<sup><xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed-methods</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptance rate: 23.1%; several barriers with regard to feasibility and acceptability</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cantrell, 2009<sup><xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qualitative</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fax referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Several barriers with regard to feasibility</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carpenter, 2012<sup><xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fax referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Several barriers with regard to feasibility</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Faseru, 2011<sup><xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fax referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptance rate: 55.8%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fellows, 2016<sup><xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fax referral and bedside warm transfer call</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptance rate: 57.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fiore, 2019<sup><xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster RCT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Referral rates: system A&#8212;17.9% (e-referral) vs. 3.8% (fax referral); system B&#8212;18.9% (e-referral) vs. 5.2% (fax referral)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flocke, 2019<sup><xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Referral rates: 21.7% (post-implementation) vs. 1.3% (pre-implementation)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flocke, 2020<sup><xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Referral rates: 30.9% (post-implementation) vs. 0.5% (pre-implementation)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Giuliani, 2019<sup><xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptance rate: 20.4%; Referral rates: 20.2% (post-implementation) vs. 7.7% (pre-implementation)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hood-Medland, 2019<sup><xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adoption rate: 17%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Houston, 2015<sup><xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster RCT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enrollment rates: 31% (intervention) vs. 11% (control)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jenssen, 2019<sup><xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enrollment rates: 10.3% (intervention) vs. 2.0% (control)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jose, 2020<sup><xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immediate scheduling of an appointment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptance rate: 71%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kruse, 2012<sup><xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed-methods</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adoption rate: 92%; positive with regard to feasibility; several barriers with regard to acceptability</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linder, 2009<sup><xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster RCT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral and fax referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adoption rate: 44%; Referral rates: 4.5% (intervention) vs. 0.4% (comparison)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">McEwen, 2012<sup><xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed-methods</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral and fax referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptance rates: 54.7% and 30.7%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Philbrick, 2009<sup><xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclear</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptance rate: 30%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ray, 2014<sup><xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster RCT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enrollment rates: 29.5% (intervention) vs. 7.6% (control)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Robbins, 2015<sup><xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fax referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptance rate: 5.4%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rothemich, 2010<sup><xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster RCT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fax referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Referral rates: 21.4% (intervention) vs. 8.7% (comparison)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sadasivam, 2013<sup><xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Several best practices with regard to feasibility</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sharifi, 2014<sup><xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fax referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perceived acceptability: 82% of the clinicians found fax referral form helpful; Referral rates: 27.7% (post-implementation) vs. 0.9% (pre-implementation)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shelley, 2010<sup><xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fax referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Referral rates: 35% (post-implementation) vs. 17% &#173;(pre-implementation)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spaducci, 2020<sup><xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptance rate: 23.2%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tang, 2014<sup><xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-randomized</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclear</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptance rate: 78%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vidrine, 2013<sup><xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster RCT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enrollment rates: 28.2% (intervention) vs. 1.6% (control); &#173;Acceptance rate: 27.6%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vidrine, 2013<sup><xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster RCT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-referral</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enrollment rates: 36.0% (intervention) vs. 1.4% (control); &#173;Acceptance rate: 40.6%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weng, 2020<sup><xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster RCT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immediate scheduling of an appointment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptance rate: 76.7%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Young, 2008<sup><xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclear</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptance rate: 45%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T2Fn1"><p>RCT = randomized controlled trial.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>PRISMA flow diagram.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ntac262f0001.jpg"/></fig><p>The programs and studies were conducted in many different settings, but most often in a specialized clinic, including clinics for cancer, pediatrics, antenatal care, family planning, internal medicine, or pulmonary medicine (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;14),<sup><xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45&#8211;48</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55&#8211;57</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></sup> primary care or general practice (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;11),<sup><xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36&#8211;38</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup> or a hospital (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;5).<sup><xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup> Several studies were also conducted in a community or outpatient clinic which primarily serves low-income smokers (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;3),<sup><xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></sup> dental practices (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;2),<sup><xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> a pharmacy (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;1),<sup><xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup> and community sites such as housing estates, shopping malls, and public transport hubs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;1).<sup><xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup></p><p>As for the type of proactive referral which was investigated in the studies: 21 studies investigated e-referrals,<sup><xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29&#8211;33</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38&#8211;40</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55&#8211;57</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59&#8211;61</xref></sup> 10 investigated fax referrals,<sup><xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43&#8211;45</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></sup> two investigated the immediate &#173;scheduling of an appointment with a smoking cessation service,<sup><xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup> and one study investigated bedside warm transfer calls to an in-hospital tobacco cessation service.<sup><xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> In three studies, it was unclear how patients were referred to a behavioral smoking cessation program.<sup><xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup> The research team assumed that these three studies investigated proactive referral since the smokers were contacted by a counselor or representative of the program after referral. Of the 34 included studies, 31 investigated proactive opt-in referrals,<sup><xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29&#8211;55</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58&#8211;60</xref></sup> and 3 studies investigated proactive opt-out referrals.<sup><xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></sup></p><p>In most studies, smokers were proactively referred to a (state) quitline (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;18)<sup><xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32&#8211;34</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41&#8211;45</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52&#8211;55</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup> or a (local) smoking cessation service (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;9).<sup><xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></sup> In a smaller number of studies, smokers were proactively referred to a group cessation program (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;3),<sup><xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></sup> a web-based intervention (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;3),<sup><xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> a tobacco treatment specialist or coordinator (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;3),<sup><xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup> an in-hospital cessation service (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;2),<sup><xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup> or a trained nurse (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;1).<sup><xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> The majority of the studies (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;28) included one or more components in their intervention in addition to proactive referral. These additional components were mostly targeted at healthcare staff, rather than at patients; they consisted of training/education (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;19),<sup><xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48&#8211;50</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52&#8211;54</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56&#8211;58</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></sup> reminders/prompts (either through the electronic health record system or a chart stamp) to screen for tobacco use and/or offer referral (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;13),<sup><xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54&#8211;58</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup> and/or performance feedback reports (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;7).<sup><xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52&#8211;54</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup></p><sec id="s18"><title>Study Quality</title><p>Results of the quality assessment are presented in <xref rid="sup4" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 2</xref>. The quality of the included studies ranged from &#8211;1 to 5 points (on a scale ranging from &#8211;5 to 5 points). One study was excluded from the quality appraisal due to the lack of a clear research question or aim, as recommended by the MMAT.<sup><xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> Overall, most quantitative descriptive studies, qualitative studies, and mixed-methods studies scored well (&#8805;3 points). RCTs and nonrandomized studies generally scored lower. Most RCTs lacked detailed information on how randomization was performed. Further, most RCTs did not describe if and/or how those conducting outcome assessments were blinded as to the study condition or aims of the study. In addition, in the majority of RCTs and nonrandomized studies, it was not clear whether the data for the outcome(s) of interest was complete and whether the intervention was administered as intended (ie, whether all included patients were offered a proactive referral by healthcare staff). Due to these shortcomings, only 42% of RCTs and nonrandomized studies combined scored well (&#8805;3 points).</p></sec><sec id="s19"><title>Effectiveness</title><p>We identified five RCTs (one parallel RCTs and four cluster RCTs) that reported the enrollment of smokers in behavioral smoking cessation programs. Four out of the five studies had low-quality scores (&lt;3 points) due to a lack of information. The five studies all investigated opt-in e-referrals as an intervention and each study found that proactively referred smokers were significantly more likely to enroll in behavioral smoking cessation programs compared to passively referred smokers.<sup><xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29&#8211;32</xref></sup> The smallest, yet still significant, the difference was reported by Houston et al. who found that, compared to passive referral, proactive referral resulted in 2.8 times more patients enrolling in a web-based program.<sup><xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> The largest difference was reported by Vidrine et al.; they found that, among a population of mostly low-income smokers, proactive referral resulted in 25.7 times more patients enrolling in the state quitline.<sup><xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="s20"><title>Feasibility</title><p>Six studies, which all scored well on quality (&#8805;3 points), reported a qualitative assessment of feasibility from the perspective of healthcare staff (ie, the extent to which proactively referring smokers to smoking cessation programs can be successfully carried out by healthcare staff). Three studies that investigated e-referrals all found that the process of using an e-referral system to proactively refer patients was easy or had minimal impact on workload.<sup><xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup> While two of these studies provided healthcare staff with training or prompts in the electronic health record, one study did not and reported that reception staff easily forgot about the process of using the e-referral system and did not always feel confident enough to discuss referrals.<sup><xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup> According to Sadasivam et al., setting up a reminder to refer smokers (eg, a prompt in the electronic health record or a physical reminder on the desk) helped to facilitate e-referrals.<sup><xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup></p><p>Two studies investigated fax referrals and found several barriers related to its feasibility: time-consuming process; lack of reliability of the fax machine; lack of knowledge where to get a fax referral form; lack of patient ability to fill out a fax referral form.<sup><xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="s21"><title>Adoption</title><p>Three studies, of which two scored well on quality (&#8805;3 points), reported adoption rates of proactive referral (ie, the proportion of healthcare staff who proactively referred smokers to behavioral smoking cessation programs). One study found that among 1600 clinicians, 17% had proactively referred patients using an e-referral system at least once.<sup><xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> In two other studies, e-referral adoption rates of 92% and 44% were reported.<sup><xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup> Important to note is that in these two studies, healthcare staff received prompts in the electronic health record to document the patient&#8217;s smoking status and use the e-referral system, which was not the case in the study which found an adoption rate of 17%.</p></sec><sec id="s22"><title>Acceptability</title><p>Four studies, of which three scored well on quality (&#8805;3 points), reported a quantitative or qualitative measure of providers&#8217; or smokers&#8217; perceived acceptability of proactive referral (ie, the extent to which proactively referring smokers to behavioral smoking cessation programs is perceived to be agreeable or satisfactory). One study found that over 80% of clinicians agreed that a fax referral system was helpful in referring patients.<sup><xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> In two qualitative studies, proactive referral (opt-in as well as opt-out) was found to be acceptable to both healthcare staff and pregnant women, as reported in interviews with healthcare staff.<sup><xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup> One study, in which reception staff were involved in the proactive referral, however also found that the reception may not be the most suitable setting for providing referrals and discussing smoking with patients.<sup><xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup> Another study reported that healthcare staff were discouraged when patients were not reached or declined enrollment after referral, and that healthcare staff did not receive enough information about cessation outcomes after referral, which decreased their motivation to refer.<sup><xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup></p><p>We found 16 studies (of which seven of good quality, ie, &#8805;3 points) that reported the patients&#8217; acceptance rate with regard to proactive referral. Among smokers who first received cessation counseling in a clinic or hospital and were then offered a referral for follow-up support, the acceptance rate ranged from 5.4% to 55.8%.<sup><xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup> The acceptance rate ranged from 20% to 78% among smokers who were referred without first receiving cessation counseling.<sup><xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34&#8211;36</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46&#8211;51</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="s23"><title>Referral Rates</title><p>Ten studies (of which four of good quality, ie, &#8805;3 points) reported rates of referral to behavioral smoking cessation programs. In seven studies, referral rates were compared between an intervention group (proactive referral) and comparison group (usual care or pre-implementation). These studies found that between 2.1 and 61.8 times more smokers were referred in the intervention group compared to the comparison group.<sup><xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52&#8211;54</xref></sup></p><p>Three studies compared referral rates between different types of proactive referral groups. Two studies found that between 3.6 and 46.3 times more smokers were referred through e-referral compared to fax referral.<sup><xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></sup> Another study found that implementing a combination of both opt-out and opt-in referrals resulted in a higher referral rate of pregnant smokers compared to implementing only opt-in referrals (61.9% vs. 54.1% respectively).<sup><xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup></p></sec></sec><sec id="s24"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="s25"><title>Key Findings</title><p>To the best of our knowledge, the current review was the first to systematically assess the effectiveness and implementability of proactive referral of smokers to behavioral smoking cessation programs by healthcare staff. Proactively referring patients, particularly with the use of an e-referral system and in combination with one or more other intervention components, was found to be effective, feasible, adoptable, and acceptable to healthcare staff across different settings. Also, the implementation of proactive referral was found to result in higher referral rates, further indicating that proactive referral can be successfully implemented in practice.</p></sec><sec id="s26"><title>Interpretation of the Findings</title><p>With regard to effectiveness, only five studies investigated enrollment rates.<sup><xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29&#8211;32</xref></sup> These studies all reported significantly higher enrollment rates among proactively referred smokers compared to passively referred smokers. Taking into account the low uptake of smoking cessation programs by smokers who attempt to quit smoking,<sup><xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> these results demonstrate the potential of proactive referral in increasing the reach of smoking cessation programs. More specifically, proactive referral by healthcare staff most strongly improves enrollment rates among low-income smokers.<sup><xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> Considering that especially low-income smokers experience a multitude of barriers which limit their ability to access smoking cessation support,<sup><xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></sup> proactive referral may thus help to reduce inequalities in the access to cessation services by directly connecting low-income smokers to cessation services.</p><p>With respect to the implementation of proactive referral, healthcare staff may encounter barriers both at the provider level (eg, too little time to refer patients, or forgetting to refer patients) and organizational level (eg, lack of reliable equipment needed to refer patients).<sup><xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup> Reported barriers were mostly related to fax referrals, which may explain why e-referral systems were found to generate more referrals to smoking cessation programs compared to fax referral systems.<sup><xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></sup> Previous research concluded that e-referral systems in healthcare can help to improve the quantity and quality of referrals and are also received well by healthcare staff in different settings.<sup><xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></sup></p><p>Interestingly, 60% of the studies specifically focused on e-referrals. The results suggest that e-referral may be preferable to fax referral in terms of implementability. It remains unclear whether e-referral may also be preferable to other types of proactive referral, such as bedside warm transfer calls to a quitline or the immediate scheduling of an appointment with a smoking cessation counselor. The advantage of such types of proactive referral is that the patient is immediately enrolled into a smoking cessation program. For hospitals, a warm transfer call is a less expensive and more effective method for enrolling smokers in quitlines compared to fax referrals.<sup><xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></sup> It would be interesting to conduct a similar cost-effectiveness analysis for e-referral versus warm transfer calls, for example, to a quitline or an in-hospital cessation service. The cost-effectiveness may differ depending on whom patients are referred to. Furthermore, &gt;90% of the studies examined opt-in proactive referrals. We found few studies which compared opt-in to opt-out proactive referrals. Only one study investigated the addition of opt-out referrals to an opt-int referral system and found promising results.<sup><xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup> More future studies on opt-out referrals, and specifically the addition of opt-out referrals to an opt-in system, are therefore recommended.</p><p>Regarding the implementability of proactive referral, we noticed that in addition to proactive referral most studies included one or more provider-targeted components in their intervention which in fact function as implementation strategies. Implementation strategies can help to overcome barriers and thus enhance the implementability of new systems and practices in healthcare.<sup><xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> These strategies, which may include provision of training, adding prompts to the electronic health record, or working with performance feedback reports, have been found to help healthcare staff to identify smokers and increase the number of smokers that receive evidence-based cessation support.<sup><xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65&#8211;67</xref></sup> A systems approach, in which healthcare staff are provided with training, support, and organizational structures to systematically identify and refer smokers, may hence be necessary to ensure that all smokers are offered tobacco-dependence treatment as a routine part of care.<sup><xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup></p><p>While proactive referral was generally found to be acceptable to healthcare staff, the proportion of smokers that agreed to be proactively referred (ie, the patients&#8217; acceptance rate) varied greatly between studies (5.4%&#8211;78%). This wide range of patients&#8217; acceptance rates between studies might be explained by the great diversity of settings as well as differences in the delivery of the intervention. For example, patients&#8217; acceptance rates of over 50% were only reported in Western countries among hospitalized patients, parents and caregivers, and cancer patients,<sup><xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></sup> indicating that proactive referral may be more acceptable among patients for whom quitting smoking is most urgent. The only study conducted in a non-Western setting found a remarkably high acceptance rate of 77% among smokers in community sites,<sup><xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> which may indicate a difference in the acceptability of proactive referral between Western and non-Western cultures.</p><p>Surprisingly, in three studies conducted among cancer patients and pregnant women, acceptance rates of around 20% were reported.<sup><xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup> We suspect that these low acceptance rates are the result of how the intervention was delivered. In these studies, healthcare staff handed a computer tablet or form to the patient which assessed smokers&#8217; interest in proactive referral, after which the referral was sent to the smoking cessation program. The healthcare staff did not further discuss the referral with smokers. While the use of a tablet or form may be an efficient way for healthcare staff to refer patients, this may not outweigh the lower number of patients who accept the referral.</p><p>We encountered several issues while appraising the quality of the different studies which may explain the mixed quality we found for RCTs and nonrandomized studies. For example, limitations in the data of the different studies (such as patient recall, the use of survey data, and the use of nontraditional data sources) made it harder to appraise the quality of the data used. Also, it was a challenge to determine whether data could be considered complete, especially in studies where electronic health record data was used, and studies often did not explicitly mention whether healthcare staff had adhered to the assigned intervention. Due to this lack of information, many studies scored low on quality. For future research on this topic, it is important that researchers explicitly address these aspects. Adherence to the intervention by healthcare staff may, for example, be assessed from electronic health record data.</p></sec><sec id="s27"><title>Limitations</title><p>Several study limitations need to be addressed. First, there was a great deal of variation in study designs, settings, types of interventions, and measurements which limits the generalizability of the findings. Due to the lack of comparability between studies, it was not possible to conduct a pooled analysis. In addition, most studies were conducted in English-speaking, Western countries, limiting the generalizability of the results to other countries. Second, we did not pre-register a protocol for this systematic review. Third, this review did not take into account difficulties that may be experienced in enrolling patients after referral. Smoking cessation programs may not always be able to reach patients after receiving a referral, or patients may eventually decide to not enroll in the program.<sup><xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> These issues may undermine the effectiveness of proactive referral. Finally, based on our results, we do not know whether proactive referral also increases smoking cessation. It is, however, conceivable that the question of smoking abstinence is less relevant in relation to the type of referral (passive or proactive), as smoking abstinence may be more strongly predicted by other factors such as the number of (attended) sessions in a smoking cessation program.<sup><xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></p></sec></sec><sec id="s28"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The current evidence clearly suggests that proactive referral by healthcare staff is effective and implementable across different settings. Proactive referral has the potential to increase the reach of smoking cessation programs and reduce inequalities in access to such programs. In the selection and implementation of smoking cessation care with a proactive referral component, it appears important to take into account different aspects, such as the type of proactive referral system used and additional strategies which can enhance implementability. Based on the results, e-referral systems may be preferable to fax referral systems. Further research is needed to determine the value of other types of proactive referral, such as warm transfer calls.</p></sec><sec id="s29" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>A Contributorship Form detailing each author&#8217;s specific involvement with this content, as well as any supplementary data, are available online at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/ntr" ext-link-type="uri">https://academic.oup.com/ntr</ext-link>.</p><supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>ntac262_suppl_Supplementary_File_S1</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ntac262_suppl_supplementary_file_s1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup2" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>ntac262_suppl_Supplementary_File_S2</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ntac262_suppl_supplementary_file_s2.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup4" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>ntac262_suppl_Supplementary_Table_S1</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ntac262_suppl_supplementary_table_s1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="sup3" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>ntac262_suppl_Supplementary_Table_S2</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ntac262_suppl_supplementary_table_s2.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec id="s30"><title>Funding</title><p>This research was funded by ZonMw under project number 531003017.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s31"><title>Declaration of Interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s32"><title>Data Availability</title><p>No new data were generated or analyzed in support of this research.</p></sec><ref-list id="r1"><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reitsma</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kendrick</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ababneh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Spatial, temporal, and demographic patterns in prevalence of smoking tobacco use and attributable disease burden in 204 countries and territories, 1990&#8211;2019: a systematic analysis from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019</article-title>. <source>Lancet.</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>397</volume>(<issue>10292</issue>):<fpage>2337</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2360</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34051883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)01169-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8223261</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Royal College of Physicians.</collab><source>Hiding in Plain Sight: Treating Tobacco Dependency in the NHS.</source><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Royal College of Physicians</publisher-name>; <year>2018</year>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.rcplondon.ac.uk/file/23966/download" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.rcplondon.ac.uk/file/23966/download</ext-link>. Accessed <comment>September 14, 2022</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>U.S. Office on Smoking and Health.</collab><source>The Health Consequences of Involuntary Exposure to Tobacco Smoke: A Report of the Surgeon General.</source><publisher-loc>Atlanta, GA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</publisher-name>; <year>2006</year>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK44324/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK44324/</ext-link>. Accessed <comment>September 14, 2022</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20669524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yousuf</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hofstra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tijssen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Estimated worldwide mortality attributed to secondhand tobacco smoke exposure, 1990&#8211;2016</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open.</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e201177</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>e201177</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32181828</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.1177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7078760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services.</collab><source>Smoking Cessation: A Report of the Surgeon General.</source><publisher-loc>Atlanta, GA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, National Center for Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion, Office on Smoking and Health</publisher-name>; <year>2020</year>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.hhs.gov/sites/default/files/2020-cessation-sgr-full-report.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.hhs.gov/sites/default/files/2020-cessation-sgr-full-report.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed <comment>September 14, 2022</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann-Boyce</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Livingstone-Banks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ord&#243;&#241;ez-Mena</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Behavioural interventions for smoking cessation: an overview and network meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev.</source><year>2021</year>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>CD013229</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD013229.pub2</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33411338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11354481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mottillo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Filion</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Belisle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Behavioural interventions for smoking cessation: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J.</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>718</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>730</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19109354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/eurheartj/ehn552</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>DM.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Behavioral health interventions: what works and why?</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bulatao</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <collab>National Research Council Panel on Race, Ethnicity, and Health in Later Life,</collab> eds. <source>Critical Perspectives on Racial and Ethnic Differences in Health in Late Life</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name>; <year>2004</year>:<fpage>643</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>674</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20669464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stead</surname><given-names>LF.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Individual behavioural counselling for smoking cessation</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev.</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>CD001292</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD001292.pub3</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12137623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stead</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Group behaviour therapy programmes for smoking cessation</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev.</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>CD001007</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD001007.pub3</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28361497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6464070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Matkin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ord&#243;&#241;ez-Mena</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann-Boyce</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Telephone counselling for smoking cessation</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev.</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>CD002850</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD002850.pub4</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31045250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6496404</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>GMJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dalili</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Semwal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Internet-based interventions for smoking cessation</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev.</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>CD007078</fpage> . doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD007078.pub5</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28869775</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6703145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McRobbie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bullen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Mobile phone-based interventions for smoking cessation</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev.</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>CD006611</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD006611.pub4</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27060875</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6485940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nilan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McNeill</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McKeever</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Raw</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>A survey of tobacco dependence treatment guidelines content in 61 countries</article-title>. <source>Addiction.</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>113</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1499</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1506</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29488266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/add.14204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6099485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hummel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nagelhout</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Quitting activity and use of cessation assistance reported by smokers in eight European countries: findings from the EUREST-PLUS ITC Europe Surveys</article-title>. <source>Tob Induc Dis.</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>suppl 2</issue>):<fpage>A6</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31363422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18332/tid/98912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6659556</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soulakova</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Crockett</surname><given-names>LJ.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Unassisted quitting and smoking cessation methods used in the United States: analyses of 2010-2011 tobacco use supplement to the current population survey data</article-title>. <source>Nicotine Tob Res.</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>30</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>39</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27798084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ntr/ntw273</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5896463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Keely</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Naud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Shape of the relapse curve and long-term abstinence among untreated smokers</article-title>. <source>Addiction.</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>29</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>38</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14678060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1360-0443.2004.00540.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Borland</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Do smokers know how to quit? Knowledge and perceived effectiveness of cessation assistance as predictors of cessation behaviour</article-title>. <source>Addiction.</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1042</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1048</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15265101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1360-0443.2004.00754.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marteau</surname><given-names>TM.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Examining why smokers do not want behavioral support with stopping smoking</article-title>. <source>Patient Educ Couns.</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>79</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>160</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>166</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19932580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pec.2009.10.007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Belisario</surname><given-names>JSM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bruggeling</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gunn</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brusamento</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Car</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Interventions for recruiting smokers into cessation programmes</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev.</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>CD009187</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD009187.pub2</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23235672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6485998</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tzelepis</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McElduff</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Proactive telephone counseling for smoking cessation: meta-analyses by recruitment channel and methodological quality</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst.</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>103</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>922</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>941</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21666098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jnci/djr169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>van Westen-Lagerweij</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bommel&#233;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Willemsen</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Croes</surname><given-names>EA.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Mentioning smoking cessation assistance during healthcare consultations matters: findings from Dutch survey research</article-title>. <source>Eur J Public Health.</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>747</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>752</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36001051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/eurpub/ckac106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9527971</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fiore</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Curry</surname><given-names>SJ.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Health system changes to facilitate the delivery of tobacco-dependence treatment</article-title>. <source>Am J Prev Med.</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>S349</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>S356</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18021910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amepre.2007.09.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McMillen</surname><given-names>JC.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Implementation strategies: recommendations for specifying and reporting</article-title>. <source>Implement Sci.</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>139</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24289295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1748-5908-8-139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3882890</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Waltz</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chinman</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>A refined compilation of implementation strategies: results from the Expert Recommendations for Implementing Change (ERIC) project</article-title>. <source>Implement Sci.</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>14</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25889199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13012-015-0209-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4328074</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vidrine</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shete</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Ask-Advise-Connect: a new approach to smoking treatment delivery in health care settings</article-title>. <source>JAMA Intern Med.</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>173</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>458</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>464</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23440173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamainternmed.2013.3751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3858085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Silmere</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Raghavan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Outcomes for implementation research: conceptual distinctions, measurement challenges, and research agenda</article-title>. <source>Adm Policy Ment Health.</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>65</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>76</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20957426</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10488-010-0319-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3068522</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>QN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pluye</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>F&#224;bregues</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <source>Mixed Methods Appraisal Tool (MMAT), Version 2018</source>. <publisher-name>Registration of Copyright (#1148552), Canadian Intellectual Property Office, Industry Canada</publisher-name>; <year>2018</year>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://mixedmethodsappraisaltoolpublic.pbworks.com/w/file/fetch/127916259/MMAT_2018_criteria-manual_2018-08-01_ENG.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">http://mixedmethodsappraisaltoolpublic.pbworks.com/w/file/fetch/127916259/MMAT_2018_criteria-manual_2018-08-01_ENG.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed <comment>September 14, 2022</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Houston</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sadasivam</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluating the QUIT-PRIMO clinical practice ePortal to increase smoker engagement with online cessation interventions: a national hybrid type 2 implementation study</article-title>. <source>Implement Sci.</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>10(</volume><issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26525410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13012-015-0336-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4630887</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jenssen</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Muthu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Parent eReferral to tobacco quitline: a pragmatic randomized trial in pediatric primary care</article-title>. <source>Am J Prev Med.</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>32</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31122792</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amepre.2019.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6644070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Funkhouser</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><collab>National Dental PBRN Collaborative Group.</collab><article-title>Smoking-cessation e-referrals: a national dental practice-based research network randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Am J Prev Med.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>158</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>165</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24439349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amepre.2013.10.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4077270</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vidrine</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shete</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The Ask-Advise-Connect approach for smokers in a safety net healthcare system: a group-randomized trial</article-title>. <source>Am J Prev Med.</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>737</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>741</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24237916</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amepre.2013.07.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4023543</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Linder</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rigotti</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>An electronic health record-based intervention to improve tobacco treatment in primary care: a cluster-randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med.</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>169</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>781</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>787</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19398690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/archinternmed.2009.53</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3005286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fellows</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mularski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leo</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Referring hospitalized smokers to outpatient quit services: a randomized trial</article-title>. <source>Am J Prev Med.</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>609</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>619</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27647061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amepre.2016.06.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5031367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Luk</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Suen</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of simple active referrals of different intensities on smoking abstinence and smoking cessation services attendance: a cluster-randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Addiction.</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>115</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1902</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1912</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32149425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/add.15029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Girgis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hobbs</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>JE.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Acceptability and effectiveness of opportunistic referral of smokers to telephone cessation advice from a nurse: a randomised trial in Australian general practice</article-title>. <source>BMC Fam Pract.</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18304363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2296-9-16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2268921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rothemich</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Woolf</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Promoting primary care smoking-cessation support with quitlines: the QuitLink Randomized Controlled Trial</article-title>. <source>Am J Prev Med.</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>367</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>374</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20307804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amepre.2010.01.008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fiore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adsit</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zehner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>An electronic health record-based interoperable eReferral system to enhance smoking Quitline treatment in primary care</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Inform Assoc.</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>8-9</issue>):<fpage>778</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>786</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31089727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jamia/ocz044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6696502</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelmutti</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brual</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Papadakos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Implementation of a comprehensive smoking cessation program in cancer care</article-title>. <source>Curr Oncol.</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>361</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>368</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31896934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3747/co.26.5201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6927783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sadasivam</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Volkman</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>; <collab>National Dental PBRN and QUITPRIMO Collaborative Groups.</collab><article-title>Implementing point of care &#8220;e-referrals&#8221; in 137 clinics to increase access to a quit smoking internet system: the Quit-Primo and National Dental PBRN HI-QUIT Studies</article-title>. <source>Transl Behav Med.</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>370</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>378</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24294325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s13142-013-0230-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3830021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carlini</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Painter</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mikko</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stoner</surname><given-names>SA.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Refer2Quit: impact of Web-based skills training on tobacco interventions and quitline referrals</article-title>. <source>J Contin Educ Health Prof.</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>187</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>195</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23008081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/chp.21144</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hood-Medland</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Health system implementation of a tobacco quitline eReferral</article-title>. <source>Appl Clin Inform.</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>735</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>742</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31578046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1055/s-0039-1697593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6774758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sharifi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Winickoff</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Enhancing the electronic health record to increase counseling and quit-line referral for parents who smoke</article-title>. <source>Acad Pediatr.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>478</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>484</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25169159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.acap.2014.03.017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Faseru</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of a hospital-based tobacco treatment service: outcomes and lessons learned</article-title>. <source>J Hosp Med.</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>211</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>218</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21480493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jhm.835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3081657</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Keyserling</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jilcott Pitts</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Outcomes of cardiovascular disease risk factor screening and referrals in a family planning clinic</article-title>. <source>J Womens Health.</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>131</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>137</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/jwh.2014.4938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4331243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25517351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boykan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Milana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Propper</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bax</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Celestino</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>implementation of an inpatient electronic referral system (opt-to-quit) from the electronic health record to the New York state smokers&#8217; quitline: first steps</article-title>. <source>Hosp Pediatr.</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>545</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>551</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27530349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1542/hpeds.2016-0004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Giuliani</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Implementation of a novel electronic patient-directed smoking cessation platform for cancer patients: interrupted time series analysis</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res.</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e11735</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30964445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2196/11735</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6477574</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jose</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ohde</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hays</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>DO.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Design and pilot implementation of an electronic health record-based system to automatically refer cancer patients to tobacco use treatment</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health.</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>40544054</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph17114054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7312526</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32517176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Philbrick</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Farris</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Faber</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Ask-advise-refer increases referrals to a smoking cessation group clinic</article-title>. <source>J Pharm Technol.</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>230</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>234</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Spaducci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McNeill</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>An observational study of system-level changes to improve the recording of very brief advice for smoking cessation in an inpatient mental health setting</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health.</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>559</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32334547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12889-020-08672-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7183585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>A surgeon led smoking cessation intervention in a head and neck cancer centre</article-title>. <source>BMC Health Serv Res.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>636</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25527115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12913-014-0636-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4301942</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Flocke</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seeholzer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Designing for sustainability: an approach to integrating staff role changes and electronic health record functionality within safety-net clinics to address provision of tobacco cessation care</article-title>. <source>Jt Comm J Qual Patient Saf.</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>798</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>807</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31648946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jcjq.2019.09.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Flocke</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seeholzer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>12-month evaluation of an EHR-supported staff role change for provision of tobacco cessation care in 8 primary care safety-net clinics</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med.</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3234</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3242</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32705473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-020-06030-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7661631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shelley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cantrell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The effect of linking community health centers to a state-level smoker&#8217;s quitline on rates of cessation assistance</article-title>. <source>BMC Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20100348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1472-6963-10-25</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2823740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0055"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adsit</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tsiolis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Using the electronic health record to connect primary care patients to evidence-based telephonic tobacco quitline services: a closed-loop demonstration project</article-title>. <source>Transl Behav Med.</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>324</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>332</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25264471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s13142-014-0259-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4167898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0056"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fahy</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>&#8220;Opt-out&#8221; referrals after identifying pregnant smokers using exhaled air carbon monoxide: impact on engagement with smoking cessation support</article-title>. <source>Tob Control.</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>300</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>306</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27225017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2015-052662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5520259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0057"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bowker</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Naughton</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Antenatal clinic and stop smoking services staff views on &#8220;opt-out&#8221; referrals for smoking cessation in pregnancy: a framework analysis</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health.</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>10041004</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph13101004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5086743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27754352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0058"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cantrell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shelley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Implementing a fax referral program for quitline smoking cessation services in urban health centers: a qualitative study</article-title>. <source>BMC Fam Pract</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20017930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2296-10-81</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2811101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0059"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Orton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bowker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Feasibility and acceptability of &#8220;opt-in&#8221; referrals for stop smoking support in pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health.</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1358</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31014015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph16081358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6518207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0060"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kruse</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Linder</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rigotti</surname><given-names>NA.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Implementation of an electronic health record-based care management system to improve tobacco treatment</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med.</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1690</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1696</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22865018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-012-2174-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3509313</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0061"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McEwen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hackshaw</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of a programme to increase referrals to stop-smoking services using Children&#8217;s Centres and smoke-free families schemes</article-title>. <source>Addiction.</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>107</volume>(<issue>Suppl 2</issue>):<fpage>8</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23121355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1360-0443.2012.04081.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0062"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>van Wijk</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Landais</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harting</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Understanding the multitude of barriers that prevent smokers in lower socioeconomic groups from accessing smoking cessation support: a literature review</article-title>. <source>Prev Med.</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>123</volume>:<fpage>143</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>151</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30902700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ypmed.2019.03.029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0063"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Azamar-Alonso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huebner</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tarride</surname><given-names>JE.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Electronic referral systems in health care: a scoping review</article-title>. <source>Clinicoecon Outcomes Res.</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>325</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>333</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31190925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/CEOR.S195597</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6511625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0064"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Faseru</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shireman</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Warm handoff versus fax referral for linking hospitalized smokers to quitlines</article-title>. <source>Am J Prev Med.</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>587</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>596</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27647059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amepre.2016.04.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5031370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0065"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bentz</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bayley</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bonin</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Provider feedback to improve 5A&#8217;s tobacco cessation in primary care: a cluster randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Nicotine Tob Res.</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>341</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>349</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17365766</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/14622200701188828</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0066"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Solberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fiore</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Use of electronic health records to support smoking cessation</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev.</source><year>2014</year>;(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>CD008743</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD008743.pub3</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25547090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7173728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0067"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Verbiest</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Crone</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Training health professionals in smoking cessation</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev.</source><year>2012</year>;(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>CD000214</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD000214.pub2</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22592671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10088066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>