<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3211</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jamasd</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JAMA Network Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2574-3805</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>JAMA Network</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10576209</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10576209.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10576209</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10576209</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37831450</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.37690</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zoi231101</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Investigation</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="online-only"><subject>Online Only</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="subject-area"><subject>Pediatrics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Health Insurance and Differences in Infant Mortality Rates in the US</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="headline">Health Insurance and Differences in Infant Mortality Rates in the US</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Health Insurance and Differences in Infant Mortality Rates in the US</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names initials="DL">Desalyn L.</given-names></name><degrees>BS</degrees><xref rid="zoi231101aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlo</surname><given-names initials="WA">Waldemar A.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi231101aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names initials="AKMF">A. K. M. Fazlur</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="zoi231101aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tindal</surname><given-names initials="R">Rachel</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi231101aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trulove</surname><given-names initials="SG">Sarah G.</given-names></name><degrees>MBA</degrees><xref rid="zoi231101aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watt</surname><given-names initials="MJ">Mykaela J.</given-names></name><degrees>BS</degrees><degrees>BA</degrees><xref rid="zoi231101aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Travers</surname><given-names initials="CP">Colm P.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi231101aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="zoi231101aff1"><label>1</label>University of Alabama School of Medicine, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham</aff><aff id="zoi231101aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Pediatrics, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham</aff><aff id="zoi231101aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Biostatistics, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham</aff><aff id="zoi231101aff4"><label>4</label>Brooke Army Medical Center, Houston, Texas</aff><author-notes><title>Article Information</title><p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> September 1, 2023.</p><p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published:</bold> October 13, 2023. doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.37690</uri></p><p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-license-permissions" ext-link-type="uri">CC-BY License</ext-link>. &#169; 2023 Johnson DL et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic>.</p><corresp id="zoi231101cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Colm P. Travers, MD, Department of Pediatrics, University of Alabama at Birmingham, 9380 Women and Infants Center, 1700 Sixth Ave S, Birmingham, AL 35233 (<email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cptravers@uabmc.edu">cptravers@uabmc.edu</email>).</corresp><p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Dr Rahman and Ms Watt had full access to all of the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Concept and design:</italic> Johnson, Travers.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> Johnson, Carlo, Rahman, Tindal, Trulove, Watt.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Johnson, Rahman, Trulove, Travers.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> Johnson, Carlo, Tindal, Watt.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Statistical analysis:</italic> Johnson, Rahman, Tindal, Trulove, Watt.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Obtained funding:</italic> Johnson, Travers.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Johnson, Carlo, Trulove, Watt, Travers.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Supervision:</italic> Travers.</p><p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr Carlo reported serving on the board of Mednax outside the submitted work. Dr Travers reported receiving grants from Owlet Baby Care, Inc, for an investigator-initiated study outside the submitted work; in addition, Dr Travers has a patent pending for a bradycardia predictor and interrupter. No other disclosures were reported.</p><p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> This study was supported by grants from the National Institute of Health (grant TL1TR003106 to Dr Johnson and grant K23HL157618 to Dr Travers) and the American Heart Association (grant 22HERNPMI985239 to Drs Travers and Carlo).</p><p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The funders had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p><p content-type="data-sharing-statement"><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> See the <xref rid="note-ZOI231101-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement</xref>.</p></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-10-13T10:00"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>10</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">447317</issue-id><elocation-id>e2337690</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-01-25 22:25:10.870"><day>25</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright 2023 Johnson DL et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic>.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2337690.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2337690.pdf">jamanetwopen-e2337690.pdf</self-uri><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.37690"/><abstract abstract-type="key-points"><title>Key Points</title><sec id="ab-zoi231101-1"><title>Question</title><p>Is health insurance type associated with differences in infant mortality rates?</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi231101-2"><title>Findings</title><p>In this cohort study of more than 13&#8201;million infants in the US, maternal private health insurance was associated with a lower risk of infant mortality and adverse infant outcomes compared with Medicaid public health insurance.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi231101-3"><title>Meaning</title><p>These findings suggest that there may be opportunities to improve access to care and reduce infant mortality among Medicaid-insured pregnancies in the US.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" specific-use="electronic"><p>This cohort study examines whether, compared with public Medicaid insurance, private insurance for the birthing parent is associated with a lower infant mortality rate among infants born in the US.</p></abstract><abstract><sec id="ab-zoi231101-4"><title>Importance</title><p>Health insurance status is associated with differences in access to health care and health outcomes. Therefore, maternal health insurance type may be associated with differences in infant outcomes in the US.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi231101-5"><title>Objective</title><p>To determine whether, among infants born in the US, maternal private insurance compared with public Medicaid insurance is associated with a lower infant mortality rate (IMR).</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi231101-6"><title>Design, Setting, and Participants</title><p>This cohort study used data from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) Wide-Ranging Online Data for Epidemiologic Research expanded linked birth and infant death records database from 2017 to 2020. Hospital-born infants from 20 to 42 weeks of gestational age were included if the mother had either private or Medicaid insurance. Infants with congenital anomalies, those without a recorded method of payment, and those without either private insurance or Medicaid were excluded. Data analysis was performed from June 2022 to August 2023.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi231101-7"><title>Exposures</title><p>Private vs Medicaid insurance.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi231101-8"><title>Main Outcomes and Measures</title><p>The primary outcome was the IMR. Negative-binomial regression adjusted for race, sex, multiple birth, any maternal pregnancy risk factors (as defined by the CDC), education level, and tobacco use was used to determine the difference in IMR between private and Medicaid insurance. The &#967;<sup>2</sup> or Fisher exact test was used to compare differences in categorical variables between groups.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi231101-9"><title>Results</title><p>Of the 13&#8201;562&#8201;625 infants included (6&#8201;631&#8201;735 girls [48.9%]), 7&#8201;327&#8201;339 mothers (54.0%) had private insurance and 6&#8201;235&#8201;286 (46.0%) were insured by Medicaid. Infants born to mothers with private insurance had a lower IMR compared with infants born to those with Medicaid (2.75 vs 5.30 deaths per 1000 live births; adjusted relative risk [aRR], 0.81; 95% CI, 0.69-0.95; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.009). Those with private insurance had a significantly lower risk of postneonatal mortality (0.81 vs 2.41 deaths per 1000 births; aRR, 0.57; 95% CI, 0.47-0.68; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001), low birth weight (aRR, 0.90; 95% CI, 0.85-0.94; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001), vaginal breech delivery (aRR, 0.80; 95% CI, 0.67-0.96; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.02), and preterm birth (aRR, 0.92; 95% CI, 0.88-0.97; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.002) and a higher probability of first trimester prenatal care (aRR, 1.24; 95% CI, 1.21-1.27; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) compared with those with Medicaid.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi231101-10"><title>Conclusions and Relevance</title><p>In this cohort study, maternal Medicaid insurance was associated with increased risk of infant mortality at the population level in the US. Novel strategies are needed to improve access to care, quality of care, and outcomes among women and infants enrolled in Medicaid.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="H1-1-ZOI231101"><title>Introduction</title><p>Infant mortality rates (IMRs) in the US are among the highest in the developed world at least in part because of a combination of racial,<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> regional,<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> and socioeconomic disparities.<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> The IMR is also substantially affected by high rates of preterm birth, which, in turn, may be affected by differences in the reporting of live births at the lowest gestations, and higher gestational age&#8211;specific IMRs within the US.<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="zoi231101r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="zoi231101r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Medicaid insurance covers pregnancy, perinatal, initial postpartum, and infant care among parents with a gross family income within 138% of the Federal Poverty Level. In 2019, 42.1% of all births in the US were covered by Medicaid insurance.<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> In some states, pregnant individuals are not automatically made beneficiaries upon conception but must go through an application process. It is possible that this process may result in higher rates of inadequate or delayed prenatal care, which is known to be associated with adverse infant outcomes.<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="zoi231101r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></p><p>In addition, Medicaid Enhanced Prenatal Care Programs that may improve access to prenatal care are associated with lower rates of infant mortality,<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> raising the question as to whether differences in care related to insurance type are associated with differences in infant mortality owing to underinsurance. Prior studies<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="zoi231101r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="zoi231101r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> have shown a higher risk of mortality among infants without insurance. Relatively few studies have compared private vs public insurance, focused on infant mortality as a single primary outcome, and adjusted for important confounders. We hypothesized that maternal private health insurance compared with Medicaid public health insurance would be associated with lower rates of infant mortality. In addition, we hypothesized that private health insurance would be associated with lower rates of inadequate prenatal care, and adverse pregnancy outcomes.</p></sec><sec id="H1-2-ZOI231101"><title>Methods</title><p>This cohort study obtained information recorded in the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention Wide-Ranging Online Data for Epidemiologic Research (CDC WONDER) expanded linked birth and infant death records database for 2017 to 2020. The inclusion criteria were all live births from 2017 to 2020 with an obstetrical estimate of 20 to 42 weeks of gestational age.<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> The study excluded stillbirths, infants with congenital anomalies and those who died as a result of congenital anomalies, those not born within a hospital, those without a recorded method of payment, and those without either private insurance or Medicaid. The Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/strobe/" ext-link-type="uri">STROBE</ext-link>) reporting guidelines for cohort studies were followed.<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> This study was reviewed by the University of Alabama at Birmingham institutional review board and was deemed non&#8211;human participant research; thus, informed consent was not required, in accordance with 45 CFR &#167;46.</p><p>All data were produced by the National Center for Health Statistics and were retrieved from the CDC WONDER expanded database using R statistical software version 4.0 (R Project for Statistical Computing). The primary outcome was the difference in IMR, defined as the number of deaths in the first 365 days after birth per 1000 live births, between private vs Medicaid insurance. Secondary outcome measures included the neonatal mortality rate (defined as the number of the deaths 0 to 27 days after birth per 1000 live births); the postneonatal mortality rate (defined as the number of the deaths from 28 to 364 days after birth per 1000 live births); the timing (trimester in which prenatal care started); the proportion of vaginal breech delivery; the proportion of prenatal steroid exposure; the proportion of low birth weight (&lt;2500 g), extremely low birth weight (&lt;1000 g), preterm (&lt;37 weeks&#8217; gestation), and extremely preterm (&lt;28 weeks&#8217; gestation) births; and the rate of maternal morbidity. Maternal morbidity used the CDC definition that includes maternal transfusion, perineal laceration, ruptured uterus, unplanned hysterectomy, and admission to an intensive care unit. Data on maternal race and ethnicity were obtained from the CDC WONDER database and are included in the analyses as a proxy for systematic racism in the US.</p><sec id="H2-1-ZOI231101"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>The statistical analyses compared those with private insurance and those with Medicaid insurance. We used negative-binomial regression to estimate the relative risk (RR) with 95% CI, adjusting for potential confounders, including race, infant sex, multiple birth, any maternal pregnancy risk factors (defined by the CDC as prepregnancy diabetes, gestational diabetes, gestational hypertension, eclampsia, previous preterm birth, and previous cesarean delivery), education level, and tobacco use. To examine differences in the timing of infant mortality by insurance type, a Kaplan-Meier survival analysis was conducted comparing infant mortality (event) by insurance type by day, from birth to 60 days after birth, and by month, from birth to 12 months after birth. A 2-sided <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.05 was used to indicate statistical significance. A sample size analysis was not performed for this population-based study. All analyses were performed using SAS statistical software version 9.4 (SAS Institute) between June 2022 and August 2023.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-3-ZOI231101"><title>Results</title><p>The study included 13&#8201;562&#8201;625 infants (6&#8201;631&#8201;735 girls [48.9%]), of whom 7&#8201;327&#8201;339 (54.0%) had mothers with private insurance and 6&#8201;235&#8201;286 (46.0%) had mothers with Medicaid. The private insurance cohort included fewer Black infants, less maternal tobacco use, and fewer female infants than the Medicaid cohort (<xref rid="zoi231101t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). There was a higher rate of multiple births and college degree obtainment in the private health insurance group. There was no difference in the proportion of mothers with at least 1 pregnancy risk factor between the private insurance cohort and the Medicaid cohort (<xref rid="zoi231101t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi231101t1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1. </label><caption><title>Baseline Demographics by Maternal Insurance Type</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="42.46%" span="1"/><col width="23.9%" span="1"/><col width="23.02%" span="1"/><col width="10.62%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Infants, No. (%) (N&#8201;=&#8201;13&#8201;562&#8201;625)</th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Private insurance (n&#8201;=&#8201;7&#8201;327&#8201;339)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medicaid (n&#8201;=&#8201;6&#8201;235&#8201;286)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maternal race</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> American Indian or Alaska Native</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29&#8201;954 (0.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93&#8201;112 (1.5)</td><td rowspan="6" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="zoi231101t1n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Asian</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">662&#8201;105 (9.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248&#8201;931 (4.0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Black or African American</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">677&#8201;404 (9.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#8201;537&#8201;953 (24.7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13&#8201;133 (0.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28&#8201;112 (0.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#8201;776&#8201;366 (78.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#8201;132&#8201;526 (66.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;1 Race</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168&#8201;377 (2.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">194&#8201;652 (3.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#8201;578&#8201;916 (48.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#8201;052&#8201;819 (49.0)</td><td rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="zoi231101t1n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#8201;748&#8201;423 (51.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#8201;182&#8201;467 (51.0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;1 Pregnancy risk factor</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#8201;962&#8201;350 (67.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#8201;216&#8201;479 (67.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.19</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple births</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">271&#8201;486 (3.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186&#8201;882 (3.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Associate&#8217;s degree or higher</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#8201;759&#8201;063 (64.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">879&#8201;142 (14.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tobacco user</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177&#8201;708 (2.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">686&#8201;385 (11.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.08</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="zoi231101t1n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Value is for Black vs non-Black groups.</p></fn><fn id="zoi231101t1n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Value is for female vs male birth.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec id="H2-2-ZOI231101"><title>Infant Mortality</title><p>Infants born to mothers with private insurance had a lower IMR compared with infants born to mothers insured by Medicaid (2.75 vs 5.30 deaths per 1000 births; adjusted relative risk [aRR], 0.81; 95% CI, 0.69-0.95; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.009) (<xref rid="zoi231101t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The neonatal mortality rate did not differ significantly between those who were privately insured compared with those with Medicaid (2.28 vs 2.89 deaths per 1000 births; aRR, 0.96; 95% CI, 0.83-1.11; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.61). The postneonatal mortality rate, however, was lower among infants born to mothers with private health insurance compared with Medicaid insurance (0.81 vs 2.41 deaths per 1000 births; aRR, 0.57; 95% CI, 0.47-0.68; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). Kaplan-Meier survival analysis demonstrated that IMR was lower for mothers with private insurance within 60 days after birth and in the first 12 months after birth (<xref rid="zoi231101f1" ref-type="fig">Figure</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi231101t2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2. </label><caption><title>Infant Mortality Outcomes by Health Insurance Type</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="28.37%" span="1"/><col width="20.85%" span="1"/><col width="14.05%" span="1"/><col width="26.33%" span="1"/><col width="10.4%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Variable</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Infant mortality rate, No. of deaths/1000 births</th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Adjusted RR (95% CI)<xref rid="zoi231101t2n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Private insurance</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medicaid</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.69-0.95)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.009</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neonatal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.28</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.89</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.83-1.11)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.61</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postneonatal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.41</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 (0.47-0.68)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviation: RR, relative risk.</p><fn id="zoi231101t2n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>RR for private vs Medicaid insurance was adjusted for race and ethnicity, sex, multiple birth, pregnancy risk factors, educational level, and tobacco exposure.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="zoi231101f1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure. </label><caption><title>Kaplan-Meier Survival Curves for Infant Mortality by Insurance Type</title><p>Infants with Medicaid had a lower survival probability than those with private insurance both within the first 60 days after birth (A) and within the first 12 months after birth (B) (both <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). The cohort includes infants born 2017 to 2020 with an obstetrical estimate of 20 to 42 weeks of gestational age. Stillbirths, infants with congenital anomalies, those not born within a hospital, those without a recorded method of payment, and those without either private insurance or Medicaid are excluded.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2337690-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="H2-3-ZOI231101"><title>Pregnancy Measures and Outcomes</title><p>Mothers of privately insured infants had a higher rate of prenatal care starting in the first trimester compared with mothers of Medicaid insured infants (aRR, 1.24; 95% CI, 1.21-1.27; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) (<xref rid="zoi231101t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Those with private insurance had lower rates of low birth weight birth (aRR, 0.90; 95% CI, 0.85-0.94; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001), preterm birth (aRR, 0.92; 95% CI, 0.88-0.97; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.002), and breech vaginal birth (aRR, 0.80; 95% CI, 0.67-0.96; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.02). Rates of maternal morbidity (aRR, 0.98; 95% CI, 0.85-1.13; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.75), extremely preterm birth (aRR, 0.91; 95% CI, 0.81-1.04; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.16), extremely low birth weight (aRR, 0.91; 95% CI, 0.79-1.04; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.15), and antenatal corticosteroid use (aRR, 0.97; 95% CI, 0.91-1.03; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.31) did not differ significantly between groups (<xref rid="zoi231101t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi231101t3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3. </label><caption><title>Secondary Pregnancy Measures and Outcomes by Insurance Type</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="33.92%" span="1"/><col width="20%" span="1"/><col width="19.13%" span="1"/><col width="19.13%" span="1"/><col width="7.82%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Outcome</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Infants, No. (%) (N&#8201;=&#8201;13&#8201;562&#8201;625)</th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Adjusted RR (95% CI)<xref rid="zoi231101t3n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Private insurance (n&#8201;=&#8201;7&#8201;327&#8201;339)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medicaid (n&#8201;=&#8201;6&#8201;235&#8201;286)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First trimester prenatal care</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#8201;279&#8201;517 (85.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#8201;160&#8201;368 (66.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 (1.21-1.27)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preterm birth</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">708&#8201;838 (9.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">743&#8201;430 (11.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.88-0.97)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Extremely preterm</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36&#8201;715 (0.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#8201;668 (0.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.81-1.04)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.16</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low birth weight</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">518&#8201;967 (7.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">604&#8201;695 (9.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 (0.85-0.94)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Extremely low birth weight</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37&#8201;402 (0.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46&#8201;065 (0.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.79-1.04)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.15</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vaginal breech delivery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8201;370 (0.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8201;193 (0.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 (0.67-0.96)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maternal morbidity</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114&#8201;482 (1.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71&#8201;963 (1.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 (0.85-1.13)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.75</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antenatal corticosteroids</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">252&#8201;346 (3.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">236&#8201;418 (3.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.91-1.03)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.31</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviation: RR, relative risk.</p><fn id="zoi231101t3n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>RR for private vs Medicaid insurance was adjusted for race, sex, multiple birth, pregnancy risk factors, education level, and tobacco use.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="H1-4-ZOI231101"><title>Discussion</title><p>This population-based cohort study found that maternal private insurance was associated with a lower IMR compared with maternal Medicaid insurance. This difference in mortality occurred primarily during the postneonatal time period. In addition, privately insured pregnancies had higher rates of early prenatal care, fewer preterm births, fewer low birth weight births, and fewer vaginal breech deliveries. Our study suggests that health care insurance coverage may be a modifiable risk factor for adverse pregnancy outcomes in the US.</p><p>Our findings support smaller or older studies reporting that maternal insurance status was associated with adverse infant outcomes, including IMR, low birth weight birth, prematurity, and complications of prematurity.<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="zoi231101r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="zoi231101r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> These include an 8-county study<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> conducted in the San Francisco Bay Area between 1982 to 1986. The findings revealed that a lack of health insurance was associated with increased risk of prolonged hospital stay, transfer to other medical institution, and infant death.<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Another study<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> used data from the Kids&#8217; Inpatient Database for the years 2003, 2006, and 2009. The study included more than 4 million infants (5.4% uninsured) and concluded that uninsured neonates had decreased risk of being admitted in transfer, decreased resource allocation, and increased risk of death in rural settings. A third study<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> included data for 24&#8201;151 infants obtained from the ParadigmHealth database between 2001 and 2005. In that study, infants with Medicaid were associated with lower birth weight, decreased Apgar score at 5 minutes, increased incidence of necrotizing enterocolitis and bacterial sepsis, and increased length of hospital stay. The study also suggested differences in postnatal resource allocation among infants by insurance status, including differences in discharge therapies such as home oxygen and apnea monitors.<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> In the current study, Medicaid insurance was not associated with differences in antenatal corticosteroid use, a key perinatal care practice among preterm infants.<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> However, there was a higher rate of breech vaginal birth among Medicaid recipients that may suggest differences in perinatal care practices between groups.<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="zoi231101r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup></p><p>In addition to higher rates of infant mortality, higher rates of postneonatal mortality were also seen in the Medicaid cohort in our study. Our findings of higher postneonatal IMRs align with a study<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> by the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development Neonatal Research Network that found a higher likelihood of post&#8211;neonatal intensive care unit discharge deaths among extremely preterm infants without private insurance. The cause of higher postneonatal mortality rates among Medicaid recipients was not evaluated in the current study, but common causes of postneonatal mortality, including sleep-related infant deaths, accidents and injuries, and infection-related deaths, may differ by socioeconomic status.<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup></p><p>Although expanded access to public health insurance has been associated with improved adult outcomes,<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> improving access to prenatal care through public insurance programs may also improve infant outcomes. Medicaid prenatal care expansion among immigrants in Oregon was associated with more prenatal care visits and improved adequacy of prenatal care, a lower extremely low birth weight rate, and a lower IMR, suggesting that increasing access to prenatal care could improve outcomes among Medicaid recipients.<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> In a previous study<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> of 9613 women who delivered in North Carolina, Medicaid insurance at delivery was associated with later initiation of prenatal care but no significant difference in rates of preterm birth or low birth weight birth, whereas data on infant mortality were not included. In the current study, we found differences between Medicaid-covered and privately insured women in early initiation of prenatal care. It is not known whether these differences are related to maternal health care&#8211;seeking behaviors or to Medicaid application delays.</p><p>There are important racial disparities in infant outcomes in the US.<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> However, genetic ancestry studies<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> suggest that the basis of race and/or ethnicity as a biological risk factor for adverse health outcomes is limited. In the current study, we adjusted for race as an important confounder related to socioeconomic status and institutional racism in the US.<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> The assertion that insurance status and related socioeconomic factors may be key factors responsible for differences in perinatal outcomes was supported by a recent study<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> from the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development Maternal-Fetal Medicine Units Network in which Black full-term neonates had worse perinatal composite outcomes. However, once adjusted for insurance status (private, government funded, or uninsured) the difference was no longer significant.</p><sec id="H2-4-ZOI231101"><title>Limitations</title><p>This study has limitations that should be mentioned. We used a national data set but we did not have access to individual-level data per CDC WONDER data use restrictions. Our data are not generalizable to all subgroups of infants within the US because we excluded infants with congenital anomalies and those born outside of a hospital. Given our large sample size and the relatively few excluded infants, the effect of this bias on the final results is likely modest. Our data only included the source of payment for delivery, which does not consider potential changes to insurance that may have occurred during the pregnancy or after delivery. The resulting bias could underestimate or overestimate the association of infant outcomes with insurance type but should have a small effect. In addition, we did not include self-pay insurance status, which was previously associated with higher rates of infant mortality compared with both mothers with Medicaid and mothers with private insurance using US national data for 2013 and 2017.<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> In secondary analyses, a lower rate of postneonatal mortality among mothers with private insurance compared with mothers with Medicaid was also reported after adjustment for maternal race, education, age, and marital status.<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Using additional data available in the CDC WONDER expanded linked birth and infant death records database, we adjusted for several important antenatal confounders, including maternal race as a proxy for systematic racism, sex, multiple birth, education level, tobacco exposure, and maternal pregnancy risk factors. We did not adjust for postnatal variables because we wanted to limit the adjustments to possible confounders known before birth. However, it is likely that there was residual bias not accounted for in our models, although factors implicated in infant mortality such as gestational age and birth weight may be directly related to insurance type and access to care.<sup><xref rid="zoi231101r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup></p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-5-ZOI231101"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In this cohort study, maternal private health insurance was associated with a lower IMR compared with Medicaid health insurance. In addition, privately insured pregnancies had higher rates of early prenatal care and fewer preterm and low birth weight births. There are opportunities to improve access to care and pregnancy outcomes among Medicaid insured pregnancies in the US.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="REF-ZOI231101"><title>References</title><ref id="zoi231101r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Travers</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carlo</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>Generic Database and Follow-up Subcommittees of the Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development Neonatal Research Network</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Racial/ethnic disparities among extremely preterm infants in the United States from 2002 to 2016</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<elocation-id>e206757</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.6757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32520359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7287569</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Travers</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Iannuzzi</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wingate</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prematurity and race account for much of the interstate variation in infant mortality rates in the United States</article-title>. <source>J Perinatol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>767</fpage>-<lpage>773</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41372-020-0640-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32152491</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Magallanes</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Majnik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Conquering racial disparities in perinatal outcomes</article-title>. <source>Clin Perinatol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>847</fpage>-<lpage>875</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clp.2014.08.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25459778</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>MacDorman</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mohangoo</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zeitlin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>International comparisons of infant mortality and related factors: United States and Europe, 2010</article-title>. <source>Natl Vital Stat Rep</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25252091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ambalavanan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wingate</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carlo</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Extremely low birth weight and infant mortality rates in the United States</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>131</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>855</fpage>-<lpage>860</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2012-2471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23545381</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Edstedt Bonamy</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zeitlin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Piedvache</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>Epice Research Group</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Wide variation in severe neonatal morbidity among very preterm infants in European regions</article-title>. <source>Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>F36</fpage>-<lpage>F45</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/archdischild-2017-313697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29353260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6762001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Osterman</surname><given-names>MJK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Driscoll</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Births: final data for 2019</article-title>. <source>Natl Vital Stat Rep</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33814033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><collab>American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists&#8217; Committee on Health Care for Underserved Women</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Protecting and expanding Medicaid to improve women&#8217;s health: ACOG Committee Opinion, number 826</article-title>. <source>Obstet Gynecol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>137</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e163</fpage>-<lpage>e168</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/AOG.0000000000004383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33760779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feijen-de Jong</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baarveld</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Determinants of prenatal health care utilisation by low-risk women: a prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Women Birth</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>87</fpage>-<lpage>94</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wombi.2015.01.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25682444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Meghea</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Raffo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leach</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Roman</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Statewide Medicaid enhanced prenatal care programs and infant mortality</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>136</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>334</fpage>-<lpage>342</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2015-0479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26148955</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Braveman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Oliva</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reiter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Egerter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Adverse outcomes and lack of health insurance among newborns in an eight-county area of California, 1982 to 1986</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>321</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>508</fpage>-<lpage>513</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM198908243210805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2761588</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morriss</surname><given-names>FH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Increased risk of death among uninsured neonates</article-title>. <source>Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1232</fpage>-<lpage>1255</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1475-6773.12042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23402526</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3725523</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brandon</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adeniyi-Jones</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kirkby</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Culhane</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Greenspan</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Are outcomes and care processes for preterm neonates influenced by health insurance status?</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>124</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>122</fpage>-<lpage>127</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2008-1318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19564291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>von Elm</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>G&#248;tzsche</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vandenbroucke</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>; <collab>STROBE Initiative</collab></person-group>. <article-title>The Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) statement: guidelines for reporting observational studies</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>370</volume>(<issue>9596</issue>):<fpage>1453</fpage>-<lpage>1457</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(07)61602-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18064739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McGoldrick</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dalziel</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Antenatal corticosteroids for accelerating fetal lung maturation for women at risk of preterm birth</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<elocation-id>CD004454</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD004454.pub4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33368142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8094626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hofmeyr</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hannah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrie</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Planned caesarean section for term breech delivery</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>2015</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<elocation-id>CD000166</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD000166.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26196961</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6505736</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Grabovac</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karim</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Isayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liyanage</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>What is the safest mode of birth for extremely preterm breech singleton infants who are actively resuscitated? a systematic review and meta-analyses</article-title>. <source>BJOG</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>125</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>652</fpage>-<lpage>663</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1471-0528.14938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28921813</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>De Jesus</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pappas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shankaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development Neonatal Research Network</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for post-neonatal intensive care unit discharge mortality among extremely low birth weight infants</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>161</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>70</fpage>-<lpage>4.e1-2</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpeds.2011.12.038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22325187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3366175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Deaths: leading causes for 2017</article-title>. <source>Natl Vital Stat Rep</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>77</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32501203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wherry</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>How have ACA insurance expansions affected health outcomes? findings from the literature</article-title>. <source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>371</fpage>-<lpage>378</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2019.01436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32119632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Swartz</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hainmueller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Expanding prenatal care to unauthorized immigrant women and the effects on infant health</article-title>. <source>Obstet Gynecol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>130</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>938</fpage>-<lpage>945</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/AOG.0000000000002275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29016491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5679477</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Insurance differences in preventive care use and adverse birth outcomes among pregnant women in a Medicaid nonexpansion state: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>J Womens Health (Larchmt)</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/jwh.2019.7658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31397625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6983742</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic structure of human populations</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>298</volume>(<issue>5602</issue>):<fpage>2381</fpage>-<lpage>2385</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1078311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12493913</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>David</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>J</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Disparities in infant mortality: what&#8217;s genetics got to do with it?</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>97</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1191</fpage>-<lpage>1197</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2005.068387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17538073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1913086</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Parchem</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Grobman</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health Human Development Maternal-Fetal Medicine Units (MFMU) Network</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Racial and ethnic disparities in adverse perinatal outcomes at term</article-title>. <source>Am J Perinatol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>557</fpage>-<lpage>566</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0041-1730348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34058765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8630098</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Min</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Min</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Disparities in infant mortality by payment source for delivery in the United States</article-title>. <source>Prev Med</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>145</volume>:<elocation-id>106361</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ypmed.2020.106361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33309872</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi231101r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of state Medicaid expansion status with low birth weight and preterm birth</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>321</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>1598</fpage>-<lpage>1609</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2019.3678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31012935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6487545</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><notes notes-type="supplementary-material" id="note-ZOI231101-1"><supplementary-material id="note-ZOI231101-1-s" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplement.</label><caption><p>
Data Sharing Statement
</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2337690-s001.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></notes></back></article></pmc-articleset>