<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Respir Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Respir Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">80</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">rr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Respiratory Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1465-9921</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1465-993X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11465623</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11465623.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11465623</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11465623</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39385232</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-024-02995-9</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2995</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Treatment patterns and patient journey in progressive pulmonary fibrosis: a cross-sectional survey</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhuri</surname><given-names initials="N">Nazia</given-names></name><address><email>nazia.chaudhuri@nhs.net</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spagnolo</surname><given-names initials="P">Paolo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valenzuela</surname><given-names initials="C">Claudia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amatto</surname><given-names initials="VC">Valeria C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names initials="OT">Oliver-Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names initials="L">Lauren</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Small</surname><given-names initials="M">Mark</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreuter</surname><given-names initials="M">Michael</given-names></name><address><email>Michael.Kreuter@marienhaus.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01yp9g959</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.12641.30</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0551 9715</institution-id><institution>Faculty of Life and Health Sciences, School of Medicine, </institution><institution>Ulster University, </institution></institution-wrap>Magee Campus, Londonderry, UK </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00240q980</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5608.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1757 3470</institution-id><institution>Respiratory Disease Unit, Department of Cardiac, Thoracic, Vascular Sciences and Public Health, </institution><institution>University of Padova, </institution></institution-wrap>Padova, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5515.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000119578126</institution-id><institution>ILD Unit, Pulmonology Department, Hospital Universitario de la Princesa, </institution><institution>Universidad Aut&#243;noma de Madrid, </institution></institution-wrap>Madrid, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.420061.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2171 7500</institution-id><institution>TA Inflammation Med, Boehringer Ingelheim International GmbH, </institution></institution-wrap>Ingelheim am Rhein, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Adelphi Real World, Bollington, UK </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410607.4</institution-id><institution>Mainz Center for Pulmonary Medicine, Department of Pneumology ZfT, Department of Pulmonary, Critical Care &amp; Sleep Medicine, </institution><institution>Mainz University Medical Center, Marienhaus Clinic Mainz, </institution></institution-wrap>Mainz, Germany </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">452476</issue-id><elocation-id>364</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>09</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-10-11 10:25:47.227"><day>11</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12931_2024_Article_2995.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par7">For patients with interstitial lung diseases (ILDs) presenting with a progressive pulmonary fibrosis (PPF) phenotype, current knowledge of disease characteristics at diagnosis, patient journey, and treatment is limited. This study aimed to describe demographics and clinical experiences of patients presenting with PPF in a European real-world setting.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par8">Data were analysed from the Adelphi Real World PPF-ILD Disease Specific Programme&#8482;, a cross-sectional survey of pulmonologists and rheumatologists in five European countries (France, Germany, Italy, Spain, United Kingdom) and internal medicine specialists (France) from April to October 2022. Physicians provided data for up to 12 consecutive patients with physician-confirmed ILD with a progressive phenotype other than idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. Analyses were descriptive.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par9">Overall, 265 physicians reported on 1,335 patients. Mean (standard deviation) age at survey date was 60.4 (11.6) years, 91.2% were white, 58.1% female, 44.0% non-smokers. Most patients (63.3%) first consulted a primary care physician. There was a mean delay of 7.8 (22.7) months between first ILD symptom and healthcare professional visit, and another 7.7 (12.8) months to ILD diagnosis. At survey date, 47.7% of patients had physician-reported moderate ILD, 42.3% had mild ILD and 10.0% had severe ILD. Disease progression was reported in the 12 months prior to the survey for 19.5% of patients; of these, progression was based on worsening symptom in 27.3% and lung function decline in 25.8%. For patients experiencing symptoms prior to ILD diagnosis (72.8%), the most common symptoms were dyspnoea on exertion (80.5%) and cough (57.8%). Overall, 17.4% of patients were misdiagnosed prior to ILD diagnosis, with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease suspected in 39.2% of them. The most frequent comorbidities were anxiety (16.9%) and gastroesophageal reflux (15.5%). Although 77.8% of patients were receiving treatment for ILD at survey date, 15.6% of patients had never been prescribed treatment for ILD.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par10">This real-world study expands our understanding of patients, diagnostic delays and treatment gaps experienced by patients diagnosed with PPF in Europe. There was a mean delay of 15.5 months between first ILD symptoms and ILD diagnosis. Given the progressive nature of PPF, diagnostic delay may lead to poor outcomes, including shorter survival.</p></sec><sec><title>Trial registration</title><p id="Par11">N/a.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12931-024-02995-9.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Pulmonary fibrosis</kwd><kwd>Progressive pulmonary fibrosis</kwd><kwd>Interstitial lung disease</kwd><kwd>Antifibrotics</kwd><kwd>Market research</kwd><kwd>Survey</kwd><kwd>Real-world data</kwd><kwd>Patient journey</kwd><kwd>Treatment patterns</kwd><kwd>Diagnosis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100008349</institution-id><institution>Boehringer Ingelheim</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par13">Interstitial lung diseases (ILDs) are a large and heterogeneous group of parenchymal pulmonary disorders, some of which have a progressive fibrosing phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF), the archetypal progressive fibrosing ILD and the most common idiopathic interstitial pneumonia, is characterised by chronic progressive fibrosis, worsening of lung function and dyspnoea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], and has a life expectancy of approximately 3&#8211;5 years after diagnosis if left untreated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Approximately one third of patients with fibrosing ILDs other than IPF may experience disease progression, defined as progressive pulmonary fibrosis (PPF) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p><p id="Par14">There are currently two licensed therapies for IPF, pirfenidone and nintedanib, which have been shown to slow the rate of lung function decline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Nintedanib has also been approved for the treatment of progressive fibrosing ILDs other than IPF (i.e., PPF), and ILD associated with systemic sclerosis (SSc-ILD) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. However, the rate of patient access to treatment is mixed. In the INSIGHTS-ILD registry of patients in Germany with PPF (excluding IPF), 45.8% were receiving nintedanib and 2.1% were receiving pirfenidone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], whereas in the US-based ILD-PRO registry of patients with PPF (also excluding IPF), 19.8% were receiving nintedanib and 3.6% were receiving pirfenidone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p><p id="Par15">PPF is characterised by worsening respiratory symptoms, decline in lung function, radiographic progression and early mortality despite appropriate management, and may have a clinical course similar to IPF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Regardless of the underlying condition, PPF occurs through similar mechanisms of self-sustained dysregulated cell repair, fibroblast proliferation and alveolar dysfunction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. However, patients with certain types of fibrosing ILDs are more prone to progression than others: it has been estimated that PPF can develop in 53% of patients with unclassifiable ILD (uILD), 40% of patients with SSc-ILD, 32% of patients with rheumatoid arthritis-associated ILD (RA-ILD), and in 21% of patients with fibrotic hypersensitivity pneumonitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p><p id="Par16">In addition, the ILD disease course may be heterogeneous, with different rates and patterns of progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. PPF has been shown to be associated with significantly higher healthcare resource utilisation (HCRU) compared with non-progressive fibrosing ILDs&#160;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Several studies have shown that patients with PPF required more follow-up visits, hospitalisations, days in hospital and laboratory/imaging tests than patients with ILD that is non-progressive or slowly progressing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Indirect costs such as loss of work productivity, job losses or early retirement were also higher for patients with PPF than those with the non-progressive phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p><p id="Par17">There is a good understanding of the epidemiology and burden of IPF as well as its frequent association with other diseases and comorbidities. The presence of these comorbidities may cause a delay in diagnosis and interfere with the disease course, thus impacting patient prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. However, little is known about the burden of PPF, the patient journey to diagnosis, the prevalence of associated comorbidities and its impact on patients&#8217; quality of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Likewise, there is a lack of understanding of the best approach to diagnose, manage and treat PPF. Therefore, this study aimed to investigate the burden, diagnosis, referral patterns and current management practices of PPF in a European real-world setting.</p><p id="Par18">Note on terminology: this study was devised, and the data collected, before publication of the updated 2022 guidelines for IPF and PPF by the American Thoracic Society (ATS), the European Respiratory Society (ERS), the Japanese Respiratory Society (JRS), and the Latin American Thoracic Association (ALAT), which provided a definition of PPF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. No specific definition of progression was used, but the disease was required to have a progressive phenotype in the opinion of the treating physician. However, for clarity, the term PPF is used throughout this manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design</title><p id="Par19">Data were drawn from the Adelphi Real World PPF-ILD Disease Specific Programme (DSP)<sup>TM</sup>, a cross-sectional survey of physicians (pulmonologists, rheumatologists or internal medicine specialists [France only]) in Europe (France, Germany, Italy, Spain, the United Kingdom [UK]) who had access to medical history data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Full details of the DSP methodology have been published previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p><p id="Par20">Physicians captured data on patient demographics, clinical characteristics, symptom burden and impact, patient management, treatment utilisation and decision-making in routine care. All information was recorded at a single point in time during the period April to October 2022 using available medical history or a specified recall period for physicians (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>); no follow-up information was collected.</p><p id="Par21">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Schematic of information collection in the PPF-ILD DSP study. DSP, Disease Specific Programme; ILD, interstitial lung disease; PPF, progressive pulmonary fibrosis</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e399" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12931_2024_2995_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Data collection</title><p id="Par22">Participating physicians completed surveys, which provided general information on management, referrals, usage, and awareness of antifibrotics and attitudes towards PPF. Physicians were instructed to complete patient record forms (PRFs) for up to 12 consecutively consulted patients with a physician-confirmed ILD diagnosis with a progressive phenotype. Each record included details regarding patient demographics, clinical characteristics (including physician-perceived disease severity, or according to Goh&#8217;s criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] for SSc-ILD only, at different stages in the patient&#8217;s journey), symptom burden and treatment history. Prospective PRFs were completed by the physician for qualifying patients as and when they consulted the physician (main DSP sample). Retrospective PRFs were collected to augment the size of the main DSP sample and were completed by additional physicians (i.e., those who had not completed surveys as part of the main DSP sample) for their last 4&#8211;6 qualifying patients. Physician-reported disease severity (mild, moderate, severe) and progression (improving, stable, progressing) were based on physician opinion and not predefined. The terms &#8216;[progressive fibrosing] PF-ILD&#8217; and &#8216;[connective tissue disease] CTD-ILD&#8217; were used in the physician surveys and PRFs.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Study population</title><p id="Par23">Patients were eligible for inclusion if they were aged over 18 years, had a physician-confirmed diagnosis of ILD and presented with a progressive phenotype (PPF), as determined by the reporting physician. No clinical definition of a progressive phenotype was pre-specified as the study was performed prior to publication of the current ATS/ERS/JRS/ALAT guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]; diagnoses therefore included the following: idiopathic non-specific interstitial pneumonia (iNSIP), fibrotic hypersensitivity pneumonitis, uILD, SSc-ILD, RA-ILD, polymyositis/dermatomyositis-ILD and Sj&#246;gren&#8217;s-associated ILD. Patients with IPF were excluded.</p><p id="Par24">Target physicians were identified in the respective European countries from public lists of healthcare professionals (HCPs). Physicians were pulmonologists, rheumatologists, or internal medicine specialists. To be included in the study, pulmonologists were required to see at least four different types of qualifying ILDs in a typical month, internal medicine specialists were required to see at least four qualifying patients with ILD in a typical month, and rheumatologists were required to see at least two different types of CTD-ILD (RA-ILD, SSc-ILD, polymyositis/dermatomyositis-ILD or Sj&#246;gren&#8217;s-associated ILD) in a typical month.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Data analyses</title><p id="Par25">As the primary research objective was descriptive in nature (i.e., no a priori hypotheses specified), the available sample size of physicians and patients was driven by the DSP data collection methodology. Formal sample size calculations were not applicable, and therefore not performed, meaning that the sample size impacted the precision of any estimates (see Supplementary Methods in Additional File 1 for details; Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). Descriptive analyses were undertaken by Adelphi Real World and conducted in UNICOM<sup>&#174;</sup> Data Collection Survey Reporter (UNICOM Global, Inc, Mission Hills, CA, USA). Descriptive statistics were used to characterise demographics, clinical characteristics, symptom burden/impact, treatment history, patient ILD milestones and consultation history, hospitalisation and HCRU. For age-based patient ILD milestones (e.g., age at first HCP visit, age at first symptom, age at diagnosis), only patients with a value recorded for each of the milestones were included. Bivariate analyses (Fisher&#8217;s exact test, T-test) were used to compare demographic data for patients with CTD-ILD and other types of ILD.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Ethics statement</title><p id="Par26">Data were collected by local fieldwork partners, and both physician and patient data were de-identified prior to receipt by Adelphi. The study received Pearl Institutional Review Board ethical exemption (22-ADRW-135) and was conducted adhering to European Pharmaceutical Market Research Association guidelines and Adelphi Real World standard operating procedures.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>PPF-ILD DSP survey sample</title><p id="Par27">Two hundred and sixty-five physicians participated in the survey and completed PRFs for 1335 patients with a physician-confirmed ILD diagnosis with PPF (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The sample was composed of 66.1% pulmonologists, 30.9% rheumatologists and 3.1% internal medicine specialists (only recruited in France). The largest group of patients were based in Germany (24.6%) and the smallest in the UK (13.8%) (Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). The ratio of patients to physicians was greatest in France (6.9) and lowest in the UK (3.7).</p><p id="Par28">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Study sample size</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Physician specialty</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Physician surveys*</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient record forms</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">265</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,335</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Pulmonologist</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">175</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">790</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Rheumatologist</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">484</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Internal medicine</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Completed by all physicians prospectively completing patient record forms for the survey</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Patient demographics</title><p id="Par29">The mean (standard deviation [SD]) age of patients at the survey date was 60.4 (11.6) years, 91.2% were white, 58.1% were female, 44.0% were non-smokers, and mean (SD) body mass index was 25.3 (3.9) kg/m<sup>2</sup> (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Few patients (5.4%) had a family history of ILD. At the survey date, 25.2% of patients were in full-time employment. Of those not in full-time employment (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;806), 18.9% were unable to work full-time due to their ILD (either working part-time, retired, on long-term sick leave or unemployed).</p><p id="Par30">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Patient demographics by type of PPF</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Type of PPF</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Other ILDs</th><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">CTD-ILD</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1,335)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">iNSIP<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;263)*</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fibrotic HP<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;225)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">uILD<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;133)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SSc-ILD<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;263)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RA-ILD<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;269)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM/DM-ILD<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;83)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SS-ILD<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;99)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age, mean (SD)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.38</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.83</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.76</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.68</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.68</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.73</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BMI, mean (SD)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.88</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.42</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.89</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.99</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.57</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female sex, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">776</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">126</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">223</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">166</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58.13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.90</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.71</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.86</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.84</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ethnicity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;White/Caucasian</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,217 (91.16)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">245 (93.16)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">216 (96.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">121 (90.98)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">237 (90.11)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">251 (93.31)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61 (73.49)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86 (86.87)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Asian (Indian subcontinent)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (0.82)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.44)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.75)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (1.52)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (2.41)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (3.03)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Asian (other)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (0.37)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.75)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.76)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (2.41)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Hispanic/Latino</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (2.25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (1.90)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (1.33)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (2.26)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (2.28)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (2.23)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (6.02)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (2.02)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Middle Eastern</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (1.87)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.38)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.44)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (3.01)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (2.66)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (1.86)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (6.02)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (2.02)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Mixed race</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (0.75)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (3.04)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.37)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.01)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Afro-Caribbean</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (2.10)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (1.14)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (1.33)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (1.50)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (1.90)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (1.12)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (8.43)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (5.05)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;South-East Asian</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (0.67)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.38)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.44)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.75)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.76)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (1.12)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.20)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Current smoker</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98 (7.34)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (9.51)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (8.44)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (9.02)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (4.18)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (7.43)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (6.02)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (6.06)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Ex-smoker</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">612 (45.84)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">128 (48.67)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104 (46.22)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59 (44.36)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">107 (40.68)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">140 (52.04)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32 (38.55)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (42.42)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Never smoked</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">588 (44.04)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103 (39.16)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99 (44.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60 (45.11)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">132 (50.19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99 (36.80)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46 (55.42)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (49.49)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Don&#8217;t know</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37 (2.77)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (2.66)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (1.33)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (1.50)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (4.94)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (3.72)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (2.02)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Employment status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Working full-time</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">336 (25.17)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70 (26.62)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64 (28.44)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (15.04)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60 (22.81)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65 (24.16)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (33.73)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (29.29)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Working part-time</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">145 (10.86)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (7.60)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (8.44)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (4.51)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (15.97)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (10.04)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (16.87)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (17.17)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;On long-term sick leave</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76 (5.69)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (3.80)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (6.22)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (5.26)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (9.13)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (4.83)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (8.43)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.01)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Homemaker</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161 (12.06)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37 (14.07)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (6.67)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (8.27)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (18.63)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (10.78)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (6.02)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (15.15)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Student</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.07)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.20)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Retired</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">517 (38.73)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">114 (43.35)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98 (43.56)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79 (59.40)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64 (24.33)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">116 (43.12)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (20.48)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (29.29)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Unemployed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68 (5.09)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (2.66)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (2.67)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (7.52)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (5.70)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (4.83)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (12.05)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (7.07)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Don&#8217;t know</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (2.32)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (1.90)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (4.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (3.42)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (2.23)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.20)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.01)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Total for iNSIP for age is <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;262</p><p>BMI, body mass index;&#160;CTD, connective tissue disease; DM, dermatomyositis; HP, hypersensitivity pneumonitis; iNSIP, idiopathic non-specific interstitial pneumonia; ILD, interstitial lung disease; PM, polymyositis; PPF, progressive pulmonary fibrosis; RA, rheumatoid arthritis; SD, standard deviation; SS, Sj&#246;gren&#8217;s; SSc, systemic sclerosis; uILD, unclassifiable interstitial lung disease</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par31">Numerically, patient demographics as defined by country or physician specialty were similar (Tables <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). The proportion of patients either working part-time, retired, on long-term sick leave or unemployed due to their ILD was comparable with the main survey population (20.1%) for both patients with CTD-ILD and other types of ILD (21.9% and 18.3%, respectively; Fisher&#8217;s exact test <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.2387). However, patients with CTD-ILD were significantly younger than those with other types of ILD (58.0 [SD 11.0] and 62.3 [SD 11.7] years, respectively; t-test <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), and a greater proportion were female (73.7% and 40.3%, respectively; t-test <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001) (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Clinical characteristics</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Disease severity</title><p id="Par32">Based on physician-reported disease severity, more patients were reported to have moderate ILD (47.7%) at survey date than mild (42.3%) or severe ILD (10.0%). The proportion of patients with severe ILD varied by reporting physician (rheumatologists 5.8%, pulmonologists 12.5%), country (Germany 0.6%, Spain 15.6%) and type of ILD (Sj&#246;gren&#8217;s-associated ILD 3.0%, polymyositis/dermatomyositis-associated ILD 14.5%) (Figure <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). For patients with SSc-ILD (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;263), most patients were classed as having limited disease (73.4%) compared with extensive disease (26.6%) for physician-reported severity of ILD according to Goh&#8217;s criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] at survey date (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par33">
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Physician-rated severity of SSc-ILD according to Goh&#8217;s criteria. ILD, interstitial lung disease; SSc, systemic sclerosis; UK, United Kingdom</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1201" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12931_2024_2995_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Disease progression</title><p id="Par34">Overall, 19.5% of patients were reported as progressing in the 12 months prior to survey date (moderately progressing 16.6%, severely progressing 2.9%), 52.2% were stable, 26.1% were improving and 2.3% were too early to tell. For those patients deemed to have progression, physicians provided one main reason for their assessment; the most frequent were worsening symptom severity (27.3%), decline in lung function (forced vital capacity [FVC] and diffusing capacity of the lungs for carbon monoxide [DLco]; 25.8%) or increased fibrosis on imaging (14.2%) (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Reasons for progression varied by country and physician specialty (Tables <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref> &amp; <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S8</xref>). For example, progression due to symptom severity ranged between 15.0% in Spain to 42.2% in the UK. Progression was reported based on symptom severity for 26.4% of patients seeing a pulmonologist and 32.6% of patients seeing a rheumatologist, and based on decline in FVC or DLco for 27.4% of patients seeing a pulmonologist and 17.4% of patients seeing a rheumatologist. Reasons for progression varied by type of ILD, with symptom severity (30.4%) or increased extent of fibrosis (19.6%) mostly reported for uILD; for RA-ILD, progression was mostly reported due to decline in lung function (29.2%) or symptom severity (25.0%) (Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S9</xref>).</p><p id="Par35">
<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Physician-reported reasons for disease progression in the last 12 months. CT, computed tomography; DLco, diffusing capacity of the lungs for carbon monoxide; FVC, forced vital capacity; HRCT, high-resolution CT; ILD, interstitial lung disease</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1227" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12931_2024_2995_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par36">Of those patients diagnosed with ILD less than 1 year before survey date, 16.8% of patients were reported to have moderately or severely progressing disease compared with 21.0% of patients diagnosed more than 1 year before (Figure <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). Physicians expected that over the next 12 months from the survey date, progression would stabilise for more than half (61.4%) of all patients. This ranged from 48.1% of patients with uILD to 70.3% of patients with RA-ILD. Expected progression in the next 12 months from the survey date based on physician perspective was aligned with clinical parameters, with patients considered as progressing presenting with lower FVC and DLco (Figure <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Comorbidities</title><p id="Par37">A total of 61.8% of patients had at least one comorbidity; the mean (SD) number of comorbidities per patient was 1.3 (1.5) and ranged from 0 to 12. The most frequent physician-reported comorbidities were anxiety (16.9%), gastroesophageal reflux (15.5%), depression (13.4%), diabetes without chronic complications (10.0%) and pulmonary hypertension (9.0%). There was some variation in comorbidities reported according to country, physician specialty and type of ILD (Tables <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S10</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S12</xref>). For example, anxiety was most frequently reported in Italy (24.7%) and France (22.5%) (lowest in Germany at 3.1% of patients) and pulmonary hypertension was reported for 14.5% of patients with SSc-ILD and 6.0% each of patients with RA-ILD and polymyositis/dermatomyositis-ILD.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Treatment</title><p id="Par38">Mean (SD) age at initial treatment was 57.8 (12.3) years (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1,000). A total of 77.8% of patients were receiving treatment for their ILD at the survey date; of those, low-dose prednisone (41.5%), nintedanib (30.9%) and mycophenolate (19.1%) were the most frequent treatments (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Of those prescribed low-dose prednisone (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;431), 21.3% were prescribed low-dose prednisone only and 78.7% were prescribed low-dose prednisone plus other treatment; of those prescribed nintedanib (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;321), 34.0% were prescribed nintedanib only and 66.0% were prescribed nintedanib plus other treatments; of those prescribed mycophenolate (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;198), 16.2% were prescribed mycophenolate only and 83.8% were prescribed mycophenolate plus other treatments.</p><p id="Par39">
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Patient treatment history</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Patient treatment</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patients currently prescribed a treatment for their ILD, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1335</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,039 (77.83)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;No, but previously prescribed treatment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 (6.59)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;No, has never been prescribed treatment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">208 (15.58)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Duration of current ILD treatment, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">705</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Mean, years (SD)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.64 (3.88)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Treatment prescribed to treat underlying autoimmune disease, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">586</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Currently prescribed treatment for ILD, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1039</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Low-dose prednisone</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">431 (41.48)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Nintedanib</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">321 (30.90)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Mycophenolate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">198 (19.06)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Methotrexate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">152 (14.63)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Cough suppressants</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">133 (12.80)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Rituximab</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">130 (12.51)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Inhaled corticosteroids</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">128 (12.32)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;High-dose prednisone</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">126 (12.13)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Oxygen therapy</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94 (9.05)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Azathioprine</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92 (8.85)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Pirfenidone</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81 (7.80)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (4.04)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Tocilizumab</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (3.27)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Cyclophosphamide</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (2.31)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Baricitinib</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (1.15)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Tacrolimus</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (0.96)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Upadacitinib</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (0.87)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Cyclosporine</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (0.38)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Tofacitinib</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (0.38)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Peficitinib</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Apremilast</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Next course of action for inadequate response to current treatment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1039</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Switch product and replace</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">195 (18.77)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Increase dose</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">178 (17.13)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Add a product to current regimen</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">172 (16.55)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Pulmonary rehabilitation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">122 (11.74)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Oxygen support</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80 (7.70)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Lung transplant</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52 (5.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Reduce dose</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36 (3.46)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Stem cell transplant</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (1.83)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Don&#8217;t know</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">190 (18.29)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reason for never prescribing treatment for ILD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">208</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Profile is manageable without treatment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101 (48.56)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Symptoms not severe enough to warrant treatment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (20.67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Diagnosed too recently</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36 (17.31)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Patient request</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (16.35)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Patient concerns over side effects</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (15.87)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Due to the underlying autoimmune disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (4.81)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Lack of information in current treatment guidelines</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (4.81)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Lack of evidence of the efficacy of current drug treatments available</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (4.33)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;No approved therapies specifically for ILD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (3.85)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Waiting for new drugs/products to be approved by regulatory bodies</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (3.37)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Disease-modifying treatment considered last option of care</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (1.44)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Medication is not covered by the patient&#8217;s insurance</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.96)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (6.73)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are n (%) unless otherwise indicated</p><p>ILD, interstitial lung disease; SD, standard deviation</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par40">For those with available data (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;705; 67.9%), mean (SD) current treatment duration was 1.6 (3.9) years at survey date. The proportion of patients currently prescribed treatment varied by country (ranging from Germany 88.4% to France 71.7%), physician specialty (pulmonologists 60.0%, rheumatologists 43.2%) and type of ILD (polymyositis/dermatomyositis-associated ILD 88.0%, uILD 54.1%) (Tables <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S13</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S15</xref>).</p><p id="Par41">If current treatment was deemed to be inadequate as judged by the treating physician, the most frequently reported next steps included switching to a different treatment (18.8%), increasing the dose (17.1%), or adding a treatment to the existing regimen (16.6%), although 18.3% of physicians did not know what the next course of action would be (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). A numerically higher proportion of physicians in the UK would switch treatment compared with physicians in Germany (29.6% and 13.8%, respectively) (Figure <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>).</p><p id="Par42">Some patients (6.6%) were not receiving treatment for their ILD at survey date but had previously been treated (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Of these, 44.3% had discontinued low-dose prednisone, 33.0% discontinued high-dose prednisone, and 20.5% discontinued nintedanib. The main reasons given by physicians for discontinuing treatment were side effects (26.1%) and poor adherence to prescribed treatment (23.9%). Overall, 15.6% of patients had never been prescribed treatment for their ILD (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The most common reason for never receiving treatment as reported by physicians was the disease being considered manageable without treatment (48.6%), which was consistent across countries, physician specialty and type of ILD.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Patient journey</title><sec id="Sec17"><title>Clinical milestones</title><p id="Par43">A total of 534 patients (40.0%) had data available regarding their diagnostic journey (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). For these patients, the mean (SD) age at first symptom of ILD was 56.9 (12.0) years, mean age at first HCP visit was 57.6 (12.1) years, and mean age at confirmed ILD diagnosis was 58.2 (12.2) years (Tables <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S16</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S18</xref>). In total, there was an average of 15.5 months between first ILD symptoms and ILD diagnosis.</p><p id="Par44">
<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Patient journey for ILD in Europe. HCP, healthcare professional; ILD, interstitial lung disease; PCP, primary care physician</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1621" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12931_2024_2995_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par45">Patient journey varied by country, reporting physician and type of ILD. For example, patients in Germany were generally younger across all milestones (e.g., mean age [SD] 52.2 [9.5] years at first symptom of ILD compared with 60.0 [11.2] years for patients in Spain). Pulmonologists reported that patients were older at first ILD symptom (mean [SD] 59.4 [11.5] years) and first HCP visit (60.2 [11.5] years) than those reported by rheumatologists (54.6 [11.2] years and 54.9 [11.2] years, respectively). Patients with Sj&#246;gren&#8217;s-associated ILD had a confirmed diagnosis of ILD at a mean (SD) age of 48.2 (14.0) years, whereas patients with SSc-ILD were mean age 62.8 (12.4) years at diagnosis.</p><p id="Par46">There was a mean (SD) delay of 7.8 (22.7) months between first ILD symptom and first HCP visit, with a further delay of 7.7 (12.8) months between first HCP visit and ILD diagnosis. This varied by country, with mean (SD) delay between first HCP visit and ILD diagnosis of 5.5 (7.2) months in France and 10.5 (14.5) months in Spain. Patients seeing a pulmonologist generally had a longer mean delay between first HCP visit and confirmed diagnosis of ILD (mean [SD] 9.1 [14.0] months). The mean delay between first HCP visit and ILD diagnosis varied between type of ILD; however, there was also wide variation within each type of ILD.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Symptom burden and diagnosis</title><p id="Par47">Of those patients reporting or presenting with symptoms at the survey date (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1,007), 72.8% of them experienced symptoms of ILD prior to a confirmed diagnosis. The most frequent symptoms experienced prior to an ILD diagnosis were dyspnoea on exertion (80.5%), cough (57.8%) and dyspnoea following exertion (37.0%). Among the 1,007 patients reporting symptoms in the 4 weeks prior to survey date, the most frequent were dyspnoea on exertion (78.4%) and cough (49.4%).</p><p id="Par48">Overall, 232 patients (17.4%) were diagnosed with another condition prior to ILD diagnosis; of these, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) was suspected or investigated in 39.2% of patients and asthma in 22.4% of patients. Rates for conditions suspected or investigated prior to ILD diagnosis varied by country, reporting physician specialty and type of ILD (Tables <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S19</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S21</xref>). In Germany (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;54), COPD was the most frequently suspected or investigated condition (77.8%), whereas in Spain (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;52), asthma (32.7%) was the most frequent. For pulmonologists (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;164), COPD (36.6%), asthma (25.6%) and heart failure (10.4%) were the most frequently suspected or investigated conditions. For rheumatologists (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;60), these were COPD (48.3%), anxiety (21.7%) and bronchitis (20.0%). COPD was the most frequently suspected or investigated condition across the different types of ILD, except for fibrotic hypersensitivity pneumonitis (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;55; asthma, 43.6%) and SSc-ILD (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;31; anxiety and COPD, both 25.8%).</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Consultation and referral history</title><p id="Par49">Most patients first consulted a primary care physician (57.0%) regarding their ILD symptoms. A total of 71.8% of patients were referred from another HCP, most frequently by a primary care physician (54.9%) (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). The most common reasons for referral were that the referring HCP did not specialise in respiratory conditions (56.7%), a lack of understanding around ILD (25.1%) and the need for additional diagnostic testing (24.5%). A pulmonologist was the diagnosing physician in 62.6% of cases, and additional physicians were involved in the diagnosis of 24.9% of all cases. According to the physician surveys (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;265), 83.4% of respondents were part of a multidisciplinary team, and within those teams most had a role in diagnosis and ongoing management (91.4%). This varied across countries, with the use of a multidisciplinary team for diagnosis reported in 40.6% of patients in Italy and 4.0% of patients in Germany.</p><p id="Par50">
<fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Physician-reported patient referral. HCP, healthcare professional; ILD, interstitial lung disease; PCP, primary care physician</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1679" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12931_2024_2995_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec20" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par51">This PPF-ILD survey adds to our understanding about care and management of patients diagnosed with ILD with PPF in Europe, in particular, the different experiences of patients with various types of ILD. Consistent with previous survey studies of patients with ILD, results showed that there was a delay of 15.5 months in diagnosis of ILD after first symptoms, including dyspnoea on exertion and cough [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p><p id="Par52">While there is a good understanding of the epidemiology and burden of IPF, little is known about the burden of PPF, the prevalence of comorbidities, and the patient journey to diagnosis. Diagnosis of ILD in general is often delayed, as is recognition of PPF, with PPF relying on evidence of progression via regular monitoring [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>].</p><p id="Par53">Over 17% of the patients in this study were misdiagnosed before ILD diagnosis. The rate of misdiagnosis in our study was lower than expected compared with existing literature; for instance, in a study of registered members of the Pulmonary Fibrosis Foundation, 56% of patients with ILD had experienced at least one misdiagnosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>].</p><p id="Par54">On average, most patients had at least one comorbidity reported in the survey, with anxiety (16.9%), gastroesophageal reflux (15.5%) and depression (13.4%) the most frequent overall. While there is limited published data available for patients with PPF, in the EMPIRE registry of patients with IPF in Central and Eastern European countries, 91% of patients reported at least one comorbidity, and more than 38% reported four or more comorbidities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The presence of multiple comorbidities at enrolment into the registry was associated with worse survival [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], similar to findings in patients with IPF at a tertiary referral centre [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. The current study adds to the limited existing literature on comorbidities, highlighting the importance of identifying and treating comorbidities in PPF.</p><p id="Par55">Given the progressive nature of PPF, understanding the patient pathway for different types of ILD and in difference countries is essential, as any delay in diagnosis and treatment may lead to a poorer prognosis. In patients with IPF, a diagnostic delay of more than a year is associated with worsened prognosis and quality of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. We found the main reasons for patient referral included the lack of specialty in respiratory conditions or lack of understanding of ILD, aligning with a retrospective analysis of an ILD referral tertiary academic centre in which 51% of patients with ILD were referred from general practice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. With a total mean (SD) of 15.5 (26.6) months between a patient first experiencing symptoms and an ILD diagnosis, and as most patients (57%) presented in primary care, there is a need for physician education on disease behaviour in PPF and for regular monitoring for progression to reduce the delay between first presentation with ILD symptoms and prompt referral to expert centres for diagnosis. Education and disease awareness programmes are also needed for patients and the general public to help encourage people to recognise symptoms and seek medical advice.</p><p id="Par56">Nearly 20% of patients were reported as progressing, based on worsening symptom severity, decline in lung function or increased fibrosis. In the current study, physicians reported decline in FVC percent predicted, worsening of symptoms and decline in DLco percent predicted as the key attributes for defining progression, in alignment with the ATS/ERS/JRS/ALAT guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Progression according to increased pulmonary fibrosis on high-resolution computed tomography (HRCT) was the least reported category out of the three; however, only one criterion for progression could be selected, which may have affected the results. Differences were noted by physician specialty, with more pulmonologists reporting a decline in FVC as the most important factor defining progression than rheumatologists, and rheumatologists using DLco more often than FVC. This highlights the importance of multidisciplinary management, particularly for patients with CTD-ILD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], given evaluation of ILD with pulmonary function tests is an expertise mainly of pulmonologists. In addition, FVC decline has been shown to have value as a predictor of mortality in both patients with IPF and with PPF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p><p id="Par57">Although this was a study on PPF, 52% of patients had progression that was reported as stable over the previous 12 months from the survey date, and 42% of patients were deemed to have &#8216;mild&#8217; disease severity at survey date based on physician opinion. This may be due to the physician&#8217;s expectation that they can at best stabilise progression for a short period of time for the most optimistic outcome possible. In a similar survey in IPF, patients with physician-reported mild or moderate disease were more likely to be classified as stable or improving than those with severe disease according to FVC data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The authors of the IPF study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] concluded that physician-reported severity was misaligned with severity as determined by FVC, potentially due to unfamiliarity with the disease or inadequately assessing symptoms.</p><p id="Par58">For those patients predicted to have &#8216;stable&#8217; disease in the next 12 months from the survey date, this may be due to physicians expecting to observe a treatment effect. As no definitions of severities were included in this study, analysis is restricted by the subjective nature of physician-determined &#8216;stable&#8217; or &#8216;mild&#8217; disease. The use of &#8216;mild&#8217;, &#8216;moderate&#8217; or &#8216;severe&#8217; as undefined terms to describe disease state have been used in IPF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. In a chart survey of patients with IPF, between 26% and 44% of patients were perceived to have mild disease and 10&#8211;16% were perceived to have severe disease by their physician [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Such findings are comparable with results from this study, and highlight potential disparities between physicians&#8217; interpretation of severity versus known burden and mortality of PPF.</p><p id="Par59">This study also found around 22% of patients were not receiving treatment at the time of the survey; 16% of these patients had never been prescribed treatment and symptom burden remained high, with over three quarters of patients symptomatic at survey date.</p><p id="Par60">The current study also highlights the differences in treatment approach across types of PPF; for example, 7% of patients with polymyositis/dermatomyositis-ILD were not prescribed treatment at survey date compared with 35% of patients with uILD. This is comparable with another survey of physicians in Europe and the US, where 25&#8211;50% of patients with PPF did not receive drug treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Despite the poor prognosis and high mortality associated with PPF, approximately 15% of patients had never received treatment for ILD at the time of the survey. An analysis of data from the Phase 3 trials of patients with IPF and other progressive fibrosing ILDs receiving either nintedanib or placebo, carried out over 52 weeks, found a similar disease course for both, underlining the possibility of a poor prognosis with PPF and the continued unmet need for timely diagnosis and treatment of the underlying ILD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p><p id="Par61">Only 25% of patients were in full-time employment at survey date, and 19% of those not in full-time employment were unable to work full-time due to their ILD (either working part-time, being retired, on long-term sick leave or unemployed). This aligns with research on the economic burden of PPF. In an economic model of PPF and SSc-ILD based on published data, the estimated annual aggregate income loss in the European Economic Area (accounting for annual sick days, early retirements, and permanently disabled patients) was &#8364;1,433&#160;million and &#8364;220&#160;million, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. In addition, productivity loss due to job losses was &#8364;194&#160;million and &#8364;26&#160;million for PPF and SSc-ILD, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p><p id="Par62">There are several limitations with the current study, including that the participating patients may not reflect the general population of patients with PPF with other underlying ILDs. The study population may also be skewed towards those more willing to consult physicians, or with more severe disease and undergoing monitoring for treatment response. The study was not based on a true random sample of physicians or patients, and no formal patient selection verification procedures were in place, with identification of the target patient group based on the judgement of the respondent physician. To minimise a potential selection bias and limit pre-selection by the physician, the sample comprised consecutive eligible patients, and all patients who met the eligibility criteria were included in the study. While the description of the type of patients included in this study reflects PPF, patients were not required to meet the 2022 ATS/ERS/JRS/ALAT guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] classification of PPF, as these criteria were not defined at the time of data collection. However, patients were required to have an ILD that the physician considered to be a progressive phenotype, and physicians did provide data on absolute decline in FVC and DLco and extent of disease on HRCT &#8211; factors used to define PPF according to guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. While some patients may not fit the current guideline criteria despite a physician clinical classification that states their condition is progressing, this method is representative of physicians&#8217; real-world classification of patients. It will be interesting to see how this evolves over time with the adoption of the ATS/ERS/JRS/ALAT guidelines for PPF. Multidisciplinary discussion (MDD) can facilitate a timely and accurate diagnosis of ILD, incorporating input from various clinicians, radiologists, pathologists and other specialists. Although the 2022 ATS/ERS/JRS/ALAT guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] focus on MDD for IPF, there is recognition of the importance of MDD for other ILDs as well [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. While the current study found that in just over 75% of cases no additional physicians were involved in the diagnosis, 83% of respondents reported being part of a multidisciplinary team, with most having a role in diagnosis and ongoing management. As diagnosis data were based on historical medical records, a single diagnosing physician may have been named, and the respondent may not have had access to further details regarding MDD of diagnosis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par63">This real-world study adds to our understanding of patients with PPF currently under the care of physicians in Europe, finding that many patients experience misdiagnosis, delays in diagnosis and gaps in treatment, with some patients having never received treatment for ILD. These findings draw attention to the unmet needs around the ongoing patient burden in PPF, the importance of referring patients with fibrosing ILD to expert centres, regular monitoring for progression and the need for access to timely treatment. Further research is needed to improve clarity in the guidelines on the diagnosis, management and treatment of all types of fibrotic ILD with a progressive phenotype.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12931_2024_2995_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#8217;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to thank all the patients whose data contributed to this manuscript. Writing, editorial support, and formatting assistance was provided by Helen Keyworth, PhD, of Nucleus Global, and was contracted and funded by Boehringer Ingelheim. Boehringer Ingelheim was given the opportunity to review the manuscript for medical and scientific accuracy as well as intellectual property considerations.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>The authors meet criteria for authorship as recommended by the International Committee of Medical Journal Editors (ICMJE). Conceptualisation: LL, MS; Ideas: PS, LL, MS; Methodology: LL, MS; Data collection: LL, MS; Data analysis: O-TC, LL, MS, MK; Data interpretation: NC, PS, CV, VCA, O-TC, LL, MS, MK;Write and review manuscript: NC, PS, CV, VCA, O-TC, LL, MS, MK.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This study of the PPF-ILD Disease Specific Programme (DSP&#8482;) dataset was supported by Boehringer Ingelheim International GmbH. The DSP is an independent survey and wholly owned Adelphi Real World product. Boehringer Ingelheim International GmbH is one of multiple subscribers to the DSP. The authors did not receive payment for the development of the manuscript. Writing, editorial support, and formatting assistance was provided by Helen Keyworth, PhD, of Nucleus Global, and was contracted and funded by Boehringer Ingelheim.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from Adelphi Real World but restrictions apply to the availability of these data, which were used under license for the current study, and so are not publicly available. Data are, however, available from the authors upon reasonable request and with permission of Adelphi Real World.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar11"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par65">The study received Pearl Institutional Review Board ethical exemption (22-ADRW-135) and was conducted adhering to European Pharmaceutical Market Research Association guidelines and Adelphi Real World standard operating procedures. The physicians provided written consent to participate in the DSP.</p></notes><notes id="FPar12"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par66">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar13" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par67">NC declares being a consultant for Boehringer Ingelheim during the development of this study, payment for consultancy activities from Boehringer Ingelheim and Roche, speaker fees from Boehringer Ingelheim, Roche and AstraZeneca, and participation in advisory boards from Boehringer Ingelheim and Roche. PS declares being a consultant for Boehringer Ingelheim during the development of this study, payment for consultancy activities and an institutional grant from PPM Services, speaker fees, participation on an advisory board and an institutional grant from Boehringer Ingelheim, institutional grants from Roche, consultancy activities for Jucabio, GlycoCore Pharma, Veracyte and Pieris, consulting and speaker fees from Chiesi, and participation on advisory boards for AstraZeneca and Structure Therapeutics. CV declares being a consultant for Boehringer Ingelheim during the development of this study. VCA is an employee of Boehringer Ingelheim International GmbH. O-TC, LL and MS are employees of Adelphi Real World. MK declares being a consultant for Boehringer Ingelheim during the development of this study.</p></notes></notes><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ALAT</term><def><p>Latin American Thoracic Association</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ATS</term><def><p>American Thoracic Society</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>COPD</term><def><p>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CTD</term><def><p>Connective tissue disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DLco</term><def><p>Diffusing capacity of the lungs for carbon monoxide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DSP</term><def><p>Disease Specific Programme</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ERS</term><def><p>European Respiratory Society</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FVC</term><def><p>Forced vital capacity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HCP</term><def><p>Healthcare professional</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HCRU</term><def><p>Healthcare resource utilisation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HRCT</term><def><p>High-resolution computed tomography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ILD</term><def><p>Interstitial lung disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>iNSIP</term><def><p>Idiopathic non-specific interstitial pneumonia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IPF</term><def><p>Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>JRS</term><def><p>Japanese Respiratory Society</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MDD</term><def><p>Multidisciplinary discussion</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PPF</term><def><p>Progressive pulmonary fibrosis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PRF</term><def><p>Patient record form</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RA</term><def><p>Rheumatoid arthritis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SD</term><def><p>Standard deviation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SSc</term><def><p>Systemic sclerosis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>uILD</term><def><p>Unclassifiable ILD</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raghu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Remy-Jardin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richeldi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johkoh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (an update) and progressive pulmonary fibrosis in adults: an official ATS/ERS/JRS/ALAT clinical practice Guideline</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>205</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>e18</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.202202-0399ST</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35486072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9851481</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Raghu G, Remy-Jardin M, Richeldi L, Thomson CC, Inoue Y, Johkoh T, et al. Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (an update) and progressive pulmonary fibrosis in adults: an official ATS/ERS/JRS/ALAT clinical practice guideline. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2022;205(9):e18&#8211;47.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35486072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1164/rccm.202202-0399ST</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9851481</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cottin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wollin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quaresma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stowasser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fibrosing interstitial lung diseases: knowns and unknowns</article-title><source>Eur Respir Rev</source><year>2019</year><volume>28</volume><issue>151</issue><fpage>180100</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/16000617.0100-2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30814139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9489101</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Cottin V, Wollin L, Fischer A, Quaresma M, Stowasser S, Harari S. Fibrosing interstitial lung diseases: knowns and unknowns. Eur Respir Rev. 2019;28(151):180100.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30814139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/16000617.0100-2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9489101</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cottin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirani</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hotchkin</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nambiar</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otaola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Presentation, diagnosis and clinical course of the spectrum of progressive-fibrosing interstitial lung diseases</article-title><source>Eur Respir Rev</source><year>2018</year><volume>27</volume><issue>150</issue><fpage>180076</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/16000617.0076-2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30578335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9489068</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Cottin V, Hirani NA, Hotchkin DL, Nambiar AM, Ogura T, Otaola M, et al. Presentation, diagnosis and clinical course of the spectrum of progressive-fibrosing interstitial lung diseases. Eur Respir Rev. 2018;27(150):180076.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30578335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/16000617.0076-2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9489068</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaunisto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salomaa</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaarteenaho</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kankaanranta</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koli</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Demographics and survival of patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis in the FinnishIPF registry</article-title><source>ERJ Open Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>00170</fpage><lpage>2018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/23120541.00170-2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31304177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6612605</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Kaunisto J, Salomaa ER, Hodgson U, Kaarteenaho R, Kankaanranta H, Koli K, et al. Demographics and survival of patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis in the FinnishIPF registry. ERJ Open Res. 2019;5(3):00170&#8211;2018.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31304177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/23120541.00170-2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6612605</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strongman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kausar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidence, prevalence, and survival of patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis in the UK</article-title><source>Adv Ther</source><year>2018</year><volume>35</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>724</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12325-018-0693-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29644539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5960490</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Strongman H, Kausar I, Maher TM. Incidence, prevalence, and survival of patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis in the UK. Adv Ther. 2018;35(5):724&#8211;36.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29644539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12325-018-0693-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5960490</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neely</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hellkamp</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Brien</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Andrade</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conoscenti</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predictors of death or lung transplant after a diagnosis of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: insights from the IPF-PRO Registry</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>105</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-019-1043-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31142314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6542049</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Snyder L, Neely ML, Hellkamp AS, O&#8217;Brien E, de Andrade J, Conoscenti CS, et al. Predictors of death or lung transplant after a diagnosis of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: insights from the IPF-PRO Registry. Respir Res. 2019;20(1):105.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31142314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12931-019-1043-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6542049</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wijsenbeek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cottin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spectrum of fibrotic lung diseases</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>383</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>958</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra2005230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32877584</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Wijsenbeek M, Cottin V. Spectrum of fibrotic lung diseases. N Engl J Med. 2020;383(10):958&#8211;68.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32877584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMra2005230</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valenzuela</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cottin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology and real-life experience in progressive pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Curr Opin Pulm Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>28</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MCP.0000000000000908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35938201</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Valenzuela C, Cottin V. Epidemiology and real-life experience in progressive pulmonary fibrosis. Curr Opin Pulm Med. 2022;28(5):407&#8211;13.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35938201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MCP.0000000000000908</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Man</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gogikar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nanda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janga</surname><given-names>LSN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sambe</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yasir</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramphall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparison of the effectiveness of Nintedanib and Pirfenidone in treating idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: a systematic review</article-title><source>Cureus</source><year>2024</year><volume>16</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e54268</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38500898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.54268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10945152</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Man RK, Gogikar A, Nanda A, Janga LSN, Sambe HG, Yasir M, Ramphall S. A comparison of the effectiveness of nintedanib and pirfenidone in treating idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: a systematic review. Cureus. 2024;16(2):e54268.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38500898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.54268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10945152</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">European Medicines Agency. Ofev<sup>&#174;</sup> (nintedanib): Summary of product characteristics 2024. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/documents/product-information/ofev-epar-product-information_en.pdf">https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/documents/product-information/ofev-epar-product-information_en.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">U.S. Food &amp; Drug Administration. OFEV<sup>&#174;</sup> (nintedanib): Prescribing information 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2022/205832Orig1s016lbl.pdf">https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2022/205832Orig1s016lbl.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">European Medicines Agency. Esbriet<sup>&#174;</sup> (pirfenidone): Summary of product characteristics 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ema.europa.eu/docs/en_GB/document_library/EPAR_-_Product_Information/human/002154/WC500103049.pdf">http://www.ema.europa.eu/docs/en_GB/document_library/EPAR_-_Product_Information/human/002154/WC500103049.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">U.S. Food &amp; Drug Administration. ESBRIET<sup>&#174;</sup> (pirfenidone): Prescribing information 2019. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2019/022535s012,208780s002lbl.pdf">https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2019/022535s012,208780s002lbl.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Behr J, Kreuter M, Prasse A, Guenther A, Bonella F, Pittrow D et al. Real-life characteristics and management of patients with fibrosing interstitial lung disease: INSIGHTS-ILD registry. Poster presented at ERS Congress. 2024; 7&#8211;11 September; Vienna, Austria 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lobo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramaswamy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swaminathan</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Veeraraghavan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of patients with progressive fibrosing ILDs in the ILD-PRO Registry</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2023</year><volume>62</volume><issue>suppl 67</issue><fpage>PA2882</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Lobo L, Liu Y, Li P, Ramaswamy M, Swaminathan AC, Veeraraghavan S, et al. Characteristics of patients with progressive fibrosing ILDs in the ILD-PRO Registry. Eur Respir J. 2023;62(suppl 67):PA2882.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of progressive fibrosing interstitial lung diseases (PF-ILD)</article-title><source>Front Med (Lausanne)</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>743977</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2021.743977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34722582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8548364</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Copeland CR, Lancaster LH. Management of progressive fibrosing interstitial lung diseases (PF-ILD). Front Med (Lausanne). 2021;8:743977.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34722582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmed.2021.743977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8548364</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>SLF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thannickal</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schlenker-Herceg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The natural history of progressive fibrosing interstitial lung diseases</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2020</year><volume>55</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2000085</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.00085-2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32217654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7315005</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Brown KK, Martinez FJ, Walsh SLF, Thannickal VJ, Prasse A, Schlenker-Herceg R, et al. The natural history of progressive fibrosing interstitial lung diseases. Eur Respir J. 2020;55(6):2000085.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32217654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/13993003.00085-2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7315005</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ley</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collard</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>TE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical course and prediction of survival in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>183</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201006-0894CI</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20935110</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Ley B, Collard HR, King TE Jr. Clinical course and prediction of survival in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2011;183(4):431&#8211;40.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20935110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1164/rccm.201006-0894CI</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cottin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teague</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Burden of Progressive-Fibrosing interstitial lung diseases</article-title><source>Front Med (Lausanne)</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>799912</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2022.799912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35178411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8843847</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Cottin V, Teague R, Nicholson L, Langham S, Baldwin M. The burden of progressive-fibrosing interstitial lung diseases. Front Med (Lausanne). 2022;9:799912.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35178411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmed.2022.799912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8843847</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wuyts</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Papiris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manali</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kilpelainen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidsen</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miedema</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Burden of Progressive Fibrosing interstitial lung disease: a DELPHI Approach</article-title><source>Adv Ther</source><year>2020</year><volume>37</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>3246</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12325-020-01384-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32445186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7467418</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Wuyts WA, Papiris S, Manali E, Kilpelainen M, Davidsen JR, Miedema J, et al. The burden of progressive fibrosing interstitial lung disease: a DELPHI approach. Adv Ther. 2020;37(7):3246&#8211;64.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32445186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12325-020-01384-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7467418</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torrisi</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vancheri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sambataro</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmucci</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vancheri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comorbidities of IPF: how do they impact on prognosis</article-title><source>Pulm Pharmacol Ther</source><year>2018</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pupt.2018.09.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30193867</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Torrisi SE, Vancheri A, Pavone M, Sambataro G, Palmucci S, Vancheri C. Comorbidities of IPF: how do they impact on prognosis. Pulm Pharmacol Ther. 2018;53:6&#8211;11.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30193867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pupt.2018.09.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jovanovic</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sterclova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mogulkoc</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewandowska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajkova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comorbidity burden and survival in patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: the EMPIRE registry study</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>135</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-022-02033-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35624513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9145164</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Jovanovic DM, Sterclova M, Mogulkoc N, Lewandowska K, Muller V, Hajkova M, et al. Comorbidity burden and survival in patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: the EMPIRE registry study. Respir Res. 2022;23(1):135.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35624513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12931-022-02033-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9145164</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Margaritopoulos</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antoniou</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comorbidities in interstitial lung diseases</article-title><source>Eur Respir Rev</source><year>2017</year><volume>26</volume><issue>143</issue><fpage>160027</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/16000617.0027-2016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28049126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9488735</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Margaritopoulos GA, Antoniou KM, Wells AU. Comorbidities in interstitial lung diseases. Eur Respir Rev. 2017;26(143):160027.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28049126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/16000617.0027-2016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9488735</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benford</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karavali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piercy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Real-world physician and patient behaviour across countries: Disease-Specific programmes - a means to understand</article-title><source>Curr Med Res Opin</source><year>2008</year><volume>24</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>3063</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1185/03007990802457040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18826746</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Anderson P, Benford M, Harris N, Karavali M, Piercy J. Real-world physician and patient behaviour across countries: Disease-Specific Programmes - a means to understand. Curr Med Res Opin. 2008;24(11):3063&#8211;72.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18826746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1185/03007990802457040</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Babineaux</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holbrook</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milligan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piercy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for validity of a national physician and patient-reported, cross-sectional survey in China and UK: the Disease Specific Programme</article-title><source>BMJ Open</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>e010352</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27531722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5013497</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Babineaux SM, Curtis B, Holbrook T, Milligan G, Piercy J. Evidence for validity of a national physician and patient-reported, cross-sectional survey in China and UK: the Disease Specific Programme. BMJ Open. 2016;6(8):e010352.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27531722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5013497</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Courcy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doslikova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karavali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piercy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Real-world evidence generation from patients, their caregivers and physicians supporting clinical, regulatory and guideline decisions: an update on Disease Specific Programmes</article-title><source>Curr Med Res Opin</source><year>2023</year><volume>39</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1707</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03007995.2023.2279679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37933204</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Anderson P, Higgins V, Courcy J, Doslikova K, Davis VA, Karavali M, Piercy J. Real-world evidence generation from patients, their caregivers and physicians supporting clinical, regulatory and guideline decisions: an update on Disease Specific Programmes. Curr Med Res Opin. 2023;39(12):1707&#8211;15.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37933204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/03007995.2023.2279679</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Veeraraghavan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansell</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Copley</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interstitial lung disease in systemic sclerosis: a simple staging system</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>177</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1248</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.200706-877OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18369202</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Goh NS, Desai SR, Veeraraghavan S, Hansell DM, Copley SJ, Maher TM, et al. Interstitial lung disease in systemic sclerosis: a simple staging system. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2008;177(11):1248&#8211;54.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18369202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1164/rccm.200706-877OC</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lobodo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danese</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lederer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding the patient journey of interstitial lung disease diagnosis: the intensity survey</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>2016</year><volume>150</volume><issue>Suppl 4</issue><fpage>468A</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chest.2016.08.482</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Cosgrove G, Bianchi P, Lobodo J, Danese S, Lederer D. Understanding the patient journey of interstitial lung disease diagnosis: the intensity survey. Chest. 2016;150(Suppl 4):468A.27502983
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Der Sar</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonella</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fourrier</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewandowska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patient reported experiences and delays during the diagnostic pathway for pulmonary fibrosis: a multinational European survey</article-title><source>Front Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>711194</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2021.711194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8371687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34422866</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">van Der Sar IG, Jones S, Clarke DL, Bonella F, Fourrier JM, Lewandowska K, et al. Patient reported experiences and delays during the diagnostic pathway for pulmonary fibrosis: a multinational European survey. Front Med. 2021;8:711194.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmed.2021.711194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8371687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34422866</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreuter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehlers-Tenenbaum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmowski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruhwyler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oltmanns</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muley</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of comorbidities on mortality in patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e0151425</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0151425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27023440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4811578</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Kreuter M, Ehlers-Tenenbaum S, Palmowski K, Bruhwyler J, Oltmanns U, Muley T, et al. Impact of comorbidities on mortality in patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. PLoS ONE. 2016;11(3):e0151425.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27023440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0151425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4811578</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hoyer N, Prior TS, Bendstrup E, Shaker SB. Diagnostic delay in IPF impacts progression-free survival, quality of life and hospitalisation rates. BMJ Open Respir Res. 2022;9(1).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjresp-2022-001276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9263910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35798532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ageely</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Boer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Voduc</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of multidisciplinary discussion (MDD) in the diagnosis and management of fibrotic interstitial Lung diseases</article-title><source>Can Respir J</source><year>2020</year><volume>2020</volume><fpage>9026171</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2020/9026171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32879642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7448233</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Ageely G, Souza C, De Boer K, Zahra S, Gomes M, Voduc N. The impact of multidisciplinary discussion (MDD) in the diagnosis and management of fibrotic interstitial lung diseases. Can Respir J. 2020;9026171.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32879642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2020/9026171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7448233</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glaspole</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahar</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical impact of the interstitial lung disease multidisciplinary service</article-title><source>Respirology</source><year>2016</year><volume>21</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1438</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/resp.12850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27427515</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Jo HE, Glaspole IN, Levin KC, McCormack SR, Mahar AM, Cooper WA, et al. Clinical impact of the interstitial lung disease multidisciplinary service. Respirology. 2016;21(8):1438&#8211;44.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27427515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/resp.12850</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flaherty</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cottin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonella</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predictors of mortality in subjects with progressive fibrosing interstitial lung diseases</article-title><source>Respirology</source><year>2022</year><volume>27</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>294</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/resp.14231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35224814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9306931</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Brown KK, Inoue Y, Flaherty KR, Martinez FJ, Cottin V, Bonella F, et al. Predictors of mortality in subjects with progressive fibrosing interstitial lung diseases. Respirology. 2022;27(4):294&#8211;300.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35224814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/resp.14231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9306931</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonella</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cottin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siddall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Small</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: physician and patient perspectives on the pathway to care from symptom recognition to diagnosis and disease burden</article-title><source>Respirology</source><year>2022</year><volume>27</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/resp.14154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34611971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9135122</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Lancaster L, Bonella F, Inoue Y, Cottin V, Siddall J, Small M, Langley J. Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: physician and patient perspectives on the pathway to care from symptom recognition to diagnosis and disease burden. Respirology. 2022;27(1):66&#8211;75.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34611971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/resp.14154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9135122</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robbie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daccord</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Devaraj</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating disease severity in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Eur Respir Rev</source><year>2017</year><volume>26</volume><issue>145</issue><fpage>170051</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/16000617.0051-2017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28877976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9488723</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Robbie H, Daccord C, Chua F, Devaraj A. Evaluating disease severity in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. Eur Respir Rev. 2017;26(145):170051.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28877976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/16000617.0051-2017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9488723</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molina-Molina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonella</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jouneau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ripamonti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unmet needs in the treatment of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis-insights from patient chart review in five European countries</article-title><source>BMC Pulm Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>124</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12890-017-0468-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28915874</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5602932</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Maher TM, Molina-Molina M, Russell AM, Bonella F, Jouneau S, Ripamonti E, et al. Unmet needs in the treatment of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis-insights from patient chart review in five European countries. BMC Pulm Med. 2017;17(1):124.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28915874</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12890-017-0468-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5602932</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wijsenbeek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreuter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bendstrup</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Progressive fibrosing interstitial lung diseases: current practice in diagnosis and management</article-title><source>Curr Med Res Opin</source><year>2019</year><volume>35</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2015</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03007995.2019.1647040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31328965</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Wijsenbeek M, Kreuter M, Olson A, Fischer A, Bendstrup E, Wells CD, et al. Progressive fibrosing interstitial lung diseases: current practice in diagnosis and management. Curr Med Res Opin. 2019;35(11):2015&#8211;24.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31328965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/03007995.2019.1647040</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lokke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castello</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinheiro Martins</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soulard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilberg</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Burden of Disease and Productivity loss in the European Economic Area in patients affected by fibrosing interstitial lung disease</article-title><source>Adv Ther</source><year>2023</year><volume>40</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>5502</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12325-023-02701-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37837527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10611590</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Lokke A, Castello L, Pinheiro Martins P, Soulard S, Hilberg O. Burden of disease and productivity loss in the European Economic Area in patients affected by fibrosing interstitial lung disease. Adv Ther. 2023;40(12):5502&#8211;18.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37837527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12325-023-02701-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10611590</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dodia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amariei</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenaa</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corwin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chelala</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Britt</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A comprehensive assessment of environmental exposures and the medical history guides multidisciplinary discussion in interstitial lung disease</article-title><source>Respir Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>106333</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rmed.2021.106333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33676119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7992253</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Dodia N, Amariei D, Kenaa B, Corwin D, Chelala L, Britt EJ, et al. A comprehensive assessment of environmental exposures and the medical history guides multidisciplinary discussion in interstitial lung disease. Respir Med. 2021;179:106333.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33676119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.rmed.2021.106333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7992253</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bleasel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lake</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The interstitial lung disease multidisciplinary meeting: a position statement from the Thoracic Society of Australia and New Zealand and the Lung Foundation Australia</article-title><source>Respirology</source><year>2017</year><volume>22</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1459</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/resp.13163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28891101</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Prasad JD, Mahar A, Bleasel J, Ellis SJ, Chambers DC, Lake F, et al. The interstitial lung disease multidisciplinary meeting: a position statement from the Thoracic Society of Australia and New Zealand and the Lung Foundation Australia. Respirology. 2017;22(7):1459&#8211;72.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28891101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/resp.13163</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>