<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Gynecol Oncol Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Gynecol Oncol Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2729</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">gore</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Gynecologic Oncology Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2352-5789</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11985054</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11985054.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11985054</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11985054</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40213528</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gore.2025.101725</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2352-5789(25)00050-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101725</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A comparison of adjuvant therapy modality and treatment outcomes between appalachian and non-appalachian patients with high-risk endometrial carcinoma</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Llanora</surname><given-names initials="JD">Josie D.</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au010"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawk</surname><given-names initials="GS">Gregory S.</given-names></name><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au015"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harbin</surname><given-names initials="LM">Laura M.</given-names></name><xref rid="af015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au020"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names initials="S">Sara</given-names></name><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au025"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names initials="M">Madison</given-names></name><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au030"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names initials="MT">Madison T.</given-names></name><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au035"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pendygraft</surname><given-names initials="E">Elizabeth</given-names></name><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au040"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names initials="LA">Lauren A.</given-names></name><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au045"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchcraft</surname><given-names initials="ML">Megan L.</given-names></name><email>mlghutchcraft@gmail.com</email><xref rid="af020" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#8270;</xref></contrib><aff id="af005"><label>a</label>University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, USA</aff><aff id="af010"><label>b</label>University of Kentucky, Lexington, KY, USA</aff><aff id="af015"><label>c</label>The West Cancer Center, Memphis, TN, USA</aff><aff id="af020"><label>d</label>Carle Cancer Institute, Carle Illinois College of Medicine, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Urbana, IL, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#8270;</label>Corresponding author. <email>mlghutchcraft@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>58</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">483240</issue-id><elocation-id>101725</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>14</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>17</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>10</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-04-11 16:25:14.540"><day>11</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2025 Published by Elsevier Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="ab005"><title>Graphical abstract</title><fig id="f0020" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk00020" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ga1.jpg"/></fig></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="ab010"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="l0005"><list-item id="o0005"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0005">Appalachian and non-Appalachian patients with high-risk endometrial cancer received similar adjuvant therapy regimens.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0010"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0010">Appalachian and non-Appalachian patients with high-risk endometrial cancer had similar survival and recurrence outcomes.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0015"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0015">Despite groups receiving similar adjuvant therapies and similar adjuvant therapy providers, more vaginal recurrences were detected in non-Appalachian patients.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><abstract id="ab015"><sec><title>Objective</title><p>The incidence and mortality of endometrial cancer is increasing. After surgical staging, patients with high-risk disease often undergo adjuvant treatment, which may include systemic therapy, radiation therapy, or combined modalities. Patients in rural Appalachia have limited access to subspecialty care needed for optimal disease management. This study aims to compare adjuvant treatment regimens and outcomes among patients with high-risk endometrial cancer living in Appalachian and non-Appalachian regions.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We retrospectively identified 179 patients with high-risk endometrial carcinoma who underwent surgical staging at a single academic medical center and received adjuvant therapy between 2012 and 2019. Patients were identified as Appalachian (n&#160;=&#160;119) and non-Appalachian (n&#160;=&#160;60) residents based on home ZIP code. Adjuvant therapy regimen, recurrence rate, recurrence location, progression free survival (PFS), and overall survival (OS) were compared. Statistical comparisons were performed using multinomial and ordinal logistic regression models, Kaplan-Meier curves, Log Rank test, two-sample t-tests, Fisher&#8217;s exact, and chi-square tests.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>There was no significant difference in adjuvant therapy regimen between groups. Overall recurrence rates were similar, though rate of vaginal recurrence was higher among non-Appalachian patients compared to Appalachian patients (42&#160;% vs. 14&#160;%, p&#160;=&#160;0.05). There were no differences in rate of pelvic or distant recurrences, PFS, or OS.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Despite lower densities of subspecialists in rural Appalachia, Appalachian and non-Appalachian patients with high-risk endometrial cancer received similar adjuvant therapy regimens and had similar disease outcomes. Further efforts should work to optimize treatment and surveillance for patients with endometrial carcinoma with barriers to subspecialty care.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="kg005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Endometrial carcinoma</kwd><kwd>Appalachia</kwd><kwd>Healthcare disparities</kwd><kwd>Adjuvant therapy</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0025">Endometrial carcinoma is the most common gynecologic cancer. Despite scientific advances, endometrial carcinoma is one of the few malignancies with increasing incidence and mortality (<xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Henley et al., 2020</xref>). Endometrial cancer is surgically staged with total hysterectomy, bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy, and lymph node assessment. The need for adjuvant treatment is based on clinicopathologic factors including age, disease stage, tumor histology, histologic grade, and presence of lymphovascular space invasion (LVSI). Based on these risk factors, patients are stratified into low-, intermediate-, and high-risk categories. High-risk endometrial cancer includes high-risk histologies (serous and clear cell adenocarcinomas, carcinosarcoma), deeply invasive high-grade endometrioid carcinoma, and advanced (International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics (FIGO) stage III/IV) disease (<xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Lewin et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">McCloskey et al., 2010</xref>). Adjuvant treatment may include systemic therapy, radiation therapy, or a combined approach.</p><p id="p0030">Research has demonstrated improved surgical staging with lymph node assessment, administration of guideline-concordant adjuvant therapy, and improved five-year progression free survival (PFS) for patients with advanced endometrial cancer when care is managed by a gynecologic oncologist (<xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Minig et al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">Ko et al., 2022</xref>, <xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Chan et al., 2011</xref>). Access to a gynecologic oncologist is crucial for optimal patient care and treatment outcomes. The majority of United States (US) gynecologic oncology practices are located in urban settings and at university hospitals, leaving many patients without access to subspecialty care (<xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">Ricci et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p id="p0035">Patients in rural locations encounter barriers to accessing a gynecologic oncologist and thus are at risk for worse outcomes (<xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">Ackroyd et al., 2021</xref>). Prior retrospective studies have identified that those with endometrial cancer who live in rural locations are less likely to undergo optimal surgical staging and receive multimodal adjuvant therapy (<xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">Zahnd et al., 2018</xref>, <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">Nguyen et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">Modesitt et al., 2006</xref>). One population-based study in Kentucky identified the association between incomplete surgical staging in rural populations and decreased disease-specific survival (<xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">Modesitt et al., 2006</xref>). Another population-based study in Utah determined that patients with endometrial cancer living in rural locations had increased risk of mortality compared to their urban counterparts (<xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Blackburn et al., 2019</xref>). These studies exhibit the impact of geographic location on the management of endometrial cancer, which prompts the need for further evaluation of other unique populations that may be impacted by similar disparities.</p><p id="p0040">Appalachia is a geographic region encompassing 420 counties across 13 states and includes approximately 25 million people (<xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">Hash et al., 2024</xref>). Compared to national averages, the Appalachian population experiences higher rates of comorbid diseases (e.g., obesity and diabetes), cancer incidence, and mortality, along with lower rates of insurance coverage and postsecondary education (<xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">Johnson et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">Riggs et al., 2022</xref>, <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Regional, 2017</xref>, <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Pollard K and Jacobsen LA</xref>). Furthermore, when comparing rural versus urban counties in the Appalachian region, rural counties are more impacted by health disparities and social determinants of health (<xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">Hogg-Graham et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Regional, 2017</xref>). Survey-based analyses of Appalachian communities have identified that those living in Appalachia are less satisfied with the quality of care they receive than their non-Appalachian counterparts (<xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">Morrone et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">McGarvey et al., 2011</xref>). A 2021 evaluation of US gynecologic oncology practices demonstrated that only 8.8&#160;% of US counties contain gynecologic oncology services. Furthermore, over 80&#160;% of Appalachian counties did not have gynecologic oncology services, despite the region having some of the highest incidences of gynecologic cancers (<xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">Ackroyd et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p id="p0045">It is essential to understand the disparities that patients experience to provide high quality care for socioeconomically diverse and medically underserved populations. To date, no study has evaluated adjuvant therapy practices for high-risk endometrial cancer among Appalachian patients. Thus, the primary objective of this study is to compare the adjuvant therapy regimens between Appalachian and non-Appalachian patients. The secondary aim of this study is to compare survival outcomes, including recurrence rate, PFS, and overall survival (OS) between groups.</p></sec><sec id="s0010"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><p id="p0050">This single-institution, retrospective cohort study was conducted following Institutional Review Board approval from the University of Kentucky (Protocol #58257). Patients aged 18&#160;years or older with high-risk endometrial carcinoma who underwent primary surgical staging at a single academic medical center and received adjuvant therapy between January 1, 2012 and December 31, 2019 were identified. The classification of high-risk endometrial carcinoma was defined as any stage high-risk histology (e.g., serous, clear cell, or carcinosarcoma) tumor, grade three deeply invasive endometrioid carcinoma, and pathologic stages III/IV disease of any histology. Those excluded from analysis had multiple primary cancers, presented for treatment of recurrent disease, did not undergo surgical staging, or were lost to follow-up before 30&#160;days after surgery. Patient demographics and clinical history, including surgico-pathologic data and adjuvant therapy characteristics, were abstracted from the electronic medical record (EMR). Publicly available resources were used to identify the dates of death (<xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">Legacy.com, 2024</xref>), if not previously identified in the EMR, driving distance from the academic medical center based on home ZIP code (<xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">Google.com, 2025</xref>), and median annual household income based on home ZIP code (<xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">Income by Zip Code, 2025</xref>). Patients were identified as residents of Appalachia and non-Appalachia based on ZIP code of residence (<xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">Appalachian Regional Commision, 2024</xref>).</p><p id="p0055">Adjuvant therapy modalities were compared between Appalachian and non-Appalachian groups. Adjuvant therapy modalities were classified as chemotherapy (CT) only, radiation therapy (RT) only, or mixed therapy (MT), which was defined as any combination of CT and RT. Disease outcomes, including recurrence rate, site of recurrence, PFS, and OS were compared between groups. PFS was defined as the time of initial surgical intervention to disease recurrence or progression based on imaging studies or physical examination. OS was defined as the time of initial surgical intervention to death from any cause.</p><p id="p0060">Survival data were analyzed using Kaplan-Meier curves, with a Log Rank test used to assess differences between groups. All other quantitative demographic and surgico-pathologic outcomes were analyzed using two-sample t-tests. Differences in categorical outcomes between groups were analyzed using a Fisher&#8217;s exact or chi-square test, as appropriate. In all cases, model assumptions were assessed using a combination of visual plots and formal testing. Across all analyses, a p-value less than or equal to 0.05 was considered statistically significant. All analyses were performed using R, version 4.3.1 (R Foundation for Statistical Computing; Vienna, Austria).</p></sec><sec id="s0015"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="s0020"><label>3.1</label><title>Demographic, social determinants of health, surgico-pathologic, and adjuvant therapy data</title><p id="p0065">Of the 182 patients initially identified, three patients were excluded (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). A total of 179 patients were eligible for final analysis. Patient demographic, social determinants of health, and surgico-pathologic characteristics are listed in <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Compared to non-Appalachian patients, those from Appalachia were more likely to identify their race as White (93.3&#160;% vs. 78.3&#160;%) and less likely as Black or African American (1.7&#160;% vs. 15.0&#160;%) (p&#160;&lt;&#160;0.05). Compared to non-Appalachian counterparts, patients residing in Appalachia had a longer driving distance to the academic medical center (Appalachian: 84.5 <inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mo>&#177;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 36.7 miles vs. non-Appalachian: 33.7 <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mo>&#177;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 46.5 miles, p&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001) and resided in a county with a lower annual median income based on home ZIP code (Appalachian: $48,583 [$40,582 to $56,671] vs. non-Appalachian $65,913 [$51,778 to $80,444], p&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001). Otherwise, demographic and surgico-pathologic characteristics, including body mass index (BMI) and comorbidities, were similar between groups.<fig id="f0005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Study flow chart.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk00005" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t0005" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic, social determinant of health, and surgico-pathologic data.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Appalachian</bold><break/><bold>(n&#160;=&#160;119)</bold></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Non-Appalachian</bold><break/><bold>(n&#160;=&#160;60)</bold></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>p-value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age &#8211; mean years&#160;&#177;&#160;SD</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.1&#160;&#177;&#160;11.9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.7&#160;&#177;&#160;10.8</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.44</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>BMI &#8211; mean kg/m<sup>2</sup>&#160;&#177;&#160;SD</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.7&#160;&#177;&#160;8.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.1&#160;&#177;&#160;11</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Race &#8211; no. (%)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Asian</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Black or African American</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (1.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (15.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;White</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">111 (93.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 (78.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Not specified</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (5.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (5.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Ethnicity &#8211; no. (%)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hispanic or Latino</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (1.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Non-Hispanic or Latino</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">96 (80.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">54 (90.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Not specified</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (17.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (8.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Tobacco Use &#8211; no. (%)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.74</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Never</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">83 (69.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 (66.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Current or Former</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 (29.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (33.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Not specified</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Comorbidities &#8211; no. (%)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hypertension</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">73 (61.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 (66.7)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.49</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hyperlipidemia</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (35.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (26.7)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.24</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Diabetes Mellitus</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (26.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (38.3)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Heart Disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (17.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (10.0)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Mean Driving Distance to Academic Medical Center</bold><xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref><bold>&#8211; mi&#160;&#177;&#160;SD</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.5&#160;&#177;&#160;36.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.7&#160;&#177;&#160;46.5</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Median Yearly Income by Home ZIP Code [IQR]</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$48,583<break/>[$40,582 to $56,671]</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">$65,913<break/>[$51,778 to $80,444]</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>FIGO Stage</bold><xref rid="tblfn2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref><bold>&#8211; no. (%)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.17</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;I</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (17.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (30.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;III</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (14.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (11.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;III</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">57 (47.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (47.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;IV</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (20.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (10.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Grade &#8211; no. (%)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.42</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (14.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (8.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (12.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (8.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">83 (73.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 (82.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Histology &#8211; no. (%)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.31</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Endometrioid</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">59 (49.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (38.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Serous</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">44 (37.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (48.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Clear cell</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (7.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (5.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Carcinosarcoma</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (5.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (6.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Undifferentiated</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Standard deviation (SD); number (no.); body mass index (BMI); kilogram (kg); meter (m); US dollars ($); miles (mi); interquartile range (IQR); International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics (FIGO).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><label>a</label><p id="np005">Location where surgical staging was completed.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn2"><label>b</label><p id="np010">FIGO staging 2009.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0070">Analyses of adjuvant therapy are described in <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The percent of patients treated with CT only (44.5&#160;% vs. 48.3&#160;%), RT only (20.2&#160;% vs. 13.3&#160;%), and MT (35.3&#160;% vs. 38.3&#160;%) were similar between Appalachian and non-Appalachian groups (<xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, p&#160;=&#160;0.53). For patients treated with CT only, there was no difference in the mean number of CT cycles (Appalachian: 5.6 <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mo>&#177;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 1.9 cycles vs. non-Appalachian: 5.1 <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mo>&#177;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 1.5 cycles, p&#160;=&#160;0.22). For patients treated with RT only, there was no difference in the mean total Gray (Gy) (Appalachian: 45.7 <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mo>&#177;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 2.7&#160;Gy vs. non-Appalachian: 46.6 <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mo>&#177;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 4.1&#160;Gy, p&#160;=&#160;0.66). Similarly, for patients treated with MT, there was no difference in mean number of CT cycles (Appalachian: 5.3 <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mo>&#177;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 1.1 cycles vs. non-Appalachian: 5.5 <inline-formula><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mo>&#177;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 1.3 cycles, p&#160;=&#160;0.68) or mean total Gy (Appalachian: 45.6 <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mo>&#177;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 13.6&#160;Gy vs. non-Appalachian: 49.2 <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mo>&#177;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 18.7&#160;Gy, p&#160;=&#160;0.48) between groups.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><bold>Adjuvant therapies.</bold> A comparison of adjuvant therapy modalities, quantities, and receipt of any therapy at an outside facility between Appalachian and non-Appalachian patients who received CT only, RT only, or MT.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Therapy Modality</bold></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Appalachian</bold><break/><bold>(n&#160;=&#160;119)</bold></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Non-Appalachian</bold><break/><bold>(n&#160;=&#160;60)</bold></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>p-value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Chemotherapy Only &#8211; no. (%)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.0 (44.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.0 (48.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Mean no. cycles&#160;&#177;&#160;SD (range)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.6 +/- 1.9<break/>(1.0 to 9.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.1 +/- 1.5<break/>(2.0 to 6.0)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.22</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Radiation Therapy Only</bold><xref rid="tblfn3" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref><bold>&#8211; no. (%)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.0 (20.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.0 (13.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Mean Gy&#160;&#177;&#160;SD (range)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.7 +/- 2.7<break/>(45.0 to 55.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.6 +/- 4.1<break/>(44.2 to 54.0)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.66</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Mixed Therapy &#8211; no. (%)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.0 (35.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.0 (38.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Mean no. cycles&#160;&#177;&#160;SD (range)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.3 +/- 1.1<break/>(3.0 to 6.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.5 +/- 1.3<break/>(3.0 to 9.0)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.68</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Mean Gy&#160;&#177;&#160;SD (range)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.6 +/- 13.6<break/>(20.0 to 99.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.2 +/- 18.7<break/>(23.4 to 100.0)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.48</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Received Adjuvant Therapy at Outside Facility</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;<bold>Any Modality &#8211; no. (%)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (22.7&#160;%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (28.3&#160;%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.36</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;<bold>Any Chemotherapy &#8211; no. (%)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (14.3&#160;%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (13.3&#160;%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.91</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;<bold>Any Radiation Therapy &#8211; no. (%)</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (9.2&#160;%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (15.0&#160;%)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Number (no.); SD (standard deviation); Gray (Gy).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn3"><label>a</label><p id="np015">Includes external beam radiation therapy and brachytherapy.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0025"><label>3.2</label><title>Location of adjuvant therapy and surveillance</title><p id="p0075">All patients underwent surgical staging at a single academic medical center by a gynecologic oncologist. Patients who received CT at the academic medical center were prescribed therapy by their gynecologic oncologist. Patients who received CT outside of the academic medical center were prescribed therapy by a local community medical oncologist. RT was administered under the supervision of a radiation oncologist at the academic medical center or from a local community radiation oncologist.</p><p id="p0080">All patients were followed by their gynecologic oncologist at the academic medical center. Patients receiving RT at the academic medical center were also followed by the university&#8217;s radiation oncology department. For patients under surveillance, visits were staggered between their community oncology providers and their academic oncology providers.</p><p id="p0085">There was no difference in the proportion of patients who received any form of adjuvant therapy in a local community practice (Appalachian: 22.7&#160;% vs. non-Appalachian: 28.3&#160;%, p&#160;=&#160;0.36). When stratifying by type of adjuvant therapy, there were also no differences in receipt of CT or RT in a local community practice (<xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0030"><label>3.3</label><title>Disease outcomes</title><p id="p0090">There was no difference in rate of recurrence between Appalachian and non-Appalachian patients (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A; 31.1&#160;% vs. 20.0&#160;% respectively, p&#160;=&#160;0.14). When evaluating the locations of recurrence between groups, fewer vaginal recurrences were diagnosed in Appalachian compared to non-Appalachian patients (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>B; 13.5&#160;% vs. 41.7&#160;%, p&#160;=&#160;0.05). Furthermore, there were no differences in pelvic (37.8&#160;% vs. 33.3&#160;%, p&#160;=&#160;1.00) or distant (89.0&#160;% vs. 100.0&#160;%, p&#160;=&#160;0.56) recurrences between groups. Differences in PFS (p&#160;=&#160;0.13) and OS (p&#160;=&#160;0.14) between groups did not reach statistical significance (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>).<fig id="f0010" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p><bold>Recurrence patterns.</bold> (A) Recurrence rate and (B) location of recurrence for Appalachian and non-Appalachian patients. Each location of recurrence was independently included for patients with multiple recurrence sites. Asterisk (*) indicates statistical significance.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk00010" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig><fig id="f0015" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p><bold>Survival outcomes.</bold> (A) Kaplan-Meier curves for progression free survival (p&#160;=&#160;0.13) and (B) overall survival (p&#160;=&#160;0.14) of Appalachian and non-Appalachian patients.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk00015" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0035"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0095">The objective of this study was to compare adjuvant treatment and disease outcomes between patients with high-risk endometrial cancer residing in Appalachian and non-Appalachian counties. Given the known healthcare disparities impacting the Appalachian population, we hypothesized that Appalachian patients would receive less adjuvant therapy and have worse disease outcomes compared to non-Appalachian patients (<xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Appalachian Regional Commision, 2017</xref>). This study determined that Appalachian patients received similar modalities and quantities of adjuvant therapy, as well as had similar recurrence rates, PFS, and OS compared to their non-Appalachian counterparts. In contrast to previously published data, we found no differences in BMI, tobacco use, medical comorbidities, cancer histology, cancer stage, or tumor grade between the groups (<xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">Johnson et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Regional, 2017</xref>). In comparison to a previously published study evaluating Appalachian and non-Appalachian patients with uterine malignancies, our study included more patients with advanced stage disease (<xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">Johnson et al., 2020</xref>). Similar to the demographic trends of the population as a whole, the Appalachian cohort had a significantly higher percentage of White and lower percentage of Black or African American patients represented compared to the non-Appalachian cohort (<xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Lewin et al., 2010</xref>).</p><p id="p0100">Our study identified a lower rate of vaginal recurrences in Appalachian patients compared to non-Appalachian patients (13.5&#160;% vs. 41.7&#160;%, p&#160;=&#160;0.05) despite receipt of similar adjuvant therapies. This finding prompts the question of whether vaginal recurrences are underdiagnosed in patients from Appalachia. Two published studies surveyed members of Appalachian communities to assess cancer beliefs and perspectives, and the authors identified common themes including fatalistic mindset within the healthcare system and preferred uncertainty of their cancer progression (<xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">Vanderpool et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Hutson et al., 2007</xref>). Given this, we hypothesize that Appalachian patients may possess unique cultural perspectives that prevent them from seeking medical evaluation for subtle symptoms of local recurrences.</p><p id="p0105">A strength of this study is its evaluation of a medically underserved, under-researched, and high-risk population group. Evaluating disparities in care is essential to understanding how to alleviate barriers that the Appalachian population may encounter. Study limitations include its retrospective nature and small sample size. Though this study&#8217;s data originates from a single academic medical center, this institution is Kentucky&#8217;s only National Cancer Institute-designated cancer center and provides most of the cancer care for patients residing in rural Appalachia. Patients who did not undergo surgical staging by a gynecologic oncologist were not included in this study, which may contribute to finding a lack of differences in outcomes (<xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Desjardins et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">Huey et al., 2019</xref>). A larger sample size may provide additional statistical power to detect differences in the measured outcomes between groups.</p><p id="p0110">This study found that Appalachian and non-Appalachian patients received similar treatments for high-risk endometrial cancer despite the geographic and cultural barriers to gynecologic oncology care Appalachian patients may encounter (<xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Caffrey, 2021</xref>). Though no differences in adjuvant therapy practices or survival outcomes were noted in this study, the rising incidence of high-risk disease and growing use of effective, specialized targeted therapies may exacerbate disparities for populations with limited access to subspecialty cancer care, such as those residing in rural Appalachia (<xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Mangone et al., 2023</xref>, <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">Hicks-Courant et al., 2021</xref>). Other studies evaluating cancer care for patients residing in rural areas suggest utilization of multi-site practices, telemedicine, and multi-specialty collaboration may benefit this population (<xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Wong et al., 2022</xref>, <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">Rutledge et al., 2017</xref>). Future research should aim to identify specific barriers that Appalachian patients may face while undergoing treatment and surveillance for high-risk endometrial cancer.</p></sec><sec id="s0045"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0120"><bold>Josie D. Llanora:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Writing &#8211; original draft, Visualization, Methodology, Investigation, Formal analysis, Data curation, Conceptualization. <bold>Gregory S. Hawk:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Writing &#8211; original draft, Validation, Software, Methodology, Formal analysis. <bold>Laura M. Harbin:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Resources, Investigation. <bold>Sara Lee:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Data curation. <bold>Madison Lane:</bold> Data curation. <bold>Madison T. Hickey:</bold> Data curation. <bold>Elizabeth Pendygraft:</bold> Data curation. <bold>Lauren A. Baldwin:</bold> Supervision, Resources, Conceptualization. <bold>Megan L. Hutchcraft:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Writing &#8211; original draft, Validation, Supervision, Project administration, Methodology, Investigation, Data curation, Conceptualization.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi005"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0125">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bi005"><title>References</title><ref id="b0005"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ackroyd</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shih</surname><given-names>Y.-C.-T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halpern</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A look at the gynecologic oncologist workforce - Are we meeting patient demand?</article-title><source>Gynecol. Oncol.</source><volume>163</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34456058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ygyno.2021.08.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8585725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0010">Appalachian Counties Served by ARC. In: Appalachian Regional Commission [Internet]. 13 Jul 2020 [cited 14 Nov 2024]. Available: https://www.arc.gov/appalachian-counties-served-by-arc/.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0015"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackburn</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soisson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deshmukh</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prognostic factors for rural endometrial cancer patients in a population-based cohort</article-title><source>BMC Public. Health.</source><volume>19</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>921</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31291920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12889-019-7262-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6617574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0020"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caffrey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disparities in Cancer Care: Has Precision Medicine Widened the Gap?</article-title><source>Am. J. Manag. Care.</source><volume>27</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>3</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0025"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapp</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osann</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Influence of gynecologic oncologists on the survival of patients with endometrial cancer</article-title><source>J. Clin. Oncol.</source><volume>29</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>832</fpage><lpage>838</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21263082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JCO.2010.31.2124</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0030"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Desjardins</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desravines</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fader</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wethington</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curriero</surname><given-names>F.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geographic disparities in potential accessibility to gynecologic oncologists in the United States from 2001 to 2020</article-title><source>Obstet. Gynecol.</source><volume>142</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>688</fpage><lpage>697</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37535956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/AOG.0000000000005284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0035">Google. <italic toggle="yes">Google Maps</italic>. [cited 12 Mar 2025]. Available: https://www.google.com/maps.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0040"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hash</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schreurs</surname><given-names>B.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolley</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiske</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health disparities in Appalachian and other rural communities</article-title><source>Int. J. Aging. Hum. Dev.</source><volume>98</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37170557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/00914150231171856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0045"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henley</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>R.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Firth</surname><given-names>A.U.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Annual report to the nation on the status of cancer, part I: National cancer statistics</article-title><source>Cancer.</source><volume>126</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>2225</fpage><lpage>2249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32162336</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cncr.32802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7299151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0050"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hicks-Courant</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanter</surname><given-names>G.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giuntoli</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names><suffix>2nd</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schapira</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bekelman</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Latif</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An increase in multi-site practices: The shifting paradigm for gynecologic cancer care delivery</article-title><source>Gynecol. Oncol.</source><volume>160</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33243442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ygyno.2020.10.030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0055"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogg-Graham</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mays</surname><given-names>G.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zephyr</surname><given-names>P.M.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geographic variation in the structure of Kentucky&#8217;s population health systems: An urban, rural, and Appalachian comparison</article-title><source>J. Appalach. Health.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35770208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.13023/jah.0203.04</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9138753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0060"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huey</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawk</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Offodile</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names><suffix>II</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Mind the Gap: Precision Oncology and Its Potential to Widen Disparities</article-title><source>JOP</source><volume>15</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JOP.19.00102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31112478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0065"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutson</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorgan</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Behringer</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mountains hold things in: the use of community research review work groups to address cancer disparities in Appalachia</article-title><source>Oncol. Nurs. Forum</source><volume>34</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>1133</fpage><lpage>1139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18024340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1188/07.ONF.1133-1139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0070"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0070">Income by Zip Code. [cited 12 Mar 2025]. <italic toggle="yes">Income by Zip Code</italic>. https://www.incomebyzipcode.com/.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0075"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>T.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeSimone</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Uterine corpus malignancies in Appalachia Kentucky: Incidence, survival, and related health disparities</article-title><source>South. Med. J.</source><volume>113</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31897496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14423/SMJ.0000000000001057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8120481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0085"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bekelman</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hicks-Courant</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brensinger</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanter</surname><given-names>G.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of gynecologic oncology versus medical oncology specialty with survival, utilization, and spending for treatment of gynecologic cancers</article-title><source>Gynecol. Oncol.</source><volume>164</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34949437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ygyno.2021.12.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0080"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="ce.other-ref_xtq_gpg_t2c">Pollard K and Jacobsen LA. The Appalachian Region: A Data Overview from the 2014-2018 American Community Survey. 2020. Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.prb.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/prb-arc-chartbook-2020.pdf" id="ir5671">https://www.prb.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/prb-arc-chartbook-2020.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0090"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0090">Legacy.com. [cited 14 Nov 2024]. Available: https://www.legacy.com.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0095"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewin</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herzog</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrena Medel</surname><given-names>N.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deutsch</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>W.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative performance of the 2009 international Federation of gynecology and obstetrics&#8217; staging system for uterine corpus cancer</article-title><source>Obstet. Gynecol.</source><volume>116</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>1141</fpage><lpage>1149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20966700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/AOG.0b013e3181f39849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0100"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mangone</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marinelli</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bisceglia</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Braghiroli</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mastrofilippo</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pezzarossi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Optimizing outcomes through a multidisciplinary team approach in endometrial cancer</article-title><source>Healthcare. (basel).</source><volume>12</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">doi:10.3390/healthcare12010064</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/healthcare12010064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10778853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38200970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0110"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCloskey</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tchabo</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>H.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Odunsi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodabaugh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singhal</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adjuvant vaginal brachytherapy alone for high risk localized endometrial cancer as defined by the three major randomized trials of adjuvant pelvic radiation</article-title><source>Gynecol. Oncol.</source><volume>116</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>404</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19944453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ygyno.2009.06.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0115"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGarvey</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leon-Verdin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Killos</surname><given-names>L.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guterbock</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>W.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health disparities between Appalachian and non-Appalachian counties in Virginia USA</article-title><source>J. Community. Health.</source><volume>36</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>348</fpage><lpage>356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20862529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10900-010-9315-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3089820</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0120"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Minig</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Padilla-Iserte</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zorrero</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relevance of gynecologic oncologists to provide high-quality of care to women with gynecological cancer</article-title><source>Front. Oncol.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>308</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26835417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fonc.2015.00308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4712269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0125"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Modesitt</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shelton</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wyatt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endometrial cancer in Kentucky: the impact of age, smoking status, and rural residence</article-title><source>Gynecol. Oncol.</source><volume>103</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>300</fpage><lpage>306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16631234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ygyno.2006.03.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0130"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrone</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuller</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicks</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Access to health care in Appalachia: Perception and reality</article-title><source>J. Appalach. Health.</source><volume>3</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35769826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.13023/jah.0304.10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9183790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0135"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Czuzoj-Shulman</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alshaya</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gotlieb</surname><given-names>W.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abenhaim</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of rural vs. urban setting on the management and outcomes of surgery for endometrial cancer</article-title><source>J. Gynecol. Obstet. Hum. Reprod.</source><volume>48</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>745</fpage><lpage>749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31176049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jogoh.2019.06.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0140"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tergas</surname><given-names>A.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Long Roche</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fairbairn</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levinson</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dowdy</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Geographic disparities in the distribution of the U.S. gynecologic oncology workforce: A Society of Gynecologic Oncology study. Gynecol</article-title><source>Oncol. Rep.</source><volume>22</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.gore.2017.11.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5699889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29201989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0145"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riggs</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bocklage</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuh</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors predicting participation in the prospective genomic sequencing study, Total Cancer Care (TCC), in Kentucky</article-title><source>J. Rural. Health.</source><volume>38</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32633045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jrh.12492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8111685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0150"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rutledge</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guest</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sussman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinney</surname><given-names>A.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimizing endometrial cancer follow-up and survivorship care for rural and other underserved women: patient and provider perspectives</article-title><source>Gynecol. Oncol.</source><volume>145</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>334</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28325583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ygyno.2017.03.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7416737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0155"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanderpool</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bear</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cancer-related beliefs and perceptions in Appalachia: Findings from 3 states</article-title><source>J. Rural. Health.</source><volume>35</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30830984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jrh.12359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7219572</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0160"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albright</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swartz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Havrilesky</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Previs</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Telemedicine and gynecologic oncology: caring for patients remotely during a global pandemic</article-title><source>AJOG Glob. Rep.</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.xagr.2022.100124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9703802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36451896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0165"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahnd</surname><given-names>W.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyon</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz-Sylvester</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Izadi</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colditz</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brard</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rural-urban differences in surgical treatment, regional lymph node examination, and survival in endometrial cancer patients</article-title><source>Cancer Causes Control.</source><volume>29</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29282582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10552-017-0998-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6311991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0105"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="ce.other-ref_hmp_hpg_t2c">Appalachian Regional Commission. Health Disparities in Appalachia 2017. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.arc.gov/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/Health_Disparities_in_Appalachia_Executive_Summary.pdf" id="ir5557">https://www.arc.gov/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/Health_Disparities_in_Appalachia_Executive_Summary.pdf.</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="da005"><title>Data availability</title><p id="p0020">Data will be made available on request.</p></sec></back></article></pmc-articleset>