<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="oto270135" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">OTO Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">OTO Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3581</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">opn</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">OTO2</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>OTO Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2473-974X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12121448</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12121448.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12121448</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12121448</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40443568</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/oto2.70135</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OTO270135</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Borderline Personality Disorder Diagnoses in Facial Plastic Surgery: A Large Database Analysis</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">Lorenz et al.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="oto270135-cr-0001" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names initials="FJ">F. Jeffrey</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5902-7054</contrib-id><xref rid="oto270135-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="oto270135-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names initials="C">Cheng</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="oto270135-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="oto270135-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Givens</surname><given-names initials="AK">Alyssa K.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="oto270135-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="oto270135-cr-0004" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walen</surname><given-names initials="SG">Scott G.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, FRCSC</degrees><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5948-7429</contrib-id><xref rid="oto270135-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>swalen1@pennstatehealth.psu.edu</email></address></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="oto270135-aff-0001">
<label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Otolaryngology&#8211;Head and Neck Surgery</named-content>
<institution>Penn State Hershey Medical Center</institution>
<city>Hershey</city>
<named-content content-type="country-part">Pennsylvania</named-content>
<country country="US">USA</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Scott G. Walen, MD, FRCSC, Department of Otolaryngology&#8211;Head and Neck Surgery, 500 University Drive, Hershey, PA 17033, USA.<break/>
Email: <email>swalen1@pennstatehealth.psu.edu</email><break/></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Apr-Jun</season><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue seq="20">2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">486007</issue-id><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/oto2.v9.2</issue-id><elocation-id>e70135</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>08</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>29</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>29</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-05-30 10:25:36.900"><day>30</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#169; 2025 The Author(s). OTO Open published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of American Academy of Otolaryngology&#8211;Head and Neck Surgery Foundation.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OTO2-9-e70135.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:OTO2-9-e70135.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="oto270135-sec-0010"><title>Objective</title><p>To determine the prevalence of borderline personality disorder among patients who undergo facial plastic surgery and identify associated demographics, clinical characteristics, and outcomes.</p></sec><sec id="oto270135-sec-0020"><title>Study Design</title><p>Retrospective cohort.</p></sec><sec id="oto270135-sec-0030"><title>Setting</title><p>More than 80 health care organizations across the United States.</p></sec><sec id="oto270135-sec-0040"><title>Methods</title><p>This retrospective cohort study queried the TriNetX Research Network to identify patients who underwent facial plastic surgeries during 2012 to 2023. Demographics, clinical characteristics, and outcomes were compared between patients with and without a diagnosis of borderline personality disorder.</p></sec><sec id="oto270135-sec-0050"><title>Results</title><p>Among 60,792 patients, there were 309 (0.51%) with a diagnosis of borderline personality disorder (mean age 45.0; 77% female, 22% male) and 60,453 controls (mean age 54.7; 63.4% female, 34.5% male). Patients with borderline personality disorder were younger (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) and more likely to be female (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). They were more likely to undergo rhinoplasty (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001), but less likely to have blepharoplasty (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) or facelift (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.01). They also had higher rates of psychiatric and substance use disorders (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). Patients with borderline personality disorder were at greater risk of postoperative emergency department visits (15.9% vs 4.8%) and hospitalization (12.0% vs 6.6%) compared to controls in the first 3 months postoperatively (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). However, these rates did not represent a significant increase relative to their own baseline levels (15.9% for emergency visits and 3.9% for inpatient admissions over a comparable 3&#8208;month period, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1.0 and .44, respectively).</p></sec><sec id="oto270135-sec-0060"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Patients with borderline personality disorder are more likely to be younger, female, undergo rhinoplasty, have additional psychiatric comorbidities, and present to the hospital at baseline and during the recovery period.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd id="oto270135-kwd-0001">borderline personality disorder</kwd><kwd id="oto270135-kwd-0002">facial plastic surgery</kwd><kwd id="oto270135-kwd-0003">type B personality disorder</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="3"/><page-count count="8"/><word-count count="4847"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>April-June 2025</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.5.6 mode:remove_FC converted:29.05.2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><fn-group><fn id="oto270135-note-0001"><p>The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the NIH.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><p>Facial plastic surgery includes a range of procedures designed to enhance esthetic appearance, with the end goal of achieving patient satisfaction. This relies on the surgeon's attention to the psychological needs of the patient before and after the operation, a factor that many believe is as important as the surgical procedure itself.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref> Overall, outcomes after facial plastic surgery are overwhelmingly positive, and patient satisfaction is high.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="oto270135-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="oto270135-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref> However, there exists a small subgroup of patients who remain dissatisfied despite achieving objectively good results from the surgeon's perspective. During consultation, assessing patients who may be predisposed to disappointment with their result is important for optimizing outcomes for the patient and surgeon alike. Several factors linked to patient dissatisfaction include younger age, male gender, unrealistic expectations, and prior unsatisfactory cosmetic surgeries. Additionally, a history of depression, anxiety, personality disorders, or body dysmorphic disorder (BDD) have also been implicated.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="oto270135-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="oto270135-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>
</p><p>Borderline personality disorder (BPD) is a mental health condition classified under type B personality disorders. Individuals with BPD often act impulsively, have tumultuous interpersonal relationships driven by splitting and fear of abandonment, and have a propensity for self&#8208;injurious behaviors.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="oto270135-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref> It is characterized by significant instability in moods, behaviors, functioning, and self&#8208;image,<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref> which is what may frequently lead these patients to facial plastic surgery clinics. It has been estimated to have a prevalence of 1.7% in the general population<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref> and may be as high as 9% in patients seeking cosmetic facial plastic surgery.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref> Morioka and Ohkubo described that patients with BPD seek esthetic plastic surgery for two main reasons: (1) insatiable requests for esthetic procedures or (2) treatment for self&#8208;injury.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref>
</p><p>BPD presents unique challenges in the context of facial plastic surgery due to the potential for postoperative dissatisfaction and complications. Understanding the psychological profile of surgical candidates is crucial, as operating on poor surgical candidates may lead to worsening psychiatric symptoms,<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref> increased likelihood of seeking additional procedures, refund demands, or even litigation.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="oto270135-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="oto270135-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>15</sup>
</xref> Identifying patients with BPD during consultation and exploring their motivations and expectations enables surgeons to deliver patient&#8208;centered care, ultimately fostering better outcomes for both the patient and surgeon.</p><p>In this large database study, we conducted an in&#8208;depth analysis of BPD in the context of facial plastic surgery. We compared patients with BPD to those without, focusing on surgical, demographic, and clinical characteristics, as well as differences in outcomes and complications, based on diagnosis (International Statistical Classification of Diseases, Tenth Revision [ICD&#8208;10]) and procedure (Current Procedural Terminology [CPT]) codes. These findings aim to enhance surgeons' preoperative evaluations and aid in identifying patients who may benefit from additional counseling when determining their surgical candidacy.</p><sec sec-type="methods" id="oto270135-sec-0080"><title>Methods</title><p>This was a retrospective cohort study with data obtained from the TriNetX Research Network (Cambridge, MA). TriNetX is a global health research network that aggregates deidentified patient data from a consortium of more than 80 health care organizations (HCOs) across the United States.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>16</sup>
</xref> The platform includes demographic information, diagnoses, procedures, medications, lab results, and other clinical data derived from electronic health records. TriNetX ensures patient privacy and data security through deidentification, and therefore it is compliant with the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA). The Penn State Institutional Review Board deemed STUDY00018629 exempt from review as it involved the analysis of deidentified data.</p><p>The database was queried utilizing ICD&#8208;10 and CPT codes to identify patients who underwent common facial plastic surgeries during 2012 through 2023. Surgical interventions included rhinoplasty, rhytidectomy, blepharoplasty, brow lift, and lipectomy. To ensure high&#8208;quality data and follow&#8208;up, patients were required to have active records for at least 1 year before and 1 year following their surgery.</p><p>Among the cohort who underwent facial plastic surgery, individuals were categorized based on whether they had a documented diagnosis of BPD (inclusive of patients diagnosed before and after their index surgery), enabling comparative analyses between those with and without BPD. Demographic variables analyzed included age, sex, region, and marital status, whereas race and ethnicity were excluded from analyses to avoid the limitations and biases often associated with these variables in database studies.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>17</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="oto270135-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>18</sup>
</xref> Clinical characteristics examined included the type of surgical intervention, coexisting medical conditions, psychiatric comorbidities, and substance use disorders. Postoperative outcomes such as rehospitalization and general complications within the first 3 months were also assessed, as well as early revision surgeries within the first year postsurgery. Baseline hospitalization rates were also evaluated during a 3&#8208;month period occurring 9 to 12 months before the index facial plastic surgery to serve as a comparative reference. This time frame was intentionally selected to avoid the perioperative period and better reflect true baseline hospitalization rates. The diagnosis and procedure codes utilized to build the cohort and execute the analyses are presented in Supplement&#160;<xref rid="oto270135-suppl-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">1</xref>, available online.</p><sec id="oto270135-sec-0090"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Relative risks (RRs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were calculated to determine the risk that patients with BPD who underwent facial plastic surgery had specific demographic, surgical, and clinical characteristics and outcomes compared to patients without BPD. A <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test was performed to determine whether there was a difference in mean age between groups. All statistical analyses were conducted using the TriNetX platform, which is based on Java, R, and Python.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="oto270135-sec-0100"><title>Results</title><sec id="oto270135-sec-0110"><title>Demographics</title><p>From 2012 to 2023, a total of 60,762 patients underwent facial plastic surgery, including 309 patients with a diagnosis of BPD (0.51%) and 60,453 controls (<xref rid="oto270135-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The mean age of patients with BPD was 45.0&#8201;&#177;&#8201;17.1 years, with 77.0% female and 22.0% male. In comparison, controls had a mean age of 54.7&#8201;&#177;&#8201;19.8 years, with 63.4% female and 34.5% male. Regarding race, &lt;10 patients in the cohort with BPD identified as American Indian or Alaska Native, Asian, black, or Native Hawaiian or other Pacific Islander, 4.2% and 5.8% identified as other or had an unknown race, respectively, and 84.1% identified as white. Among controls, 0.4% identified as American Indian or Alaska Native, 3.4% as Asian, 3.5% as black, 0.2% as Native Hawaiian or other Pacific Islander, 4.4% and 8.7% as other or unknown, respectively, and 79.4% as white. Regarding ethnicity, 8.4% of patients with BPD identified as Hispanic or Latino, 81.2% as not Hispanic or Latino, and 10.4% had an unknown ethnicity. In the control cohort, 9.4% identified as Hispanic or Latino, 75.0% as not Hispanic or Latino, and ethnicity was unknown for 15.6%. Among patients with BPD, 65.7% (n&#8201;=&#8201;203) had a known diagnosis before the time of surgery, whereas 34.3% (n&#8201;=&#8201;106) were diagnosed postoperatively. Patients with BPD were significantly younger (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) and more likely to be female (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) compared to those without BPD. They were also significantly more likely to reside in the Midwest (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) and to be divorced or never married (both <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="oto270135-tbl-0001" content-type="Table" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Differences in Demographics Between Patients With Borderline Personality Disorder and Controls Who Underwent Facial Plastic Surgery (n&#8201;=&#8201;60,762)<xref rid="oto270135-tbl1-note-0002" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr valign="bottom" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Borderline personality disorder (n&#8201;=&#8201;309)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls (n&#8201;=&#8201;60,453)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR (95% CI)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, y</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.0&#8201;&#177;&#8201;17.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.7&#8201;&#177;&#8201;19.8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" valign="top" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">238 (77.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38,303 (63.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 (1.14&#8208;1.29)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (22.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,867 (34.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 (0.52&#8208;0.79)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;10 (&lt;3.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,283 (2.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" valign="top" rowspan="1">Race</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">American Indian or Alaska Native</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;10 (&lt;3.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">242 (0.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;10 (&lt;3.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2039 (3.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black or African American</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;10 (&lt;3.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2104 (3.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native Hawaiian or other Pacific Islander</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (0.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (4.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2675 (4.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown race</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (5.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5233 (8.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">260 (84.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48,064 (79.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" valign="top" rowspan="1">Ethnicity</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic or Latino</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (8.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5695 (9.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not Hispanic or Latino</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">251 (81.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45,361 (75.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown ethnicity</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (10.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9397 (15.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" valign="top" rowspan="1">Region</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midwest</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (25.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,255 (18.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 (1.13&#8208;1.66)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Northeast</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (27.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,626 (29.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.79&#8208;1.13)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.53</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other/unknown</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;10 (&lt;3.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">989 (1.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (27.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,382 (32.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.73&#8208;1.04)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.12</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">West</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (18.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,201 (18.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.80&#8208;1.28)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" valign="top" rowspan="1">Marital status</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Divorced</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (8.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2274 (3.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.32 (1.62&#8208;3.34)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (10.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,444 (20.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52 (0.38&#8208;0.72)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never married</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (17.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6877 (11.3%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56 (1.23&#8208;1.99)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189 (61.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36,206 (59.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.93&#8208;1.12)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.64</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Widowed</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;10 (&lt;3.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2652 (4.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8208;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="oto270135-tbl1-note-0001"><p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; RR, relative risk.</p></fn><fn id="oto270135-tbl1-note-0002"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>For demographic outcomes with 1 to 10 people, TriNetX rounds to 10.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="oto270135-sec-0120"><title>Surgical Characteristics</title><p>In terms of surgical intervention, patients with BPD were significantly more likely to undergo rhinoplasty compared to patients who did not have BPD (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) (<xref rid="oto270135-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). These patients were also less likely to undergo blepharoplasty (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) or facelift (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.01). There were no significant differences in the rates of browlift (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.59) or lipectomy (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.54) between groups.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="oto270135-tbl-0002" content-type="Table" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Differences in Surgical and Clinical Characteristics Between Patients With Borderline Personality Disorder and Controls Who Underwent Facial Plastic Surgery (n&#8201;=&#8201;60,762)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr valign="bottom" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Borderline personality disorder (n&#8201;=&#8201;309)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls (n&#8201;=&#8201;60,453)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR (95% CI)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" valign="top" rowspan="1">Surgery</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blepharoplasty</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (31.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28,873 (47.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65 (0.55&#8208;0.77)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Browlift</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (16.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9507 (15.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.83&#8208;1.37)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.59</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facelift</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (4.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5086 (8.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 (0.29&#8208;0.85)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.01</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipectomy</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (2.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1440 (2.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 (0.64&#8208;2.33)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.54</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rhinoplasty</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">196 (63.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24,933 (41.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54 (1.41&#8208;1.67)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" valign="top" rowspan="1">Medical comorbidities</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerebrovascular diseases</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (26.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,196 (16.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55 (1.29&#8208;1.88)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic kidney diseases</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (13.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7173 (11.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 (0.89&#8208;1.55)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.26</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic lower respiratory diseases</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177 (57.3%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,009 (31.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82 (1.65&#8208;2.01)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertensive diseases</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">161 (52.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30,393 (50.3%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.93&#8208;1.15)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.51</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischemic heart diseases</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (29.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,008 (21.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39 (1.17&#8208;1.64)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver disease</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98 (31.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9514 (15.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02 (1.71&#8208;2.38)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type 2 diabetes mellitus</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (32.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,951 (23.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61 (1.27&#8208;2.05)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" valign="top" rowspan="1">Psychiatric comorbidities</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286 (92.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21,659 (35.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.58 (2.50&#8208;2.67)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bipolar disorder</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142 (46.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1735 (2.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.01 (14.07&#8208;18.23)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delusional disorder</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (13.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">618 (1.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.32 (10.44&#8208;19.65)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">277 (89.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,422 (32.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.04 (12.52&#8208;26.01)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eating disorder</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (19.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">988 (1.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.68 (9.21&#8208;14.82)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OCD</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (16.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">778 (1.3%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.08 (10.11&#8208;16.92)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142 (46.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2147 (3.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.94 (11.39&#8208;14.70)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self&#8208;harm</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 (22.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">732 (1.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.71 (15.04&#8208;23.27)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" valign="top" rowspan="1">Substance use disorders</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abuse of other psychoactive substances</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102 (33.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3058 (5.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.98 (7.11&#8208;11.35)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol use disorders</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102 (33.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5643 (9.3%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.54 (3.01&#8208;4.15)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cannabis disorders</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (24.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1480 (2.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.18 (8.33&#8208;12.43)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cocaine abuse</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (12.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">541 (0.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.38 (9.78&#8208;18.31)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhalant abuse</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (10.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">492 (0.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.33 (8.73&#8208;17.41)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nicotine dependence</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156 (50.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,326 (17.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.96 (2.64&#8208;3.31)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Opioid disorders</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (19.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1483 (2.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.78 (6.15&#8208;9.84)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="oto270135-tbl2-note-0001"><p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; OCD, obsessive&#8208;compulsive disorder; PTSD, posttraumatic stress disorder; RR, relative risk.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="oto270135-sec-0130"><title>Clinical Characteristics</title><p>Clinically, patients with BPD had significantly higher rates of cerebrovascular diseases, chronic lower respiratory diseases, ischemic heart diseases, liver disease, and type 2 diabetes (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) (<xref rid="oto270135-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). They also had significantly higher rates of comorbid depression, anxiety, bipolar disorder, posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD), obsessive&#8208;compulsive disorder, delusional disorders, eating disorders, and a history of self&#8208;harm (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). Furthermore, these patients were also more likely to have a documented substance use disorder, including nicotine dependence, alcohol use disorders, cannabis disorder, opioid disorders, cocaine abuse, inhalant abuse, and abuse of other psychoactive substances (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001).</p></sec><sec id="oto270135-sec-0140"><title>Postoperative Care and Complications</title><p>During the baseline period (9&#8211;12 months before surgery), patients with BPD had significantly higher rates of emergency department visits and inpatient admissions compared to controls (both <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001) (<xref rid="oto270135-tbl-0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). These elevated rates persisted in the 3 months following surgery, with BPD patients again demonstrating significantly higher emergency department visits and inpatient admissions than controls (both <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). However, when comparing postoperative health care utilization to baseline within the BPD group, emergency department visit rates remained unchanged (RR 1.00, 95% CI 0.70&#8208;1.44, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1.0), and inpatient admissions were not significantly different from baseline (RR 1.19, 95% CI 0.76&#8208;1.87, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.44).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="oto270135-tbl-0003" content-type="Table" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Differences in Baseline Hospitalization Rates, Rehospitalization, General Postoperative Complications, and Revision Surgery Between Patients With Borderline Personality Disorder and Controls Who Underwent Facial Plastic Surgery (n&#8201;=&#8201;60,762)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000; border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="center" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr valign="bottom" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Borderline personality disorder (n&#8201;=&#8201;309)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls (n&#8201;=&#8201;60,453)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR (95% CI)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" valign="top" rowspan="1">Baseline hospitalization rate 1&#8201;y to 9&#8201;mo before surgery</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emergency department</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (15.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2341 (3.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.10 (3.16&#8208;5.31)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient admission</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (10.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1904 (3.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.19 (2.27&#8208;4.46)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" valign="top" rowspan="1">Rehospitalization 0 to 3&#8201;mo</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emergency department</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (15.9%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2907 (4.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.30 (2.55&#8208;4.27)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient admission</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (12.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3999 (6.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81 (1.34&#8208;2.45)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" valign="top" rowspan="1">General postoperative complications 0 to 3&#8201;mo</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bleeding/hematoma</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.3%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232 (0.4%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.12&#8208;5.99)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.86</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgical site infection</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133 (0.2%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 (0.05&#8208;11.71)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.82</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wound dehiscence</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (1.3%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">422 (0.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85 (0.70&#8208;4.93)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" valign="top" rowspan="1">Revision surgery 0 to 1&#8201;y</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blepharoplasty</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/96 (2.1%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1048/28,873 (3.6%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 (0.15&#8208;2.26)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.43</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Browlift</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/52 (4.8%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">339/9507 (3.5%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.27&#8208;4.06)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.96</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facelift</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/13 (0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">193/5086 (3.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.06&#8208;14.33)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.96</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipectomy</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/9 (0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58/1440 (4.0%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23 (0.08&#8208;18.57)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.88</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rhinoplasty</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/196 (7.7%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1312/24,933 (5.3%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47 (0.90&#8208;2.40)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.13</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="oto270135-tbl3-note-0001"><p>Abbreviation: RR, relative risk.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><p>The rates of general postoperative complications, such as bleeding/hematoma, surgical site infections, and wound dehiscence, were minimal and did not differ significantly between groups (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;.05). Although patients with BPD who underwent rhinoplasty had a higher rate of revision surgery compared to controls, this difference was not statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;.13). Revision rates for other procedures, including blepharoplasty, brow lift, facelift, and lipectomy, showed no significant differences between groups (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;.05).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="oto270135-sec-0150"><title>Discussion</title><p>The literature consistently documents a higher prevalence of psychiatric comorbidities, including BPD,<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref> among individuals seeking facial plastic surgery.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>19</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="oto270135-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>20</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="oto270135-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>21</sup>
</xref> Previous research across various surgical fields has shown that patients with psychiatric conditions are at an elevated risk for postoperative complications.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>22</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="oto270135-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>23</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="oto270135-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>24</sup>
</xref> In facial plastic surgery, a study by Napoleon reported that patients with BPD had markedly lower postoperative satisfaction scores (1.5/10) compared to those with other personality disorders (5/10) and those without any personality disorders (7.4/10).<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref> Our study extends upon prior research by providing a comprehensive, large&#8208;scale analysis of the demographics, surgical preferences, clinical characteristics, and outcomes for patients with BPD undergoing facial plastic surgery. Overall surgical complication and early revision rates were low. Patients with BPD were more than three times as likely to visit the emergency department and nearly twice as likely to require hospital admission postoperatively; however, these rates were comparable to their preoperative baseline.</p><p>The prevalence of documented BPD in this cohort who underwent facial plastic surgery was relatively low, with only 0.51% having a diagnosis. However, it is likely that the true prevalence of BPD is higher, as the condition is underdiagnosed.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0025" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>25</sup>
</xref> Moreover, these data reflect only those who proceeded with surgery, and the number of patients with BPD who present to the clinic seeking surgical consultation is likely much greater. This limits the applicability of our findings to surgical candidacy decisions. It has been estimated that the rate of BPD could be as high as 9% in this population.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref> Additionally, more than a third of patients in our cohort were not diagnosed with BPD until after surgery, highlighting the importance of screening for BPD and other psychiatric conditions. Early identification can facilitate appropriate psychiatric evaluation and treatment, ensuring comprehensive care.</p><p>We found that these patients were, on average, 10 years younger, more frequently female, and more likely to be divorced compared to the general population. BPD symptoms are often identified before adulthood.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0026" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>26</sup>
</xref> This may have contributed to the younger demographic among the BPD cohort compared to controls undergoing surgery and does not necessarily indicate that BPD directly leads individuals to pursue surgical interventions. Although facial plastic surgery is more common among females,<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0027" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>27</sup>
</xref> the proportion of female patients with BPD undergoing these procedures was disproportionately high, consistent with earlier findings that BPD is more commonly diagnosed in women.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>28</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="oto270135-bib-0029" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>29</sup>
</xref> However, recent research suggests that this gender disparity may be influenced by diagnostic biases rather than reflecting actual differences in prevalence.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0030" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>30</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="oto270135-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>31</sup>
</xref> Therefore, facial plastic surgeons should not overlook the potential for a BPD diagnosis in male patients. BPD symptoms vary by gender: females often show emotional instability, interpersonal issues, and comorbid mental health conditions such as mood disorders, PTSD, and eating disorders. Conversely, males are more prone to explosive temperaments, aggression, and substance abuse.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0032" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>32</sup>
</xref> Other indicators that a patient may have BPD include a history of adverse childhood events, previous esthetic procedures with different surgeons, splitting perspectives of clinic staff or past surgeons, and changing bodily concerns over time.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref> Up to 90% of patients with BPD report a history of traumatic childhood experiences.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0033" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>33</sup>
</xref>
</p><p>Patients with BPD were more than 50% more likely to undergo rhinoplasty and less likely to select blepharoplasty or facelift. Rhinoplasty, being one of the most psychologically impactful surgeries, may attract patients with BPD due to their heightened concerns about self&#8208;image. This preference aligns with findings of another study on patients with BDD, who also favored rhinoplasty.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0034" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>34</sup>
</xref> Such trends reflect the deep&#8208;seated issues with self&#8208;identity and body image prevalent in both BPD and BDD. It is likely that many patients with BPD in our study had comorbid BDD; however, this was unable to be reliably measured given that the ICD&#8208;10 code for BDD (F45.22) was only recently introduced in October 2023. Studies have estimated the prevalence of BDD in the facial plastic surgery setting to be more than 13%.<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0035" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>35</sup>
</xref> As more patients are ascribed the BDD ICD&#8208;10 code over time, a similar study could be conducted to further characterize that condition.</p><p>There was a high prevalence of medical and psychiatric comorbidities, as well as substance abuse among patients with BPD undergoing facial plastic surgery. Psychiatric conditions and substance use are common in BPD,<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0036" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>36</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="oto270135-bib-0037" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>37</sup>
</xref> and likely contributed to the increased rates of emergency department visits and inpatient admissions observed. These elevated rates were present not only during the postoperative recovery period but also during the preoperative baseline. These findings suggest that although BPD is associated with elevated health care utilization, surgery did not appear to amplify this difference beyond the already high baseline. Their elevated health care use may reflect a broader pattern of chronic or baseline health system interaction rather than a disproportionate response to surgery itself. Another possible hypothesis for this is that patients with BPD are already engaged in frequent health care contact, so new surgical issues may be managed within existing patterns of care. Regardless of whether surgery influences postoperative health care utilization for this patient population, there is a need for thorough preoperative assessments and a multidisciplinary approach to address both the physical and psychological health of this population.</p><p>Overall, patients with BPD may have difficulty achieving satisfaction with their surgical results due to the inherent characteristics of the condition, such as pervasive instability in mood and self&#8208;image. The impulsivity associated with BPD often leads to rushed decisions about undergoing surgery without thoroughly considering the long&#8208;term consequences, increasing the likelihood of disappointment with the results. True subjective outcomes, such as patient satisfaction, could not be captured in this large database study, which remains a valuable area for future research. However, one notable finding in our analysis of revision surgery was that patients with BPD who underwent rhinoplasty were 1.5 times as likely to undergo revision surgery in the first year, though this did not achieve statistical significance. Our analysis was limited to revision surgeries occurring within 1 year of the index procedure due to sample size constraints; as many revisions take place beyond this period, longer&#8208;term outcomes may not have been fully captured in this cohort. Additionally, if a patient sought further care by a different surgeon at an outside HCO, they would not have been counted as undergoing revision surgery. Therefore, although early reoperation rates offer some insight, they may not fully reflect the broader picture of dissatisfaction in patients with BPD.</p><p>The specialty of facial plastic surgery should consider these findings to enhance preoperative screening and patient counseling when determining surgical candidacy to achieve optimal outcomes for both patients and surgeons. Future studies could focus on developing standardized protocols for managing patients with BPD in facial plastic surgery, evaluating the impact of multidisciplinary care teams, and investigating long&#8208;term surgical outcomes and satisfaction in this unique patient population.</p><p>This study represents the largest analysis to date of patients with BPD undergoing facial plastic surgery, but it has several limitations. First, the analysis relies on the accuracy of diagnosis and procedure codes documented in medical records, so there is potential for underdiagnosis or misclassification. The database nature of the study limits the level of detail available for individual patients, requiring all BPD diagnoses to be grouped together, despite the condition varying in severity and duration (mild/severe, acute/chronic).<xref rid="oto270135-bib-0038" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>38</sup>
</xref> Additionally, we were unable to determine which patients were receiving professional psychiatric treatment. It was also not possible to determine the reason behind each emergency department visit. Another limitation is that TriNetX mainly gathers data from large HCOs, excluding smaller, private, or cosmetic&#8208;only practices from the analysis and thus limiting generalizability. There were also statistically significant differences in demographics and comorbidities between groups which may have impacted outcome data including procedure type and health care utilization; however, we were unable to perform propensity score matching as the BPD patients meeting matching criteria was too small to yield statistically meaningful results. Finally, it was not possible to differentiate between cosmetic and functional procedures using the database, so some noncosmetic cases were likely included. Although this study offers valuable insights into the prevalence, demographics, clinical characteristics, and outcomes of patients with BPD undergoing facial plastic surgery, caution must be taken in interpreting these findings. Ultimately, surgical decisions should be made on an individualized basis, taking into account the full clinical context and unique needs of each patient.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="oto270135-sec-0160"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Patients with BPD seeking facial plastic surgery exhibit distinct demographic profiles, specific surgical preferences, and higher rates of psychiatric comorbidities and substance use disorders compared to the general population undergoing facial plastic surgery.</p></sec><sec id="oto270135-sec-0170"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>
<bold>F. Jeffrey Lorenz</bold>, concept design, data collection, reviewing data analysis, writing manuscript; <bold>Cheng Ma</bold>, concept design, reviewing data analyses, critical editing of manuscript and final approval; <bold>Alyssa K. Givens</bold>, concept design, reviewing data analyses, critical editing of manuscript and final approval; <bold>Scott G. Walen</bold>, concept design, reviewing data analyses, critical editing of manuscript and final approval.</p></sec><sec id="oto270135-sec-0180"><title>Disclosures</title><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="oto270135-sec-0190"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="oto270135-sec-0200"><title>Funding source</title><p>The project was supported by the National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences, National Institutes of Health (NIH), through Grant UL1 TR002014.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting information</title><supplementary-material id="oto270135-suppl-0001" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>
<bold>Supporting Information</bold>.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="OTO2-9-e70135-s001.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="oto270135-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="oto270135-bib-0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0001"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sykes</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Patient selection in facial plastic surgery</article-title>. <source>Facial Plast Surg Clin North Am</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>173</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>176</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fsc.2007.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18355699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0002"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Litner</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rotenberg</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adamson</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Impact of cosmetic facial surgery on satisfaction with appearance and quality of life</article-title>. <source>Arch Facial Plast Surg</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>79</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>83</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archfaci.10.2.79</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18347233</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0003"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guyuron</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bokhari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Patient satisfaction following rhinoplasty</article-title>. <source>Aesthetic Plast Surg</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>153</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>157</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02275535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8801805</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0004"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Honigman</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Castle</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A review of psychosocial outcomes for patients seeking cosmetic surgery</article-title>. <source>Plast Reconstr Surg</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>113</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1229</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>1237</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.PRS.0000110214.88868.CA</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15083026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1762095</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="oto270135-cit-0005"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Milothridis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Predicting factors of postoperative satisfaction in cosmetic medicine</part-title>. In: <source>Cosmetic Patient Selection and Psychosocial Background</source>. <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>; <year>2020</year>:<fpage>79</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-44725-0_9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0006"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Herruer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Prins</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>van Heerbeek</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Verhage&#8208;Damen</surname><given-names>GWJA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ingels</surname><given-names>KJAO</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Negative predictors for satisfaction in patients seeking facial cosmetic surgery: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Plast Reconstr Surg</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>135</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1596</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>1605</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PRS.0000000000001264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26017596</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0007"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leichsenring</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leibing</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kruse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>New</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leweke</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Borderline personality disorder</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>377</volume>(<issue>9759</issue>):<fpage>74</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(10)61422-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21195251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0008"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gunderson</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Herpertz</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Skodol</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Torgersen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zanarini</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Borderline personality disorder</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Dis Primers</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>18029</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrdp.2018.29</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29795363</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0009"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Skodol</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Personality disorders in DSM&#8208;5</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Clin Psychol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>317</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>344</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-clinpsy-032511-143131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22458868</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0010"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Napoleon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The presentation of personalities in plastic surgery</article-title>. <source>Ann Plast Surg</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>208</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000637-199309000-00001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8239409</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0011"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morioka</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ohkubo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Borderline personality disorder and aesthetic plastic surgery</article-title>. <source>Aesthetic Plast Surg</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1169</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>1176</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00266-014-0396-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25209530</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0012"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wever</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wever</surname><given-names>AME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Constantian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychiatric disorders in facial plastic surgery</article-title>. <source>Facial Plast Surg Clin North Am</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>451</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>460</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fsc.2020.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33010863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0013"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shridharani</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Magarakis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Manson</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychology of plastic and reconstructive surgery: a systematic clinical review</article-title>. <source>Plast Reconstr Surg</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>126</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2243</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>2251</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PRS.0b013e3181f445ae</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21124167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0014"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ambro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychological considerations in revision rhinoplasty</article-title>. <source>Facial Plast Surg</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>03</issue>):<fpage>288</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>292</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0028-1083083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18951316</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0015"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mastrogiovanni</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Plastic surgery and the malpractice industry</article-title>. <source>Plast Reconstr Surg</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>147</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>239</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>247</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PRS.0000000000007497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33370072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0016"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Topaloglu</surname><given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Palchuk</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Using a federated network of real&#8208;world data to optimize clinical trials operations</article-title>. <source>JCO Clin Cancer Informatics</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/CCI.17.00067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6816049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30652541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0017"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nead</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hinkston</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wehner</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cautions when using race and ethnicity in administrative claims data sets</article-title>. <source>JAMA Health Forum</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<elocation-id>e221812</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamahealthforum.2022.1812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36218996</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0018"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Flanagin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Updated guidance on the reporting of race and ethnicity in medical and science journals</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>326</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>621</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2021.13304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34402850</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0019"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ericksen</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Billick</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychiatric issues in cosmetic plastic surgery</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Q</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>343</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>352</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11126-012-9204-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22252848</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0020"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ishigooka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Iwao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuyama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Murasaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Demographic features of patients seeking cosmetic surgery</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>283</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>287</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1440-1819.1998.00388.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9681579</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0021"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ritvo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Melnick</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Glick</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychiatric conditions in cosmetic surgery patients</article-title>. <source>Facial Plast Surg</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>194</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>197</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2006-950177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17048160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0022"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zeber</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pugh</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mortensen</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Restrepo</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Postoperative complications in the seriously mentally ill</article-title>. <source>Ann Surg</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>248</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>31</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SLA.0b013e3181724f25</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18580204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0023"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wirtalla</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sharoky</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kelz</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Disparities in operative outcomes in patients with comorbid mental illness</article-title>. <source>Surgery</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>163</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>667</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>671</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.surg.2017.09.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29241988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0024"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Spataro</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Olds</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kandathil</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Most</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comparison of reconstructive plastic surgery rates and 30&#8208;day postoperative complications between patients with and without psychiatric diagnoses</article-title>. <source>Aesthet Surg J</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>NP684</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>NP694</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/asj/sjaa313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33220052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="oto270135-cit-0025"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Is borderline personality disorder underdiagnosed and bipolar disorder overdiagnosed?</part-title> In: <source>Borderline Personality and Mood Disorders</source>. <publisher-name>Springer New York</publisher-name>; <year>2015</year>:<fpage>65</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>78</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4939-1314-5_4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0026"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Biskin</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The lifetime course of borderline personality disorder</article-title>. <source>Can J Psychiatry</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>303</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>308</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/070674371506000702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26175388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4500179</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0027"><article-title>Cosmetic surgery national data bank statistics</article-title>. <article-title>Aesthet Surg J</article-title>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>29</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/asj/36.Supplement_1.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4954552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27069249</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0028"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>De Moor</surname><given-names>MHM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Distel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Trull</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boomsma</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Assessment of borderline personality features in population samples: is the Personality Assessment Inventory&#8211;Borderline Features scale measurement invariant across sex and age?</article-title><source>Psychol Assess</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>125</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>130</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0014502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19290772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0029"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gunderson</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Borderline personality disorder</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>364</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>2037</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>2042</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMcp1007358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21612472</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0030"><article-title>The role of labeling processes in diagnosing borderline personality disorder</article-title>. <article-title>Am J Psychiatry</article-title>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>140</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1527</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>1529</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/ajp.140.11.1527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6625010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0031"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bjorklund</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>No man's land: gender bias and social constructivism in the diagnosis of borderline personality disorder</article-title>. <source>Issues Ment Health Nurs</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>3</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01612840500312753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16352513</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0032"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sansone</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sansone</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gender patterns in borderline personality disorder</article-title>. <source>Innov Clin Neurosci</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>16</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>20</lpage>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21686143" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21686143</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21686143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3115767</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0033"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cattane</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lanfredi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cattaneo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Borderline personality disorder and childhood trauma: exploring the affected biological systems and mechanisms</article-title>. <source>BMC Psychiatry</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>221</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12888-017-1383-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28619017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5472954</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0034"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hale</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mundra</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Le</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kaoutzanis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mathes</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The heart of it all: body dysmorphic disorder in cosmetic surgery</article-title>. <source>J Plast Reconstr Aesthetic Surg</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>442</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>448</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bjps.2023.10.068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37944455</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0035"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of body dysmorphic disorder and surgeon diagnostic accuracy in facial plastic and oculoplastic surgery clinics</article-title>. <source>JAMA Facial Plast Surg</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>269</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>274</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamafacial.2016.1535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27930752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5543317</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0036"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>C&#8208;C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L&#8208;Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y&#8208;H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comorbidity study of borderline personality disorder: applying association rule mining to the Taiwan national health insurance research database</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Inform Decis Mak</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>8</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12911-016-0405-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28077135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5225571</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0037"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kienast</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stoffers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bermpohl</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lieb</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Borderline personality disorder and comorbid addiction</article-title>. <source>Dtsch Arztebl Int</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>280</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>286</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3238/arztebl.2014.0280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24791755</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4010862</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="oto270135-bib-0038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="oto270135-cit-0038"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Berrocal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz Moreno</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rando</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Benvenuti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cassano</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Borderline personality disorder and mood spectrum</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Res</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>159</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>300</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>307</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2007.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18445508</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>