<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Anesthesiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Anesthesiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">11</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcanes</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Anesthesiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2253</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10050824</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10050824.2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10050824</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10053644</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36991313</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12871-023-02062-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2062</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">2</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A multi-disciplinary program for opioid sparse arthroplasty results in reduced long-term opioid consumption: a four year prospective study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names initials="DY">D-Yin</given-names></name><address><email>d-yin.lin@sa.gov.au</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samson</surname><given-names initials="AJ">Anthony J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#8217;Mello</surname><given-names initials="F">Freeda</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names initials="B">Brigid</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cehic</surname><given-names initials="MG">Matthew G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names initials="C">Christopher</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kroon</surname><given-names initials="HM">Hidde M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaarsma</surname><given-names initials="RL">Ruurd L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.414925.f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9685 0624</institution-id><institution>Department of Anaesthesia, </institution><institution>Flinders Medical Centre, </institution></institution-wrap>Flinders Drive Bedford Park, Adelaide, SA 5042 Australia </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.1014.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0367 2697</institution-id><institution>Discipline of Perioperative Medicine, College of Medicine and Public Health, </institution><institution>Flinders University, </institution></institution-wrap>Adelaide, South Australia Australia </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.414925.f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9685 0624</institution-id><institution>Department of Orthopaedic and Trauma Surgery, </institution><institution>Flinders Medical Centre, </institution></institution-wrap>Adelaide, South Australia Australia </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.416075.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0367 1221</institution-id><institution>Department of Surgery, </institution><institution>Royal Adelaide Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Adelaide, South Australia Australia </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.1010.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 7304</institution-id><institution>Discipline of Surgery, Adelaide Medical School Faculty of Health and Medical Science, </institution><institution>University of Adelaide, </institution></institution-wrap>Adelaide, South Australia Australia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>23</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">425101</issue-id><elocation-id>97</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>8</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>29</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>29</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-03-31 16:10:45.053"><day>31</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-version" specific-use="live"><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10050824</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12871-023-02062-8</article-id><article-version>1</article-version><pub-date><day>29</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></pub-date></event><event event-type="pmc-version" specific-use="live"><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10053644</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12871-023-02062-8</article-id><article-version>2</article-version><pub-date><day>29</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></pub-date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12871_2023_Article_2062.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par1">The current opioid epidemic poses patient safety and economic burdens to healthcare systems worldwide. Postoperative prescriptions of opioids contribute, with reported opioid prescription rates following arthroplasty as high as 89%. In this multi-centre prospective study, an opioid sparing protocol was implemented for patients undergoing knee or hip arthroplasty. The primary outcome is to report our patient outcomes in the context of this protocol, and to examine the rate of opioid prescription on discharge from our hospitals following joint arthroplasty surgery. This is possibly associated with the efficacy of the newly implemented Arthroplasty Patient Care Protocol.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Over three years, patients underwent perioperative education with the expectation to be opioid-free after surgery. Intraoperative regional analgesia, early postoperative mobilisation and multimodal analgesia were mandatory. Long-term opioid medication use was monitored and PROMs (Oxford Knee/Hip Score (OKS/OHS), EQ-5D-5&#160;L) were evaluated pre-operatively, and at 6 weeks, 6 months and 1 year postoperatively. Primary and secondary outcomes were opiate use and PROMs at different time points.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">A total of 1,444 patients participated. Two (0.2%) knee patients used opioids to one year. Zero hip patients used opioids postoperatively at any time point after six weeks (p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001). The OKS and EQ-5D-5&#160;L both improved for knee patients from 16 (12&#8211;22) pre-operatively to 35 (27&#8211;43) at 1 year postoperatively, and 70 (60&#8211;80) preoperatively to 80 (70&#8211;90) at 1 year postoperatively (p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001). The OHS and EQ-5D-5&#160;L both improved for hip patients from 12 (8&#8211;19) preoperatively to 44 (36&#8211;47) at 1 year postoperatively, and 65 (50&#8211;75) preoperatively to 85 (75&#8211;90) at 1 year postoperatively (p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001). Satisfaction improved between all pre- and postoperative time points for both knee and hip patients (p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Knee and hip arthroplasty patients receiving a peri-operative education program can effectively and satisfactorily be managed without long-term opioids when coupled with multimodal perioperative management, making this a valuable approach to reduce chronic opioid use.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12871-023-02062-8.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; The Author(s) 2023</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">The current opioid epidemic poses significant economic and patient safety burdens to healthcare systems. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] This is an issue of growing concern around the world. In the United States, for instance, opioid prescriptions have tripled from 1999 to 2014, leading to a three-fold increase of opioid-related overdoses, and in Australia over 70% of opioid overdoses are prescription related. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]</p><p id="Par6">Orthopedic surgery is in the top 5 specialties who provide opioid prescriptions, and one of the largest providers of postoperative narcotics. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] Arthroplasty surgery is associated with high incidences of new opioid prescriptions in previously opioid na&#239;ve patients, with reported incidences of 17.4 to as high as 89%, with an upwards trend in opioid prescription rates in some countries. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] In the last decade, there has been a conscious shift away from opioid based medications to treat postoperative pain in orthopaedic surgery. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] In an effort to reduce rates of new opioid prescriptions, some studies have reported successful implementation of novel opioid sparing protocols for postoperative care following procedures normally accompanied with high rates of opioid prescriptions, including arthroplasty surgery. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] These studies show a tendency towards higher rates of opioid prescription. Our study describes a protocol that aims to safely reduce the incidence of postoperative opioid prescription while achieving good patient satisfaction and patient related outcomes.</p><p id="Par7">Sabatino et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] described a median prescription rate of ninety 5-mg oxycodone or equivalent pills per patient who underwent total hip or knee arthroplasty with a large proportion of these medications going unused. This would seem to indicate that opioids are perhaps overprescribed following TKR/THR, and that there is room for reducing these prescriptions postoperatively.</p><p id="Par8">In view of this growing opioid problem, the Departments of Anesthesiology and Orthopedic Surgery of our large teaching hospitals have implemented an Arthroplasty Patient Care Protocol (Addendum 1), focused on intensive pre-operative education and early postoperative mobilisation with the aim to limit postoperative opioid subscriptions and with the expectation of an opioid-free postoperative trajectory. The aim of this study was to evaluate if this protocol is indeed effective in decreasing longer-term opioid use, while maintaining patient satisfaction and early recovery.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Outcomes</title><p id="Par9">The primary outcome is to report our patient related outcomes in the context of this protocol, and to examine the rate of opioid prescription on discharge from our hospitals following joint arthroplasty surgery. Time points are preoperative, six weeks postoperative, three months postoperative and one year postoperative.</p><p id="Par10">Three validated patient reported outcome measures (PROMs) scores were taken: the Oxford Knee Score (OKS) or Oxford Hip Score (OHS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], the EQ-5D-5&#160;L score [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], and a 5-point Likert scale for patient satisfaction. Also recorded were the use of opioids at all time points.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Patients and methods</title><p id="Par11">This is a multi-centre prospective observational study. This study was conducted at two tertiary teaching hospitals (FMC and NH) in Adelaide, Australia. Orthopaedic surgeons and anesthesiologists work routinely across both sites, performing 500&#8211;600 arthroplasty procedures per year. Due to SARS Covid-19 related restrictions on elective operations, this number was reduced in 2020 to 307.</p><p id="Par12">All consecutive adult patients who underwent elective knee or hip arthroplasty were approached for informed consent to participate over a three-year period. Patients were prospectively enrolled from 8th January 2018 to 1st of October 2020, with a 1 year follow up. The local Human Research Ethics Committee granted multi-centre approval (SALHN/329.17).</p><p id="Par13">At both hospitals, the Arthroplasty Patient Care Protocol (Addendum 1) was implemented in 2018.</p><p id="Par14">This protocol, based on previous publications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], was created with multidisciplinary input from orthopaedic surgeons, anesthesiologists, physiotherapists and nursing staff. In short, the protocol involves the following. Preoperative: To qualify for surgery, patients are to taper or cease opioids and attend compulsory educational sessions. These sessions are in a group-based format and include explanations of prehabilitation techniques, the operative procedure including the anesthetic, early postoperative mobilisation, and postoperative pain and pain relief. There are also interactive question and answer components with the treating orthopaedic surgeon, physiotherapists and nurses. Emphasis is placed on the expectation for patients to be comfortably opioid-free long term postoperatively, but with low threshold to discuss pain management options. The use of simple analgesic alternatives (paracetamol and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs if not contraindicated) is encouraged with education provided for dosing intervals. All hospital prescribers undergo mandatory education regarding the opioid sparse program prior to patient contact. Intra-operative: Spinal anesthesia without intrathecal morphine is the preferred anesthesia method with local infiltration analgesia (LIA) by the surgeon. Standard regional anesthesia was an adductor canal block for knee, and from 2019 a pericapsular nerve group (PENG) block for hip arthroplasty was added. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] Postoperative: Anesthesiologists and the Acute Pain Service review all patients daily, reinforcing the expectation of opioid-free recovery with administration of regular simple oral analgesia. Patients are allowed opioids as an inpatient if indicated. The inpatient stay is extended if indicated by acute (on chronic) pain and subsequent opioid titration, until the multidisciplinary team determines that the patient is optimised to proceed comfortably as an opioid sparse outpatient. Patients are discharged with a maximum of ten tablets of opioid medication (oxycodone or tramadol) without repeat prescriptions. There is some flexibility if inpatient opioid use indicates that 10 tablets is unlikely to be adequate, but this is by extremely infrequent exception. Postoperative: Orthopaedic surgical follow-up takes place at six weeks and three months. If a patient requires review for postoperative pain, there are appointment slots available in the outpatient clinic. If these are not possible for logistical reasons, the patient is encouraged to see their treating primary care physician who has had a letter sent to them communicating that a joint replacement has been carried out and the opioid sparse expectation of the postoperative trajectory.</p><p id="Par15">This approach is also supported on a national level by a revision to the Pharmaceutical Benefit Scheme in Australia, implemented since 1 June 2020. Postsurgical patients with acute non-cancer pain only qualify for financial cover for a half-pack (10 tablets) of opioid based medication. Any prescription above this amount is paid for by the patient themselves. Long term opioid prescribing requires registration of the patient, and completion of an &#8216;Authority Prescription&#8217; process with written or telephone approval from a central government agency. Currently, a program known as Script Check is being implemented in Australia, which allows a registered medical practioner to check if a patient has had multiple opioid prescriptions. It allows the program user to check in real-time the prescribing history of a particular patient for high-risk prescriptions, including all opioid based medications. It will shortly be mandatory to cross reference a patient using this system prior to providing such a prescription.</p><p id="Par16">Protocol follow-up for this study took place at four different time points: preoperatively, and at six weeks, six months and one year postoperatively. Data were recorded by a dedicated research assistant, using scripted questionnaires either via telephone or via a posted written survey. The same script was used at all four time points. Three validated patient reported outcome measures (PROMs) scores were taken: the Oxford Knee Score (OKS) or Oxford Hip Score (OHS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], the EQ-5D-5&#160;L score [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], a 5-point Likert scale for patient satisfaction, and the use of opioids at all time points. Data were entered into a password secured database stored on the hospital computer network. The database was subdivided into knee or hip arthroplasty. A random sample of patients (n&#8201;=&#8201;52) were called by a separate research assistant to corroborate entered data.</p><p id="Par17">The primary outcome was opiate use at the different time points. Secondary outcomes were the PROMs at the different time points.</p><p id="Par18">The analyses were performed using SPSS version 27 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA) and GraphPad Prism version 8 (GraphPad Software, La Jolla, Calif, USA). The Shapiro-Wilk test showed that all continuous variables were nonparametric and are therefore described as median with interquartile range (IQR). Categorical variables are described as frequency with percentages. Univariate analyses were carried out using the chi-squared test or Fisher&#8217;s exact test (for n&#8201;&lt;&#8201;20) for categorical variables, and the Mann-Whitney U-test for continuous variables. A p-value of &lt;&#8201;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p id="Par19">Out of 1,728 consecutive patients who were invited to participate, 1,444 (84%) provided informed consent.</p><sec id="Sec5"><title>Knee arthroplasty group</title><p id="Par20">A total of 917 patients underwent knee arthroplasty. The majority was female (n&#8201;=&#8201;613; 67%) with a median age of 73 (IQR 65&#8211;80), median body mass index (BMI) of 32&#160;kg/m<sup>2</sup> (IQR 28&#8211;36) and most had surgery for a primary replacement, 909 (99%). Of the knee arthroplasty patients, 232 (25%) used opioids preoperatively. At baseline, 655 (72%) patients reported no or minimal anxiety/depression (EQ-5D-5&#160;L score), moderate anxiety/depression was reported by 198 (21%) and 64 (7%) had severe or extreme preoperative anxiety/depression. (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>)</p><p id="Par21">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics for knee arthroplasty patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Knees<break/>(n&#8201;=&#8201;917)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age</bold> in years, median (IQR)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73 (65&#8211;80)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Gender, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>&#8195;Male</p><p>&#8195;Female</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>304 (33)</p><p>613 (67)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Weight</bold> in kg, median (IQR)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88.9 (75.1&#8211;100)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>BMI</bold> in kg/m<sup>2</sup>, median (IQR)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32 (28&#8211;36)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Type of surgery, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>&#8195;Primary</p><p>&#8195;Revision</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>909 (99)</p><p>8 (1)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Operative side, n (%)</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>&#8195;Left</p><p>&#8195;Right</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>403 (44)</p><p>514 (56)</p></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviations: IQR: interquartile range</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par22">Of the 917 patients who consented to participate in the questionnaire follow-up, 59 (6.4%) were lost to follow-up at six weeks (a slightly higher number of 86 (9.3%) for the satisfaction component). 179 (19.5%) were lost to follow up at six months, and 353 (38.5%) did not respond to the 1 year questionnaire.</p><p id="Par23">Two (0.2%) patients used long-term opioids postoperatively, at six weeks, six months and one year after surgery (p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001 compared to preoperatively). (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) Both were using opioids preoperatively.</p><p id="Par24">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Pre- and postoperative opiate use and patient Reported Outcome Measures (PROMs) for knee arthroplasty</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Knees<break/>(n&#8201;=&#8201;917)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p-value<break/>(comparison to pre-operative)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Opiate use</bold>, n (%)<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;pre-operative</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">232 (25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;6 weeks postoperative<sup>1</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;6 months postoperative<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;1 year postoperative<sup>3</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Oxford Knee Score total</bold>, median (IQR)<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;pre-operative</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (12&#8211;22)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;6 weeks postoperative<sup>1</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (21&#8211;33)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;6 months postoperative<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (27&#8211;40)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;1 year postoperative<sup>3</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 (27&#8211;43)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>EQ-5L-5D Health Questionnaire total</bold>,</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">median (IQR)<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;pre-operative</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70 (60&#8211;80)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;6 weeks postoperative<sup>1</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80 (70&#8211;90)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;6 months postoperative<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80 (70&#8211;90)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;1 year postoperative<sup>3</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80 (70&#8211;90)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par25">The total Oxford Knee Score improved significantly after surgery from 16 points (range 12&#8211;22) preoperatively to 35 points (range 27&#8211;43) at one year (p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001). Similarly, the total EQ-5D-5&#160;L score improved from 70 points (range 60&#8211;80) preoperatively, to 80 points (range 70&#8211;90) at one year (p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001). (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>)</p><p id="Par26">
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Pre- and postoperative patient Reported Outcome Measures (PROMs) for knee arthroplasty</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pre-operatively</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 weeks</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 months</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 year</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>EQ-5L-5D pain/discomfort score</bold>, n (%)<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;917</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;885</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;747</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;578</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;No pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60 (7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">164 (22)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">186 (32)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Slight pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74 (8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">373 (42)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">365 (49)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">248 (43)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Moderate pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">349 (38)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">166 (22)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">105 (18)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Severe pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">410 (45)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">358 (41)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46 (6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37 (6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Extreme pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72 (8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">&#8195;Lost to follow up</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>83 (9)</p><p>11 (1)</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">32</italic>
</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">170</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">339</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>EQ-5L-5D anxiety/depression score</bold>, n (%)<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;917</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;883</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;742</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;574</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Not anxious/depressed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">386 (42)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">530 (60)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">468 (63)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">367 (64)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Slightly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">269 (30)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">219 (25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">171 (23)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">152 (26)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">anxious/depressed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">198 (21)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86 (12)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Moderately</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 (5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103 (11)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">anxious/depressed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Severely</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">175</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">343</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">anxious/depressed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">34</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Extremely</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">anxious/depressed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">&#8195;Lost to follow up</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Likert patient satisfaction</bold>, n (%)<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;917</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;831</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;708</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;564</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Very satisfied</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">350 (42)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">340 (48)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">267 (47)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>$</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Satisfied</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">210 (30)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">170 (30)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Ambivalent</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">301 (36)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100 (14)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77 (14)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Dissatisfied</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46 (6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38 (7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Very dissatisfied</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">122 (15)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">&#8195;Lost to follow up</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>46 (6)</p><p>12 (1)</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">86</italic>
</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">209</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">353</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>IQR: interquartile range</p><p><sup>*</sup> p-values for pre-operative vs. each individual postoperative time point</p><p><sup>$</sup> p-values for six-week vs. each individual postoperative time point</p><p><sup>1</sup> 59 lost to follow up; <sup>2</sup> 179 lost to follow up; <sup>3</sup> 353 lost to follow up</p><p><sup>a</sup> Fisher&#8217;s exact test, <sup>b</sup> Mann-Whitney U test; <sup>c</sup> Chi-squared test</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par27">At 6 weeks postoperatively, anxiety/depression had improved to 749 (85%) with no or minimal anxiety/depression, 103 (12%) with moderate symptoms, and 31 (3%) with severe or extreme anxiety/depression (p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001 compared to preoperatively).</p><p id="Par28">At 6 weeks postoperatively, 433 (49%) patients reported no or slight pain, 358 (41%) had moderate pain, and 94 (10%) reported severe or extreme pain. At six months, 529 (71%) had no or slight pain, 166 (22%) moderate and 52 (7%) had severe or extreme pain. At one year, 434 (75% of 578 respondents) had absent or minimal pain, 105 (18%) had moderate pain symptoms, and 39 (7%) had severe or extreme pain. Both patients who continued using opioids reported severe or extreme pain at one-year follow-up. These incidences are significantly improved compared to preoperative baseline (p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001).</p><p id="Par29">At six weeks 651 (78%) patients were satisfied, 122 (15%) were ambivalent and 58 (7%) were dissatisfied with their overall experience and surgery (86 lost to follow up for satisfaction questionnaire at six weeks).</p><p id="Par30">PROMs showed an upwards trend across all questionnaires and domains within the questionnaires, consistent with improving function. The Oxford Knee Score showed a significant median postoperative improvement of 11 points at six weeks, and 19 points at one year. (Table&#160;3) Improvements were made at all time points across all PROMs (p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Hip arthroplasty group</title><p id="Par31">527 (36%) patients received a hip arthroplasty, who were predominantly female (n&#8201;=&#8201;333; 63%), with a median age of 73 (IQR 66&#8211;81) and median BMI of 30&#160;kg/m<sup>2</sup> (28&#8211;36). 187 (35%) patients reported using opioid based medication prior to operation. (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>)</p><p id="Par32">
<table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Characteristics for hip arthroplasty patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hips<break/>(n&#8201;=&#8201;527)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age</bold> in years, median (IQR)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73 (66&#8211;81)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Gender</bold>, n (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">194 (37)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">333 (63)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Weight</bold> in kg, median (IQR)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83.0 (70.6&#8211;97.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>BMI</bold> in kg/m<sup>2</sup>, median (IQR)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (26.2&#8211;34.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Type of surgery</bold>, n (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Primary</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">519 (98.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Revision</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (1.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Operative side</bold>, n (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Left</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">219 (42)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Right</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">308 (58)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Pre-operative opiate use</bold>, n (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">187 (35)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">340 (65)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviations: IQR: interquartile range</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par33">Of the 527 patients who consented to participate in the questionnaire follow-up, 59 (11.2%) were lost to follow-up at six weeks (a slightly higher number of 60 (11.4%) for the satisfaction component). 180 (34.2%) were lost to follow up at six months, and 256 (48.6%) did not respond to the 1 year questionnaire.</p><p id="Par34">At baseline, 344 (66%) patients had no or slight anxiety or depression, moderate anxiety or depression was present in 106 (20%) patients, and 57 (10%) had severe or extreme anxiety or depression. This had improved by six weeks postoperative to 421 (88%) with no or minimal anxiety or depression as part of the EQ-5D-5&#160;L PROM, and 47(10%) with moderate symptoms. 9 (2%) patients had severe and zero had extreme depression/anxiety.</p><p id="Par35">Zero patients in the hip group used opioid based medication after six weeks, this continued out to a year. (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>)</p><p id="Par36">
<table-wrap id="Tab5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Pre- and postoperative opiate use and patient Reported Outcome Measures for (PROMs) for hip arthroplasty</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hips<break/>(n&#8201;=&#8201;527)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Opiate use</bold>, n (%)<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;pre-operative</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">187 (35)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;6 weeks postoperative<sup>1</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;6 months postoperative<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;1 year postoperative<sup>3</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Oxford Hip Score total</bold>, median (IQR)<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;pre-operative</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (8&#8211;19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;6 weeks postoperative<sup>1</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (24&#8211;37)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;6 months postoperative<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38 (31&#8211;44)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;1 year postoperative<sup>3</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44 (36&#8211;47)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>EQ-5L-5D Health Questionnaire total</bold>,</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">median (IQR)<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65 (50&#8211;75)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;pre-operative</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80 (70&#8211;90)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;6 weeks postoperative<sup>1</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80 (70&#8211;90)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;6 months postoperative<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85 (75&#8211;90)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;1 year postoperative<sup>3</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par37">At six weeks, 318 (60%) patients had no or slight pain, 134 (25%) had moderate pain, and 26 (5%) reported severe pain. At six months, 297 (85%) had no or slight pain, 39 (11%) moderate and 11 (4%) had severe or extreme pain. At one year, 252 (93% of 271 respondents) had absent or minimal pain, 17 (6%) had moderate pain symptoms, and 2 (1%) had severe or extreme pain. At all postoperative follow-up points, comparison to preoperative incidences were significantly improved (p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001).</p><p id="Par38">At 6 weeks postoperative 412 (78%) patients were satisfied, 22 (4%) were ambivalent, 27 (6%) were dissatisfied 66 (13%) were lost to follow-up. This remained consistent at six months and one year. This represented a significant change in incidence (p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001).</p><p id="Par39">The Oxford Hip Score showed a median postoperative improvement of 19 points at six weeks, and 31 points at a year. (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>) Statistically significant improvements were made at all time points across all PROMs (p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001).</p><p id="Par40">
<table-wrap id="Tab6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Pre- and postoperative patient Reported Outcome Measures (PROMs) for hip arthroplasty</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pre-operatively</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 weeks</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 months</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 year</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>EQ-5L-5D pain/discomfort score</bold>, n (%)<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;527</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;477</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;347</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;271</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;No pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">111 (23)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">181 (52)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200 (73)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Slight pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32 (6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">116 (33)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52 (19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Moderate pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">152 (29)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">207 (43)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39 (11)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Severe pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">187 (235)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Extreme pain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">153 (29)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">134 (28)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">&#8195;Lost to follow up</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>24 (5)</p><p>1 (1)</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">50</italic>
</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">180</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">256</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>EQ-5L-5D anxiety/depression score</bold>, n (%)<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;507</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;477</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;345</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;269</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Not anxious/depressed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">199 (38)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">332 (70)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">257 (74)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">210 (78)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Slightly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">145(28)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89 (18)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62 (18)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (16)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">anxious/depressed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">106 (20)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 (10)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Moderately</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">anxious/depressed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Severely</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">20</italic>
<sup><italic toggle="yes">^</italic></sup>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">50</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">182</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">258</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">anxious/depressed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Extremely</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">anxious/depressed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">&#8195;Lost to follow up</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Likert patient satisfaction</bold>, n (%)<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;527</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;461</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;317</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n&#8201;=&#8201;240</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Very satisfied</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">291 (63)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">203 (64)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">157 (65)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001<sup>$</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Satisfied</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80 (25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60 (25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Ambivalent</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">121 (26)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Dissatisfied</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Very dissatisfied</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">&#8195;Lost to follow up</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>19 (4)</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">66</italic>
</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">210</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">287</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>IQR: interquartile range</p><p><sup>*</sup> p-values for pre-operative vs. each individual postoperative time point</p><p><sup>^</sup> declined to answer</p><p><sup>$</sup> p-values for six-week vs. each individual postoperative time point</p><p><sup>1</sup> 59 lost to follow up; <sup>2</sup> 180 lost to follow up; <sup>3</sup> 256 lost to follow up</p><p><sup>a</sup> Fisher&#8217;s exact test, <sup>b</sup> Mann-Whitney U test; <sup>c</sup> Chi-squared test</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par41">This study demonstrates that a patient education protocol with emphasis on patient expectation management coupled with a multi-disciplinary approach to pain management can result in a long-term opioid free recovery. This is supported on a national level in Australia by multiple programs designed to restrict and monitor opioid prescribing. Similar programs in other countries have also shown success in previous studies. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]</p><p id="Par42">The subject of opioid use for pain management is &#8216;one of intense international interest&#8217;, according to Morgan et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] Dependence can develop following the use of prescription opioids after surgery. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] Health systems internationally have flagged this as an area of concern and strategies aimed at minimising postoperative opioid prescriptions are increasingly suggested. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] That said, opioids are a cornerstone of postoperative pain management and inadequate analgesia can result in delayed mobilisation and recovery. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] The results of the current prospective study, however revealed no decrease in PROM outcomes during an opioid free postoperative phase, showing that joint arthroplasty surgery can be managed with simple analgesia postoperatively without compromising quality of recovery. Pain scores are also comparable with previously published studies, if not lower. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] Pain scores at 6 weeks postoperatively for TKA were described in previous studies as moderate (approximately 5 on a 11 point Likert scale), and decreasing for the following 12 months postoperatively. Another study found at 12 months postoperatively for TKA that 40% of patients had moderate to severe pain. Chronic pain and dissatisfaction have been reported as being as high as 10&#8211;34% of patients at 12 months after TKA. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] Our study describes perhaps less pain, with a majority reporting only slight pain at 6 weeks and moderate pain being the second most common response with a similar pattern of pain improvement over the 12 months of follow-up.</p><p id="Par43">Patient satisfaction rates at our institution are consistent or better than reported incidences from other tertiary centres, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] describing dissatisfaction rates of up to 20% under a classic opioid prescribing regime. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] This may, however, not be related to the opioids specifically, but likely also to the hands-on care, meticulous preoperative preparation, and extensive follow up.</p><p id="Par44">Twenty-five (5%) hip patients reported severe or extreme postoperative pain, and 94 (10%) knee patients at six weeks postoperatively. The limitation to this result is that data collection did not specify the location of and frequently patients were reporting pain in the contralateral joint, likely due to the same underlying pathology. Interestingly, these patients did not report dissatisfaction with the surgery, nor did they use postoperative opioids, making it plausible their pain was indeed not related to the operated joint.</p><p id="Par45">The two patients who remained on opioids postoperatively both recorded preoperative opioid use and severe anxiety and/or depression at all time points. PROM improvements were consistent with average results from the group. One patient reported low patient satisfaction, and both had continuing severe pain despite the prescription of opioid medication.</p><p id="Par46">We compare our incidence of 2/1444 patients who remained on long term opioid medications with previously published incidences of Australian hip and knee arthroplasty patients who followed a traditional regime, i.e. not opioid sparse. It has been described in a similar population as our own as 10% at 6 months postoperatively following TKR, and 4% at 6 months postoperatively following THR. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]</p><p id="Par47">Despite the common use of prescription opioids for chronic non-cancer pain, there remains no strong scientific evidence to support this routine practice. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] This study illustrates that recovery from arthroplasty surgery can be achieved with good patient satisfaction and high-quality PROM outcomes, while remaining opioid sparse. Furthermore, opioid use is associated with an increase in long-term utilisation of health care services, as well as inflicting a significant economic burden. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</p><p id="Par48">PROM surveys and long-term opioid based data collection will be integrated shortly into the national Australian Orthopaedic Association joint registry database. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] This promises to provide an interesting look into opioid prescription and recovery on a large scale in the future. It is likely that the presence of an Acute Pain Service, as well as the use of novel regional anaesthesia assisted in this outcome.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par49">Despite the favourable outcomes described in this study, some limitations do need to be addressed. There is unfortunately no historical data collection at our centre prior to implementation of this protocol, and hence we cannot definitively conclude that a change has been actuated. We have compared to published data in other centres, with similar patient populations and more classic opioid regimes to illustrate the difference. These prescription rates are self-reported by patients, which is also a limitation.</p><p id="Par50">We acknowledge that there may in fact be a cultural component to the result of a low opioid prescription rate, where the team approach is to &#8216;just say no&#8217; to continuing postoperative opioids. We would argue that if that is a factor in our positive outcomes, that it is not necessarily a weakness. Our high patient satisfaction rate and good PROM results despite our low opioid prescription rates show that it is attainable.</p><p id="Par51">It is also possible that the patients who were lost to follow-up were taking opioids. It is unfortunately not possible for us to determine if this is the case. The pattern of lost to follow-up is that the percentage attrition is greater the further away from index surgery, which is not consistent with attrition due to opioid prescribing rates in the acute postoperative phase continuing from surgery. Non-responders had comparable baseline characteristics to responders, i.e. were not more likely to be using opioids preoperatively. The attrition rate, for example 6.4% at 6 weeks for TKA, is also lower than most opioid prescribing rates described in previously published studies. We hope that in the near future with the implementation in Australia of Script Check, that it becomes easier to determine patient opioid use across all health providers.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par52">In conclusion, the results of this multi-centre prospective study show no decrease in PROM outcomes or patient satisfaction during an opioid free postoperative phase for the vast majority of patients. This illustrates that joint arthroplasty surgery can be managed with non-opiod analgesia postoperatively between six weeks and one year, without compromising pain scores or quality of recovery. This topic should be considered for future investigation by means of a randomized controlled trial.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec10"><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12871_2023_2062_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#8217;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>N/A.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>D-Yin Lin,: This author conceived, designed, submitted to Ethics and Governance, Adelaide, South Australia, Australia. This author also prepared the drafts, analyzed and prepared the data, and approved and submitted the final manuscript. Anthony J. Samson,: This author conceived, designed and realized the study protocol, supervised the database, realized the study, acquired the data, and approved the final manuscript. Freeda D&#8217;Mello.: This author maintained the database, conducted the data entry, and approved the final manuscript. Brigid Brown,: This author conceived and designed the study and approved the final manuscript. Matthew G. Cehic,: This author conceived and designed the study and approved the final manuscript. Christopher Wilson,: This author conceived, assisted with designing, realized the study, and approved the final manuscript. Hidde M. Kroon,: This author conceived, assisted with designing, conducted statistical analyses, critically revised the drafts, and approved the final manuscript. Professor Ruurd L. Jaarsma,: This author conceived, assisted with designing, realized the study, provided departmental support, revised the drafts, and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>The authors have no sources of funding to declare for this manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p>The datasets generated and/or analysed during the current study are not publicly available as this was not approved by the Ethics Committee but are available in a deidentified format from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar212" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p id="Par457">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><notes id="FPar213"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par458">The local Human Research Ethics Committee granted multi-centre approval (SALHN/329.17). All participants gave informed consent prior to inclusion. All Methods were carried out in accordance with relevant guidelines, regulations and the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></notes><notes id="FPar214"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par459">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar215" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p id="Par460">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><glossary><title>List of abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>PROMs</term><def><p id="Par56">Patient reported outcome measures</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LIA</term><def><p id="Par57">Local infiltration analgesia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PENG</term><def><p id="Par58">Pericapsular nerve group block</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BMI</term><def><p id="Par59">Body mass index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OKS</term><def><p id="Par60">Oxford Knee Score</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OHS</term><def><p id="Par61">Oxford Hip Score</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An overview of the patterns of prescription opioid use, costs and related harms in Australia</article-title><source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source><year>2014</year><volume>78</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1159</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bcp.12446</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24962372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4243891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berterame</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erthal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fellner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vosse</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clare</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of and barriers to access to opioid analgesics: a worldwide, regional, and national study</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2016</year><volume>387</volume><issue>10028</issue><fpage>1644</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(16)00161-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26852264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roxburgh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobbins</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gisev</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Trends in heroin and pharmaceutical opioid overdose deaths in Australia</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source><year>2017</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2017.07.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28826104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabatino</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunkel</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramkumar</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keeney</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jevsevar</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Excess opioid medication and variation in prescribing patterns following common orthopaedic procedures</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source><year>2018</year><volume>100</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.17.00672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29406338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6818977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lovecchio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Derman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stepan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iyer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christ</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimaldi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Support for Safer Opioid Prescribing Practices: a catalog of published use after orthopaedic surgery</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source><year>2017</year><volume>99</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>1945</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.17.00124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29135671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pace</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gannon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedland</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spurlin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of inpatient opioid consumption on persistent use following total knee arthroplasty</article-title><source>Reg Anesth Pain Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>46</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/rapm-2020-101582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33172905</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Brug</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelissen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lijfering</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Steenbergen</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosendaal</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Dorp</surname><given-names>ELA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Opioid prescribing patterns after arthroplasty of the knee and hip: a dutch nationwide cohort study from 2013 to 2018</article-title><source>Acta Orthop</source><year>2022</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>667</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2340/17453674.2022.3993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35848731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9327187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trasolini</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKnight</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorr</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Opioid Crisis and the Orthopedic Surgeon</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source><year>2018</year><volume>33</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>3379</fpage><lpage>82e1</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2018.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30075877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manjunath</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gualtieri</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fried</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarzkopf</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macaulay</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patient satisfaction after total hip arthroplasty is not influenced by reductions in Opioid Prescribing</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source><year>2021</year><volume>36</volume><issue>7S</issue><fpage>250</fpage><lpage>S7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2021.02.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33640183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ceuppens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dudi-Venkata</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beh</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedrikovetski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Feasibility study of an online modifiable enhanced recovery after surgery protocol with specific focus on opioid avoidance</article-title><source>ANZ J Surg</source><year>2020</year><volume>90</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1947</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ans.15976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32407004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahure</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waren</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lajam</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slover</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Utilization of a Novel opioid-sparing protocol in primary total hip arthroplasty results in reduced opiate consumption and Improved Functional Status</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source><year>2020</year><volume>35</volume><issue>6S</issue><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>S6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2020.02.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32139187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Helmerhorst</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindenhovius</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vrahas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ring</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kloen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Satisfaction with pain relief after operative treatment of an ankle fracture</article-title><source>Injury</source><year>2012</year><volume>43</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1958</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.injury.2012.08.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22901424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Questionnaire on the perceptions of patients about total knee replacement</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source><year>1998</year><volume>80</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.80B1.0800063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9460955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>EuroQol</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>EuroQol&#8211;a new facility for the measurement of health-related quality of life</article-title><source>Health Policy</source><year>1990</year><volume>16</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0168-8510(90)90421-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10109801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fatehi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ring</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Talking points for the safe and effective alleviation of pain</article-title><source>Bone Joint J</source><year>2020</year><volume>102&#8211;B</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1122</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.102B9.BJJ-2020-0091.R1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32862693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Devin</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armaghani</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bible</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shau</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Approach to pain management in chronic opioid users undergoing orthopaedic surgery</article-title><source>J Am Acad Orthop Surg</source><year>2014</year><volume>22</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>614</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5435/JAAOS-22-10-614</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25281256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postoperative opioid cessation rates based on preoperative opioid use: analysis of common orthopaedic procedures</article-title><source>Bone Joint J</source><year>2019</year><volume>101&#8211;B</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1570</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.101B12.BJJ-2019-0080.R2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31787005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cusano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halawi</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combating the opioid epidemic: experience with a single prescription for total joint arthroplasty</article-title><source>Arthroplast Today</source><year>2020</year><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>668</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.artd.2020.07.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32875017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7451889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saies</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pawar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vermeulen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pericapsular nerve group (PENG) block provides improved short-term analgesia compared with the femoral nerve block in hip fracture surgery: a single-center double-blinded randomized comparative trial</article-title><source>Reg Anesth Pain Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>46</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>398</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/rapm-2020-102315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33637625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lin DY, Morrison C, Brown B, Saies A, Pawar R, Vermeulen M et al. In reply to: &#8216;towards precision regional anesthesia: is the PENG block appropriate for all hip fracture surgeries?&#8216;.Reg Anesth Pain Med. 2021.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/rapm-2021-102926</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34158375</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>DBC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruddell</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akelman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Has a prescription-limiting Law in Rhode Island helped to Reduce Opioid Use after Total Joint Arthroplasty?</article-title><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>478</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CORR.0000000000000885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31389888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7438153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seitz</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janiszewski</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>GP</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tapscott</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Einstein</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluating opioid analgesic prescribing limits: a narrative review</article-title><source>Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</source><year>2022</year><volume>31</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>605</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pds.5425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35247021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9078148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What&#8217;s New in hip replacement</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source><year>2021</year><volume>103</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>1667</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.21.00612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34293773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayes</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dingmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bullard</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hopfer</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Binswanger</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Opioid use and storage patterns by patients after Hospital Discharge following surgery</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e0147972</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26824844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4732746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedberg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Livingston</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Otterloo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrating Public Health and Health Care Strategies to address the opioid epidemic: the Oregon Health Authority&#8217;s Opioid Initiative</article-title><source>J Public Health Manag Pract</source><year>2019</year><volume>25</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PHH.0000000000000849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30048336</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kehlet</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postoperative pain, analgesia, and recovery-bedfellows that cannot be ignored</article-title><source>Pain</source><year>2018</year><volume>159</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>S6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/j.pain.0000000000001243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30113942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindberg</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miaskowski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rustoen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aamodt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lerdal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preoperative risk factors associated with chronic pain profiles following total knee arthroplasty</article-title><source>Eur J Pain</source><year>2021</year><volume>25</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>680</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ejp.1703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33259681</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7986219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Getachew</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lerdal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smastuen</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gay</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aamodt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tesfaye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High levels of preoperative pain and fatigue are red flags for moderate-severe pain 12 months after total knee arthroplasty-A longitudinal cohort study</article-title><source>Musculoskelet Care</source><year>2021</year><volume>19</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/msc.1522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8247059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33085181</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beswick</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wylde</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gooberman-Hill</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dieppe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What proportion of patients report long-term pain after total hip or knee replacement for osteoarthritis? A systematic review of prospective studies in unselected patients</article-title><source>BMJ Open</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e000435</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2011-000435</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22357571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3289991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hejazi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McAllister</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Revisiting patient satisfaction following total knee arthroplasty: a longitudinal observational study</article-title><source>BMC Musculoskelet Disord</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>423</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12891-018-2340-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30497445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6267049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahlenberg</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krell</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessment of a satisfaction measure for Use after primary total joint arthroplasty</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source><year>2020</year><volume>35</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1792</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2020.02.039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32173615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross-Adjie</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monterosso</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bulsara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bowel management post major joint arthroplasty: results from a randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>Int J Orthop Trauma Nurs</source><year>2015</year><volume>19</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijotn.2014.04.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25846222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manchikanti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atluri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benyamin</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falco</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helm Ii</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Opioids in chronic noncancer pain: have we reached a boiling point yet?</article-title><source>Pain Physician</source><year>2014</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>E1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.36076/ppj.2014/17/E1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24452651</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagemeier</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Introduction to the opioid epidemic: the economic burden on the healthcare system and impact on quality of life</article-title><source>Am J Manag Care</source><year>2018</year><volume>24</volume><issue>10 Suppl</issue><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>S6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29851449</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Registry AOANJR. AOA PROMs Pilot Project: Final Report 2021 [Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://aoanjrr.sahmri.com/documents/10180/681914/AOANJRR+PROMs+Pilot+Final+Report">https://aoanjrr.sahmri.com/documents/10180/681914/AOANJRR+PROMs+Pilot+Final+Report</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>