<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">61</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcpcnc</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Pregnancy and Childbirth</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2393</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11549744</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11549744.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11549744</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11549744</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39516756</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12884-024-06882-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">6882</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Neighborhood socioeconomic status and postpartum depression among commercial health insurance enrollees: a retrospective cohort study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baser</surname><given-names initials="O">Onur</given-names></name><address><email>onur.baser@bogazici.edu.tr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Isenman</surname><given-names initials="L">Lauren</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baser</surname><given-names initials="E">Erdem</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="W">Wenjing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cigdem</surname><given-names initials="B">Burhan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03z9tma90</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.11220.30</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2253 9056</institution-id><institution>Department of Economics, </institution><institution>Bogazici University, </institution></institution-wrap>Istanbul, Turkey </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>School of Public Health, City University of New York, New York, NY 10027 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Columbia Data Analytics, 300 North 5th Ave., Suite 250, Ann Arbor, MI USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Mergen Analytics, Ankara, Turkey </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">452035</issue-id><elocation-id>732</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>08</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>09</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-11-14 06:25:35.803"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12884_2024_Article_6882.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Postpartum depression (PPD) is a prevalent psychological condition. Although the effect of obstetrical and maternal complications on PPD are well described, the impact of neighborhood socioeconomic status (SES) on PPD is relatively unexplored.</p></sec><sec><title>Objectives</title><p id="Par2">This study examined the relationship between neighborhood SES score and PPD.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par3">A summary SES measure for each U.S. zip code was constructed using income, education, and occupational 2021 Census data and linked to national commercial claims for 2017&#8211;2023. PPD status using diagnosis codes at outpatient and inpatient visits, and prescription drug use 3, 6, 9, and 12 months postpartum, were determined. Multivariate analysis controlled for potential confounders.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par4">PPD prevalence in commercial claims was 11.48%. Patients with PPD had higher rates of obstetrical (OR: 1.555, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001) and maternal complications (OR: 1.145, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001), and more lifestyle risk factors (OR: 1.113, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001). Comorbidity scores were higher for patients with PPD. Controlling for age and clinical factors, living in a disadvantaged neighborhood was associated with an increased incidence of PPD (OR: 1.137, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001).</p></sec><sec><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par5">Claims data may include potential inaccurate coding of diagnoses/procedures. Clinical information is limited to conditions and treatments defined by ICD-10-CM codes. Area-based SES measures inevitably misclassify people on both ends of the socioeconomic spectrum (this misclassification is random; direction of bias is known).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par6">The inverse and significant effect of area-based high SES on PPD rates demonstrates that preventive efforts may require interventions focusing on both the patient and the lived environment.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12884-024-06882-5.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Postpartum depression</kwd><kwd>Socioeconomic status</kwd><kwd>Maternal age</kwd><kwd>Lifestyle factors</kwd><kwd>Obstetric factors</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par10">Postpartum depression (PPD) is a major depressive episode that typically occurs within one to 12 months after childbirth and is a highly prevalent psychological condition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. A 2021 meta-analysis by Wang et al. found that 17.22% of postpartum women worldwide had experienced PPD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. </p><p id="Par11">Several risk factors are associated with PPD, including obstetric factors (gestational diabetes, cesarean section, multiple births), lifestyle factors (reduced sleep, poor diet), and maternal age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Measures of socioeconomic status (SES) relating to neighborhood are generally defined by educational attainment, income level, and employment status within areas of residence, and tend to play a large role in determining individual health outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. One neighborhood characteristic associated with low SES is limited accessibility to healthcare resources, which may elevate the risk of PPD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. </p><p id="Par12">Although economic segregation is growing in the U.S. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], the extent to which neighborhood characteristics are related to the incidence of PPD has not been established on a nationally representative scale. Previous studies analyzing this association have looked only at U.S. regional or state-level data or data from countries outside the U.S [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. </p><p id="Par13">The aim of this study is to investigate the effect of neighborhood SES score on PPD within 12 months postpartum among commercial health insurance enrollees. This study allows us to examine, for the first time, the association of SES score and PPD rates in the U.S. on a nationally representative scale.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par14">This retrospective cohort study is based on Kythera Labs data for the years 2017&#8211;2023. Kythera Labs data contain medical and pharmacy claims with 79% coverage of all U.S. patients. The data covers 310&#160;million patients, 6.1&#160;million practitioners, 1.6&#160;million organizations, and 1.4&#160;million facilities, generating at least 40&#160;billion healthcare claims [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The data contains both open claims and closed claims. The closed claims contain around 172&#160;million patients with commercial healthcare insurance, which is used for this study.</p><p id="Par15">Data included the unique de-identified numbers of patients, age, gender, types of insurance, zip codes, diagnostic codes according to the <italic toggle="yes">International Classification of Diseases</italic> (ICD-10), procedures, and medications. The details of the data have been published elsewhere, and the healthcare outcomes derived from these data were compared with other data sets for validity and consistency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. </p><p id="Par16">We identified women who delivered (ICD-10: O80-O84) during the identification period (January 2018&#8211;July 2022). The delivery date was designated as the index date. Patient claims were required to be in the data continuously for 12 months pre-index date (baseline period) and post-index date (follow-up period) (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). PPD is defined in 3-month intervals within a year as follows: (a) at least one PPD diagnosis (ICD-10: F53), (b) at least one depression diagnosis (ICD-10: F32, F33, F34, F38, F39, F41) or (c) at least one pharmacy claim for Zulresso (National Drug Code: 72152-547-20) within 12 months postpartum.</p><p id="Par17">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Study timeline</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e344" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12884_2024_6882_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par18">To distinguish new onset of depressive illness during the postpartum period from an ongoing episode, we excluded women with prenatal depression disorder during the baseline, using appropriate ICD-10 codes.</p><p id="Par19">We analyzed a set of demographic and clinical variables at baseline. Age was determined from the relevant field in the Kythera data and was categorized as &lt;&#8201;20, 21&#8211;24, 25&#8211;29, 30&#8211;34, and 35 years and older. Three different comorbidity indices were derived during the baseline period to control for differences in overall comorbidities between patients with and those without PPD: updated Charlson Comorbidity Index (CCI), Chronic Disease Score (CDS), and Elixhauser Index. The original CCI encompassed 19 categories of medical comorbidities that were identifiable within medical conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. The original index has since adopted several weights, some of which allow outpatient diagnoses to contribute to the score, and was translated to the updated ICD-10 codes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. CDS is an aggregate comorbidity measure based on current medication use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The score increases with the number of chronic diseases under treatment and the complexity of the treatment regimen. The Elixhauser Index is based on a comprehensive set of 30 ICD-9-CM comorbidity flags and has been updated to ICD-10 codes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Current coding for the index is available from the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality. It has been shown that using all these indexes improves the performance of the outcomes research models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Obstetrical and maternal complications as well as lifestyle factors were identified using appropriate ICD-10 codes (Appendix Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">A1</xref>).</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Socioeconomic status</title><p id="Par20">This study utilized a summary measure of SES for each U.S. zip code using data on income, education, and occupation from the five-year estimates for 2021 U.S. Census data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. These data are compiled over a period of five years to provide more reliable estimates, particularly for smaller geographic areas and smaller population subgroups. The five-year estimates typically cover a period of five calendar years leading up to the census year. For instance, the 2021 estimates would cover data collected from 2017 to 2021. The longer survey period allows for more accurate estimation of characteristics that may have low prevalence or fluctuate over time, such as certain demographic traits or socioeconomic indicators in small geographic areas. These five-year estimates are widely accepted and used by researchers, policymakers, businesses, and community organizations precisely because they offer a more comprehensive and statistically robust view of the population and its characteristics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. These estimates refer to statistical projections released by the Census Bureau every five years, covering various geographic, demographic, and socioeconomic factors. Using five-year estimates has two main advantages: it [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] provides a larger sample size for more credible data and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] considers trends over five years for a comprehensive perspective. We then linked this information to the enrollees&#8217; zip code of residence in the Kythera files. Previous research identified six variables by factor analysis of census block groups that could be meaningfully combined into a summary SES score [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. These variables include three measures of wealth/income (log of the median household income [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], log of the median value of housing units [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], and the percentage of household receiving interest, dividend, or net rental income [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]), two measures of education (the percentage of adults&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;25 years of age who had completed high school or the percentage of adults&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;25 years of age who had completed college) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], and one measure of occupation/employment (the percentage of employed persons&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;16 years of age in executive, managerial, or professional specialty occupations) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. The <italic toggle="yes">z</italic> score for each variable is calculated by subtracting the overall mean and dividing it by the standard deviation. For example, if the <italic toggle="yes">z</italic> score for zip code 10,013 for the median housing income is 5, the median housing income among the residents in that zip code is five standard deviations higher than the overall median of housing income in the U.S. The SES score was then constructed by summing the <italic toggle="yes">z</italic> scores for each of the six variables. Of the 33,774 zip code areas, 4,912 had missing data, with 4,161 having three or fewer missing variables. To address this, we applied the method of missing data imputation with grouping or stratification. We divided each variable into 10 tiers based on data set size and filled missing data using medians within each tier. After imputation, we combined the data with the existing population data, resulting in comprehensive information for 29,167 zip code areas. Summary SES scores ranged from &#8722;&#8201;10.6320 to 23.0279, with larger scores corresponding to greater socioeconomic disadvantage. Subjects were sorted according to summary SES scores and grouped in terciles. SES characteristics are shown in Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><p id="Par21">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of U.S. zip codes of commercially enrolled patients according to summary SES score tercile</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (Low)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (Middle)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (High)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>No. of patients</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">498,782</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">498,745</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">513,852</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Median SES summary score (range)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.16 (-10.63, 3.03)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.65 (3.03, 6.55)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.90 (6.55, 23.03)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Wealth/income</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Median household income ($)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50,895</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70,215</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">105,802</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Median value of housing unit ($)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">154,400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">250,300</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">465,000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Household with interest, dividend, or rental income (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Education</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Adult residents who completed at least high school (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92.30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Adult residents who completed at least college (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.90</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Employment</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Employed residents with management, professional, and related occupations (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.79</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>SES: socioeconomic status</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par22">Patients with PPD within 12 months and patients without PPD were analyzed descriptively by demographic factors, clinical factors, obstetrical complications, maternal comorbidities, and lifestyle risk factors within 12 months at baseline. Numbers and percentages were provided for the categorical variables; means and standard deviations were provided for continuous variables. Student&#8217;s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-tests and Pearson chi-square tests were used to test statistically significant differences between the two cohorts at the 5% level for continuous and categorical variables, respectively. Standardized differences were also calculated for each variable. We constructed a logistic regression model to predict the likelihood of PPD within 12 months postpartum for each SES score group (low, medium, and high).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec4" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p id="Par23">Of 1,565,789 commercial enrollees, a total of 179,728 (11.48%) PPD events occurred during the 12-month follow-up period after applying inclusion and exclusion criteria. Of the commercial cohort for whom SES score was categorized as unknown, 3.5% were not included in the descriptive and multivariate analysis. Around 45% of the PPD events occurred within 3 months, and 15% of the events occurred between 9 and 12 months. Approximately 21% of PPD events occurred between 3 and 6 months. Around 18% of PPD events occurred between 6 and 9 months (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par24">
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Timing of first PPD diagnosis during follow-up intervals within one year postpartum</p><p>PPD, postpartum depression</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e569" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12884_2024_6882_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par25">Among the commercial enrollees, 3.5% were excluded from the descriptive and multivariate analysis because their SES score was categorized as unknown. The distributions of each of the component SES-related variables according to tercile of the overall summary SES score are given in Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. For example, median household income in the zip code of residence increased in a linear fashion from $50,895 for patients in the lowest SES tercile to $105,802 for patients in the highest SES tercile; the percentage of adult residents who completed college increased from 19.20% in the lowest SES tercile to 56.90% in the highest; and the percentage of employed residents with management, professional, and related occupations increased from 29.04% in the lowest SES tercile to 56.79% in the highest.</p><p id="Par26">Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows a comprehensive summary of PPD rates and various demographic and clinical factors stratified by sSES score terciles. Without any risk adjustment, PPD rates are highest in the middle SES group and lowest in the high-SES group, suggesting an inverse relationship between SES and PPD rates. (12.1% vs. 10.18%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001). The data show a higher concentration of younger mothers (&#8804;&#8201;20 and 21&#8211;24 age groups) in the low-SES category compared to the high-SES category, which has a higher proportion of older mothers (30&#8211;34 and 35&#8201;+&#8201;age groups). The low-SES group has higher comorbidity scores, rates of obstetrical and maternal complications, as well as lifestyle risk factors, compared to the middle and high-SES groups.</p><p id="Par27">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Postpartum depression rates and summary of demographic and clinical factors by SES score tercile</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (Low)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (Middle)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (High)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>No. of patients</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">498,782</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">498,745</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">513,852</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;PPD rates</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.10%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.17%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.19%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Age group (y)</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;&#8804;&#8201;20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38,158</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23,366</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,036</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;21&#8211;24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87,709</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67,933</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43,025</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;25&#8211;29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">148,883</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">144,233</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">113,947</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;30&#8211;34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">139,094</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">162,238</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">194,450</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;35+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84,923</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100,969</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">149,382</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;ADI score</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">274,778</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22,337</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89,412</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Middle</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">148,660</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104,689</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">272,377</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;High</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73,645</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">385,097</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">135,429</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Comorbidity scores</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Charlson Comorbidity Index&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76,610</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58,294</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70,384</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Chronic Disease Score&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,620</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,845</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,945</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Elixhauser index&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46,671</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36,559</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38,749</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Baseline characteristics</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Obstetrical complications</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">379,566</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">367,287</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">382,511</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Maternal complications</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97,582</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88,821</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88,784</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Lifestyle risk factors</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76,830</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65,255</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62,358</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>PPD: postpartum depression; SES: socioeconomic status</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par28">Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> shows the obstetrical, maternal, and lifestyle risk factors among patients with and without PPD. Some of the most frequent comorbidities for PPD and non-PPD cohorts were other maternal diseases (60.16% vs. 45.26%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001) and abnormal findings (48.64% vs. 43.96%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001); pre-eclampsia or eclampsia comorbidities were significantly higher for the PPD cohort (14.30% vs. 10.23%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001).</p><p id="Par29">
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Obstetrical, maternal, and lifestyle risk factors among commercially insured patients with and without PPD measured within 12 months of delivery</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">PPD (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;173,416)</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Without PPD (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1,337,963)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;Value</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic>/Mean</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%/Std</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic>/Mean</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%/Std</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Obstetrical complications*</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Severe perineal laceration</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">358</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.21%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,692</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6474</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Postpartum hemorrhage</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,159</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.97%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30,850</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.31%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Puerperal sepsis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">440</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Infection of obstetric surgical wound</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">134</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">611</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Venous complication in puerperium</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">344</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,551</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.19%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4900</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Obstetric embolism</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">312</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,428</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.11%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Complication of anesthesia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">443</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.26%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,417</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Complication of the puerperium</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,545</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.77%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36,065</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.70%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Other maternal diseases</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104,334</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.16%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">605,531</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.26%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Cesarean section</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26,938</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.53%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">191,180</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.29%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Multiple births</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8387</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Preterm and low-birth-weight infants</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">519</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0584</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Abnormal findings</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84,353</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.64%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">588,145</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.96%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Postpartum anemia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,984</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.30%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25,155</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.88%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Negative birth experience</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7,066</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.07%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41,299</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.09%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Meconium passage</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">320</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,139</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.16%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0165</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Umbilical cord prolapse</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">195</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.11%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,343</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.10%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1380</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Prior history of abortion</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8,548</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.93%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63,218</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.72%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Prior history of ectopic pregnancy</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">562</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2665</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Prior history of hydatidiform mole</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">167</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1445</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Other obstetric trauma</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8,555</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.93%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51,700</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.86%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Premature rupture of membranes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,204</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.19%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89,956</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.72%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Placental disorders</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,338</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.96%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71,115</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.32%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Placenta previa</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8,257</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.76%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59,070</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.41%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Premature separation of the placenta</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,437</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.83%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8,436</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.63%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Maternal comorbidities **</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Preexisting hypertension</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,220</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.59%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31,297</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.34%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Gestational hypertension</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8,727</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.03%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46,351</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.46%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Pre-eclampsia or eclampsia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24,797</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.30%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">136,844</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.23%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Gestational diabetes mellitus</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,962</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.63%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">106,577</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.97%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Pre-existing diabetes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,212</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.28%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,967</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.04%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Lifestyle risk factors **</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Vitamin D deficiency</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,915</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.41%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45,699</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.42%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9194</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Obese and overweight</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23,003</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.26%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">129,271</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.66%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Sleep disorders</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,873</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.66%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9,689</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.72%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Lack of physical exercise</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">138</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3663</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Poor eating habits</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">145</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0058</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Vitamin B6 deficiency</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0055</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Smoking</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">855</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.49%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,684</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>PPD: postpartum depression; STD: standardized difference</p><p>* Measured 12 months prior to first date of PPD. For the no PPD group assign an end date (delivery&#8201;+&#8201;randomly between minimum of (PPD dates-delivery dates) and maximum of (PPD dates-delivery dates) rates from PPD group</p><p>** Measured 1 year prior to delivery</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par30">Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> shows baseline characteristics of women with and without PPD within 12 months. Increased age was associated with decreased PPD rates. Additionally, comorbidity indexes and individual comorbidities are higher in patients with PPD than in those without PPD. Without adjusting for age and comorbidities, there is an inverse relationship between SES and PPD since the SES score is significantly lower in patients with PPD than those without (4.87 vs. 5.23, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001).</p><p id="Par31">
<table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of women with and without PPD within 12 months of delivery</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>Age and comorbidity characteristics</bold>
</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">PPD (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;173,416)</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Without PPD (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1,337,963)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;Value</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Std. Diff.</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic>/Mean</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%/Std</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic>/Mean</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%/Std</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age group (y)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.69</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1233</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8804;&#8201;20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,414</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.01%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64,151</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.79%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0559</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21&#8211;24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26,526</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.30%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">172,146</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.87%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0719</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25&#8211;29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49,551</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.57%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">357,521</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.72%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0418</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30&#8211;34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53,193</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.67%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">442,599</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.08%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0513</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35+</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33,732</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.45%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">301,546</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.54%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0743</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Comorbidity scores</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Charlson Comorbidity Index&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,604</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.92%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7,471</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.56%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0475</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Chronic Disease Score&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33,324</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.22%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">171,937</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.85%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1861</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Elixhauser index&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20,577</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.87%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98,113</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.33%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1687</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>SES characteristics</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;SES score</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.87</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0834</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Median household income ($)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75,467</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30,338</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78,295</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32,527</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0876</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Median value of housing unit ($)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">312,677</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">227,555</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">352,525</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">258,991</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1559</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Household with interest, dividend, or rental income (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0369</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Adult residents who completed at least high school (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89.76</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.76</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89.45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0382</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Adult residents who completed at least college (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.88</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.93</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0978</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Employed residents with management, professional, and related occupation (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.54</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.77</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.36</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0859</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Baseline characteristics</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Baseline characteristics</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>N/Mean</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>%/Std</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>N/Mean</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>%/Std</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold>
<bold>Value</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Std. Diff.</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Obstetrical complications</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">143,011</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.47%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">986,353</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73.72%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2017</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Maternal complications</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38,248</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.06%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">236,939</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.71%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1127</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Lifestyle risk factors</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29,896</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.24%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">174,547</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.05%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1227</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>PPD: postpartum depression; SES: socioeconomic status; Std. Diff: standardized difference </p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par32">All variables contributing to SES score, including household and educational attainment values, demonstrate statistically significant differences between patients with and without PPD.</p><p id="Par33">Figure&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> shows that older ages have a significant inverse association with PPD. Both individual comorbidities and index values showed that PPD rates are higher with a higher number of comorbidities. Patients with PPD had higher rates of obstetrical (OR: 1.555, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001) and maternal complications (OR: 1.145, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001), and more lifestyle risk factors (OR: 1.113, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001). Comorbidity scores were higher for patients with PPD. After adjusting for age and comorbidities, the low-SES or medium-SES group had significantly higher odds of having PPD than the high-SES group (adjusted OR: 1.137, 95% CI: [1.124, 1.149], <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001).</p><p id="Par34">
<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Odds Ratio for PPD Among Commercial Enrollees</p><p>OR: odds ratio; PPD: postpartum depression; SES: socioeconomic status</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1849" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12884_2024_6882_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec5" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par35">Our study reveals a significant association between neighborhood SES and PPD diagnosis. These findings contribute to the growing body of literature examining the impact of neighborhood-level factors on perinatal mental health outcomes. To our knowledge, this study is the first to report the association of SES and PPD rates in national commercial health claims in the U.S. Some of the prior research on the association between high PPD rates and low SES showed an inverse relationship using national data outside the U.S., local U.S. data sets, surveys, clinical data, and meta-analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Wang and Geng [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] found that higher SES was associated with significantly improved physical health. Cai et al. concluded that increased educational attainment was correlated with a decreased risk of developing major depressive disorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. One study concluded that PPD prevalence was greater in Palestine than in higher-income countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Another found that mothers with four characteristics related to decreased SES (low-income, unmarried, unemployed, and less than a college degree) were at 11 times greater risk of developing increased depressive symptoms 3 months postpartum than women without characteristics of decreased SES [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Some of the previous research, however, showed a more tenuous association between depression and SES [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. In a meta-analysis, Lorant showed that only 5 out of 11 specific studies showed a higher prevalence in the lower-SES group [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Mirotznik also showed such inconclusive results for depression, suggesting inequalities in depression should be further investigated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Our findings indicate that, on a national scale, one&#8217;s neighborhood of residence contributes to the risk of PPD. We found a consistent inverse relationship between PPD and SES score. Therefore, excluding SES as a risk factor in any outcome research studies might result in omitted variable bias and therefore bias the effect of exposure variables on outcomes.</p><p id="Par36">Our findings demonstrating a negative association between SES scores and PPD in national commercial claims data also align with those of a recent study conducted in Northern California [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. The cross-sectional study, which included 122,995 postpartum individuals, indicated that higher neighborhood disadvantage was correlated with increased PPD risk, with significant racial and ethnic variations. Specifically, Black individuals exhibited the highest overall risk, while Hispanic individuals showed no significant association between neighborhood disadvantage and PPD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. A study by Giurgescu et al. also found that women living in neighborhoods with higher deprivation had increased odds of postpartum depressive symptoms, even after controlling for individual-level factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Similarly, Meltzer-Brody et al. (2018) reported that neighborhood-level poverty was associated with increased risk of PPD diagnosis in a large cohort study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Several mechanisms may explain the link between neighborhood SES and PPD. Low-SES neighborhoods often have limited access to mental health services, support groups, and other resources crucial for maternal well-being [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Living in disadvantaged neighborhoods can expose women to chronic stressors such as crime, noise, and poor housing conditions, potentially exacerbating postpartum mental health issues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Neighborhood disadvantage may correlate with reduced social cohesion and support networks, which are protective factors against PPD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Poor neighborhood infrastructure, lack of green spaces, and limited recreational facilities may contribute to social isolation and reduced physical activity, both risk factors for PPD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. </p><p id="Par37">The prevalence of PPD in our study was 11.48%, which is higher than the previously reported estimates published in 2014, indicating 7% among privately insured women and 13% among women with Medicaid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Although PPD remains underreported, several factors may contribute to this observed increase. Increased awareness of PPD has likely made healthcare providers more vigilant in screening for and diagnosing the condition, resulting in higher reported prevalence rates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Improved access to mental health services, including the adoption of telemedicine, may have also facilitated the diagnosis and reporting of PPD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Additionally, changes in insurance coverage, particularly those associated with the Affordable Care Act, may have enhanced access to postpartum care and mental health services [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Economic uncertainties and social isolation, such as those experienced during the COVID-19 pandemic, have likely elevated stress levels among new mothers, thereby contributing to higher rates of PPD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. </p><p id="Par38">Past research has also shown that obstetric factors, lifestyle factors, and maternal age are associated with PPD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. The results showed that maternal age is inversely associated with PPD. Comorbidities, including obstetrical complications and lifestyle factors, were generally associated with an increased risk for PPD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. </p><p id="Par39">The results also demonstrated that the percentage of PPD events occurring within 12 months was highest from 0 to 3 months and continuously decreased from 3 to 12 months. This finding is consistent with previous literature, which found that most PPD events happen within 0 to 3 months postpartum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><sec id="Sec6"><title>Sensitivity analysis</title><p id="Par40">To enhance our understanding of the relationship between PPD rates and SES we conducted two distinct sensitivity analyses. These analyses aimed to address potential confounding factors and to provide a more comprehensive assessment of the SES-PPD association. First, the authors acknowledge that the initial analysis period (2017&#8211;2023) encompassed the peak years of the COVID-19 pandemic, which may have significantly impacted mental health outcomes, healthcare delivery, and socioeconomic disparities. To account for this potential confounder, we excluded deliveries from 2019 to 2021 and re-estimated the PPD rates. In this adjusted analysis, each SES tercile comprised approximately 177,000 patients. The PPD rate for the lowest SES tercile was 11.98%, compared to 10.03% for the highest tercile. After adjusting for age and comorbidities, we found that women in the low-SES or medium-SES groups had significantly higher odds of experiencing PPD compared to those in the high-SES group (adjusted OR: 1.14, 95% CI: [1.117, 1.16], <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001). Notably, these estimates remained consistent to two decimal places with our primary analysis. Secondly, to capture a more nuanced understanding of the relationship between neighborhood characteristics and PPD prevalence, we employed the Neighborhood Deprivation Index (NDI) as an alternative measure of socioeconomic conditions. The NDI is a composite score that incorporates multiple indicators of deprivation, including income, education, employment, and housing conditions, allowing for a more comprehensive comparison of relative deprivation across different geographic areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. In this analysis, each NDI tercile contained approximately 500,000 patients. The PPD rate for the lowest (most deprived) tercile was 13.82%, compared to 9.61%% for the highest (least deprived) tercile. After adjusting for age and comorbidities, findings again indicated that women in the low-SES or medium-SES groups had significantly higher odds of experiencing PPD compared to those in the high-SES group (adjusted OR: 1.02, 95% CI: [1.01, 1.04], <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.01). These sensitivity analyses corroborate our primary findings, demonstrating the robustness of the observed association between socioeconomic disadvantage and increased PPD risk, even when accounting for potential pandemic-related confounders and utilizing alternative measures of neighborhood socioeconomic status.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par41">These findings may have limited generalizability due to the exclusion of Medicaid deliveries, which comprise approximately 40% of all deliveries in the U.S. This exclusion is particularly significant given that the SES of individuals covered by Medicaid tends to be systematically lower than that of those with private insurance. Moreover, this study was conducted using data exclusively from the U.S. healthcare system and population. While this provides valuable insights into PPD prevalence and its association with neighborhood socioeconomic status within the U.S. context, it is important to note that these findings may not be directly applicable to other countries or regions.</p><p id="Par42">Both SES and mental health care are heavily influenced by racial factors in the U.S. However, this study does not include a discussion on race due to the absence of a race variable in the Kythera dataset, limiting our ability to explore racial disparities in the findings.</p><p id="Par43">This study has several limitations related to the use of administrative datasets, which may be subject to inaccurate coding of patient clinical diagnoses and procedures, as well as clinical information limited to conditions and treatments defined by ICD-10-CM codes. Since the analysis was based on the review of claims data that were not originally designed for research, some information is bound to be missing. However, we were able to control for a number of important patient risk factors, including age, several comorbidity indexes, and individual comorbidities specific to PPD. This analysis focused on PPD diagnoses rather than PPD itself due to the limitations of the administrative data. It is well-documented that PPD is notoriously underdiagnosed, and literature suggests that this underdiagnosis occurs along SES lines. These findings pertain to diagnosed cases of PPD, and we acknowledge that the true prevalence of PPD may be higher and influenced by various socioeconomic factors.</p><p id="Par44">Another potential limitation of this study is related to the use of area-based measures. Ideally, we would have been able to assess both individual and area-based socioeconomic measures, because using area-based measures alone inevitably misclassifies people within areas on both ends of the socioeconomic spectrum. This misclassification is random, and the direction of bias is known [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. If area-based SES shows a disparity, the effect will likely be larger when one includes individual-based SES. One advantage of area-based measurements is their ability to incorporate contextual information pertaining to various elements that impact all individuals within a certain area, such as the geographical positioning and standard of public amenities such as hospitals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Our estimates would also be better if they were based on more granular area-based scores such as census tracts rather than zip codes, since the former were designed to produce socioeconomically similar groupings. However, numerous studies have consistently indicated that employing zip code&#8211;level metrics yields comparable yet more conservative estimations of socioeconomic gradients in health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par45">Socioeconomic disadvantage is unequivocally associated with higher rates of PPD in the U.S. This relationship underscores the necessity for comprehensive interventions that address not only the individual patient&#8217;s needs but also the broader socioeconomic environment in which they reside. Effective prevention and management of PPD should therefore incorporate strategies that improve both healthcare access and the overall quality of life in disadvantaged neighborhoods.</p><sec id="Sec9"><title>Implications for policy and practice</title><p id="Par46">Based on U.S. commercial health claims, a mother&#8217;s SES contributes to the risk of PPD, after controlling for age and comorbidities. To accurately assess the effect of exposure variables on outcomes, SES should be included as a risk factor for PPD. Effective preventive interventions might focus on the patient&#8217;s lived environment including SES, as well as individual physical risk factors like age and comorbidities.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12884_2024_6882_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#8217;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank Amy Endrizal and Michael Moriarty for assistance in editing the manuscript.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>O.B. provided the supervision, conceptualization, methodology, validation, and visualization of the research and participated in the writing process from the original draft preparation to the reviewing and editing of the manuscript. L.I. participated in the project management, supervision, methodology, analysis, investigation of the literature review and the writing process from the original draft preparation to the reviewing and editing of the manuscript. E.B., W.L., and B.C. participated in the investigation of the data, methodology, software, validation, analysis, and data curation.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This research received no external funding.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from Kythera Labs but restrictions apply to the availability of these data, which were used under license for the current study, and so are not publicly available. Data are however available from Kythera Labs upon request and licensing agreement (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.kytheralabs.com/">https://www.kytheralabs.com/</ext-link>).</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par48">The raw dataset on which this study is based is available through a commercial data licensing agreement with Kythera labs. Kythera data has been expertly determined by Datavant&#8217;s Privacy Hub (Mirador) to comply with statistical de-identification required by HIPAA and associated regulations. The analysis of de-identified, publicly available data does not constitute human subjects research as defined by US Department of Health and Human Services 45 CFR 46.102 and does not require IRB review. The study was conducted in accordance with the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></notes><notes id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par49">This study utilized deidentified data. The analysis of de-identified, publicly available data does not constitute human subjects research as defined by US Department of Health and Human Services 45 CFR 46.102. As such, consent for publication is not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar5" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par50">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wang Z, Liu J, Shuai H, Cai Z, Fu X, Liu Y et al. Mapping global prevalence of depression among postpartum women. Transl Psychiatry. 2021;11(1).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41398-021-01663-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8528847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34671011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehendale</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors of postpartum depression</article-title><source>Cureus</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e30898</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36465774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.30898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9711915</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Agrawal I, Mehendale AM, Malhotra R. Risk factors of postpartum depression. Cureus. 2022;14(10):e30898.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36465774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.30898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9711915</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Falana</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postpartum depression: are you listening?</article-title><source>Nurs Clin North Am</source><year>2019</year><volume>54</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>561</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cnur.2019.07.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31703781</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Falana SD, Carrington JM. Postpartum depression: are you listening? Nurs Clin North Am. 2019;54(4):561&#8211;7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31703781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cnur.2019.07.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qandil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jabr</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collin</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postpartum depression in the occupied Palestinian territory: a longitudinal study in bethlehem</article-title><source>BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>375</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12884-016-1155-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27887649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5124263</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Qandil S, Jabr S, Wagler S, Collin SM. Postpartum depression in the occupied Palestinian territory: a longitudinal study in bethlehem. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2016;16(1):375.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27887649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12884-016-1155-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5124263</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gjerdingen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crow</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGovern</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Center</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in depressive symptoms over 0&#8211;9 months postpartum</article-title><source>J Womens Health (Larchmt)</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/jwh.2010.2355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21351876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3058896</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Gjerdingen D, Crow S, McGovern P, Miner M, Center B. Changes in depressive symptoms over 0&#8211;9 months postpartum. J Womens Health (Larchmt). 2011;20(3):381&#8211;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21351876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/jwh.2010.2355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3058896</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolbier</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rush</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahadeo</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaffer</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Community Child Health Network I. relationships of race and socioeconomic status to postpartum depressive symptoms in rural African American and non-hispanic white women</article-title><source>Maternal Child Health J</source><year>2013</year><volume>17</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1277</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10995-012-1123-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3584227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22961387</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Dolbier CL, Rush TE, Sahadeo LS, Shaffer ML, Thorp J. The Community Child Health Network I. relationships of race and socioeconomic status to postpartum depressive symptoms in rural African American and non-hispanic white women. Maternal Child Health J. 2013;17(7):1277&#8211;87.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10995-012-1123-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3584227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22961387</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goyal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How much does low socioeconomic status increase the risk of prenatal and postpartum depressive symptoms in first-time mothers?</article-title><source>Womens Health Issu</source><year>2010</year><volume>20</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.whi.2009.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2835803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20133153</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Goyal D, Gay C, Lee KA. How much does low socioeconomic status increase the risk of prenatal and postpartum depressive symptoms in first-time mothers? Womens Health Issu. 2010;20(2):96&#8211;104.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.whi.2009.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2835803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20133153</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guintivano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manuck</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meltzer-Brody</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predictors of postpartum depression: a comprehensive review of the last decade of evidence</article-title><source>Clin Obstet Gynecol</source><year>2018</year><volume>61</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>591</fpage><lpage>603</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/GRF.0000000000000368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29596076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6059965</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Guintivano J, Manuck T, Meltzer-Brody S. Predictors of postpartum depression: a comprehensive review of the last decade of evidence. Clin Obstet Gynecol. 2018;61(3):591&#8211;603.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29596076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/GRF.0000000000000368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6059965</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belouali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raja</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kharrazi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing the racial and socioeconomic disparities in postpartum depression using population-level hospital discharge data: longitudinal retrospective study</article-title><source>JMIR Pediatr Parent</source><year>2022</year><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e38879</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/38879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36103575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9623466</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Liu S, Ding X, Belouali A, Bai H, Raja K, Kharrazi H. Assessing the racial and socioeconomic disparities in postpartum depression using population-level hospital discharge data: longitudinal retrospective study. JMIR Pediatr Parent. 2022;5(4):e38879.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36103575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2196/38879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9623466</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zlotnick</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tzilos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seifer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stout</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Randomized controlled trial to prevent postpartum depression in mothers on public assistance</article-title><source>J Affect Disord</source><year>2016</year><volume>189</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2015.09.059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26454186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4641029</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Zlotnick C, Tzilos G, Miller I, Seifer R, Stout R. Randomized controlled trial to prevent postpartum depression in mothers on public assistance. J Affect Disord. 2016;189:263&#8211;8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26454186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jad.2015.09.059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4641029</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaedrahmati</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kazemi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kheirabadi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebrahimi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahrami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postpartum depression risk factors: a narrative review</article-title><source>J Educ Health Promot</source><year>2017</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>60</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jehp.jehp_9_16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28852652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5561681</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Ghaedrahmati M, Kazemi A, Kheirabadi G, Ebrahimi A, Bahrami M. Postpartum depression risk factors: a narrative review. J Educ Health Promot. 2017;6:60.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28852652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/jehp.jehp_9_16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5561681</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coxe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fennie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madhivanan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trepka</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antenatal stressful life events and postpartum depressive symptoms in the United States: the role of women&#8217;s socioeconomic status indices at the state level</article-title><source>J Womens Health (Larchmt)</source><year>2017</year><volume>26</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/jwh.2016.5872</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27875058</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Mukherjee S, Coxe S, Fennie K, Madhivanan P, Trepka MJ. Antenatal stressful life events and postpartum depressive symptoms in the United States: the role of women&#8217;s socioeconomic status indices at the state level. J Womens Health (Larchmt). 2017;26(3):276&#8211;85.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27875058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/jwh.2016.5872</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fairthorne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanley</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oberlander</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Depressed women of low socioeconomic status have high numbers of physician visits in the year before pregnancy: implications for care</article-title><source>J Clin Med Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>516</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14740/jocmr3377w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29707094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5916541</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Fairthorne J, Hanley GE, Oberlander TF. Depressed women of low socioeconomic status have high numbers of physician visits in the year before pregnancy: implications for care. J Clin Med Res. 2018;10(6):516&#8211;22.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29707094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14740/jocmr3377w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5916541</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantwell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The classification of perinatal mood disorders&#8212;suggestions for dsmv and icd11</article-title><source>Arch Women&#8217;s Ment Health</source><year>2010</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00737-009-0122-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20127452</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Jones I, Cantwell R. The classification of perinatal mood disorders&#8212;suggestions for dsmv and icd11. Arch Women&#8217;s Ment Health. 2010;13(1):33&#8211;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20127452</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00737-009-0122-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossick</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossick</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callegari</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katon</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experiences of racism and postpartum depression symptoms, care-seeking, and diagnosis</article-title><source>Arch Women&#8217;s Ment Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>25</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>717</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00737-022-01232-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35504987</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Bossick AS, Bossick NR, Callegari LS, Carey CM, Johnson H, Katon JG. Experiences of racism and postpartum depression symptoms, care-seeking, and diagnosis. Arch Women&#8217;s Ment Health. 2022;25(4):717&#8211;27.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35504987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00737-022-01232-w</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galea</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Population health in an era of rising income inequality: USA, 1980&#8211;2015</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2017</year><volume>389</volume><issue>10077</issue><fpage>1475</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(17)30571-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28402829</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Bor J, Cohen GH, Galea S. Population health in an era of rising income inequality: USA, 1980&#8211;2015. Lancet. 2017;389(10077):1475&#8211;90.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28402829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(17)30571-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kythera Labs. 2022. cited 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.kytheralabs.com/Accessed9/12/2023">https://www.kytheralabs.com/Accessed9/12/2023</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Baser O SG, Yapar N, Baser E, Mete F. Use of open claims vs closed claims in health outcomes research. JHEOR. 2023;10(2):44&#8211;52.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.36469/001c.87538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10484335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37692913</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glasheen</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cordier</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gumpina</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haugh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Renda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Charlson comorbidity index: Icd-9 update and icd-10 translation</article-title><source>Am Health Drug Benefits</source><year>2019</year><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31428236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6684052</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Glasheen WP, Cordier T, Gumpina R, Haugh G, Davis J, Renda A. Charlson comorbidity index: Icd-9 update and icd-10 translation. Am Health Drug Benefits. 2019;12(4):188&#8211;97.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31428236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6684052</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buist</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fishman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chronic disease score as a predictor of hospitalization</article-title><source>Epidemiology</source><year>2002</year><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00001648-200205000-00016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11964937</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Putnam KG, Buist DS, Fishman P, Andrade SE, Boles M, Chase GA, et al. Chronic disease score as a predictor of hospitalization. Epidemiology. 2002;13(3):340&#8211;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11964937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00001648-200205000-00016</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sura</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Senagore</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adapting the elixhauser comorbidity index for cancer patients</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>2018</year><volume>124</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2018</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cncr.31269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29390174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5910176</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Mehta HB, Sura SD, Adhikari D, Andersen CR, Williams SB, Senagore AJ, et al. Adapting the elixhauser comorbidity index for cancer patients. Cancer. 2018;124(9):2018&#8211;25.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29390174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cncr.31269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5910176</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephenson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The estimation power of alternative comorbidity indices</article-title><source>Value Health</source><year>2008</year><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>946</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1524-4733.2008.00343.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18489502</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Baser O, Palmer L, Stephenson J. The estimation power of alternative comorbidity indices. Value Health. 2008;11(5):946&#8211;55.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18489502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1524-4733.2008.00343.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">United States Census Bureau. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.census.gov/Accessed9/12/2023">https://www.census.gov/Accessed9/12/2023</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Snow MS. Delivering what users want: the evolution of census bureau small area data. US Census Bureau; 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>AVD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merkin</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnett</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chambless</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Massing</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nieto</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neighborhood of residence and incidence of coronary heart disease</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>345</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM200107123450205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11450679</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Roux AVD, Merkin SS, Arnett D, Chambless L, Massing M, Nieto FJ, et al. Neighborhood of residence and incidence of coronary heart disease. N Engl J Med. 2001;345(2):99&#8211;106.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11450679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJM200107123450205</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">United States Census Bureau. Income in the past 12 months (in 2021 inflation-adjusted dollars). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.census.gov/table?q=Median+Income&amp;g=010XX00US,$8600000&amp;tid=ACSST5Y2021.S1901">https://data.census.gov/table?q=Median+Income&amp;g=010XX00US,$8600000&amp;tid=ACSST5Y2021.S1901</ext-link> Accessed 9/12/2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">United States Census Bureau. Selected housing characteristics. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.census.gov/table?q=housing+value&amp;">https://data.census.gov/table?q=housing+value&amp;</ext-link>g=010XX00US,$8600000&amp;tid=ACSDP5Y2021.DP04 Accessed 9/12/2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">United States Census Bureau. Interest, dividends, or net rental income in the past 12 months for households. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.census.gov/table?q=interest,+dividend,+or+rental+income+in+household&amp;g=010XX00US,$8600000&amp;tid=ACSDT5Y2021.B19054">https://data.census.gov/table?q=interest,+dividend,+or+rental+income+in+household&amp;g=010XX00US,$8600000&amp;tid=ACSDT5Y2021.B19054</ext-link> Accessed 9/12/2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">United States Census Bureau. Selected population profile in the united states. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.census.gov/table?q=occupations+&amp;t=Educational+Attainment&amp;">https://data.census.gov/table?q=occupations+&amp;t=Educational+Attainment&amp;</ext-link>g=010XX00US,$8600000&amp;tid=ACSSPP1Y2021.S0201 Accessed 9/12/2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wang J, Geng L. Effects of socioeconomic status on physical and psychological health: Lifestyle as a mediator. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2019;16(2).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph16020281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6352250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30669511</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Socioeconomic status, individual behaviors and risk for mental disorders: a mendelian randomization study</article-title><source>Eur Psychiatry</source><year>2022</year><volume>65</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e28</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/j.eurpsy.2022.18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35431011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9158396</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Cai J, Wei Z, Chen M, He L, Wang H, Li M, et al. Socioeconomic status, individual behaviors and risk for mental disorders: a mendelian randomization study. Eur Psychiatry. 2022;65(1):e28.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35431011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1192/j.eurpsy.2022.18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9158396</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorant</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deli&#232;ge</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Philippot</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ansseau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Socioeconomic inequalities in depression: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Am J Epidemiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>157</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwf182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12522017</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Lorant V, Deli&#232;ge D, Eaton W, Robert A, Philippot P, Ansseau M. Socioeconomic inequalities in depression: a meta-analysis. Am J Epidemiol. 2003;157(2):98&#8211;112.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12522017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/aje/kwf182</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mirotznik J. Epidemiological findings on selected psychiatric disorders in the general population. Adversity, stress, and psychopathology. 1998:235&#8201;&#8211;&#8201;84.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Onyewuenyi</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaritsky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>MLR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pettway</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quesenberry</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neighborhood disadvantage, race and ethnicity, and postpartum depression</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2023</year><volume>6</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>e2342398</fpage><lpage>e</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.42398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37955900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10644210</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Onyewuenyi TL, Peterman K, Zaritsky E, Weintraub MLR, Pettway BL, Quesenberry CP, et al. Neighborhood disadvantage, race and ethnicity, and postpartum depression. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6(11):e2342398&#8211;e.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37955900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.42398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10644210</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giurgescu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slaughter-Acey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dove-Medows</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neighborhoods, racism, stress, and preterm birth among African American women: a review</article-title><source>West J Nurs Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>44</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/01939459211041165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34455864</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Giurgescu C, Misra D, Slaughter-Acey J, Gillespie S, Nowak A, Dove-Medows E, et al. Neighborhoods, racism, stress, and preterm birth among African American women: a review. West J Nurs Res. 2022;44(1):101&#8211;10.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34455864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/01939459211041165</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meltzer-Brody</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergink</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vigod</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munk-Olsen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Postpartum psychiatric disorders</article-title><source>Nat Reviews Disease Primers</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrdp.2018.22</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29695824</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Meltzer-Brody S, Howard LM, Bergink V, Vigod S, Jones I, Munk-Olsen T, et al. Postpartum psychiatric disorders. Nat Reviews Disease Primers. 2018;4(1):1&#8211;18.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrdp.2018.22</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29695824</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozhimannil</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trinacty</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huskamp</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Racial and ethnic disparities in postpartum depression care among low-income women</article-title><source>Psychiatr Serv</source><year>2011</year><volume>62</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>619</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/ps.62.6.pss6206_0619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21632730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3733216</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Kozhimannil KB, Trinacty CM, Busch AB, Huskamp HA, Adams AS. Racial and ethnic disparities in postpartum depression care among low-income women. Psychiatr Serv. 2011;62(6):619&#8211;25.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21632730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1176/appi.ps.62.6.619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3733216</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Campo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stergiopoulos</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nir</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Misir</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>How did a housing first intervention improve health and social outcomes among homeless adults with mental illness in toronto? Two-year outcomes from a randomised trial</article-title><source>BMJ open</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>e010581</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27619826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5030577</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">O&#8217;Campo P, Stergiopoulos V, Nir P, Levy M, Misir V, Chum A, et al. How did a housing first intervention improve health and social outcomes among homeless adults with mental illness in toronto? Two-year outcomes from a randomised trial. BMJ open. 2016;6(9):e010581.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27619826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5030577</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Surkan</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trachtenberg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKinlay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellinger</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuropsychological function in children with blood lead levels&#8201;&lt;&#8201;10 &#181;g/dl</article-title><source>Neurotoxicology</source><year>2007</year><volume>28</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1170</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuro.2007.07.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17868887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2276844</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Surkan PJ, Zhang A, Trachtenberg F, Daniel DB, McKinlay S, Bellinger DC. Neuropsychological function in children with blood lead levels&#8201;&lt;&#8201;10 &#181;g/dl. Neurotoxicology. 2007;28(6):1170&#8211;7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17868887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.neuro.2007.07.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2276844</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kendig</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors predicting health services use among older people in China: an analysis of the China health and retirement longitudinal study 2013</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12913-016-1307-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26892677</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4758158</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Gong CH, Kendig H, He X. Factors predicting health services use among older people in China: an analysis of the China health and retirement longitudinal study 2013. BMC Health Serv Res. 2016;16:1&#8211;16.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26892677</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12913-016-1307-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4758158</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis of postpartum depression and timing and types of treatment received differ for women with private and medicaid coverage</article-title><source>Womens Health Issu</source><year>2018</year><volume>28</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>524</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.whi.2018.08.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30314906</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Sherman LJ, Ali MM. Diagnosis of postpartum depression and timing and types of treatment received differ for women with private and medicaid coverage. Womens Health Issu. 2018;28(6):524&#8211;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.whi.2018.08.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30314906</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postpartum depression</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2002</year><volume>287</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>762</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.287.6.762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11851544</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Miller LJ. Postpartum depression. JAMA. 2002;287(6):762&#8211;5.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11851544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.287.6.762</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wassef</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wassef</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Telemedicine in perinatal mental health: perspectives</article-title><source>J Psychosom Obstet Gynaecol</source><year>2022</year><volume>43</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0167482X.2021.2024162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34989294</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Wassef A, Wassef E. Telemedicine in perinatal mental health: perspectives. J Psychosom Obstet Gynaecol. 2022;43(2):224&#8211;7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34989294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/0167482X.2021.2024162</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effectiveness of telemedicine interventions on women with postpartum depression: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Worldviews Evidence&#8208;Based Nurs</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/wvn.12576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35349219</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Liu X, Huang S, Hu Y, Wang G. The effectiveness of telemedicine interventions on women with postpartum depression: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Worldviews Evidence&#8208;Based Nurs. 2022;19(3):175&#8211;90.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/wvn.12576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35349219</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perraillon</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leiferman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Battaglia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrato</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of the affordable care act on women&#8217;s postpartum insurance and depression in 5 states that did not expand medicaid, 2012&#8211;2015</article-title><source>Med Care</source><year>2022</year><volume>60</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MLR.0000000000001652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34670222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8811754</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Schuster AL, Perraillon MC, Paul JJ, Leiferman JA, Battaglia C, Morrato EH. The effect of the affordable care act on women&#8217;s postpartum insurance and depression in 5 states that did not expand medicaid, 2012&#8211;2015. Med Care. 2022;60(1):22&#8211;8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34670222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MLR.0000000000001652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8811754</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waschmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gievers</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hildebrand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating the impact of the covid-19 pandemic on postpartum depression</article-title><source>J Womens Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>31</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>772</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/jwh.2021.0428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35394366</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Waschmann M, Rosen K, Gievers L, Hildebrand A, Laird A, Khaki S. Evaluating the impact of the covid-19 pandemic on postpartum depression. J Womens Health. 2022;31(6):772&#8211;8.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/jwh.2021.0428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35394366</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Purrington</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastert</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madhav</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snider</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruterbusch</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of area-level socioeconomic disadvantage in racial disparities in cancer incidence in metropolitan detroit</article-title><source>Cancer Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>14623</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cam4.6065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37184135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10358249</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Purrington KS, Hastert TA, Madhav KC, Nair M, Snider N, Ruterbusch JJ, et al. The role of area-level socioeconomic disadvantage in racial disparities in cancer incidence in metropolitan detroit. Cancer Med. 2023;12(13):14623&#8211;35.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37184135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cam4.6065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10358249</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehkopf</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waterman</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparing individual-and area-based socioeconomic measures for the surveillance of health disparities: a multilevel analysis of massachusetts births, 1989&#8211;1991</article-title><source>Am J Epidemiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>164</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>823</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwj313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16968866</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Subramanian S, Chen JT, Rehkopf DH, Waterman PD, Krieger N. Comparing individual-and area-based socioeconomic measures for the surveillance of health disparities: a multilevel analysis of massachusetts births, 1989&#8211;1991. Am J Epidemiol. 2006;164(9):823&#8211;34.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16968866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/aje/kwj313</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waterman</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehkopf</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Painting a truer picture of us socioeconomic and racial/ethnic health inequalities: the public health disparities geocoding project</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source><year>2005</year><volume>95</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>312</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2003.032482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15671470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1449172</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Krieger N, Chen JT, Waterman PD, Rehkopf DH, Subramanian S. Painting a truer picture of us socioeconomic and racial/ethnic health inequalities: the public health disparities geocoding project. Am J Public Health. 2005;95(2):312&#8211;23.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15671470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2105/AJPH.2003.032482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1449172</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>