<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Crit Illn Inj Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Crit Illn Inj Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1647</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ijcritill</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJCIIS</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Int J Crit Illn Inj Sci</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Critical Illness and Injury Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2229-5151</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2231-5004</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer -- Medknow Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10664035</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10664035.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10664035</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10664035</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38023581</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijciis.ijciis_14_23</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJCIIS-13-118</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>What is the right gentamicin dose for multiple trauma patients? A Monte Carlo simulation exploration study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names initials="MY">Mohammad Yaseen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiwattanawongsa</surname><given-names initials="K">Kamonthip</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaijamorn</surname><given-names initials="W">Weerachai</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charoensareerat</surname><given-names initials="T">Taniya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doungngern</surname><given-names initials="T">Thitima</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Department of Clinical Pharmacy, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Prince Songkla University, Hat Yai, Songkhla, Thailand</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>1</label>Department of Pharmacy Practice, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Chulalongkorn University, Pathum Wan, Bangkok, Thailand</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>2</label>Faculty of Pharmacy, Siam University, Bangwa, Pasicharoen, Bangkok, Thailand</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Prof. Thitima Doungngern, Department of Clinical Pharmacy, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Prince Songkla University, Hat Yai, 90112 Songkhla, Thailand. E-mail: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="dthitima@pharmacy.psu.ac.th">dthitima@pharmacy.psu.ac.th</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jul-Sep</season><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">449582</issue-id><fpage>118</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-01-28 11:25:10.250"><day>28</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#169; 2023 International Journal of Critical Illness and Injury Science</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncsalicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access journal, and articles are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as appropriate credit is given and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="IJCIIS-13-118.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><sec><title>Background:</title><p>The appropriate dose of gentamicin is important to prevent and treat infections. The study aimed to determine the optimal dose of gentamicin to achieve the probability of pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic (PK) targets for efficacy and safety in multiple trauma patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>PK parameters of gentamicin in multiple trauma patients were gathered to develop a one-compartment PK model for prediction. The Monte Carlo simulation method was performed. The 24-h area under the concentration time curve to the minimum inhibitory concentration ratio (AUC24h/MIC) &#8805;50 was defined for the infection prevention target. AUC24h/MIC &#8805;110 or the maximum serum concentration to MIC ratio &#8805;8&#8211;10 was for the treatment of serious Gram-negative infection target. The risk of nephrotoxicity was the minimum serum concentration &#8805;2 mg/L. The optimal dose of gentamicin was determined when the efficacy target was &gt;90% and the risk of nephrotoxicity was lowest.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>The optimal gentamicin dose to prevent infection when the MIC was &lt;1 mg/L was 6&#8211;7 mg/kg/day. A higher dose of gentamicin up to 10 mg/kg/day could not reach the target for treating serious Gram-negative infection when the expected MIC was &#8805;1 mg/L. The probability of nephrotoxicity was minimal at 0.2&#8211;4% with gentamicin doses of 5&#8211;10 mg/kg/day for 3 days.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions:</title><p>Once daily gentamicin doses of 6&#8211;7 mg/kg are recommended to prevent infections in patients with multiple trauma. Gentamicin monotherapy could not be recommended for serious infections. Further clinical studies are required to confirm our results.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Gentamicin</kwd><kwd>multiple trauma</kwd><kwd>pharmacodynamics</kwd><kwd>pharmacokinetics</kwd><kwd>surgical site infection</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Surgical site infections (SSIs) have been reported as high as 50% in trauma patients with Gustilo-Anderson Type-III open bone fractures.[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] Contaminated traumatic wounds can lead to nonunion of bone, osteomyelitis, and life-threatening complications, including sepsis.[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] Therefore, early antibiotic prophylaxis is strongly recommended for preventing complications from infection.[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] The Eastern Association for the Surgery of Trauma recommends a combination of cefazolin and gentamicin in trauma patients with type II and III open fractures.[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] This combination showed to reduce the rate of SSIs following the injury.[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] In addition, the rates of nonunion, death, and re-hospitalization at 1-year post-injury in patients were lower with patients with type III open fractures.[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</p><p>Following the injury, traumatized patients may develop a systemic inflammatory response syndrome causing elevated cardiac output and enhanced renal perfusion that augment renal clearance (ARC). The incidence of ARC in trauma patients was reported as high as 85% and is more common in younger patients (age &lt; 50 years) with fewer comorbidities. The ARC usually resolved after 1 week of injury.[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] Due to pathophysiologic changes resulting from injury, it can increase the clearance of medications eliminated renally, like gentamicin. In general, gentamicin is a hydrophilic drug with a small volume of distribution (Vd) and its clearance (CL) is proportional to the glomerular-filtration rate.[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] However, the Vd and CL of gentamicin in multiple trauma patients were found to be greater than the healthy adult population.[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] Because the bactericidal effect of gentamicin is concentration-dependent,[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] it is challenging to maintain the pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic (PK/PD) target in patients with severe trauma.</p><p>The recommended PK/PD target of gentamicin for treating of infections is the maximum serum concentration to MIC ratio (Cmax/MIC) of &#8805;8&#8211;10.[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] Recently, the 24-h area under the concentration time curve (AUC24h) to the MIC ratio target of &#8805;110 is also recommended because it showed a good predictor to improve clinical outcomes in patients with a serious bacterial infection when gentamicin was used as monotherapy.[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] To optimize the efficacy of gentamicin therapy for serious Gram-negative infections, we therefore chose the Cmax/MIC ratio &#8805;8&#8211;10 or AUC24 h/MIC ratio &#8805; 110 as the targets for the treatment of serious infections in critically ill trauma patients. However, the target of gentamicin therapy for SSIs prevention after the injury has not been fully clarified. <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> study revealed that the in AUC24h/MIC ~30&#8211;50 demonstrated bacteriostatic activity.[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] Therefore, the AUC24h/MIC &#8805;50 was considered for a PK/PD target to prevent SSIs or treat SSIs in a situation of low bacterial load with the effective irrigation and debridement to control a source of infection. In this study, we aimed to determine the optimal dosage regimen for gentamicin to achieve the PK/PD targets for the treatment and prevention of infection, and the risk of nephrotoxicity in critically ill multiple trauma patients using Monte Carlo simulation (MCS). We focused on achieving the PK/PD targets on the acute phase of injury, the first 72 h after a traumatic event and surgery.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>METHODS</title><sec><title>Search strategy</title><p>The following Medical Subject Heading terms as follows: &#8220;gentamicin or aminoglycoside&#8221; AND &#8220;PK&#8221; AND &#8220;trauma&#8221; and synonymous words were used to search in PubMed, EMBASE and EBSCO. All original publications that were entered into the databases by September 2022 were included, and the search was limited to the human and English language study. In addition, we examined the secondary references available online and included them if they were eligible.</p></sec><sec><title>Study selection and data extraction</title><p>The studies were included if they were the traditional PK studies of gentamicin and conducted in critically ill multiple trauma adult patients admitted to trauma or intensive care units who received gentamicin intravenously. The following studies were excluded: (1) Population PKs, (2) received extracorporeal membrane oxygenation or renal replacement therapy, (3) pregnancy, and (4) burn. Two researchers (AMY and TD) independently reviewed and assessed the studies for possible inclusion. The Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-analyses (PRISMA) guideline was followed for data extraction. Disagreement between the two independent investigators was resolved by discussions with a third independent researcher (WC).</p><p>Gentamicin PK parameters (i.e., Vd, CL, and Ke) were extracted and pooled for use as the input parameters for the MCS. Other extracted data included patient demographic data (i.e. age, body weight and/or dosing weight, severity of injury/illness, and renal function), and number of patients in the study,</p></sec><sec><title>Monte Carlo simulations and pharmacodynamic target</title><p>The one-compartment PK model (Equation 1) was developed to assess gentamicin disposition for the first 72 h of therapy initiation.</p><p>
<inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="IJCIIS-13-118-g001.jpg"/>
</p><p>Where D is the gentamicin dose (mg/kg), TBW is the total body weight (kg), Ke is the elimination rate constant (h<sup>&#8722;1</sup>), t is the infusion time (h), T is the dosing interval (h), and CL is Clearance (L/h).</p><p>In this MCS, we assumed a minimum body weight of 40 kg for the virtual adult population. A standard gentamicin dose of 5&#8211;7 mg/kg/day and a higher dose of 8&#8211;10 mg/kg/day were used in the simulation. We created concentration-time profiles for 10,000 virtual subjects using Crystal Ball, Oracle software.[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] According to the European Committee on Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing,[<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] different MIC breakpoints for resistance of 0.5, 1, 2, and 4 mg/L were used to represent coagulase-negative staphylococci, <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic>. In this study, we selected AUC24h/MIC &#8805;50 as the PK/PD target for the prevention of infection and AUC24h/MIC &#8805;110 or Cmax/MIC &#8805;8&#8211;10 were selected for the treatment of serious Gram-negative infections. Cmax was determined at the end of infusion, and the Cmin was determined at the time 24-h after initiation of therapy (prior to the next dose). The AUC24h for each day was calculated using the trapezoidal formula for each virtual individual. The AUC24h &gt;700 mg &#215; h/L,[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] or Cmin &#8805;2 mg/L[<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] in all virtual subjects after 3 days of treatment was assessed for possible nephrotoxicity. After running the MCS, we calculated the probability of target attainment (PTA) using PK/PD targets, as previously mentioned. The optimal dose of gentamicin was determined when the PTA reached at least 90% with the lowest risk of nephrotoxicity.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>The study selection process is shown in <xref rid="ijciis.ijciis_14_23-f001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. After eliminating the duplication, 377 records were screened by two independent investigators. Eighty-six records were eligible for full-text article assessment. Four PK studies of gentamicin in trauma patients were found as shown in <xref rid="ijciis.ijciis_14_23-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] As this study focused on the alteration of the PKs after serious injury, we therefore excluded the studies of a critically ill patients that involved &lt;50% of trauma patients and/or the studies that we were unable to verify the severity of injuries. Thus, we further removed two studies because one study was conducted in a mixed group of critically ill sepsis patients that included only 15.6% of trauma patients[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and another study of patients admitted to the trauma unit without reporting the severity of the injury.[<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] As a result, two traditional PK studies of gentamicin in 50 patients with severe multiple trauma admitted to the intensive care units were finally included for the MCS.[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] Assessments and analysis of risk of bias, heterogeneity, and publication bias were not performed because the small number of studies and sample sizes was included.</p><fig position="float" id="ijciis.ijciis_14_23-f001" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Study selection process</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJCIIS-13-118-g002.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="ijciis.ijciis_14_23-t001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Pharmacokinetic parameters of gentamicin in multiple trauma patients*</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vd (L/kg)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CL (L/h)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ke (1/h)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Townsend et al., 1989[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38&#177;0.10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.38&#177;2.76</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple trauma, blunt injuries <italic toggle="yes">indication</italic>: Documented infection <italic toggle="yes">trauma score</italic>: 11.7&#177;3.6 age (years), range: 16&#8211;92</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangha et al., 1995[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47&#177;0.14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18&#177;0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple trauma with grade II&#8211;III open fractures <italic toggle="yes">indication</italic>: Prophylactic therapy <italic toggle="yes">APACHE II score, range</italic>: 6&#8211;18 age (years), range: 18&#8211;70</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40&#177;0.10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19&#177;0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple trauma with Grade II&#8211;III open fractures indication: Prophylactic therapy APACHE II score, range: 6&#8211;19 age (years), range: 18&#8211;39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finnell et al., 1998[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28&#177;0.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26&#177;0.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple trauma admitted to trauma unit <italic toggle="yes">indication</italic>: Documented infection (60%), empiric treatment (18%), and preemptive for orthopedic procedures (22%) <italic toggle="yes">severity of injury</italic>: NA age (years) 43.0&#177;15.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gonclaves-pereira et al., 2010[<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41 (0.36&#8211;0.46)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42 (2.68&#8211;4.73)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 (0.1&#8211;0.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Critically ill medical (62.5%), surgical (18.8%), trauma (15.6%), and neurosurgery (3.1%) patients <italic toggle="yes">indication</italic>: <italic toggle="yes">Sepsis</italic>: 8 (4&#8211;11) <italic toggle="yes">median age</italic> (years): 68 (48&#8211;79)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*Data presents in mean&#177;SD or median IQR. IQR: Interquartile range, APACHE II: Acute physiology and chronic health evaluation, CL: Clearance, Ke: Elimination rate constant, NA: Not available, SOFA: Sequential organ failure assessment, Vd: Volume of distribution, SD: Standard deviation</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Most gentamicin concentrations were reported at the first treatment dose. Patient characteristics and PK parameters are shown in <xref rid="ijciis.ijciis_14_23-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The pooled mean &#177; SD (lower, upper range) of Vd, CL, and Ke of gentamicin used for the MCS was 0.39 &#177; 0.10 (0.05, 1) L/kg, 7.38 &#177; 2.76 (0.5, 13) L/h, and 0.19 &#177; 0.08 (0.5, 0.55) h<sup>-1</sup>, respectively. The body weight used in this study was 71.5 &#177; 16.4 kg.</p><sec><title>Probability for efficacy</title><p>Simulated Cmax, Cmin, and AUC24h of gentamicin using a standard dose (5&#8211;7 mg/kg/day) and a high-dose regimen (8&#8211;10 mg/kg/day) are presented in <xref rid="ijciis.ijciis_14_23-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Cmax, Cmin, and AUC24h values increased slightly on day 3 compared to day 1 of treatment.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="ijciis.ijciis_14_23-t002" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Simulation generated pharmacokinetic parameters* of once-daily gentamicin treatment in multiple trauma patients on day 1 (0&#8211;24 h) and day 3 (48&#8211;72 h)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Gentamicin dose (mg/kg/day)</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Day 1</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Day 3</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cmax (mg/L)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cmin (mg/L)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC24h (mg&#183;h/L)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cmax (mg/L)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cmin (mg/L)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC24h (mg&#183;h/L)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3&#177;6.8 (0.9&#8211;72.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25&#177;0.28 (0&#8211;2.78)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.9&#177;24.6 (12.5&#8211;255.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6&#177;6.7 (1.3&#8211;72.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27&#177;0.32 (0&#8211;3.30)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.5&#177;25.5 (16.7&#8211;256.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3&#177;8.1 (1.5&#8211;117.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31&#177;0.34 (0&#8211;3.17)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.2&#177;29.8 (18.5&#8211;97.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6&#177;8 (2.0&#8211;117.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34&#177;0.40 (0&#8211;4.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.4&#177;31 (18.9&#8211;309.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5&#177;9.6 (1.3&#8211;102.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35&#177;0.37 (0&#8211;3.58)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.2&#177;35.0 (17.6&#8211;346.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8&#177;9.5 (1.8&#8211;102.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38&#177;0.45 (0&#8211;4.41)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.8&#177;36.2 (23.4&#8211;348.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.3&#177;10.7 (1.9&#8211;150.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39&#177;0.44 (0&#8211;4.36)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.4&#177;38.8 (23.4&#8211;412.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7&#177;10.6 (2.5&#8211;153.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43&#177;0.51 (0&#8211;5.48)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.6&#177;40.2 (25.2&#8211;412.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.7&#177;12.2 (2.0&#8211;159.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45&#177;0.49 (0&#8211;4.84)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.9&#177;45.0 (25.7&#8211;493.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1&#177;12.0 (2.6&#8211;163.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49&#177;0.58 (0&#8211;6.67)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.6&#177;46.5 (29.4&#8211;529.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3&#177;13.4 (1.9&#8211;176.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49&#177;0.52 (0&#8211;4.22)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110.4&#177;48.7 (25.3&#8211;473.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8&#177;13.3 (2.5&#8211;176.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53&#177;0.61 (0&#8211;5.22)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115.5&#177;50.1 (33.1&#8211;477.9)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*Data present in mean&#177;SD (range).AUC24h: Area under 24-h time curve, Cmax: Maximum plasma concentration, Cmin: Minimum plasma concentration, SD: Standard deviation</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>At the MIC of 0.5 mg/L, all study gentamicin doses attained &gt;95% of the prophylactic target (AUC24h/MIC &#8805;50) on the 1<sup>st</sup> day of treatment [<xref rid="ijciis.ijciis_14_23-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>]. However, when the MIC increased to 1 mg/L, only 8 to 10 mg/kg/day of gentamicin achieved a prophylactic target of more than 90% on day 3 of treatment. When the MIC was &#8805;2 mg/L, approximately 30%&#8211;50% of virtual patients achieved the prophylactic target. &lt;5% of virtual patients achieved the target for the treatment of serious infections (AUC24h/MIC &#8805;110), and none succeeded when the MIC was 4 mg/L.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="ijciis.ijciis_14_23-t003" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Percent probability of prefer AUC24h/MIC target attainment by minimum inhibition concentration among simulated multiple trauma patients on day 1 and day 3 of treatment</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="5">Gentamicin.dose (mg/kg/day)</th><th align="center" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Percentage probabilities of prefer AUC24h/MIC in target</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="8" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Day 1 (0&#8211;24 h)</th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Day 3 (48&#8211;72 h)</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;30</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;50</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;80</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;110</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;30</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;50</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;80</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;110</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prefer MIC 0.5 mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preferred MIC 1 mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preferred MIC 2 mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preferred MIC 4 mg/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>AUC24h: Area under 24-h time curve, MIC, Minimum inhibition concentration</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>At the MIC of 0.5 mg/L, the minimum gentamicin doses attaining a Cmax/MIC &#8805;8 and &#8805;10 for more than 90% were 6 and 7 mg/kg/day, respectively [<xref rid="ijciis.ijciis_14_23-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>]. However, at the MIC &#8805;1 mg/L, no study gentamicin doses achieved a Cmax/MIC &#8805;10 for more than 90%.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="ijciis.ijciis_14_23-t004" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Percent probability of prefer Cmax/MIC target attainment by minimum inhibition concentration among simulated multiple trauma patients on day 1 and day 3 of treatment</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="5">Gentamicin dose (mg/kg/day)</th><th align="center" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Percentage probabilities of Cmax/MIC in target</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="8" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">MIC 0.5 mg/L</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">MIC 1 mg/L</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">MIC 2 mg/L</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">MIC 4 mg/L</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;8</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;10</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;8</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;10</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;8</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;10</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;8</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;10</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 1 (0&#8211;24 h)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 3 (48&#8211;72 h)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Cmax: Maximum plasma concentration, MIC: Minimum inhibition concentration</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Risk of nephrotoxicity</title><p>The risk of nephrotoxicity predicted on Cmin &#8805;2 mg/L was low [<xref rid="ijciis.ijciis_14_23-t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>]. &lt;10% of virtual patients had Cmin &gt;1 mg/L. The risk of nephrotoxicity doubled after 3 days of treatment compared with the initial therapy. None of the virtual patients had a AUC24h &gt;700 mg&#183;h/L.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="ijciis.ijciis_14_23-t005" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Percent probability of nephrotoxicity among simulated multiple trauma patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Gentamicin doses (mg/kg/day)</th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Percentage probabilities of nephrotoxicity</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Day 1 (0&#8211;24 h)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Day 3 (48&#8211;72 h)</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cmin &#8805;2 mg/L</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cmin &gt;1 mg/L</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cmin &#8805;2 mg/L</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cmin &gt;1 mg/L</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.95</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.57</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.90</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.57</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.41</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.89</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.86</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.50</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Cmin: Minimum plasma concentration</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>It has been well accepted that early antibiotic prophylaxis and control of infectious sources are important in preventing SSIs in critically ill trauma patients.[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] Gentamicin in combination with cefazolin have been shown to reduce SSIs in patients with type II and type III open fractures.[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] Although, the use of gentamicin for antibiotic prophylaxis in type III open fracture is less popular due to concerns about the risk of nephrotoxicity.[<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] Proper dose selection and close monitoring may optimize the efficacy and safety of gentamicin treatment.</p><p>This is the first study to use two different PK/PD targets, Cmax/MIC ratio and AUC24h/MIC ratio, to optimize gentamicin dosage regimen for the treatment and prevention of infections in critically ill multiple trauma patients. The bactericidal activity of gentamicin depends on its plasma concentration. The AUC24h/MIC ratio ~30 to 50 and ~100 demonstrated bacteriostatic effect and bacterial killing effect of 1&#8211;2 log<sub>10</sub>, respectively.[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] Smith <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] reported that an AUC24h/MIC ratio &#8805;110 significantly improved the clinical cure in patients with serious Gram-negative bacterial infections. Thus, in this study, we chose the AUC24h/MIC &#8805;110 or Cmax/MIC &#8805;8&#8211;10 as the therapeutic targets for serious Gram-negative infections. The AUC24h/MIC &#8805;50 was also chose as the target for prophylaxis. We also considered the AUC24h/MIC &lt;30 to indicate a high risk of treatment failure.</p><p>Changes in the PK parameters of gentamicin in patients with multiple traumas can affect its efficacy. Compared to the healthy volunteers (Vd of 0.2&#8211;0.3 L/kg), the greater Vd was observed in multiple trauma patients in the early phase of injury.[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] Sangha <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] reported the Vd of gentamicin following traumatic events as high as 0.47 &#177; 0.14 L/kg. Whereas, Townsend <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] conducted a PK study on gentamicin in blunt trauma patients and found a slightly smaller Vd of 0.38 &#177; 0.10 L/kg, but approximately 51% (19/37) of patients were started on aminoglycosides therapy after 5 days of traumatic events. Moreover, in their study also separately reported the Vd of gentamicin in patients with an isolated closed head injury who had a less global tissue injury and less aggressive fluid resuscitation which found to be close to the healthy population (Vd 0.27 &#177; 0.04 L/kg).[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] Larger Vd of gentamicin also reported in all types of critically ill patients.[<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] The increase in Vd in multiple trauma patients may be attributed to various reasons, such as early phase of injury, severity of injury, physiological response due to inflammation, and fluid resuscitation.[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] Moreover, gentamicin CL in multiple trauma patients (7.38 &#177; 2.76 L/h) was also faster than the CL in a general adult population (ranged from 4.31 to 5.12 L/h/70 kg).[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] A population PK study conducted by Barletta <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] using nonlinear mixed effect models in critically ill trauma patients also revealed a slightly lower gentamicin CL (5.47 L/h) and Vd (0.3 L/kg). The patient in that study was in postresuscitation phase.[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] Rapid gentamicin CL may be associated with the ARC during the early stage of injury.[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</p><p>To protect against highly susceptible pathogens (MIC &#8804;0.5 mg/L), our simulations in multiple trauma patients showed that gentamicin 5 mg/kg/day was sufficient to achieve a prophylactic target of AUC24h/MIC &#8805;50 for &gt;90%. However, when the MIC increased to 1 mg/L, the PTA decreased to 51.8%. More importantly, approximately 10% of virtual patients using gentamicin 5 mg/kg/day were at risk of treatment failure (AUC24h/MIC &lt;30). If the dose of gentamicin increased to 6 and 7 mg/kg/day, the chances of treatment failure were reduced to 4% and 1.5%, respectively. Sorger <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] conducted a study in patients with grade II or grade III open fractures and found that gentamicin 6 mg/kg once daily had a lower SSI infection rate, compared to gentamicin 5 mg/kg in two divided doses (6.7% vs. 13.6%, respectively).[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] Gentamicin once daily dosing revealed to have the better response than the multiple dosing regimen. In addition, Redfern <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] found that cefazolin plus gentamicin 7 mg/kg/day or a renally adjusted dose not only reduced the rate of SSIs after 30 days, but also reduced the incidence of non-union, death, and re-hospitalization at 1 year post-injury. The clinical outcomes of gentamicin and cefazolin used were similar to those of the piperacillin/tazobactam regimen for type III open fracture antibiotic prophylaxis.[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] Thus, in situations with a low incidence of gentamicin resistance, gentamicin doses of 6&#8211;7 mg/kg/day in combination with cefazolin and wound irrigation and debridement should be considered to prevent infection in trauma patients with fractures. In addition, other factors that may enhance the risk of infections such as hyperglycemia, shock, blood transfusion and hypothermia should be closely monitored and controlled to reduce the SSI.[<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</p><p>Our study found that if the MIC was &#8805;1 mg/L, all studied doses of gentamicin were insufficient to attain the PK/PD targets for the treatment of serious infection. A higher dose of 8&#8211;10 mg/kg/day of gentamicin can be used for the treatment if the MIC was &lt;1 mg/L. In addition to AUC24h/MIC and Cmax/MIC, the French guidelines also recommend maintaining the Cmax target from 30 to 40 mg/L after the 1<sup>st</sup> day for the treatment of serious Gram-negative infections.[<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] Our simulation found only 1.8 to 6.8% of standard gentamicin dose of 5 to 7 mg/kg/day reached the Cmax &#8805;30 mg/L target, and a high dose of 10 mg/kg/day of gentamicin could reach target for only 17.8%. Therefore, gentamicin may not be an appropriate choice for multiple trauma patients as a monotherapy to treat serious Gram-negative infections.</p><p>High doses of gentamicin should be initiated cautiously in multiple trauma patients, and close monitoring of its efficacy and safety is required. Since AUC-based monitoring requires two blood samples, one taken after the end of gentamicin infusion and another taken between 6 and 22 h post-infusion,[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] our finding, therefore, is helpful for guiding the dose of gentamicin in multiple trauma patients. We simulated gentamicin plasma concentrations for 3 days during the early phase after injury because it was estimated that by day 3 of treatment, the wounds should have shown themselves whether they were infected or not and the culture results would be available. If the culture results reveal Gram-negative pathogens sensitive to gentamicin with a high MIC, an alternative antibiotic option must be considered.</p><p>Gentamicin administered once daily showed less nephrotoxicity than multiple daily doses. Rybak <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] reported that AUC24h was a good predictor of nephrotoxicity in patients receiving gentamicin once-daily dosing for at least 72 h. They reported that the risk of nephrotoxicity increased when the AUC24h daily exposure was &gt;700 mg &#215; h/L.[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] The risk of nephrotoxicity is also significantly lower when Cmin &lt;2 mg/L than when Cmin &#8805;2 mg/L.[<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] However, a Cmin &lt;1 mg/L has been recommended in clinical practice to minimize nephrotoxicity.[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] Therefore, we selected these two parameters to predict gentamicin-induced nephrotoxicity. Our simulations revealed that once-daily gentamicin dosing of 5 to 10 mg/kg had a minimal risk of nephrotoxicity (Cmin &#8805;2 mg/L), ranging from 2.2% to 4% on day 3 of treatment. No AUC24h value was &gt;700 mg &#215; h/L. Similar to the study in open fracture patients with normal baseline renal function (eGFR &gt;60 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup>), the incidence of gentamicin-induced nephrotoxicity using the RIFLE criteria was 4%.[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] Whereas Oliveira <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] reported an incidence of gentamicin-induced nephrotoxicity, defined as a decrease in estimated glomerular-infiltration rate of &gt;20% from baseline, which was as high as 60% in patients admitted to a clinical-surgical intensive care unit. However, they included patients with impaired renal function (eGFR &#8805;30 mL/min/1.73 m<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) at baseline in their study.[<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] Therefore, the risk of gentamicin-induced nephrotoxicity is low if gentamicin is administered to trauma patients with normal baseline renal function. Gentamicin is avoided in patients at risk of nephrotoxicity, such as those aged &gt;60 years, hypotension, receiving iodinated contrast, and concomitant use of nephrotoxic drugs.[<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</p><p>This study has some limitations. First, we predicted gentamicin concentrations based on 50 critically ill trauma patients from two studies; therefore, the inter- or intra-patient variability in pathophysiological conditions could not be excluded. The dosing recommendation for gentamicin should be utilized in patients with similar characteristics or PK profiles. Our result may not apply if the patient has significant changes in PK parameters within the first 72 h of injury. Second, the risk of publication bias and heterogeneity test could not be excluded. Third, total body weight was utilized for dose estimation; therefore, the recommended optimal doses cannot be applied to ideal body weight or the adjusted body weight of gentamicin dosing. Finally, our study predicted the gentamicin concentrations based on the PK parameters during the acute phase after injury. If clinicians plan to continue treatment for more than 3 days, efficacy and toxicity should be closely monitored.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>Once daily gentamicin dose of 6&#8211;7 mg/kg/day was adequate to attain the PK/PD target for preventing infection with a minimum risk for nephrotoxicity in multiple trauma patients when the expected MIC was &lt;1 mg/L. However, a high dose of gentamicin of up to 10 mg/kg/day did not reach the target for treating serious Gram-negative bacterial infections if the MIC was &#8805;1 mg/L. Therefore, gentamicin should not be recommended as monotherapy for empiric or documented therapy of Gram-negative bacteria in patients with multiple traumas.</p><sec><title>Research quality and ethics statement</title><p>This study did not require approval by the Institutional Review Board/Ethics Committee as it relies only on publicly available data. The systematic review portion was not registered with PROSPERO. The authors followed the applicable EQUATOR Network (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.equator-network.org/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.equator-network.org/</ext-link>) guidelines, specifically the PRISMA guideline, during the conduct of this research project.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-statement"><title>Financial support and sponsorship</title><p>This research was funded by a scholarship under Thailand&#8217;s Education Hub for ASEAN Countries (TEH-AC), Graduate School, and partially by the Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Prince of Songkla University, Hat Yai, Thailand.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>We would like to thank Assistant Professor Dr. Sutthiporn Pattharachayakul and Associate Professor Dr. Wibul Wongpoowarak for their valuable comments on this manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajkumari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A study on surgical site infections after trauma surgeries in a tertiary care hospital in North India</article-title><source>Indian J Med Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25579155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4311327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Isaac</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danial</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mourkus</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibiotic prophylaxis in adults with open tibial fractures:What is the evidence for duration of administration?A systematic review</article-title><source>J Foot Ankle Surg</source><year>2016</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26364701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.jfas.2015.07.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mabvuure</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hindocha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current concepts of prophylactic antibiotics in trauma:A review</article-title><source>Open Orthop J</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23248721</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2174/1874325001206010511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3522105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early prevention of trauma-related infection/sepsis</article-title><source>Mil Med Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>33</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27833759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s40779-016-0104-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5101695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Enninghorst</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peralta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshino</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pape</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Physiological assessment of the polytrauma patient:Initial and secondary surgeries</article-title><source>Eur J Trauma Emerg Surg</source><year>2011</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>559</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26815466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00068-011-0161-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoff</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonadies</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cachecho</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorlac</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>East practice management guidelines work group:Update to practice management guidelines for prophylactic antibiotic use in open fractures</article-title><source>J Trauma</source><year>2011</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21610369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/TA.0b013e31820930e5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coccolini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rausa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montori</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fugazzola</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ceresoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sartelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for infections in trauma patients</article-title><source>Curr Trauma Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>91</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sorger</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruhnke</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjornson</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cockrin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Once daily, high dose versus divided, low dose gentamicin for open fractures</article-title><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00003086-199909000-00026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10627736</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Redfern</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wasilko</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Groth</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McMillian</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>CS</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Surgical site infections in patients with type 3 open fractures:Comparing antibiotic prophylaxis with cefazolin plus gentamicin versus piperacillin/tazobactam</article-title><source>J Orthop Trauma</source><year>2016</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26825490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/BOT.0000000000000554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hobbs</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shea</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Implications of augmented renal clearance on drug dosing in critically Ill patients:A focus on antibiotics</article-title><source>Pharmacotherapy</source><year>2015</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1063</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26598098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/phar.1653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdul-Aziz</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alffenaar</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bassetti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bracht</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimopoulos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marriott</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial therapeutic drug monitoring in critically ill adult patients:A position paper</article-title><source>Intensive Care Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>1127</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32383061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00134-020-06050-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7223855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aminoglycoside pharmacokinetics:Dosage requirements and nephrotoxicity in trauma patients</article-title><source>Crit Care Med</source><year>1989</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2914447</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sangha</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyagawa</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Healy</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjornson</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetics of once-daily dosing of gentamicin in surgical intensive care unit patients with open fractures</article-title><source>Ann Pharmacother</source><year>1995</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7756706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/106002809502900201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Finnell</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cropp</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ensom</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validation of the Hartford nomogram in trauma surgery patients</article-title><source>Ann Pharmacother</source><year>1998</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9562135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1345/aph.17243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bland</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pai</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lodise</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reappraisal of contemporary pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic principles for informing aminoglycoside dosing</article-title><source>Pharmacotherapy</source><year>2018</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>1229</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30403305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/phar.2193</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimizing aminoglycoside use</article-title><source>Crit Care Clin</source><year>2011</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21144989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ccc.2010.11.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="book" publication-format="print"><collab>Oracle Corporation</collab><article-title>Oracle Crystal Ball Classroom Edition</article-title><comment>Version 11.1.2.4</comment><publisher-loc>Redwood Shores, CA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oracle Corporation</publisher-name><year>2021</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage" publication-format="web"><collab>European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases</collab><source>The European Committee on Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing. Breakpoint tables for Interpretation of MICs and Zone Diameters. Version 13.0</source><year>2023</year><comment>Available from: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.eucast.org">http://www.eucast.org</uri></comment><date-in-citation>[Last accessed on 2023 Jan 20]</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rybak</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abate</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruffing</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lerner</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drusano</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prospective evaluation of the effect of an aminoglycoside dosing regimen on rates of observed nephrotoxicity and ototoxicity</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>1999</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>1549</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10390201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/aac.43.7.1549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC89322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shigemi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takesue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A meta-analysis of the target trough concentration of gentamicin and amikacin for reducing the risk of nephrotoxicity</article-title><source>J Infect Chemother</source><year>2021</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33077364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jiac.2020.09.033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gon&#231;alves-Pereira</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>P&#243;voa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetics of gentamicin in critically ill patients:Pilot study evaluating the first dose</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2010</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1258</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19832713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2009.03074.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goulet</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cicalo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Machado-Aranda</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Napolitano</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence-based protocol for prophylactic antibiotics in open fractures:Improved antibiotic stewardship with no increase in infection rates</article-title><source>J Trauma Acute Care Surg</source><year>2014</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25159242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/TA.0000000000000398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ballow</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Booker</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schentag</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of aztreonam and tobramycin in hospitalized patients</article-title><source>Clin Ther</source><year>2001</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1231</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11558860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0149-2918(01)80103-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hodiamont</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Broek</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Vroom</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prins</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Math&#244;t</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Hest</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical pharmacokinetics of gentamicin in various patient populations and consequences for optimal dosing for gram-negative infections:An updated review</article-title><source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source><year>2022</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>1075</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35754071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40262-022-01143-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9349143</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barletta</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nix</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nix</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erstad</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Population pharmacokinetics of aminoglycosides in critically ill trauma patients on once-daily regimens</article-title><source>J Trauma</source><year>2000</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>869</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11086778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00005373-200011000-00013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Augmented renal clearance in critical illness:An important consideration in drug dosing</article-title><source>Pharmaceutics</source><year>2017</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>36</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28926966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/pharmaceutics9030036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5620577</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><collab>French health products safety agency</collab><article-title>Update on good use of injectable aminoglycosides, gentamycin, tobramycin, netilmycin, amikacin. Pharmacological properties, indications, dosage, and mode of administration, treatment monitoring</article-title><source>Med Mal Infect</source><year>2012</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22770656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.medmal.2011.07.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheadle</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for surgical site infection</article-title><source>Surg Infect (Larchmt)</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><fpage>S7</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16834549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/sur.2006.7.s1-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pannell</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inaba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marecek</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibiotic related acute kidney injury in patients treated for open fractures</article-title><source>Injury</source><year>2016</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>653</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26854072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.injury.2016.01.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbieri</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zanetta</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burdmann</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and risk factors for aminoglycoside nephrotoxicity in intensive care units</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2009</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>2887</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19364846</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/AAC.01430-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2704674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Folse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hydrick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for kidney dysfunction with the use of gentamicin in open fracture antibiotic treatment</article-title><source>J Orthop Trauma</source><year>2018</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>573</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30086044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/BOT.0000000000001282</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>