<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="bcp15596" xml:lang="en" article-type="brief-report" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Clin Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Br J Clin Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">379</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">blackwellopen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BCP</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0306-5251</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1365-2125</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Wiley Open Access Collection</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10107630</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10107630.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10107630</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10107630</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36471568</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bcp.15596</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">BCP15596</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Short Communication</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical Toxicology Pro/Con Debates Series</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Fomepizole should not be used more liberally in paracetamol overdose</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">Dear</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="bcp15596-cr-0001" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dear</surname><given-names initials="JW">James W.</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8630-8625</contrib-id><xref rid="bcp15596-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>james.dear@ed.ac.uk</email></address></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="bcp15596-aff-0001">
<label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Pharmacology, Therapeutics and Toxicology, Centre for Cardiovascular Science</named-content>
<institution>University of Edinburgh, The Queen's Medical Research Institute</institution>
<city>Edinburgh</city>
<country country="GB">UK</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence</bold><break/>
James W. Dear, University/BHF Centre for Cardiovascular Science, University of Edinburgh, The Queen's Medical Research Institute, 47 Little France Crescent, Edinburgh EH16 4TJ, UK.<break/>
Email: <email>james.dear@ed.ac.uk</email><break/></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>89</volume><issue seq="240">2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">433603</issue-id><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bcp.v89.2</issue-id><issue-title>Themed Issue: Global Pharmacovigilance</issue-title><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>601</lpage><history><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>7</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>8</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>05</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>18</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-04-18 03:10:12.287"><day>18</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#169; 2022 The Author. <italic toggle="yes">British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</italic> published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of British Pharmacological Society.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use and distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non&#8208;commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="BCP-89-599.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:BCP-89-599.pdf"/><abstract><p>Fomepizole is a promising new treatment for preventing liver injury following paracetamol (acetaminophen) overdose. However, we need robust clinical trials to be performed to demonstrate its effect on clinical outcomes that are important to our patients and important to healthcare providers. Until such trials are performed, the toxicology community should learn the lessons from the COVID pandemic&#8212;potential novel therapeutic options may be theoretically appealing, but their effectiveness needs to be assessed in robust clinical trials before they are used in clinical practice.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="bcp15596-kwd-0001">acetaminophen</kwd><kwd id="bcp15596-kwd-0002">fomepizole</kwd><kwd id="bcp15596-kwd-0003">overdose</kwd><kwd id="bcp15596-kwd-0004">paracetamol</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="2074"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>February 2023</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.2.7 mode:remove_FC converted:17.04.2023</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><p content-type="self-citation">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-9001"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dear</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Fomepizole should not be used more liberally in paracetamol overdose</article-title>. <source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>599</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>601</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bcp.15596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36471568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10107630</pub-id></mixed-citation>
</p></notes></front><body id="bcp15596-body-0001"><p>The COVID&#8208;19 pandemic has dominated healthcare for the last couple of years. The enormous challenge presented by the emergence of this new infectious disease in late 2019 resulted in drug and vaccine development being performed at <italic toggle="yes">warp speed</italic>. When COVID was first identified, clinicians searched for licensed medicines with mechanisms of action consistent with a potentially effective treatment. Hydroxychloroquine was identified as a potential treatment because it has in vitro activity against SARS&#8208;CoV&#8208;2<xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref> and early small observational studies suggested a possible benefit.<xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref> There were high&#8208;profile leaders who promoted using hydroxychloroquine to prevent and treat COVID,<xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref> and doctors prescribed it based on this limited evidence base. Fortunately, from the start of the pandemic, the <italic toggle="yes">Recovery</italic> platform trial tested multiple treatments in a large randomized clinical trial that measured mortality as the primary endpoint. <italic toggle="yes">Recovery</italic> conclusively demonstrated hydroxychloroquine had no benefit when 1561 hospitalized patients with COVID were treated with this drug compared with 3155 patients who received standard care.<xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref> In fact, a subsequent meta&#8208;analysis suggests hydroxychloroquine may harm patients.<xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref> Despite the initial hope that resulted in doctors prescribing hydroxychloroquine, it proved ineffective when tested in a robust large study. Fomepizole may be the toxicology community's hydroxychloroquine unless we learn the lessons of COVID and come together to perform robust randomized trials before prescribing an untested treatment.</p><p>Paracetamol (acetaminophen) overdose is common. There is a clear unmet need for new treatments. Currently, the only effective treatment for preventing liver injury after paracetamol overdose is acetylcysteine. If treatment is commenced within 8&#160;h of the overdose, then acetylcysteine is almost 100% effective at preventing liver failure. However, its effectiveness drops substantially when treatment is delayed. Acetylcysteine is near ineffective at reducing liver injury when treatment is delayed greater than around 20&#8201;h after overdose; however, delayed treatment may reduce the subsequent development of hepatic encephalopathy and mortality.<xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref> For patients who present to hospital late following a significant paracetamol overdose, we need effective new treatment strategies to prevent liver injury in this high&#8208;risk group. Within this space, fomepizole has emerged as a potential new candidate.</p><p>Fomepizole is well known to toxicologists as an effective treatment for toxic alcohol poisoning due to its ability to inhibit the enzyme alcohol dehydrogenase.<xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref> The potential as a treatment for paracetamol overdose is unrelated to this mechanism of action. Fomepizole is a potent inhibitor of the cytochrome P450 enzymes that produce the paracetamol toxic metabolite (NAPQI) that is responsible for liver injury. Furthermore, in mice, fomepizole prevents liver injury after the metabolism phase of paracetamol mainly through the inhibition of c&#8208;Jun N&#8208;terminal kinase activation. The pre&#8208;clinical evidence base for fomepizole is impressive, largely due to the work of Hartmut Jaeschke's group.<xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref> In humans, well&#8208;performed clinical studies confirm that fomepizole inhibits the oxidative metabolism of paracetamol.<xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref> However, there is no trial evidence that fomepizole prevents liver injury in humans. These trials need to be performed. Sometimes, it is suggested that &#8216;trials cannot be performed in clinical toxicology&#8217;. As paracetamol overdose is common, this is untrue. In the United Kingdom, every 5&#160;min someone presents to hospital following a paracetamol overdose&#8212;the same frequency as myocardial infarction. It is hard to imagine cardiologists prescribing a medicine because it works in mouse models and defending that position by saying clinical trials cannot be performed in ischaemic heart disease.</p><p>There are a number of reasons to insist on robust, randomized trial evidence for the clinical effectiveness of fomepizole before it is used to treat paracetamol overdose in routine clinical practice. Advocates of its use suggest it has a role in large overdoses when there is a high concentration of paracetamol in the circulation. Given fomepizole's ability to inhibit the P450 enzymes, this makes theoretical sense. However, the P450 enzyme inhibitor cimetidine has been tested in this indication in the past and failed to demonstrate clinical effectiveness, albeit in small studies.<xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref> If P450 enzyme inhibition is the correct target for a new therapy, there may be cheaper alternatives to the expensive option presented by using fomepizole. Finally, and perhaps most importantly, we do not know whether using a higher dose of acetylcysteine for larger overdoses will be sufficient alone to prevent liver injury in this group of patients. This approach is likely to be substantially cheaper than using fomepizole (which costs around &#163;725 per dose). Currently, patients receive a dose of acetylcysteine that is based only on their body weight. It is clear from the basic pharmacology, mathematical modelling<xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>15</sup>
</xref> and observational studies<xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>16</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>17</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>18</sup>
</xref> that patients taking a large overdose may not be receiving enough acetylcysteine to prevent liver injury. There are new regimens for administering acetylcysteine that produce substantially lower rates of adverse drug reactions compared with the standard 21&#8208;h regimen.<xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>19</sup>
</xref> These new regimens allow Phase 2 clinical trials of high&#8208;dose acetylcysteine treatment in selected patients with a reasonable expectation of not producing dose&#8208;limiting toxicity. Before advocating a new expensive treatment, the toxicology community should focus on defining the optimal dose of acetylcysteine.</p><p>Fomepizole use in paracetamol overdose is occasionally defended as it is claimed to have an excellent safety profile. This seems to be correct in its licensed indication&#8212;treatment of toxic alcohol poisoning. We do not know if it is safe in patients who have overdosed on paracetamol, and there are reasons for a degree of caution. A Phase 1 trial of fomepizole demonstrated a small increase in alanine transaminase (ALT) activity in six of 15 healthy subjects.<xref rid="bcp15596-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>20</sup>
</xref> Although unlikely, when combined with a potentially hepatotoxic dose of paracetamol, this small ALT rise could translate into increased cases of significant liver injury. A fomepizole&#8208;induced increase in ALT, even if benign, may result in patients having unnecessary prolonged treatment with acetylcysteine, as ALT is the key biomarker that informs decisions to stop treatment. We do not have robust data to know the answers to these questions about safety.</p><p>Fomepizole has promise as a treatment for paracetamol overdose. But we do not have data from randomized trials about clinically important outcomes such as liver injury, hospital length of stay and liver failure, and we do not have an adequate safety dataset. Now is the time for the toxicology community to follow the example of the <italic toggle="yes">Recovery Trial</italic> and come together to perform large platform trials to evaluate new treatments that have evidence of clinical efficacy from Phase 2 trials. Candidate treatments include high&#8208;dose N&#8208;acetylcysteine (NAC) and fomepizole. This is the hard thing to do; the easier option is to start prescribing treatments without a robust evidence base. The danger is fomepizole becomes like hydroxychloroquine in COVID, advocated as a treatment without robust evidence of benefit for our patients.</p><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="bcp15596-sec-0002"><title>COMPETING INTERESTS</title><p>J.W.D. was the Chief Investigator on the POP Trial of calmangafodipir in paracetamol overdose.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="bcp15596-sec-0004"><title>DATA AVAILABILITY STATEMENT</title><p>No new data were used in this paper.</p></sec><ref-list id="bcp15596-bibl-0001" content-type="cited-references"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0002"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Remdesivir and chloroquine effectively inhibit the recently emerged novel coronavirus (2019&#8208;nCoV) in vitro</article-title>. <source>Cell Res</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>269</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>271</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41422-020-0282-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32020029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7054408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0003"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gautret</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lagier</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Parola</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin as a treatment of COVID&#8208;19: results of an open&#8208;label non&#8208;randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Int J Antimicrob Agents</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<elocation-id>105949</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.105949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32205204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7102549</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11718083"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0004"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Niburski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Niburski</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Impact of Trump's promotion of unproven COVID&#8208;19 treatments and subsequent Internet trends: observational study</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<elocation-id>e20044</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/20044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33151895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7685699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0005"><collab collab-type="authors">Group RC</collab>
, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Horby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mafham</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of hydroxychloroquine in hospitalized patients with Covid&#8208;19</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>383</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>2030</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>2040</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2022926</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33031652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7556338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0006"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Axfors</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Janiaud</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mortality outcomes with hydroxychloroquine and chloroquine in COVID&#8208;19 from an international collaborative meta&#8208;analysis of randomized trials</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>2349</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-22446-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33859192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8050319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0007"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smilkstein</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kulig</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rumack</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Efficacy of oral N&#8208;acetylcysteine in the treatment of acetaminophen overdose. Analysis of the national multicenter study (1976 to 1985)</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>319</volume>:<fpage>1557</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>1562</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM198812153192401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3059186</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0008"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Keays</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wendon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Intravenous acetylcysteine in paracetamol induced fulminant hepatic failure: a prospective controlled trial</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>303</volume>(<issue>6809</issue>):<fpage>1026</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>1029</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.303.6809.1026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1954453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1671790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0009"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brent</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Fomepizole for ethylene glycol and methanol poisoning</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>360</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>2216</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>2223</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMct0806112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19458366</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0010"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Akakpo</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Delayed treatment with 4&#8208;methylpyrazole protects against acetaminophen hepatotoxicity in mice by inhibition of c&#8208;Jun n&#8208;terminal kinase</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Sci</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>170</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>57</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>68</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/toxsci/kfz077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30903181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6592188</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0011"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Akakpo</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kandel</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>4&#8208;Methylpyrazole protects against acetaminophen hepatotoxicity in mice and in primary human hepatocytes</article-title>. <source>Hum Exp Toxicol</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1310</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>1322</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0960327118774902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29739258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6482816</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0012"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Padilla&#8208;Jones</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effect of 4&#8208;methylpyrazole on oxidative metabolism of acetaminophen in human volunteers</article-title>. <source>J Med Toxicol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>169</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>176</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13181-019-00740-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31768936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7099124</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0013"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mullins</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yeager</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Metabolic and mitochondrial treatments for severe paracetamol poisoning: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Clin Toxicol (Phila)</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1284</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>1296</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15563650.2020.1798979</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32762579</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0014"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burkhart</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Janco</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kulig</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rumack</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cimetidine as adjunctive treatment for acetaminophen overdose</article-title>. <source>Hum Exp Toxicol</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>299</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>304</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/096032719501400311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7779462</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0015"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rumack</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Acetaminophen and acetylcysteine dose and duration: past, present and future</article-title>. <source>Clin Toxicol (Phila)</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>91</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>98</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/15563650.2012.659252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22320209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0016"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hendrickson</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>What is the most appropriate dose of N&#8208;acetylcysteine after massive acetaminophen overdose?</article-title><source>Clin Toxicol (Phila)</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15563650.2019.1579914</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30777470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0017"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cairney</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Al&#8208;Hourani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eddleston</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dear</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Plasma paracetamol concentration at hospital presentation has a dose&#8208;dependent relationship with liver injury despite prompt treatment with intravenous acetylcysteine</article-title>. <source>Clin Toxicol (Phila)</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>405</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>410</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/15563650.2016.1159309</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27108714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0018"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>DJB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dargan</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Archer</surname><given-names>JRH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Outcomes from massive paracetamol overdose: a retrospective observational study</article-title>. <source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1263</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>1272</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bcp.13214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28002875</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5427245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0019"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chiew</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Isbister</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>BSH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Massive paracetamol overdose: an observational study of the effect of activated charcoal and increased acetylcysteine dose (ATOM&#8208;2)</article-title>. <source>Clin Toxicol (Phila)</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1055</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>1065</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15563650.2017.1334915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28644687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0020"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dear</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thanacoody</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Reduction of adverse effects from intravenous acetylcysteine treatment for paracetamol poisoning: a randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>383</volume>(<issue>9918</issue>):<fpage>697</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>704</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(13)62062-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24290406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bcp15596-bib-0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="bcp15596-cit-0021"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sebastian</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barron</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carriere</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McMartin</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of 4&#8208;methylpyrazole, methanol/ethylene glycol antidote, in healthy humans</article-title>. <source>J Emerg Med</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>455</fpage>&#8208;<lpage>461</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0736-4679(90)90176-V</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2212566</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>