<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Perm J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1290</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">permanentej</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">tpj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Permanente Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1552-5767</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-5775</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Kaiser Permanente</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10013719</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10013719.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10013719</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10013719</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36891646</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7812/TPP/22.057</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">TPJ-22-057</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Computerized Tomography&#8211;Based Screening for Moderate to Severe Hepatic Steatosis in a Multiethnic Population</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takakusagi</surname><given-names initials="MN">Melia Nicole</given-names></name><degrees>BS</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="corr1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="R">Ruixue</given-names></name><degrees>BS</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names initials="BJI">Bradley James Ikaika</given-names></name><degrees>BA</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3072-108X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names initials="HC">Hyo-Chun</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
<institution content-type="department">John A. Burns School of Medicine</institution>, <institution>University of Hawaii at M&#257;noa</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Honolulu</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">HI</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
<institution content-type="department">Diagnostic Imaging</institution>, <institution>Hawaii Permanente Medical Group</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Honolulu</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">HI</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>
</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="corr1">Melia Nicole Takakusagi, BS <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mailto:meliat@hawaii.edu">meliat@hawaii.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2023-03-09"><day>09</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>27</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">431278</issue-id><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-04-14 06:10:17.930"><day>14</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2023 The Authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>Published by The Permanente Federation LLC under the terms of the CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 license <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="tpp_22.057.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="tpp_22.057.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background and Aim</title><p>Data on prevalence of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease in Hawaii is limited. This study determined the prevalence of moderate to severe hepatic steatosis within a multicultural, multiethnic, and multiracial cohort in Hawaii undergoing computerized tomography (CT) for reasons unrelated to fatty liver disease.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>The authors performed a retrospective analysis of all patients who were members of an integrated health care system with CT scans including the liver between January 1, 2020, and December 31, 2020. Moderate to severe hepatic steatosis was determined by an average attenuation value &lt; 40 Hounsfield units for non-contrast-enhanced CT and a mean attenuation value &lt; 90 Hounsfield units for contrast-enhanced CT. Patients&#8217; electronic medical records were reviewed for existing diagnoses of hepatic steatosis, obesity, and diabetes mellitus type 2 and data to calculate a Fibrosis-4 (FIB-4) index.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Approximately 26.6% had moderate to severe hepatic steatosis, while only 11.3% of those patients had an active diagnosis of fatty liver disease. Native Hawaiians and Pacific Islanders (33.1%) had the greatest prevalence of hepatic steatosis, followed by White people (28.4%), Asian people (27.7%), and other ethnicities (10.8%). About 61.4% patients with fatty liver had a diagnosis of obesity, while 33.4% had a body mass index &lt; 30.0 kg/m<sup>2</sup>. Finally, 86.2% patients had enough information in their electronic medical records from which to calculate a FIB-4 score and the mean FIB-4 index was 1.66 &#177; 3.50.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Moderate to severe hepatic steatosis is common among patients undergoing CT studies for reasons not related to hepatic steatosis in this multiethnic population most of whom did not have a diagnosis of fatty liver disease.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>CT</kwd><kwd>Nonalcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</kwd><kwd>hepatic steatosis</kwd><kwd>Native Hawaiian and Pacific Islanders</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="1"/><ref-count count="18"/><page-count count="7"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) affects an estimated 25% of the global population, with prevalence varying by region of the world as well as race/ethnicity.<sup>
<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1,2</xref>
</sup> However, accurate data for many locations is unavailable; 1 large study using Medicare claims found Native Hawaiians and Japanese Americans had NAFLD prevalences of 2.3% and 4.4%, respectively, supporting observations elsewhere that NAFLD is underdiagnosed.<sup>
<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2,3</xref>
</sup> This is problematic because NAFLD results in increased overall mortality,<sup>
<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
</sup> in addition to a chance of progression from NAFLD to nonalcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH), cirrhosis, and hepatocellular carcinoma.</p><p>The gold standard for diagnosis of NASH is liver biopsy, which is too invasive to recommend for screening.<sup>
<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
</sup> Computerized tomography (CT), with or without contrast, is specific for diagnosis of moderate to severe hepatic steatosis.<sup>
<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6,7</xref>
</sup> Given the use of CT imaging to address many clinical questions, otherwise undetected NAFLD cases could be diagnosed if CT images were regularly assessed for evidence of hepatic steatosis.</p><p>This study was performed to determine the prevalence of moderate to severe hepatic steatosis in a multiethnic population undergoing CT, which included the liver, but these tests were performed for other indications unrelated to fatty liver disease in an integrated health care system.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>This study was performed with institutional review board approval with waiver of informed consent because it involved only review of existing health care information with no direct patient interactions. This is a retrospective review of all CT scans of the chest or abdomen performed between January 1, 2020, and December 31, 2020, on patients between the ages of 20&#8211;75 within an integrated health care system. In addition, the analysis was limited to those patients who did not have prior CT imaging of the chest or abdomen within 5 years prior to 2020. For patients with multiple CT studies performed during 2020, the authors preferentially selected a study done without IV contrast. The authors excluded all CT angiographic studies, as well as those CT studies obtained with IV contrast that were not obtained within the portal venous phase (70 seconds after start of contrast injection). Details on the cases excluded and included are presented in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. Only 1 CT study was evaluated for each unique patient. On each CT scan, 4 regions of interest (ROIs) of the liver were obtained, 2 in the right lobe with 1 ROI above and below the portal plane, respectively, and 2 in the left lobe with 1 ROI above and below the portal plane, respectively. The mean of all 4 ROIs was calculated to adjust for liver heterogeneity. For non-contrast CTs, patients with a mean attenuation value &lt; 40 Hounsfield units were considered to have moderate to severe hepatic steatosis.<sup>
<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
</sup> For contrast-enhanced CTs, a mean attenuation value &lt; 90 Hounsfield units was used to identify patients with moderate to severe hepatic steatosis.<sup>
<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
</sup>
</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1:</label><caption><p>Selection of study participants.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="tpp_22.057-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>All encounters for patients within this integrated health care system are contained in a common electronic medical record (EMR). For all patients identified with moderate to severe hepatic steatosis, the following data from their EMR was extracted, if available: body mass index (BMI), height, weight, alanine transaminase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), platelet count, and hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c). All values were preferentially collected from the same year and closest date to when the CT scan was performed; however, values that were not available within the same year as the corresponding CT scan were obtained from the next closest year. The Fibrosis-4 (FIB-4) score was calculated for those patients with available data. The patients' EMRs were also used to determine existing ICD-10 diagnoses. The authors specifically looked for the following diagnoses: obesity (defined as BMI &#8805; 30, E66.x), diabetes mellitus type 2 (E11.xx), and fatty liver/hepatic steatosis (K76.0 or K75.81). Patient demographic information, including age, gender, race, and ethnicity, were also collected. Race and ethnicity are self-reported in this EMR. Patients were classified as part-Hawaiian or Pacific Islander if they listed part-Hawaiian in their race or listed a Pacific island as their ethnicity such as Marshallese, Chukese, Tongan, and Samoan. Patients were categorized as Asian if they listed their ethnicity as Filipino and Okinawan in addition to the major Pacific Rim nations such as Japan, China, Korea, and Vietnam. Patients were classified as White if they listed their race as White or ethnicity as United States or other European country. Patients who did not fit into 1 of the above 3 categories were classified as other, which included those who listed their race as Black or Hispanic.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 2568 CT scans of the chest or abdomen on unique participants were reviewed. The authors excluded 247 participants who only received a CT study with IV contrast not obtained within the portal venous phase. Out of the remaining 2321 CT studies, 2.4% of cases were contrast-enhanced chest CT, 5.9% unenhanced chest CT, 61.9% enhanced abdominal CT, and 29.9% unenhanced abdominal CT. A total of 617 participants (26.6%) met the inclusion criteria for moderate to severe hepatic steatosis. About 5.5% of positive cases were found on contrast-enhanced chest CT, 2.9% on unenhanced chest CT, 67.4% on enhanced abdominal CT, and 24.2% on unenhanced abdominal CT.</p><p>There were 617 participants (26.6%) who were found to have moderate to severe hepatic steatosis. The mean age was 50.6 &#177; 14.2 years, with a wide age distribution, as shown in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>. Although there was a slight preponderance of women in the study sample (52.2% female and 47.8% male), there was a statistically significant increased prevalence of moderate to severe hepatic steatosis in men than women (&#967;<sup>2</sup> test, p &lt; 0.001), with 39.4% female and 60.6% male participants with moderate to severe hepatic steatosis.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2:</label><caption><p>Age distribution of patients with moderate to severe hepatic steatosis. Note: Only patients ages 20&#8211;75 were included in this study.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="tpp_22.057-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>The average BMI was 34.5 &#177; 8.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup> and 61.4% of participants carried an active diagnosis of obesity in their EMR. There were 9 patients who did not have a BMI or height and weight values listed in their EMR. A total of 206 patients with moderate to severe hepatic steatosis had a BMI &lt; 30.0.</p><p>Mean HbA1c was 6.4 &#177; 1.7%. There were 163 patients with a HbA1c in the prediabetic range of 5.7&#8211;6.4%. Approximately 145 patients had a HbA1c greater than 6.4%. About 26.1% of individuals carried an active diagnosis of diabetes mellitus type 2 in their EMR, which did not include 16 patients whose HbA1c closest to the time of their CT scan was greater than 6.4%.</p><p>The reference ranges in the authors&#8217; regional laboratory are as follows: for ALT, 5&#8211;63 U/L; AST, 11-41 U/L; and for platelet count, 130&#8211;440 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup>/&#181;L. The average ALT was 45.6 &#177; 77.4 U/L, with 73 patients having an ALT &lt; 63 U/L; the average AST was 50.5 &#177; 158.0 U/L, with 110 patients having an AST &lt; 41 U/L; and the average platelet count was 264.0 &#177; 96.4 &#215; 10<sup>9</sup>/&#181;L, with 28 patients with PLT &lt; 440 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup>/&#181;L and 29 patients with PLT &lt; 130 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup>/&#181;L. Mean FIB-4 index was calculated to be 1.66 &#177; 3.5. Details of the demographics regarding the positive cases of hepatic steatosis are presented in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The FIB-4 index utilizes age, ALT, AST, and platelet count to predict fibrosis.<sup>
<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
</sup> Within this cohort of those with moderate to severe hepatic steatosis, 94.7% had ALT levels available in their EMR, 87% had AST levels available in their EMR, and 98.5% had platelet count available in their EMR. Approximately 86.2% of patients had a combination of all 3 values available from which to calculate a FIB-4 score. Among these 532 fatty liver patients with calculated FIB-4 scores, 66.7% were below an index of 1.3, 24.1% were in an indeterminate range between 1.3 and 2.67, and 9.2% were above an index of 2.67, suggestive of advanced fibrosis.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1:</label><caption><p>Demographics of moderate to severe hepatic steatosis cases</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Demographic categories</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (years)</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">617</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.57</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">608</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.46</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Obesity active diagnosis</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">379</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diabetes mellitus type 2 active diagnosis</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hepatic steatosis active diagnosis</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hemoglobin A1c</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">533</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.39</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.66</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ALT (U/L)</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">584</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.64</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AST (U/L)</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">537</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.52</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">158.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Platelets (10<sup>9</sup> U/L)</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">608</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">263.97</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FIB-4 Index<xref rid="T1_FN1" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">532</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.66</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">243</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">374</td><td align="center" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.62</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T1_FN1"><label>a</label><p>FIB-4 Index includes all 3 laboratory values (ALT, AST, and Platelets)</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN2"><p>ALT, alanine transaminase; AST, aminotransferase; BMI, body mass index; FIB-4, Fibrosis-4; SD, standard deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Within the 617 positive cases, 398 participants had an active diagnosis of obesity, 161 participants had an active diagnosis of type 2 diabetes mellitus, and only 70 participants carried an active diagnosis of fatty liver disease according to their EMR. As shown in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>, only 21 participants (3.4%) had all 3 diagnoses in their EMR. Ninety (14.6%) participants were diagnosed with both type 2 diabetes mellitus and obesity, 30 (4.9%) participants were diagnosed with both obesity and hepatic steatosis, and 6 (1.0%) participants were diagnosed with both type 2 diabetes mellitus and hepatic steatosis. A total of 156 participants carried none of these diagnosis. The prevalence of hepatic steatosis based on race was 33.1% Native Hawaiian and Pacific Islanders, 28.4% White, 27.7% Asian, and 10.9% other (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3:</label><caption><p>Overlap of active diagnosis of hepatic steatosis, obesity, and type 2 diabetes mellitus in patients with moderate to severe hepatic steatosis.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="tpp_22.057-g003.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4:</label><caption><p>Prevalence of hepatic steatosis based on race.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="tpp_22.057-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>NAFLD and NASH have become highly prevalent causes of liver disease worldwide.<sup>
<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup> The authors' multispecialty medical group does not recommend routine CT imaging of the liver to evaluate liver steatosis. Therefore, the study population represents a nonrandom sample of patients between 20 and 75 years of age and undergoing CT scans for reasons not related to fatty liver disease, but which included the liver as part of the imaging field. This study was conducted to determine the prevalence of moderate to severe hepatic steatosis as might be seen by radiologists within a diverse multiethnic population undergoing CT. This study found a 26.6% prevalence of moderate to severe hepatic steatosis in the study sample. However, only 11.3% of these participants had an active diagnosis of fatty liver disease in their EMR. Therefore, there may be considerable value in having radiologists evaluate for hepatic steatosis in patients undergoing CT for reasons unrelated to fatty liver disease. When moderate to severe hepatic steatosis is found on CT imaging unrelated to fatty liver disease, it would be helpful for this finding to be automatically flagged on the patient&#8217;s EMR problem list for the patient&#8217;s primary care physician to review. At a time when most radiology reports are directly available to patients, it would also be important that patients be recommended to follow up with their health care practitioner about the significance of this finding, which will vary from patient to patient. The authors acknowledge that although there is great value in alerting clinicians of the incidental findings of fatty liver when CT is used for other reasons, CT scan is not the primary modality for measuring liver steatosis.</p><p>NAFLD and NASH have been shown to be associated with obesity, as well as type 2 diabetes mellitus.<sup>
<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
</sup> However, only 3.4% of patients in this sample had a combination of active diagnoses of hepatic steatosis, obesity, and type 2 diabetes mellitus in their EMR. In comparison, 25.3% of patients did not have any of these 3 relevant active diagnosis (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). Within this study, 61.4% of individuals with fatty liver were found to be obese (BMI &lt; 30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>). However, 206 patients with moderate to severe hepatic steatosis had a BMI &lt; 30.0. This demonstrates the advantage of using a cross-sectional imaging technique such as CT to evaluate for patients with steatosis as a substantial proportion will not have overt obesity. About 26.1% of patients found to have liver steatosis had an active diagnosis of type 2 diabetes mellitus in their EMR. Previous studies have shown that NAFLD and type 2 diabetes mellitus have not only been found to commonly exist together, but NAFLD has been shown to increase certain cardiovascular events and diabetic microvascular complications.<sup>
<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10,11</xref>
</sup> Therefore, it may be beneficial to review the imaging repository of T2DM patients for prior CT studies, which may demonstrate moderate to severe hepatic steatosis. Although liver ultrasound studies can also provide this information, ultrasound tends to have lower specificity for the detection of moderate to severe hepatic steatosis.<sup>
<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
</sup>
</p><p>Another important finding of this study is the prevalence of hepatic steatosis based on race. Multiple studies show that the overall ethnic prevalence of NAFLD in the United States is highest among Hispanic people, followed by White people, and lowest among the Black population, with very little information on Pacific Islander and Asian people.<sup>
<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13&#8211;15</xref>
</sup> The state of Hawaii has greater ethnic diversity than the remainder of the United States. Based on census race data from 2019,<sup>
<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
</sup> 37.6% of Hawaii residents identify as Asian, 25.5% identify as White, 10.1% identify as Pacific Islander (including Native Hawaiian), 24.2% identify as multiracial, and less than 10% as Black or other. In the United States as a whole, 76.3% identify as White, 5.9% as Asian, and the remainder as Black, other, or multiracial. In this study sample, Native Hawaiian and Pacific Islander constituted 33.1% of the participants with moderate to severe hepatic steatosis based on their CT results despite being one of the minority populations within the state of Hawaii. This could be attributed to the many health disparities Native Hawaiians and Pacific Islanders face. The second largest population with moderate to severe hepatic steatosis were those who identified as White, with a prevalence of 28.4%. This is proportional to the White population within Hawaii, which is the second largest population within the state. Those who identified as Asian had a prevalence of 27.7%, making them the third largest population found to have fatty liver disease despite being the largest ethnic population within Hawaii.</p><p>The prevalence of NAFLD has been found to increase with age.<sup>
<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup> As seen in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>, moderate to severe hepatic steatosis was most prevalent in participants between 50 and 59 years of age. However, as shown in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>, there is a relatively symmetric distribution of moderate steatosis centered around the 50&#8211;59 years age group with 9.1% of participants found between ages 20 and 29 years, and 19.6% participants between ages 70 and 75 years.</p><p>Liver biopsy is the gold standard for diagnosis of NASH; however, the FIB-4 index has been found to be a useful noninvasive tool in evaluating the likelihood of advanced fibrosis in NAFLD patients.<sup>
<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5,8</xref>
</sup> This method outperformed other noninvasive markers of fibrosis, such as the NAFLD fibrosis score.<sup>
<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
</sup> A study has found that a FIB-4 cutoff value of 1.3 had a negative predicative value for advanced fibrosis of 83%, while a threshold value of 2.67 had a positive predictive value of 80%.<sup>
<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
</sup> In this nonrandom sample, 86.2% of individuals with moderate to severe hepatic steatosis had all the laboratory tests results required to calculate a FIB-4 index, and based on these values, 9.2% are suggested to have advanced fibrosis. The prevalence of severe liver fibrosis may vary if all patients with fatty liver had FIB-4 scores available. In an integrated health care system such as the one in this study, it may be beneficial to have an alert be triggered for the primary care physician to consider ordering this battery of test in patients with a new diagnosis of moderate to severe hepatic steatosis based on their CT study if the patient does not already have an active diagnosis in their EMR.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Limitations</title><p>One of the limitations of this study is the use of average of 4 ROIs to determine the mean liver attenuation value. This method is not as accurate in comparison to an automated or semi-automated volumetric analysis, especially if such an analysis could avoid the liver vessels. Additionally, the use of an automated or semi-automated volumetric method might be difficult to implement into the routine workflow of a busy radiologist if the volumetric analysis had to be performed on a separate workstation. A second limitation involves the patient&#8217;s ethnicity, which is self-reported into the EMR system. Multiethnic and multiracial individuals are common within Hawaii&#8217;s population. The accuracy of racial and ethnic identity when self-reported by the patient is cannot be verified.</p><p>There is currently no approved therapy for NAFLD, and treatment has been focused on preventing risk factors associated with the disease, most notably through weight loss.<sup>
<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9,17</xref>
</sup> Although there has been recent interest in pharmaceutical treatment for NAFLD,<sup>
<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
</sup> it has been shown overall that there is an underwhelming low rate of awareness among individuals with NAFLD within the United States.<sup>
<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
</sup> Given that early intervention of NAFLD risk factors is the mainstay treatment, proper diagnosis and raising patient awareness of the disease may be beneficial for this population.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors would like to thank the patients for their contributions, including the use of data from the electronic health record.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn1" fn-type="supported-by"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> None declared</p></fn><fn id="fn2" fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Conflicts of Interest:</bold> None declared</p></fn><fn id="fn3" fn-type="con"><p><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Ruixue Zhang, BS, Bradley James Ikaika Thomas, BA, and Hyo-Chun Yoon, MD, PhD, contributed equally to the data acquisition, analysis, and initial manuscript preparation. Melia Nicole Takakusagi, BS, performed the final manuscript edits and preparation for submission.</p></fn><fn id="fn4" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethics Approval:</bold> This study was approved by the institutional review board with a waiver of informed consent because this was a retrospective review with no direct patient interactions.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Younossi</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelatif</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fazel</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wymer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Global epidemiology of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease-meta-analytic assessment of prevalence, incidence, and outcomes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hepatology</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>73</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.28431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26707365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Setiawan</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stram</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Porcel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Le Marchand</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Noureddin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of chronic liver disease and cirrhosis by underlying cause in understudied ethnic groups: The multiethnic cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hepatology</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1969</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1977</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.28677</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27301913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5115980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Loomis</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fairburn-Beech</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Real-world data reveal a diagnostic gap in non-alcoholic fatty liver disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>130</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12916-018-1103-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30099968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6088429</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lymp</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>St Sauver</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The natural history of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease: A population-based cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Gastroenterology</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>129</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>113</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>121</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2005.04.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16012941</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chalasani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Younossi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lavine</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The diagnosis and management of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease: Practice Guideline by the American Association for the Study of Liver Diseases, American College of Gastroenterology, and the American Gastroenterological Association</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hepatology</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2005</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2023</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.25762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22488764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pickhardt</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Graffy</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Liver steatosis categorization on contrast-enhanced CT using a fully automated deep learning volumetric segmentation tool: Evaluation in 1204 healthy adults using unenhanced CT as a reference standard</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">AJR Am J Roentgenol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>217</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>359</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>367</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2214/AJR.20.24415</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32936018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pickhardt</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Specificity of unenhanced CT for non-invasive diagnosis of hepatic steatosis: Implications for the investigation of the natural history of incidental steatosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Radiol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1075</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1082</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00330-011-2349-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22138733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lydecker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of noninvasive markers of fibrosis in patients with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1104</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1112</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cgh.2009.05.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19523535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3079239</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sheka</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adeyi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hameed</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ikramuddin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Nonalcoholic steatohepatitis: A review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>323</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1175</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1183</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.2298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32207804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Targher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bertolini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rodella</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease is independently associated with an increased incidence of cardiovascular events in type 2 diabetic patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Care</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2119</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2121</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc07-0349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17519430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Targher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lonardo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease and chronic vascular complications of diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Endocrinol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>99</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>114</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrendo.2017.173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29286050</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Liver fat imaging-a clinical overview of ultrasound, CT, and MR imaging</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br J Radiol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>91</volume>(<issue>1089</issue>):<fpage>20170959</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1259/bjr.20170959</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29722568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6223150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Oji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mufti</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Racial and ethnic disparities in nonalcoholic fatty liver disease prevalence, severity, and outcomes in the United States: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>198</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>210</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cgh.2017.09.041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28970148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5794571</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Samji</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Snell</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Singal</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Satapathy</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Racial disparities in diagnosis and prognosis of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Liver Dis (Hoboken)</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>66</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>72</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cld.948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32922753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7474141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Talens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tumas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lazarus</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Benach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peric&#224;s</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>What do we know about inequalities in NAFLD distribution and outcomes? A scoping review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>21</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm10215019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8584385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34768539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="report"><person-group><collab>US Census Bureau</collab></person-group>. <article-title>
Hawaii Population Characteristics 2019
</article-title>. <year>2020</year>. <comment>Accessed</comment><date-in-citation>1 February 2023</date-in-citation>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://census.hawaii.gov/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/Hawaii-Population-Characteristics-2019.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://census.hawaii.gov/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/Hawaii-Population-Characteristics-2019.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Promrat</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kleiner</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Niemeier</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Randomized controlled trial testing the effects of weight loss on nonalcoholic steatohepatitis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hepatology</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>121</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>129</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.23276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19827166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2799538</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alqahtani</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Paik</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Arshad</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Younossi</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Poor awareness of liver disease among adults with NAFLD in the United States</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hepatol Commun</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1833</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1847</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep4.1765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34558829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8557315</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>