<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Healthc Manag</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Healthc Manag</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2035</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">lwwopen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JHCMA</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Healthcare Management</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1096-9012</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Lippincott Open Access</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10635334</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10635334.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10635334</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10635334</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37944171</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JHM-D-22-00253</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Providers' Perceptions of the Effectiveness of Electronic Health Records in Identifying Opioid Misuse</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glenn</surname><given-names initials="J">Jeffrey</given-names></name><degrees>DrPH</degrees><email>jeff_glenn@byu.edu</email><xref rid="corr1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names initials="D">Danica</given-names></name><email>dntopham@gmail.com</email><aff>Department of Public Health, Brigham Young University, Provo, Utah</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiesset</surname><given-names initials="HF">Heather F.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>Heather.Thiesset@uvu.edu</email><aff>College of Health and Public Service, Utah Valley University, Orem, Utah</aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="corr1">For more information, contact Dr. Glenn at <email>jeff_glenn@byu.edu</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>68</volume><issue>6</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">448858</issue-id><fpage>390</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>09</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-10-09 11:25:14.900"><day>09</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2023 The Authors. Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. on behalf of the Foundation of the American College of Healthcare Executives</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0</ext-link> (CCBY-NC-ND), where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially without permission from the journal.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jhcma-68-390.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jhcma-68-390.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Goal:</title><p>This study aimed to understand prescribing providers' perceptions of electronic health record (EHR) effectiveness in enabling them to identify and prevent opioid misuse and addiction.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>We used a cross-sectional survey designed and administered by KLAS Research to examine healthcare providers' perceptions of their experiences with EHR systems. Univariate analysis and mixed-effects logistic regression analysis with organization-level random effects were performed.</p></sec><sec><title>Principal Findings:</title><p>A total of 17,790 prescribing providers responded to the survey question related to this article's primary outcome about opioid misuse prevention. Overall, 34% of respondents believed EHRs helped prevent opioid misuse and addiction. Advanced practice providers were more likely than attending physicians and trainees to believe EHRs were effective in reducing opioid misuse, as were providers with fewer than 5 years of experience.</p></sec><sec><title>Practical Applications:</title><p>Understanding providers' perceptions of EHR effectiveness is critical as the health outcome of reducing opioid misuse depends upon their willingness to adopt and apply new technology to their standardized routines. Healthcare managers can enhance providers' use of EHRs to facilitate the prevention of opioid misuse with ongoing training related to advanced EHR system features.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The opioid epidemic in the United States has reached monumental proportions, with more than 2 million people misusing opioids and consuming more than 80% of the global supply (<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">Manchikanti &amp; Singh, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">Wilson et al., 2020</xref>). Opioids were involved in 46,802 overdose deaths, accounting for roughly 70% of all drug overdose deaths in the United States in 2018 (<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">Hedegaard et al., 2020</xref>). Furthermore, opioid misuse can cause respiratory depression and other long-term sequela.</p><p>Among the many factors that contribute to the opioid epidemic, providers' prescribing practices play a major role in the quantity of leftover prescription opioids at large in the community and the potential for misuse (<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">Chou et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Dowell et al., 2016</xref>). It is estimated that most patients are overprescribed opioids for pain management (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">Bicket et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">Colton et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">Hagemeier, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">Kolodny et al., 2015</xref>). Although many opioid use disorder patients obtain their drugs from a provider, they may also get them from friends and family who have leftovers from their prescriptions or conditions. The source can also vary based on the duration of use (<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">Hughes et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">Park &amp; Wu, 2020</xref>). Furthermore, multiple pain management prescriptions from multiple providers frequently confuse patients on what they should be taking and lead to excessive consumption (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">Preuss et al., 2020</xref>). The ability to distinguish between patients with legitimate pain management needs and patients who are seeking to misuse opioids is also a difficult challenge for prescribing providers (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">Preuss et al., 2020</xref>). Moreover, patients have different tolerance levels to pain medications and require individualized pain management plans that providers may overlook in favor of standardized prescriptions (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">Preuss et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p>Electronic health records (EHRs) captured by electronic health (or medical) record systems (EHR systems) can be instrumental in helping providers implement guidelines to reduce the prevalence of prescription opioid misuse. This is done by encoding opioid dependence as an International Classification of Diseases (ICD) code. Since their development in the 1970s, EHR systems have greatly increased a clinical provider's ability to capture a patient's condition and clinical summary (<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">Lingren et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">March et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">Yadav et al., 2017</xref>). Furthermore, EHR systems have given providers tools to improve patient care by tracking long-term outcomes, reducing potential medical errors, coordinating providers in patient care, and providing efficiency in billing (<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">Keasberry et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">Lingren et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>Although available features vary among different EHR systems, they are commonly designed to assist providers in better monitoring and controlling the amount of prescribed opioids with patient dashboards, decision support tools, documentation of tapering plans, and default dosage settings (<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">Electronic Health Record Association, 2018</xref>). Many systems can be integrated with state-controlled substance databases to track prescriptions and ensure that patients are not &#8220;doctor shopping&#8221; to obtain multiple opioid prescriptions for the same condition (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">Holt et al., 2018</xref>). Other tools such as alerts within a patient's EHR can help notify providers of frequent users so that these patients can be referred for chronic pain outpatient management (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">Kahler et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">Lowenstein et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p>Some studies have demonstrated that tools can assist providers in identifying and preventing prescription opioid misuse (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Averitt et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">Brown et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">Chiu et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">Delgado et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">Price-Haywood et al., 2018</xref>). However, the effectiveness of EHR systems in enabling providers to address misuse depends largely on providers' willingness to accept and adopt the technology into everyday practice (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">Dornan et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">Venkatesh et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>Individual and organizational factors influence EHR usage by physicians (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">Gagnon et al., 2016</xref>). The unified theory of acceptance and use of technology (UTAUT) is a widely used framework to explain the acceptance of different technologies in many fields and has been applied specifically to understand EHR system adoption among physicians (<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">Venkatesh et al., 2011</xref>). The UTAUT proposes three direct determinants of behavior intention: performance expectancy, effort expectancy, and social influence. <italic toggle="yes">Performance expectancy</italic>, defined as the degree to which an individual believes that using the system will help them better attain significant rewards (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">Archer &amp; Cocosila, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">Venkatesh et al, 2011</xref>), is closely associated with perceived usefulness. <italic toggle="yes">Effort expectancy</italic> is defined as the degree of ease associated with the use of the system (<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">Venkatesh et al., 2011</xref>). The UTAUT also suggests that gender, age, experience, and voluntariness are contingencies that alter the effect of these determinants on intention to use the system (<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">Venkatesh et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>This study aimed to understand factors associated with prescribing providers' perceptions of EHR effectiveness (i.e., performance expectancy) in enabling them to identify and prevent prescription opioid misuse&#8212;a critical factor in determining whether providers are likely to accept and use available technology for addressing opioid misuse.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>METHODS</title><sec><title>Study Design</title><p>We used a descriptive, cross-sectional survey covering healthcare professionals' experiences with EHR systems to examine their perceptions of whether their systems and the ICD-10 codes for opioid dependence enable them to identify prescription opioid misuse. The survey was designed and administered by KLAS Research (KLAS), an independent health information technology (HIT) firm that collaborates with health systems to research the clinician's EHR system experience and other HIT issues.</p></sec><sec><title>Survey Instrument</title><p>KLAS researchers designed the survey instrument based on their knowledge of the HIT field and preliminary discussions with HIT specialists. The survey included 49 questions about the respondents' clinical background, specialty, years of experience, and a range of topics related to experience with an EHR system&#8212;including one Likert scale question asking them to indicate whether their system enables them to identify and prevent opioid misuse and addiction.</p></sec><sec><title>Study Population</title><p>Study participants included clinicians working in more than 200 provider organizations that partner with KLAS. While the survey was administered to all types of clinicians within a participating organization, this analysis considered only responses from prescribing providers (physicians, physician residents or fellows, and advanced practice providers).</p></sec><sec><title>Data Collection</title><p>Surveys were administered online between January 2017 and November 2019. The leadership of one of KLAS's partner organizations (hospital, clinic, or health system) distributed the survey to all targeted clinicians to invite them to participate. Prospective participants were informed about the purpose of the survey and that participation was voluntary. They gave implied consent by responding to the survey. They were given the option to remain anonymous or to attach their name to their responses, but data given from KLAS to the authors were deidentified. This study was exempt from institutional review board approval.</p></sec><sec><title>Data Analysis</title><p>Statistical analyses were performed using Stata statistical software (Ver. 16.1). The primary outcomes were self-reported responses of agreement with whether providers believed the EHR effectively enabled them to identify and prevent opioid misuse and addiction, which is a measure closely associated with performance expectancy.</p><p>For a simplified presentation of the results and to create a dichotomous variable for the logistic regression analysis, Likert scale responses for this question about perceived effectiveness were combined to show agreement (<italic toggle="yes">agree</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">somewhat agree</italic>) and nonagreement (<italic toggle="yes">neutral, disagree</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">somewhat disagree</italic>). To simplify the analysis, self-reported provider specialties were condensed into categories based on American Board of Medical Specialties guidance. Specialties presented in the results were deemed mutually exclusive. Univariate analyses were conducted using &#967;<sup>2</sup> tests to assess the statistical association between the perceived EHR effectiveness in enabling providers to prevent opioid misuse and various individual and organizational factors theorized by the authors and others to be associated with this dependent variable (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">Dornan et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">Venkatesh et al., 2011</xref>). These variables included factors related to effort expectancy (e.g., training, satisfaction with their EHR system, and burnout), experience, provider type, specialty type, and organization type. A mixed-effects logistic regression analysis with organization-level random effects included all covariates identified as relevant through the literature review and univariate analysis, as well as which EHR system was used.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>A total of 134,124 healthcare professionals participated in the survey, of whom 17,790 (13%) from 99 different sites met the inclusion criteria for this analysis as prescribing providers who responded to the question about opioid misuse (see Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Of these, 71% were physicians, 25% were advanced practice providers (APPs), and 4% were trainees (including fellows and residents). Participants had a wide range of years in practice, with 32% having practiced for 25 years or more. The top three specialties were internal medicine (25%), family medicine (16%), and surgery/anesthesiology (14%); 44% of all participants reported using their EHR systems for less than 5 years.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><title>Demographics</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physicians</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">APPs</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trainees</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,748 (70.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,436 (24.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">786 (4.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,970 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Years in practice</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#8211;4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">637 (5.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">643 (14.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">414 (52.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,694 (9.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#8211;14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,701 (29.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,629 (36.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">336 (42.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,666 (31.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8211;24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,789 (29.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,103 (24.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (1.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,907 (27.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,579 (35.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,057 (23.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (2.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,652 (31.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (0.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (0.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (0.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (0.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Specialty</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Internal medicine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,394 (26.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">992 (22.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">179 (22.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,565 (25.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family medicine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,892 (14.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">882 (19.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">143 (18.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,917 (16.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgery/anesthesiology</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,774 (13.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">604 (13.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (11.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,465 (13.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emergency/urgent care</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,189 (9.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">370 (8.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (8.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,626 (9.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pediatrics</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,097 (8.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">257 (5.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 (13.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,459 (8.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurology/rehabilitation</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">812 (6.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">369 (8.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (6.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,233 (6.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OB/GYN</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">737 (5.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212 (4.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (2.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">972 (5.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer/palliative</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">356 (2.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249 (5.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (2.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">627 (3.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mental health</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">267 (2.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (1.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (5.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">368 (2.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">852 (6.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177 (4.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (5.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,070 (6.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">378 (3.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266 (6.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (3.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">668 (3.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Years using EHR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,995 (39.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,356 (53.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">605 (77.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,956 (44.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,625 (59.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,044 (46.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160 (20.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,829 (54.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128 (1.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (0.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (2.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185 (1.0)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p><italic toggle="yes">Note.</italic> APP = advanced practice provider; EHR = electronic health record; OB/GYN = obstetrician/gynecologist.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows the percentage of participants in various categories who agreed that EHRs helped to prevent opioid misuse and addiction. Overall, 34% of respondents believed EHRs enabled them to prevent opioid misuse and addiction. A review of the full range of responses in the Likert scale indicates that 5.2% strongly agreed, 29.1% agreed, 65.7% neither agreed nor disagreed, 17.5% disagreed, and 8% strongly disagreed that EHRs were helpful. The bivariate analysis found that APPs were more likely to agree that EHRs were helpful with opioid misuse and addiction (43%) than physicians (32%) and trainees (34%). Years of practice had a large inverse correlation with the dependent variable while years using EHR systems had a small correlation. Regarding specialties, more than 40% of family practitioners and emergency/urgent care providers found EHRs helpful with opioids compared with fewer than 30% of surgeons/anesthesiologists, pediatricians, and oncologists/palliative care providers.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><title>Bivariate Analysis: EHRs Help Prevent Opioid Misuse and Addiction</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agree</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> (&#967;<sup>2</sup>)</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,162 (34.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,970 (100.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Provider type</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physician</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,012 (31.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,748 (70.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Advanced practice provider</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,883 (42.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,436 (24.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trainee</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">267 (34.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">786 (4.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Years in practice</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#8211;4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">728 (43.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,694 (9.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#8211;14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,067 (36.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,666 (31.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8211;24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,615 (32.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,907 (27.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,739 (30.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,652 (31.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (25.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (0.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Years using EHR system</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,686 (33.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,141 (45.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,476 (35.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,829 (54.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specialty</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Internal medicine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,505 (33.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,565 (25.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family medicine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,344 (46.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,917 (16.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgery/anesthesiology</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">661 (26.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,465 (13.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emergency/urgent care</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">670 (41.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,626 (9.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pediatrics</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">421 (28.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,459 (8.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurology/rehabilitation</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">403 (32.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,233 (6.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OB/GYN</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">341 (35.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">972 (5.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer/palliative</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176 (28.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">627 (3.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mental health</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118 (32.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">368 (2.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">312 (29.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,070 (6.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211 (31.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">668 (3.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organization type (# of sites)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ambulatory care group (19)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">406 (28.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,435 (8.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Children's hospital (7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">403 (30.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,313 (7.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community hospital (14)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">318 (32.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">983 (5.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community health system (19)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,142 (39.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,861 (15.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midsize health system (11)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,037 (43.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,395 (13.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large health system (18)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,795 (32.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,580 (31.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic health system (11)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,061 (31.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,403 (18.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Satisfaction with EHR system</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dissatisfied</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,031 (16.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,373 (35.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Satisfied</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,118 (44.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,566 (64.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (41.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (0.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial training prepared users well</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disagree</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,146 (24.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,643 (48.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agree</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,862 (43.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,978 (50.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154 (44.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">349 (1.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ongoing training is enough</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disagree</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,123 (23.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,240 (51.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agree</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,764 (47.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,994 (44.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">275 (37.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">736 (4.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average engagement</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not engaged</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,801 (26.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,704 (37.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Engaged</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,111 (39.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,506 (58.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250 (32.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">760 (4.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Burnout</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not burned out</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,003 (37.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,620 (59.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Burned out</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,152 (27.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,139 (23.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,007 (31.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,211 (17.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p><italic toggle="yes">Note.</italic> EHR = electronic health record; OB/GYN = obstetrician/gynecologist.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In the bivariate analysis, providers' satisfaction with and interactions with EHR systems and associated training appeared to influence their beliefs about the effectiveness of EHRs in enabling them to prevent opioid misuse and addiction. While 44% of participants who reported satisfaction with their EHR systems believed EHRs were helpful with opioid misuse, only 16% of dissatisfied participants agreed. Regarding training, providers who felt their initial training prepared them well; providers who felt their ongoing training was sufficient were both more likely to report that EHRs were helpful with opioid misuse. More providers who reported being engaged with various EHR system features felt EHRs were helpful with opioids (39%) compared with providers who reported not being engaged (27%). Finally, providers who reported being burned out were less likely to believe EHRs were helpful with opioids.</p><p>Odds ratios from the multivariate analysis are shown in Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. When controlling for all other covariates, the only variable that showed no statistically significant association was years using EHRs. Satisfaction (<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> = 2.7) had the strongest association with the perception that EHRs helped prevent opioid misuse and addiction. Ongoing training (<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> = 1.8), initial training (<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> = 1.29), and engagement with EHR system features (<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> = 1.43) also had strong, statistically significant associations with believing EHRs enable the prevention of opioid misuse, while burnout (<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> = 0.8) was inversely correlated with the dependent variable.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 3</label><caption><title>Multivariate Regression: Agreement That EHRs Help Prevent Opioid Misuse and Addiction (n = 13,199)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">SE</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Years using EHR &#8805;5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Satisfied with EHR system</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.72</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00<xref rid="tbl3-2" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.148</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial training prepared users well</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00<xref rid="tbl3-2" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.060</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ongoing training is enough</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00<xref rid="tbl3-2" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.082</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Engaged</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00<xref rid="tbl3-2" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.065</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Burned out</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00<xref rid="tbl3-2" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Years in practice</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">0&#8211;4 (reference)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#8211;14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02<xref rid="tbl3-1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8211;24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.03<xref rid="tbl3-1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02<xref rid="tbl3-1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Provider type</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Physician (reference)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resident</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.103</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Advanced practice provider</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00<xref rid="tbl3-2" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.065</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Specialty</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Internal medicine (reference)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer/palliative</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.85</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.137</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emergency/urgent care</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.89</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00<xref rid="tbl3-2" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.126</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family medicine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00<xref rid="tbl3-2" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.104</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mental health</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.186</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurology/rehabilitation</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.95</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OB/GYN</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pediatrics</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00<xref rid="tbl3-2" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.066</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgery/anesthesiology</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00<xref rid="tbl3-2" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Organization type</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Large health system (reference)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic health system</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.176</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ambulatory care group</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.74</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.84</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.269</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Children's hospital</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.82</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.311</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community health system</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.243</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community hospital</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.82</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.248</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midsize health system</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.00<xref rid="tbl3-2" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.503</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p><italic toggle="yes">Note.</italic> EHR = electronic health record; OB/GYN = obstetrician/gynecologist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="tbl3-1"><p>*<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .05.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="tbl3-2"><p>**<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Other categories in the multivariate analysis showed statistically significant associations for some variables compared with the reference groups. Providers with more than 4 years of practice were less likely to perceive EHRs as helpful in preventing opioid misuse compared with those with 4 years or fewer of practice. APPs (<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> = 1.3) were more likely than physicians to perceive EHRs as helpful. Some specialties&#8212;emergency/urgent care (<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> = 1.6) and family medicine (<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> = 1.6)&#8212;were more likely to find EHRs helpful than did the reference group (internal medicine), while other specialties&#8212;pediatrics (<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> = 0.7) and surgery/anesthesiology (<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> = 0.7)&#8212;were less likely to find EHRs helpful. Regarding organization type, only providers from midsize health systems (<italic toggle="yes">OR</italic> = 2.1) had a statistically significant association different from the reference group (large health systems).</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>This study suggests that prescribing providers generally do not perceive EHRs to be effective tools to facilitate the identification and prevention of opioid misuse and addiction in their patient populations. Overall, APPs were more likely than attending physicians and trainees to believe EHRs are effective in reducing opioid misuse, as were providers with fewer than 5 years of experience. This may be due in part to APPs' greater familiarity and understanding of EHRs as they take over many of the day-to-day tasks and frontline care of patients, including data entry (<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">Thiesset et al., 2020</xref>), as well as newer providers' reliance on EHR systems instead of having to undergo the transition from more traditional paper methods in providing clinical care (<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">Zandieh et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p>Of all the factors studied, providers' satisfaction with their EHR system was the most highly correlated with their perception that EHRs are effective in enabling the prevention of opioid misuse. Sufficient training and provider engagement with system features were found to be important, too. Providers' specialties are also closely associated with perceived EHR effectiveness. Providers who reported being burned out were less likely to see EHRs as effective.</p><p>EHR system satisfaction is likely both a cause and an effect of provider perceptions that EHRs can be used to prevent opioid misuse. Satisfied providers are more likely to see their EHR system as effective in preventing opioid misuse, and providers who see it as effective are more likely to report satisfaction. This close association between satisfaction and perceptions of effectiveness is not surprising given previous empirical studies of the UTAUT that link performance expectancy and effort expectancy&#8212;both of which include elements of satisfaction&#8212;to behavioral intention to use an EHR system (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">Archer &amp; Cocosila, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">Hamid &amp; Cline, 2013</xref>).</p><p>Effort expectancy, or perceived ease of use, is an important component of the UTAUT that directly relates to the quality of training. In this study, training was found to be a key factor related to perceptions of EHR effectiveness. Respondents were asked both whether their initial training prepared them well and whether ongoing training was sufficient. While both variables were found to be correlated with perceived EHR effectiveness in preventing opioid misuse, ongoing training showed a much stronger association than initial training. This makes sense, given that many of the features used to prevent opioid misuse and addiction (e.g., dosage calculators, dashboards, and decision support tools) are less likely to be a focus of initial training and more likely to be something that providers incorporate into their practice as they become more familiar with the system. This finding highlights the importance of ongoing training in optimizing the potential benefit of EHRs in clinical settings, both for preventing opioid misuse and for addressing other issues that require the use of more advanced EHR system features. The findings that ongoing training and provider satisfaction with systems are both closely associated with perceptions that EHRs are an effective tool in preventing opioid misuse suggest that ongoing training produces more capable users who become more satisfied with their EHR systems as expertise continues to increase.</p><p>While providers who had been practicing for fewer years were more likely to perceive EHRs as effective in preventing opioid misuse, no statistically significant association was found between providers' years of experience using their EHR system and perceived effectiveness. This finding is consistent with other studies in which the UTAUT has been applied to provider use of EHRs, where age was shown to play a moderating role but experience was not (<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">Venkatesh et al., 2011</xref>). Age effects in the UTAUT hold across providers because younger providers are more likely to have interacted with EHR systems in professional school and are more likely than older providers to feel comfortable adopting EHR systems and, more specifically, using advanced features that target opioid misuse.</p><p>In terms of experience not being a moderating factor for provider use of EHRs but being a moderator for adoption of other technologies to which the UTAUT has been applied, Venkatesh and colleagues and others have hypothesized that EHR systems are more disruptive to routines and processes than many other technologies, so years of experience alone (as opposed to factors such as age, EHR-specific training, and level of engagement with system features) is unlikely to affect whether providers perceive EHRs to be effective, even years into implementation (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">Ellis et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">Meigs &amp; Solomon, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">Rathert et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">Venkatesh et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>While not every EHR system has the same features, and some may be more effective if they have additional modules, the majority have standard features concerning opioid misuse detection, including charting of the clinical provider's impressions of a patient's misuse potential, access to prescription drug monitoring programs, laboratory tests or toxicology screens, and physical examination findings from previous providers (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">Ellis et al., 2019</xref>). Additional modules can contain provider alerts if multiple opioid prescriptions are written by different providers, if patients try to use an electronic narcotic prescription at multiple pharmacies, and for current lists of medications that providers can review before issuing a new pain management prescription (<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">Venkatesh et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p>Without a clear diagnosis of opioid use disorder or patterns of opioid misuse as identified by ICD-10 codes and in provider notes, patients may not be getting effective pain management and can be overprescribed opioids. The effectiveness of EHRs is dependent on providers' ability to screen and diagnose misuse and effectively chart this information (<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">Thiesset et al., 2020</xref>). Not all EHR systems are equal, and ease of use may determine whether this information is properly recorded and used by other prescribing providers and thus affects whether providers perceive the EHR as an effective tool in preventing opioid misuse.</p><sec><title>Study Limitations</title><p>This study was limited by a lack of multiple questions regarding opioid misuse and EHRs as tools for prevention as well as questions about specific features of tools. Key demographic variables found in previous studies to play a role in EHR adoption were also missing (e.g., gender and age), so this study was unable to fully explore those important factors. The sample was self-selected from KLAS partner organizations and therefore was not necessarily a representative sample, which may be a source of bias. This was a large national survey; however, providers at individual centers or using different operating systems could have different perceptions regarding EHR use. Also, participants who responded with the neutral option were grouped with those who did not agree EHRs were helpful. While this is an appropriate way to analyze Likert scale data, the analysis might change depending on how the respondents are categorized.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>Understanding providers' perceptions of EHR effectiveness is critical for behavior change because the outcome of reducing prescription opioid misuse depends upon their willingness to adopt and apply new technology to standardized routines. This understanding highlights a potential preventive strategy that could have a pronounced positive effect on the identification of opioid misuse in clinical settings.</p><p>If providers are satisfied with their EHR system and receive ongoing training on its use, they will be more likely to use these features in preventing opioid misuse. Healthcare managers should increase their efforts to address these specific issues as they work to expand the meaningful use of EHRs in the United States.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Archer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cocosila</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A comparison of physician pre-adoption and adoption views on electronic health records in Canadian medical practices</article-title>. <source>Journal of Medical Internet Research</source>, <volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>e57</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>e57</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/jmir.1726</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21840835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3222163</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Averitt</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slovis</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tariq</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vawdrey</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perotte</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Characterizing non-heroin opioid overdoses using electronic health records</article-title>. <source>JAMIA Open</source>, <volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>77</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>86</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jamiaopen/ooz063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32607490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7309230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bicket</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pronovost</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Prescription opioid analgesics commonly unused after surgery: A systematic review</article-title>. <source>JAMA Surgery</source>, <volume>152</volume>(<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>1066</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1071</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2017.0831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28768328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5701659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kritz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zavala</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Evaluation of an electronic medical record system at an opioid agonist treatment program</article-title>. <source>Journal of Addiction Medicine</source>, <volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>96</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>101</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ADM.0000000000000018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24562402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3962043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jean</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoag</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freedman-Weiss</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Healy</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>K. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Association of lowering default pill counts in electronic medical record systems with postoperative opioid prescribing</article-title>. <source>JAMA Surgery</source>, <volume>153</volume>(<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>1012</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1019</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2018.2083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30027289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6583068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Leon-Casasola</surname><given-names>O. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bickler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassidy</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chittenden</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manworren</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCarberg</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perkal</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suresh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sluka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strassels</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Management of postoperative pain: A clinical practice guideline from the American Pain Society, the American Society of Regional Anesthesia and Pain Medicine, and the American Society of Anesthesiologists' Committee on Regional Anesthesia, Executive Committee, and Administrative Council</article-title>. <source>Journal of Pain</source>, <volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>131</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>157</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpain.2016.02.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26827847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colton</surname><given-names>I. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahern</surname><given-names>T. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacLean</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lahiri</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alef</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinthorsson</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertges</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Postoperative opioid prescribing patterns and use after vascular surgery</article-title>. <source>Vascular Medicine</source>, <volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>63</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>69</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1358863X18807540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30449260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shofer</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halpern</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meisel</surname><given-names>Z. F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perrone</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Association between electronic medical record implementation of default opioid prescription quantities and prescribing behavior in two emergency departments</article-title>. <source>Journal of General Internal Medicine</source>, <volume>33</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>409</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>411</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-017-4286-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29340937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5880773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dornan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinyopornpanish</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiraporncharoen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashmi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dejkriengkraikul</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angkurawaranon</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Utilisation of electronic health records for public health in Asia: A review of success factors and potential challenges</article-title>. <source>Biomed Research International</source>, <volume>2019</volume>, <fpage>7341841</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2019/7341841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31360723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6644215</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dowell</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haegerich</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>CDC guideline for prescribing opioids for chronic pain&#8212;United States, 2016</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>, <volume>315</volume>(<issue>15</issue>), <fpage>1624</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1645</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2016.1464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26977696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6390846</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Electronic Health Record Association</collab>. (<year>2018</year>). <source>CDC opioid guideline: Implementation guide for electronic health records</source>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ehra.org/sites/ehra.org/files/EHRA-CDC-Opioid-Guideline-Implementation-Guide-for-EHRs.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ehra.org/sites/ehra.org/files/EHRA-CDC-Opioid-Guideline-Implementation-Guide-for-EHRs.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Genes</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma'ayan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Predicting opioid dependence from electronic health records with machine learning</article-title>. <source>BioData Mining</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13040-019-0193-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30728857</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6352440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gagnon</surname><given-names>M.-P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simonyan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghandour</surname><given-names>E. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Godin</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Labrecque</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ouimet</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rousseau</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Factors influencing electronic health record adoption by physicians: A multilevel analysis</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Information Management</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>258</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>270</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2015.12.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagemeier</surname><given-names>N. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Introduction to the opioid epidemic: The economic burden on the healthcare system and impact on quality of life</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Managed Care</source>, <volume>24</volume>(<issue>10</issue><supplement>Suppl.</supplement>), <fpage>S200</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>S206</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29851449</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamid</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cline</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Providers' acceptance factors and their perceived barriers to electronic health record adoption</article-title>. <source>Online Journal of Nursing Informatics</source>, <volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ojni.org/archive.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://ojni.org/archive.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedegaard</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mini&#241;o</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Drug overdose deaths in the United States, 1999&#8211;2018</article-title>. <source>National Center for Health Statistics Data Brief, No. 356</source>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data/databriefs/db356-h.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data/databriefs/db356-h.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCall</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cattabriga</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smalley</surname><given-names>E. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Using controlled substance receipt patterns to predict prescription overdose death</article-title>. <source>Pharmacology</source>, <volume>101</volume>(<issue>3&#8211;4</issue>), <fpage>140</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>147</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000484667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29248915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bogdan</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dart</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Active surveillance of abused and misused prescription opioids using poison center data: A pilot study and descriptive comparison</article-title>. <source>Clinical Toxicology</source>, <volume>45</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>144</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>151</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15563650600981137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17364631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahler</surname><given-names>Z. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Musey</surname><given-names>P. I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>A. N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strachan</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shufflebarger</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Effect of a &#8220;no superuser opioid prescription&#8221; policy on ED visits and statewide opioid prescription</article-title>. <source>Western Journal of Emergency Medicine</source>, <volume>18</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>894</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>902</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5811/westjem.2017.6.33414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28874942</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5576626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keasberry</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>A. I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Staib</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashby</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Going digital: A narrative overview of the clinical and organisational impacts of eHealth technologies in hospital practice</article-title>. <source>Australian Health Review</source>, <volume>41</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>646</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>664</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/AH16233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28063462</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolodny</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Courtwright</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreiner</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eadie</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>The prescription opioid and heroin crisis: A public health approach to an epidemic of addiction</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Public Health</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>559</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>574</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-publhealth-031914-122957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25581144</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lingren</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadhasivam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsolo</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Electronic medical records as a replacement for prospective research data collection in postoperative pain and opioid response studies</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Medical Informatics</source>, <volume>111</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2017.12.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29425633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5808990</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lowenstein</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grande</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perrone</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashburn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Impact of a state opioid prescribing limit and electronic medical record alert on opioid prescriptions: A difference-in-differences analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of General Internal Medicine</source>, <volume>35</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>662</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>671</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-019-05302-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31602561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7080923</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manchikanti</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Therapeutic opioids: A ten-year perspective on the complexities and complications of the escalating use, abuse, and nonmedical use of opioids</article-title>. <source>Pain Physician</source>, <volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue><supplement>Suppl.</supplement>), <fpage>S63</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>S88</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18443641</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>March</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scholl</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dversdal</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Use of electronic health record simulation to understand the accuracy of intern progress notes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Graduate Medical Education</source>, <volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>237</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>240</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4300/JGME-D-15-00201.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27168894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4857515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meigs</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Electronic health record use a bitter pill for many physicians</article-title>. <source>Perspectives in Health Information Management</source>, <volume>13</volume>(<issue>Winter</issue>), <fpage>1d</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4739443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26903782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Sources of misused prescription opioids and their association with prescription opioid use disorder in the United States: Sex and age differences</article-title>. <source>Substance Use &amp; Misuse</source>, <volume>55</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>928</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>936</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10826084.2020.1713818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31975639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7166157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Preuss</surname><given-names>C. V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalava</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <source>Prescription of controlled substances: Benefits and risks</source>. <publisher-name>StatPearls Publishing</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Price-Haywood</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harden-Barrios</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burstain</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Intelligent clinical decision support to improve safe opioid management of chronic noncancer pain in primary care</article-title>. <source>Ochsner Journal</source>, <volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>30</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5855418/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5855418/</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29559866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5855418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rathert</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mittler</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fleig-Palmer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Seven years after meaningful use: Physicians' and nurses' experiences with electronic health records</article-title>. <source>Health Care Management Review</source>, <volume>44</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>30</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/hmr.0000000000000168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28614166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiesset</surname><given-names>H. F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schliep</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valentin</surname><given-names>V. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gren</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Porucznik</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Opioid misuse and dependence screening practices prior to surgery</article-title>. <source>Journal of Surgical Research</source>, <volume>252</volume>, <fpage>200</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>205</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jss.2020.03.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32283333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8668076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Venkatesh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malicki</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawk</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Onofrio</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinsman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Assessing the readiness of digital data infrastructure for opioid use disorder research</article-title>. <source>Addiction Science &amp; Clinical Practice</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>24</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13722-020-00198-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32650817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7350566</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Venkatesh</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sykes</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>, January 4&#8211;7). <source>&#8220;Just what the doctor ordered&#8221;: A revised UTAUT for EMR system adoption and use by doctors</source> [conference session]. 44th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences, Kauai, HI, <publisher-loc>United States</publisher-loc>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/HICSS.2011.1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kariisa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seth</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>H. T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Drug and opioid-involved overdose deaths&#8212;United States, 2017&#8211;2018</article-title>. <source>Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report</source>, <volume>69</volume>(<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>290</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>297</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6911a4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32191688</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7739981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kazanji</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Narayan</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paudel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falatko</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoichet</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maddens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Comparison of accuracy of physical examination findings in initial progress notes between paper charts and a newly implemented electronic health record</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association</source>, <volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>140</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>144</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jamia/ocw067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27357831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7654088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zandieh</surname><given-names>S. O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon-Flannery</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuperman</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langsam</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaushal</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Challenges to EHR implementation in electronic-versus paper-based office practices</article-title>. <source>Journal of General Internal Medicine</source>, <volume>23</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>755</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>761</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-008-0573-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18369679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2517887</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>