<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Saudi Med J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Saudi Med J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2699</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">saudimedj</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SAMJDI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Saudi Medical Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0379-5284</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1658-3175</issn><issn-l>0379-5284</issn-l><publisher><publisher-name>Saudi Medical Journal</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12010501</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12010501.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12010501</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12010501</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40254329</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15537/smj.2025.46.4.20240999</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">SaudiMedJ-46-4-398</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Emergency patients with mild elevations of serum lipase and acute pancreatitis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7994-3412</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Althunayyan</surname><given-names initials="SM">Saqer M.</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS, SBEM</degrees><xref rid="a1" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alali</surname><given-names initials="AK">Abdulmajed K.</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref rid="a1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alanazi</surname><given-names initials="LK">Laila K.</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref rid="a1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alkhalifah</surname><given-names initials="SS">Salma S.</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref rid="a1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mashdali</surname><given-names initials="EM">Emad M.</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref rid="a1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malabarey</surname><given-names initials="MA">Mohammed A.</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref rid="a1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>AlAsiri</surname><given-names initials="SA">Saad A.</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS, SBEM</degrees><xref rid="a1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mobrad</surname><given-names initials="AM">Abdulmajeed M.</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref rid="a1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><aff id="a1">
<italic toggle="yes">From the Accidents and Trauma Department (Althunayyan), Prince Sultan Bin Abdulaziz College for Emergency Medical Services, King Saud University; from the Emergency Department (Alali, Alanazi, Alkhalifah, Mashdali), Dr. Sulaiman Al-Habib Hospital Al-Ryyan; from the Emergency And Urgetn Care Department (AlAsiri), Health Holding Company; from the Department of Emergency Medicine (Malabarey) College of Medicine, King Saud University; and from the Department of Emergency Medical Services (Mobrad), Prince Sultan Bin Abdulaziz College for Emergency Medical Services, King Saud University, Riyadh, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia.</italic>
</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><italic toggle="yes">Address correspondence and reprint request to: Dr. Saqer M. Althunayyan, Accidents and Trauma Department, Prince Sultan Bin Abdulaziz College for Emergency Medical Services, King Saud University, Riyadh, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. E-mail: <email>salthunayyan@ksu.edu.sa</email></italic>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>46</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">486925</issue-id><fpage>398</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>02</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>22</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-04-22 10:25:27.857"><day>22</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#169; Saudi Medical Journal</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access journal and articles published are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (CC BY-NC). Readers may copy, distribute, and display the work for non-commercial purposes with the proper citation of the original work.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="smj-46-4-398.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><sec id="s1"><title>Objectives:</title><p>To estimate the incidence of AP and determine potential predictors and the outcomes. Elevated lipase level of &lt;3 times the upper limit of normal (ULN) cause diagnostic confusion for acute pancreatitis (AP).</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Methods:</title><p>A multicenter, 6-year retrospective study enrolled adult patients who were detected with lipase level of 80&#8211;240 IU/L in the Emergency Department (ED). The Revised Atlanta Classification was used to identify AP within 72 hour (hr) from the first ED visit.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results:</title><p>Of 1082 patients, 68 (6.3%) had AP, 393 (36.3%) were hospitalized, 64 (6%) required intensive care unit admission, and 2 (0.2%) died. Most AP cases were confirmed using computed tomography CT; 47 (69.1%), followed by repeated lipase level 15 (22.1%) and ultrasound 14 (20.6%). Alcohol exhibited the highest adjusted odds ratio of predicting AP (3.9&#8211;45.6), followed by white blood cell count (1.340&#8211;6.222), male gender (1.451&#8211;4.308), and higher lipase level (1.009&#8211;1.02). Among AP cases, 11.8% required ICU admission and 1 died within 72&#160;hr. Chronic heart disease, obesity, fever, and tachycardia were associated with these critical outcomes.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Among the study sample, 6.3% were diagnosed with AP. Most of the cases confirmed by CT and alcohol was the strongest risk factor in predicting AP. A prediction score system to stratify AP risk when lipase is &lt;3 ULN is warranted.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords:</title><kwd>acute pancreatitis</kwd><kwd>lipase</kwd><kwd>mild elevations</kwd><kwd>emergency</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p><bold>A</bold>cute pancreatitis (AP), which is an acute inflammatory process of the pancreas, is one of the prevalent emergency diseases causing hospitalization.<sup><xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Globally, the incidence of AP has increased over time and is associated with significant morbidity and mortality.<sup><xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Early diagnosis and appropriate severity stratification can prevent disease progression.<sup><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> The Revised Atlanta Classification indicated meeting 2 out of three criteria to confirm AP diagnosis.<sup><xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> These criteria included acute upper pancreatic pain, elevated serum lipase that is more than triple the upper limit of normal (ULN), and any radiological finding consistent with AP. An elevated lipase test is carried out to diagnose AP with a sensitivity of 80%&#8211;91% if it is increased more than 3 times the ULN.<sup><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Lipase starts to increase within 4-8 hours (hr) of the onset of AP symptoms, peaks at 24&#160;hr, and returns to normal within 8-14 days.<sup><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></p><p>An elevated lipase can be clinically categorized for acute upper abdominal pain according to the elevation as a significant elevation of &gt;3 (ULN), which is diagnostic of AP, and high lipase but &lt;3 ULN are less specific and may not be indicative of AP.<sup><xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> The uncertainty of this category causes diagnostic confusion in emergencies, where rapid decision-making is crucial.<sup><xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> Emergency physicians may discharge the patient and try to arrange close monitoring of repeat lipase, whereas others admit the patient for further evaluation.<sup><xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> Some experts recommended doing a computed tomography (CT) contrast study before the discharge to detect pancreatitis, thereby resolving this diagnostic dilemma.<sup><xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Computed tomography is &gt;90% sensitive and specific to diagnosing AP but is not always available in the Emergency Department (ED) or urgent care clinic and is still not free from risks.<sup><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> Therefore, others recommend the use of abdominal ultrasound (US) first, and if AP is not confirmed, then CT will be performed.<sup><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup></p><p>A retrospective study for nonspecific abdominal pain was conducted to identify appropriate investigation of patients with mild elevations of amylase or lipase of &lt;3 ULN in the outpatient clinic.<sup><xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> After extensive radiological investigation and according to the cost-effectiveness balance the study recommend against the investigations for these group patients. However, this study was conducted for outpatient clinics and may not apply to emergency patients with acute abdominal pain.</p><p>Another retrospective study for a mild increase in amylase/lipase levels investigates the assumption that lower enzyme levels indicate a milder form of acute early pancreatitis.<sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> The patients were categorized according to their initial high lipase levels (lipase: &#8804;3 UNL and &gt;3 UNL). They revealed that the severity and progression of AP are independent of the initial level of elevated amylase/lipase. They found that some clinicians frequently overlooked or underestimated the severity of patients with lipase levels of &#8804;3 UNL.<sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup></p><p>Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) complicated the interpretation of lipase. Previous studies revealed that COVID-19 is associated with Hyperlipasemia and the majority of them &lt;3 ULN.<sup><xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> It was not clinically associated with AP despite this high prevalence of hyperlipasemia among patients with COVID-19.</p><p>This study is to estimate the percentage of those patients who end up diagnosed with AP and to risk stratify them by evaluating the possible predictors guiding safer dispositions as the literature contains no conclusive evidence regarding the diagnostic approach of the emergency patient with mildly elevated lipase.</p><sec id="s6"><title>Methods</title><p>This study was conducted in accordance with the principles of the Helsinki Declaration, and the Institutional Review Board (IRB) of Alhabib Medical group approved this study. This study did not involve any experiments on human or animal participants. This is a multicenter, retrospective cohort, observation study of 6 years from January 2017 to January 2023, from the ED of the 4 branches of Dr. Sulaiman Al-Habib Medical Group (HMG) in Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</p><p>The data was retrieved by information technology representatives of our institute as they extracted data for all adult patients (&#8805;18 years) with mild elevated lipase of 80&#8211;240 IU/L in the ED from the electronic medical records using the hospital automation system. In our institution, the ULN for lipase was 80 IU/L, whereas 240 IU/L represents 3 ULN, which is consistent with another diagnostic study cut-off14. Our data collector gathered the remaining data by accessing the medical records electronic system (VIDA) by determining the medical record number date and time of the visit and gender. We exclude known cases of patients with chronic pancreatitis or recurrent attacks of pancreatitis (defined as &gt;2 episodes of AP), patients without abdominal pain, abnormal high liver function tests, or patients discharged against medical advice from ED. The abnormal high liver enzyme is defined as elevated alanine transaminase (ALT) of more than triple or elevated direct bilirubin of &gt;50% of high total bilirubin with tripling alkaline phosphatase (ALP) and gamma-glutamyl transferase (ggt), consistent with obstructive jaundice.</p><p>Data, including patient demographics, comorbidity, chief complaint, signs and symptoms, laboratory results, CT findings within 72&#160;hr, US findings within 72&#160;hr, mortality rate within 72&#160;hr, repeated lipase within 72&#160;hr, and disposition, were obtained. All of our data collectors were physicians to improve the quality of data collection and the interpretation of the final diagnosis and clinical course. Additionally, we standardize them with an online data collection sheet (Google Sheets), and all the data collectors read the research proposal and attend online meetings to explain the data collection process. The primary investigator frequently monitored the data collection process to notify about any extreme result or missed important element.</p><p>The outcome of focus is the highest repeated lipase level within 72&#160;hr and radiological finding within 72&#160;hr. We label the patient as a confirmed case of AP according to the Revised Atlanta Classification if the repeated lipase of &gt;240 or the US or CT finding is consistent with AP. All the radiological report is performed by the radiologist consultant in our institute.</p><sec id="s6-1"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data was analyzed using Statistical Package for the Social Sciences version 26 (IBM Corp., Armonk, N.Y., USA). The descriptive statistics were expressed as frequency, percentages, mean, and standard deviation (SD). The Chi-square test was conducted to find out the association between pancreatitis and pancreatitis respect to categorical demographic of the patients, while independent sample t-test used to find out continues data and logistic regression was presented by crude odd ratio and adjusted odd ratio, with a 95% confidence interval (CI) for both tests. A value of <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Results</title><p>This study analyzed 1082 patients, of whom 6.3% had AP according to The Revised Atlanta Classification. Additionally, 36.4% of patients were admitted to the hospital, 6% required ICU admission within 72 hours, and 0.2% died. It is evident that the mean age of the whole study population was 46 years, and the gender distribution revealed slightly higher number of male patients (male: 52.1%; females: 47.9%). Moreover, <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows that 27.8% patients had diabetes mellitus, 24.9% had hypertension, 5.2% had chronic heart disease, 6.5% had ischemic heart disease, 6.4% had chronic renal disease, and 21.1% had gallstone.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="t1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>- Comparison of demographic, clinical, and laboratory variables between patients with and without acute pancreatitis.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total patients (N=1082)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pancreatitis (n=68)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-pancreatitis (n=1014)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, (mean, SD) years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.0 (16.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67, 46.2 (16.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">843, 45.2 (16.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.779</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">564 (52.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (72.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">515 (50.8%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">518 (47.9%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (27.9%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">499 (49.2%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes mellitus</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">243 (26.9%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (26.9%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225 (22.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.993</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214 (23.8%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (23.9%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198 (23.8%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.988</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic heart disease</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (5.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (5.6%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.713</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischemic heart disease</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (6.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (6.6%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.493</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic renal disease</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (6.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (6.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.777</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyperlipidemia</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103 (11.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (12.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (11.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.829</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol consumption</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (1.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (9.8%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (0.6%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GLP-1 agonist medicines</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (2.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (2.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.634</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Covid-19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (1.6%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (1.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.710</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, (mean, SD), (n=157)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.0 (6.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(29.8, 6.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(28.9, 6.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.745</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature of &lt;36&#176;C or &gt;38&#176;C</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (6.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (15.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (6.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulse rate of &gt;109 beats/min</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (5.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (5.90%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (5.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.847</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Required narcotic analgesia</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118 (13.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (19.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 (12.7%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.116</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epigastric tenderness</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">583 (67.8%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (78.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">533 (67.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.066</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vomiting</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">444 (49.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (50.7%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">410 (49.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.832</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Required &#8805; 2 antiemetic&#8217;s</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (6.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (6.6%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.494</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abdominal guarding or rigidity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (3.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (3.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.876</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rebound tenderness</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (5.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (5.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.830</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipase level N, (mean, SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1082, (123.5, 42.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68, (156.0, 46.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(121.4, 41.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amylase level N, (mean, SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">237, (99.3, 43.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29, (100.0, 51.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208, (99.2, 42)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.925</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gallbladder stone</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(228, 21.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(15, 22.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(213, 21.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.387</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood glucose (mean, SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68, (150.7, 132.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (90.4, 101.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64, (154.4, 134)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.353</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ph of &lt;7.35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (33.8%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (20.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (35.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.235</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBC N, (mean, SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1041, (8.5, 3.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66, (10.1, 4.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">975, (8.3, 3.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBC of &lt;3 or &gt;14.9 mm<sup>3</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (5.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (13.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (4.7%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST IU/L N, (mean, SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">929, (30.2, 32.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61, (33.5, 39.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">868, (30.0, 34.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.429</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT IU/L N, (mean, SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">883, (31.6, 39.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58, (43.5, 78.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">825, (30.8, 34.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDH U/LN, (mean, SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13, (200.3, 65.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2, (171.0, 69.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11, (205.6, 67.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.516</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcium N, (mean, SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121, (1.4, 0.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20, (1.5, 0.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101, (1.4, 0.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.387</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hematocrit of &lt;30% or &gt;45.9%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">309 (28.6%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (30.9%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">288 (28.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.661</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea of &gt;8.92 mmol/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (10.7%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.9%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91 (11.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital admission</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">393 (36.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (80.9%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">338 (33.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Required ICU admission</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (6.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (11.8%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (5.6%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mortality</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, (1.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>SD: standard division, BMI: body mass index, WBC: white blood cells, AST: aspartate transaminase ALT: alanine transaminase LDH: alkaline phosphatase, ICU: intensive care unit</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p><xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> illustrates the number of patients and confirmed AP cases. The statistics indicated that 47 (17.7%) of 265 patients tested by CT exhibited pancreatitis, only 2% of patients using US had AP, and 6.7% patients undergoing repeated lipase tests demonstrated pancreatitis. A total of 7 (10.3%) cases were diagnosed solely by repeated lipase.</p><fig position="float" id="f1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>- Distribution of the number of patients with confirmed acute pancreatitis according to diagnostic tests. CT: computed tomography, US: ultrasound</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="smj-46-4-398_1.jpg"/></fig><p><xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows an analysis of the comparison of AP predictors with the Chi-square test and independent sample t-test. Male patients represent 52.1% (n=564 of 1082) of the cases, including 72.1% (n=49) in the pancreatitis group and 50.8% (n=515) in the non-pancreatitis group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.05). Lipase level had a mean (SD) of 123.5 (42.6), and the comparison across the two groups in terms of outcomes demonstrated a high statistically significant difference in a mean (SD) of 156.0 (46.4) for the pancreatitis group and 121.4 (41.4) for the non-pancreatitis group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.05). White blood cell (WBC) count was statistically different in both continuous and categorical variables with a cut-of value of &lt;3 or &gt;14.9&#160;mm<sup><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>. White blood cell comparison indicated a mean (SD) of 10.1 (4.4) mm<sup><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> in the pancreatitis group and 8.3 (3.4) mm<sup><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> in the non-pancreatitis group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.05), and the comparison of categorical variables revealed 13.2% (n=9) of patients with pancreatitis and 4.7% (n=48) with no pancreatitis (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>= 0.002). This is the opposite with urea, with a cut-off value of 8.92 mmol/L. Urea demonstrated a mean (SD) of 6.0 (6.5) mmol/L. The comparison revealed a mean (SD) of 4.2 (1.9) mmol/L in the pancreatitis group and 6.1 (6.7) mmol/L in the non-pancreatitis group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.05), and categorical analysis indicated that 1.9% (n = 1) of patients had pancreatitis, whereas 11.3% (n = 91) had no pancreatitis (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.030).</p><p>The comparison across for ALT between the two groups revealed significant differences with a mean (SD) of 43.5 (78.4) in the pancreatitis group and 30.8 (34.7) in the non-pancreatitis groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.016). Calcium demonstrated a statistical difference in categorical, with a cut-off value of 8 g/dL (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.05), but urea indicated an association in those without AP. AP, statistically significant differences for hospital admission requiring intensive care unit (ICU) admission, and mortality indicated <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values of 0.000, 0.037, and 0.023, respectively.</p><p><xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents associated factors using logistic regression with outcomes being binary: pancreatitis or non-pancreatitis. Male was considered a statistically significant factor (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.001) with a crude odd ratio (OR) of 2.499 and 95% CI of 1.451&#8211;4.304. The OR of male was 2.5 (95% CI: 1.451&#8211;4.308) after adjusting for age. Remarkably, alcohol was associated with pancreatitis, with the highest crude OR of 17.956 and the adjusted OR of 13.267. Pulse rate exhibited a statistically significant risk factor as continuous variables (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.030, crude OR: 1.019, 95% CI: 1.002&#8211;1.036; adjusted OR: 1.020, and 95% CI:1.003&#8211;1.037). Moreover, lipase level (continuous) demonstrated a high statistically significant risk factor (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.000 for both crude and adjusted ORs). WBCs were highly statistically significant for continuous analysis, with a cut-off of &lt;3.0 or &gt;14.9&#160;mm<sup><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>, a crude OR of 1.116 (95% CI: 1.055&#8211;1.180), and an adjusted OR of 1.103. Furthermore, WBCs with a cut-off of &lt;3.0 or &gt;14.9&#160;mm<sup><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> indicated a statistically significant association with an OR of 3.070 and an adjusted OR of 2.887.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="t2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>- Comparison of AP predictor using logistic regression.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude OR (95% CI)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjusted OR (95% CI)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (continues)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.002 (0.987&#8211;1.017)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.779</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.002 (0.987&#8211;1.016)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.868</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (&#8805;60), years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.953 (0.517&#8211;1.756)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.876</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.791 (0.288&#8211;2.170)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.649</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.499 (1.451&#8211;4.304)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.500 (1.451&#8211;4.308)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol consumption</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.956 (5.310-60.720)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.267(3.86&#8211;45.575)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COVID-19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.801 (0.217&#8211;14.974)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.586</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.836 (0.216&#8211;15.57)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.578</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI kg/m<sup>2</sup> (continues)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.917&#8211;1.135)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.712</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.027 (0.918&#8211;1.149)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.638</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI of &gt;30&#160;kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.744 (0.179&#8211;3.089)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.684</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.702 (0.165&#8211;2.984)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.632</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vomiting</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.055 (0.641-1.736)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.832</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.116 (0.675-1.846)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.669</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epigastric tenderness</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.762 (0.957-3.246)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.812 (0.981-3.349)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.058</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature (continues)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.028 (0.912&#8211;1.160)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.647</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.023 (0.908&#8211;1.154)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.707</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature of &lt;36&#176;C or &gt;38&#176;C</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.005 (0.582&#8211;6.909)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.271</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.064 (0.591&#8211;7.208)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.256</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulse rate of &gt;109 beats/min</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.109 (0.389&#8211;3.158)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.847</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.131 (0.394&#8211;3.243)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.819</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipase IU/L (continues)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.014 (1.009&#8211;1.020)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.015 (1.009&#8211;1.02)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amylase level U/L (continues)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.999 (0.990&#8211;1.008)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.891</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0.991&#8211;1.009)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.942</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gallbladder stone</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.678 (0.389&#8211;1.184)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.172</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.694 (0.396&#8211;1.215)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.201</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose mg/dL(continues)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.995 (0.985&#8211;1.005)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.352</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.995 (0.985&#8211;1.004)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.295</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose of &gt;200&#160;mg/dL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032 (0.004&#8211;0.243)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021 (0.003&#8211;0.174)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PH of &lt;7.35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.458 (0.123&#8211;1.704)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.244</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.441 (0.119&#8211;1.630)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.220</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBC10<sup>9</sup>/L (continues)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.116 (1.055&#8211;1.180)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.103 (1.042&#8211;1.168)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WB (&lt;3or&gt;14.9 10<sup>9</sup>/L)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.070 (1.437&#8211;6.557)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.887 (1.340&#8211;6.222)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST of &gt;100 IU/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.002 (0.995&#8211;1.008)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.641</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.003 (0.995&#8211;1.008)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.610</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT IU/L (continues)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.004 (1.0&#8211;1.009)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.004 (0.999&#8211;1.009)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.106</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcium of &lt;8 g/dL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.141 (0.484&#8211;2.691)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.764</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.047 (0.423&#8211;2.592)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.921</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bicarbonate&lt;21mEq/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.135 (0.170&#8211;0.271)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.135</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.477 (0.173&#8211;1.315)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.153</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hematocrit of &lt;30% or &gt;45.9%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.126(0.661&#8211;1.918)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.661</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.788 (0.447&#8211;1.390)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.411</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea mmol/L (continues)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.857 (0.751&#8211;0.978)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.758 (0.637&#8211;0.902)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea of &gt;8.92 mmol/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.148 (0.020&#8211;1.086)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.112 (0.015&#8211;0.856)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pleural effusion</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.213 (0.729&#8211;6.714)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.161</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.334 (0.732&#8211;7.443)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.152</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>AP: acute pancreatitis, CI: confidence interval, OR: odds ratio, BMI: body mass index, WBC: white blood cells, COVID: coronavirus disease, AST: aspartate transaminase ALT: alanine transaminase LDH: alkaline phosphatase, ICU: intensive care unit</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p><xref rid="t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> represents an analysis of mortality or ICU admission predictor within 72&#160;hr among AP cases, categorizing them into 2 groups of mortality or ICU admission (critical group) and no mortality or ICU admission (non-critical group). Chronic heart disease was observed in 4.5% (n=3 of 68) of the cases, including 22.2% in the critical group and 1.7% in the non-critical group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.006). Furthermore, pulse rate indicated a statistically significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.025), including 22.2% of patients in the critical group and 3.4% in the non-critical group. Finally, body mass index (BMI) (continuous analysis) exhibited a strong statistically significant difference in mortality or ICU admission within AP (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.041, with a mean [SD] of 41.8 [0.1] in the critical group and 28.1 [5.0] in the non-critical group.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="t3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>- Predictor of mortality or ICU admission within 72&#160;hr among acute pancreatitis cases.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total patients (N=68)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No mortality or requirement of ICU (n=59)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mortality or ICU admission (n=9)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (mean, SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (46.1, 16.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59(45.7,16.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (48.8, 10.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.589</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (72.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (69.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (88.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.227</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (27.9%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (30.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11.1%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes mellitus</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (26.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (25.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (33.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.616</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (23.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (20.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (44.4.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.112</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic heart disease</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.7%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (22.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischemic heart disease</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.293</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic renal disease</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.293</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyperlipidemia</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (12.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (12.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.920</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol consumption</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (9.8%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (9.6%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.889</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gallbladder stone</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (22.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (22.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (22.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.796</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (mean,+SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(29.8+6.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (28.1+5.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (41.8+0.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI of &gt;30&#160;kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (50.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (42.9%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (100.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.285</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulse rate &gt;109 beats/min</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (5.9%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (22.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systolic blood pressure mmHg (mean, SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66(137.0+21.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57(135.2+19.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (148.1+28.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.090</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature of &gt;38&#176;C</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (5.9%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (22.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Required narcotic analgesia</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (19.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (20.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Required two or more antiemetics</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.489</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abdominal guarding or rigidity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2.9%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.575</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipase level IU/L(Mean, SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68(156.1,46.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59(153.0,47.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (175.6, 39.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.177</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amylase level U/L (Mean, SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (100.0, 51.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (97.8, 51.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (110.6, 55.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.622</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rebound tenderness</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.514</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PH of &lt;7.35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (31.6%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (25.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (66.7%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.154</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBC 10<sup>9</sup>/L (mean, SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (10.0, 4.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (9.8, 4.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (11.5, 6.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.317</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBC 10<sup>9</sup>/L (&lt;3.0 or &gt;14.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (10.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (8.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (22.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.206</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST IU/L (Mean, SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61(33.4,39.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54(31.3,38.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (50.1, 49.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.244</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST of &gt;100 IU/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.293</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT IU/L (mean, SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (43.5, 78.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52(37.0,61.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (99.9, 166.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcium of &lt;8 g/dL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (29.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (28.8%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (33.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.782</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bicarbonate of &lt;21mEq/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (7.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (8.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.364</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hematocrit of &lt;30% or &gt;45.9%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (30.9%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (30.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (33.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.864</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea mmol/L (Mean, SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4.2, 1.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (4.1, 2.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4.8, 1.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.374</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea (&gt;8.92) mmol/L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.7%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.694</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pleural effusion</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (7.8%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (6.8%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.495</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>ICU: intensive care unit, SD: standard division, BMI: body mass index, WBC: white blood cells, AST: aspartate transaminase ALT: alanine transaminase LDH: alkaline phosphatase, ICU: intensive care unit</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Discussion</title><p>This is the first study to describe patients with mild lipase elevation in ED. This multicenter study revealed that 1082 patients met our inclusion-exclusion criteria with a mean initial lipase level of 123.5 &#177; 42.6 IU/L. Their mean age was 46 years and approximately one-third of patients were admitted to the hospital (n=393) and 6.3% were diagnosed with AP (n=68).</p><p>Most AP cases were confirmed using CT (69.1%), followed by repeated lipase levels (22.1%) and US (20.6%). From a different perspective, AP was diagnosed in 17.7% of patients who underwent CT scans, 7% of those who had repeated laboratory tests, and 2% of patients who did ultrasounds. This indicated the higher yield of CT in the ED compared to other diagnostic modalities, not only confirming AP faster but also rolling out other deferential that cause high lipase. We concur with the case series of eight AP cases in the ED with completely normal initial lipase as they revealed that serially trending lipase was less likely to yield to diagnostic level, and they recommended early CT.<sup><xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> Remarkable finding in the current study about the CT utilization in which only (24.5%) of the patients underwent CT within 72 hours for their abdominal pain, which is below what was reported in a cross-sectional study which found (83%) confirmed AP cases had CT performed in ER or during their hospital course.<sup><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> Therefore, we recommend against admitting these cases for monitoring the lipase for the diagnosis while CT is feasible.</p><p>Among AP cases, 55 (80%) were admitted from the first ED visit, indicating that approximately 20% of AP cases were prematurely discharged without picking the appropriate diagnosis and the diagnosis was made in the follow-up clinic or after repeated ED visits within 72&#160;hr. This confirms that some clinicians still underestimate the cases with mildly elevated lipase levels.<sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup></p><p>We determined predictors that are associated with AP to be male gender, alcohol intake, higher lipase level, abnormal WBC count, and higher ALT. Male gender and alcohol intake are risk factors for pancreatitis, and our result revealed an adjusted OR of 1.387&#8211;4.153 for the male gender, whereas the highest adjusted OR was associated with alcohol intake at 3.9&#8211;45.617. Gallbladder stone is another known risk factor for biliary pancreatitis, and this explains our negative correlation as we excluded cases with labs consistent with obstructive jaundice. <xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows that the clinical presentation failed to predict AP, which can be explained by the nonspecific signs and symptoms mimicking AP and the symptomatic management that may mask the diagnosis. A retrospective study from Thailand was conducted to predict AP without relying on lipase or diagnostic radiological tests.<sup><xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> Consistent with our study, they revealed that clinical manifestations of the surgical abdomen, such as guarding and rebound tenderness, cannot predict AP, whereas a history of alcohol drinking increases the likelihood of the diagnosis. However, they demonstrated that pain characteristics and vomiting indicate a diagnosis that was not found in our study, which may be attributed to different inclusion and exclusion criteria. Our study agreed with others that amylase did not help and failed to add diagnostic value to lipase levels.<sup><xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup></p><p>Among our 68 confirmed AP cases, 8 (11.8%) required ICU admission and only 1 patient died within 72&#160;hr. Interestingly, this percentage is higher than 2 studies conducted in Saudi Arabia reported an ICU admission rate of 5%&#8211;9%.<sup><xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> This may be attributed to the clinician&#8217;s decision when the lipase of &lt;3 ULN delayed the full management or hesitated to do the workout determining the etiology that causes disease progression. In other respects, this may be attributed to the lower threshold of ICU admission in the private sector. However, recent multicenter international studies revealed the rate of ICU admission at 7.6&#8211;13.3%.<sup><xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup></p><p>Regarding our patients with AP, we revealed an association between ICU admission and chronic heart disease and obesity, fever, and heart rate of &#8805;109 bpm. Furthermore, an earlier literature revealed that obesity increase the risk of worse outcome among AP cases.<sup><xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Thus, we recommend lowering the threshold for ICU admission for those patients with one or more of these risk factors or considering starting the management empirically if confirming the diagnosis is subject to delay. The remaining classical risk factors for deterioration that were adapted from various severity scoring systems failed to predict ICU admission. We highly recommend establishing a special prediction score system for risk stratification of AP with lipase of &lt;3 ULN.</p><p>This research has some limitations despite being a multicenter study. First, all of the study centers were located in one city in Saudi Arabia (Riyadh), which affected the generalizability of the study results. We faced difficulty collecting data in several aspects due to the retrospective nature of the study. Specifically, not all patients had regular follow-ups within 72 hours at our institutes. Therefore, we cannot definitively label the 6.3% confirmed cases of pancreatitis as the true incidence rate, which may actually be higher. Additionally, some emergency department documentation was poor or not fully detailed regarding clinical presentation, and not all important laboratory results were ordered during the initial visit. Furthermore, we did not specify the staging of reported comorbidities, especially in relation to chronic renal disease and whether the patient was on dialysis, which could affect lipase interpretation. Finally, the uniqueness of this emergency department study challenges us to place our findings in the context of comparison in order to validate our recommendations.</p><p>In conclusion, this study found that among emergency patients with mild lipase elevations (&lt;3 ULN), 6.3% were diagnosed with AP. Given the higher diagnostic yield of CT, we recommend integrating CT scans into the diagnostic protocols for those patients. Alcohol was the strongest risk factor that predicted the diagnosis. Among the confirmed AP cases 11.8% required ICU admission within 72&#160;hr. We urge clinicians to lower the threshold for ICU admissions in patients with risk factors for deterioration, and emphasizing the need for a proactive approach in managing AP. We recommend establishing a special prediction score system to risk stratify AP when the lipase &lt;3 ULN.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>
<italic toggle="yes">This study was supported by the College of Prince Sultan Bin Abdulaziz for Emergency Medical Services, Deanship of Scientific Research, King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia. We would like to express our appreciation to the Deanship of Scientific Research at King Saud University.The authors acknowledge Enago (Crimson Interactive Inc.) for providing professional English language editing services for this manuscript.</italic>
</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>
<boxed-text position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Disclosure.</bold> Authors have no conflict of interests, and the work was not supported or funded by any drug company.</p></boxed-text>
</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tenner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vege</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sheth</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Conwell</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>American college of gastroenterology guidelines: management of acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source><year>2024</year>; <volume>119</volume>: <fpage>419</fpage>-<lpage>437</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38857482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14309/ajg.0000000000002645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bawazeer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nathens</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Clinical practice guideline: management of acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Can J Surg</source><year>2016</year>; <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>128</fpage>-<lpage>140</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27007094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1503/cjs.015015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4814287</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Recent Advances in diagnosis and severity assessment of acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Prague Med Rep</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>121</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>-<lpage>86</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14712/23362936.2020.6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32553091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mederos</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reber</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Girgis</surname><given-names>MD.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>325</volume>: <fpage>382</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33496779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2020.20317</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sepp&#228;nen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>Puolakkainen P.</given-names><surname>Classification</surname></string-name></person-group>, <article-title>severity assessment, and prevention of recurrences in acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Scandinavian Journal of Surgery</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>-<lpage>58</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32192420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1457496920910007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alyahya</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alalshaikh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Altaweel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alsaleh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alsaeed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Somily</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alotaibi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alaqeel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Al Mehlisi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abuguyan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Altuwaijri</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The prevalence of simultaneously ordering amylase and lipase for diagnosing pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Emerg Med Int</source><year>2023</year>; <volume>2023</volume>: <fpage>3988278</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37811499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2023/3988278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10551519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vege</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Clinical manifestations and diagnosis of acute pancreatitis [Internet]. UpToDate; 2024 [cited 2024 Sep 12]</article-title>. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.uptodate.com/contents/clinical-manifestations-and-diagnosis-of-acute-pancreatitis" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.uptodate.com/contents/clinical-manifestations-and-diagnosis-of-acute-pancreatitis</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vege</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Approach to the patient with elevated serum amylase or lipase [Internet]. UpToDate; 2024 [cited 2024 Sep 12]</article-title>. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.uptodate.com/contents/approach-to-the-patient-with-elevated-serum-amylase-or-lipase" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.uptodate.com/contents/approach-to-the-patient-with-elevated-serum-amylase-or-lipase</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Metri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>VK.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Predicting the severity of acute pancreatitis: Current approaches and future directions</article-title>. <source>Surg Open Sci</source><year>2024</year><month>Mar</month><day>27</day>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.sopen.2024.03.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11033200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38650599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stiffler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jowell</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Branch</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pappas</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Extensive investigation of patients with mild elevations of serum amylase and/or lipase is &#8216;low yield&#8217;</article-title>. <source>Can J Gastroenterol</source><year>2002</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>849</fpage>-<lpage>854</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12522473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2002/836012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lankisch</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burchard-Reckert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lehnick</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Underestimation of acute pancreatitis: patients with only a small increase in amylase/lipase levels can also have or develop severe acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Gut</source><volume>44</volume>: <fpage>542</fpage>-<lpage>544</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10075962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/gut.44.4.542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1727444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pochapin</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kothari</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Hyperlipasemia in absence of acute pancreatitis is associated with elevated D-dimer and adverse outcomes in COVID 19 disease</article-title>. <source>Pancreatology.</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>698</fpage>-<lpage>703</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33741267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pan.2021.02.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7929790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McNabb-Baltar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>DX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Grover</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Redd</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hathorn</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Lipase elevation in patients with COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>115</volume>: <fpage>1286</fpage>-<lpage>1288</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32496339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14309/ajg.0000000000000732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7288768</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Esmaili</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mehramuz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maroufi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ghasemi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pourlak</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Diagnostic value of amylase and lipase in diagnosis of acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Biochem Pharmacol J</source><year>2017</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>389</fpage>-<lpage>394</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sanjeev</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ghatak</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Normal lipase acute pancreatitis: A case report and brief review of literature</article-title>. <source>Emerg Med J</source><year>2022</year>; <fpage>18</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ullah</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thode</surname><suffix>Jr</suffix>, <given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>A J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morley</surname>, <given-names>EJ.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The role of emergency department computed tomography in early acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Am J Emerg Med</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>92</fpage>-<lpage>95</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33866269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajem.2021.04.026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Joo</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Risk factors of acute pancreatitis in young adults: a nationwide population-based cohort study in South Korea</article-title>. <source>Pancreas</source><year>2025</year>; <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>e39</fpage>-<lpage>e44</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39074055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MPA.0000000000002394</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liengswangwong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Preechakul</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yuksen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jenpanitpong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tienpratarn</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Watcharakitpaisan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Clinical prediction score for early diagnosis of acute pancreatitis in emergency departments</article-title>. <source>Open Access Emerg Med</source><year>2022</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>-<lpage>366</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35924030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/OAEM.S371237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9342661</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>OZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bhayana</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Lipase or amylase for the diagnosis of acute pancreatitis?</article-title><source>Clin Biochem</source><year>2017</year>; <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1275</fpage>-<lpage>1280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28720341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.clinbiochem.2017.07.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alyahya</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alalshaikh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Altaweel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alsaleh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alsaeed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Somily</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>The prevalence of simultaneously ordering amylase and lipase for diagnosing pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Emerg Med Int</source><year>2023</year>; <volume>2023</volume>: <fpage>3988278</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37811499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2023/3988278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10551519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alshahrani</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Durrani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mostafa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nasser</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Rising incidence of acute pancreatitis in the Southern region of Saudi Arabia, a retrospective study</article-title>. <source>Pak J Surg</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>36</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aljiffry</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alhazmi</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alqam</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Takieddin</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abulfaraj</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiological features of acute pancreatitis (AP): largest single-center, cohort study in the western region of Saudi Arabia</article-title>. <source>Cureus</source><year>2023</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>e38445</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37273380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.38445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10234453</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sternby</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bolado</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Canaval-Zuleta</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marra-L&#243;pez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hernando-Alonso</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>del-Val-Anto&#241;ana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Determinants of severity in acute pancreatitis: a nation-wide multicenter prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Ann Surg</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>270</volume>: <fpage>348</fpage>-<lpage>355</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29672416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/SLA.0000000000002766</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>A 5-year retrospective cohort study: epidemiology, etiology, severity, and outcomes of acute pancreatitis</article-title>. <source>Pancreas</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>1161</fpage>-<lpage>1167</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32897999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MPA.0000000000001637</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ince</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seven</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ko&#231;han</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kiremit&#231;i</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Y&#305;ld&#305;z</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>&#350;ent&#252;rk</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The course of acute pancreatitis in patients with different BMI groups</article-title>. <source>Pancreatology</source><year>2022</year>: <volume>22</volume>; <fpage>348</fpage>-<lpage>355</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35322789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pan.2022.03.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Visceral adipose tissue predicts severity and prognosis of acute pancreatitis in obese patients</article-title>. <source>Hepatobiliary Pancreat Dis Int</source><year>2024</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>458</fpage>-<lpage>462</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37648552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.hbpd.2023.08.014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>