<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2757</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cureus</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10120882</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10120882.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10120882</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10120882</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37090286</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.36529</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Ophthalmology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Psychiatry</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Topiramate-Induced Aqueous Misdirection in a Nanophthalmic Eye</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names initials="A">Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names initials="JR">John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names initials="A">Ahsan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names initials="K">Kiersten</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paroya</surname><given-names initials="S">Shahnawaz</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahesh</surname><given-names initials="S">Sankara</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Ophthalmology, Boston University Chobanian &amp; Avedisian School of Medicine, Boston, USA </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Ophthalmology, New York Medical College, Valhalla, USA </aff><aff id="aff-3">
<label>3</label>
Biology, The University of Kansas, Kansas City, USA </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Ahsan Hussain <email>ahsan893@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>22</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">430120</issue-id><elocation-id>e36529</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>22</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>22</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-04-24 12:10:12.393"><day>24</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023, Hussain et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Hussain et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="cureus-0015-00000036529.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/62099-topiramate-induced-aqueous-misdirection-in-a-nanophthalmic-eye">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/62099-topiramate-induced-aqueous-misdirection-in-a-nanophthalmic-eye</self-uri><abstract><p>A 51-year-old female was referred to the emergency department with a one-day history of severe right eye pain, blurry vision, and conjunctival injection. A review of past ocular history was notable for nanophthalmos and narrow angles with patent peripheral iridotomies. Anterior segment exam findings were consistent with aqueous misdirection and a review of medications indicated recent topiramate initiation for headaches and depression. The acute attack was initially controlled with medical management and plans for future surgical intervention were made. Although ocular screening prior to initiation of topiramate is not recommended, this case highlights the importance of pre-screening in a patient with a pre-existing condition such as nanophthalmos. Additionally, this case addresses the ocular side effects of anti-depressants and the emerging relationship between glaucoma and depression. Appropriately addressing these issues and coordinating care with behavioral health providers has the potential to prevent optic nerve damage and loss of vision.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>ophthalmology</kwd><kwd>ciliary body</kwd><kwd>angle closure</kwd><kwd>glaucoma</kwd><kwd>topiramate</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Topiramate is an anti-epileptic drug that has been used off-label for the treatment of migraines, as well as some mood disorders including biopolar disorder and depression. One of the known side effects of topiramate is acute angle-closure glaucoma thought to be caused by ciliochoroidal effusion with forward displacement of the lens-iris diaphragm and anterior chamber shallowing, resulting in acute myopia and angle-closure glaucoma [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].&#160;We present the first reported case of topiramate-induced&#160;angle-closure glaucoma in a nanophthalmic eye. Although ocular screening prior to initiation of topiramate is not recommended, this case highlights the importance of pre-screening in a patient with a pre-existing condition such as nanophthalmos, which is often associated with varying degrees of angle-closure glaucoma.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case presentation</title><p>A 51-year-old female with a past medical history of depression and migraine presented to the emergency department with a one-day history of severe right eye pain, blurry vision, and conjunctival injection. Past ocular history was notable for nanophthalmia in both eyes with axial lengths of 17.29 right eye (OD) and 16.96 left eye (OS). On an earlier exam, the patient&#8217;s best-corrected visual acuity was 20/50 with a refractive error of +9.00 diopters&#160;in both eyes. The patient had narrow angles and had undergone prophylactic laser peripheral iridotomies (LPIs). She was seen in the neurology clinic one month prior to this presentation and was started on topiramate 25mg for her migraine headaches and depression.</p><p>The patient&#8217;s best-corrected visual acuity was counting fingers in the right eye and 20/50 in the left eye.&#160;Her intraocular pressure (IOP) was 65 and 12 in the right and left eye, respectively. Anterior segment exam showed 3+ conjunctival injection and mild corneal edema with a severely narrow anterior chamber depth of 0.69 mm (Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Pentacam photograph of the right eye demonstrating narrow angles and a severely shallow anterior chamber with a depth of .69mm. </title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="cureus-0015-00000036529-i01.jpg"/></fig><p>In addition, there was iridocorneal touch and 360 degrees of peripheral anterior synechiae with anterior displacement of the lens-iris diaphragm. The posterior segment exam showed a cup to disc ratio of 0.2 with normal appearing fovea and peripheral retina. In the setting of elevated intraocular pressure, anterior chamber shallowing, with a patent peripheral iridotomy, her exam findings were consistent with aqueous misdirection likely due to ciliary effusion and rotation of the ciliary body from topiramate&#160;[<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The offending agent was subsequently discontinued and she was treated to lower the IOP with intravenous acetazolamide, intravenous mannitol, and multiple rounds of topical glaucoma medications, including dorzolamide, timolol, and brimonidine. A cycloplegic was administered to facilitate posterior rotation of ciliary body and lens-iris diaphragm. After stabilizing her IOP, a vitrectomy and lensectomy were performed to provide definitive management.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Topiramate-induced secondary angle-closure glaucoma is a rare side effect of a common medication. Despite initial approval as an anti-epileptic drug, neurologists and psychiatrists frequently prescribe this agent for the treatment of migraine headaches, depression, and bipolar disorder. This drug is well-documented to cause anterior rotation of the ciliary body and decrease zonular tension with forward displacement of the lens [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The pathogenesis of this aqueous misdirection is likely due to excess fluid accumulation in the ciliary body and choroid due to the increased permeability of ciliochoroidal vasculature [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Routine ocular screening prior to starting topiramate is not traditionally recommended.&#160;However, a nanophthalmic eye has a higher baseline risk for angle closure due to a narrow anterior chamber, as well as an increased risk of developing uveal effusions due to the thickening of the sclera. Scleral thickening of up to twice the normal depth with atypical collagen fibrils results in the obstruction of venous vortex drainage and a decreased uveoscleral outflow [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In our case, a crowded anterior segment, baseline risk of uveal effusions, and simultaneous use of Topiramate fashioned the perfect storm for angle closure.</p><p>Initial management of aqueous misdirection involves lowering the intraocular pressure with aqueous suppressants, employing cycloplegic drops to aid in posterior rotation of the ciliary body and lens, and using hyperosmotic agents to reduce vitreous volume. In the early stage of glaucoma, laser peripheral iridotomy (LPI) can help eliminate the pupillary block before the occurrence of peripheral anterior synechiae develops [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].&#160;While the initial treatment is through medical management, studies show a recurrence rate as high as 100% with medical therapy alone [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Definitive treatment includes surgical and can involve a lensectomy and vitrectomy to create a unicameral eye. Operating with a shallow or flat anterior chamber in nanophthalmic eyes presents a unique challenge even in the hands of skilled ophthalmologists. A shallow anterior chamber creates a difficult environment to perform capsulorhexis and routine maneuvers without damaging intraocular structures. Decompressing the vitreous through a surgical vitrectomy can greatly aid in increasing anterior chamber size and decrease positive pressure prior to phacoemulsification [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].&#160;Other surgical treatments that have been advocated include irido-zonulo-hyaloidectomy with or without a vitrectomy [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Additional considerations include creating scleral windows to enhance uveoscleral outflow and to decrease the potential for uveal effusions and expulsive choroidal hemorrhage during cataract surgery.</p><p>Though this case demonstrates the association between topiramate and aqueous misdirection, it also highlights the pressing relationship between glaucoma patients and clinical depression. Glaucoma can be a debilitating disease that significantly impacts the quality of life of an individual. Recent studies have consistently demonstrated the alarmingly high rate of depression in glaucoma patients [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>-<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Studies show as high as 57% of patients with primary open-angle (POAG) meeting clinical parameters for depression and glaucoma patients face a 1.7x increased risk of developing depression [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Moreover, the likelihood of clinical depression is positively correlated with glaucoma severity [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Stamatiou et al. performed a systematic review of the literature and found certain risk factors such as age, female gender, advanced-stage disease, faster visual loss progression, and the lifestyle of patients were proven to increase the prevalence of depression in glaucoma patients [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>This unfortunate reality needs to be recognized and care must be coordinated with the patient&#8217;s behavioral health provider. While topiramate is believed to induce ciliochoroidal swelling and anterior movement of the lens, other antidepressant medications can cause primary angle closure through alternative mechanisms. The current standard of treatment for clinical depression involves initiating a selective serotonin-reuptake inhibitor (SSRI). This class of medications can trigger iris dilation and induce pupillary block through anticholinergic properties. Patients with narrow angles should prophylactically receive LPIs prior to starting SSRI, and high-risk eyes such as nanophthalmic eyes should not be prescribed an angle-closure-provoking medication. A careful review of systemic medications and medical history by the ophthalmologist can help coordinate care with the patient&#8217;s neurologists and behavioral health providers [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. An open dialogue regarding mental health in glaucoma patients and appropriate referral to qualified professionals needs to be implemented routinely to not only coordinate care for the patient&#8217;s eyes but overall well-being.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>We present the first reported case of topiramate-induced angle-closure glaucoma in a nanophthalmic eye. In addition to reviewing the management of aqueous misdirection, our case highlights the emerging relationship between glaucoma and clinical depression. As the preponderance of contemporary anti-depressive agents can induce angle closure glaucoma, careful attention must be placed on high-risk patients and treatment needs to be coordinated with the patient&#8217;s mental health provider.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Human Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study</p></fn></fn-group><notes><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></fn-group></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Mechanism of topiramate-induced acute-onset myopia and angle closure glaucoma</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><volume>137</volume><year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14700673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0002-9394(03)00774-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Topiramate induced acute angle closure glaucoma</article-title><source>Open Ophthalmol J</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Aminlari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>East</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quillen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><volume>2</volume><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19478906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2174/1874364100802010046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2687928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Topiramate-Induced Angle Closure</article-title><source>EyeRounds.org. April</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Quist</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fortenbach</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2019</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://webeye.ophth.uiowa.edu/eyeforum/cases/283-topiramate-induced-angle-closure.htm">https://webeye.ophth.uiowa.edu/eyeforum/cases/283-topiramate-induced-angle-closure.htm</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Abnormal collagen fibrils in nanophthalmos: a clinical and histologic study</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugino</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wanner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>108</fpage><volume>106</volume><year>1999</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0002-9394(98)00302-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9933017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>Glaucoma</article-title><source>Review of Ophthalmology, 3rd Edition</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trattler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><year>2023</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.elsevier.com/books/review-of-ophthalmology/unknown/978-0-323-39057-6">https://www.elsevier.com/books/review-of-ophthalmology/unknown/978-0-323-39057-6</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Management of glaucoma in patients with nanophthalmos</article-title><source>Eye (Lond)</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yalvac</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Satana</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozkan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eksioglu</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>838</fpage><lpage>843</lpage><volume>22</volume><year>2008</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/sj.eye.6702742">https://doi.org/10.1038/sj.eye.6702742</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17293784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.eye.6702742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Outcomes of different management options for malignant glaucoma: a retrospective study</article-title><source>Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Debrouwere</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stalmans</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Calster</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spileers</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeyen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stalmans</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><volume>250</volume><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21858468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00417-011-1763-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The treatment of malignant glaucoma in nanophthalmos: a case report</article-title><source>BMC Ophthalmol</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>54</fpage><volume>18</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29471807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12886-018-0714-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5824548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Surgical management of malignant glaucoma: a retrospective analysis of fifty eight eyes</article-title><source>Eye (Lond)</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Balekudaru</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choudhari</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rewri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>947</fpage><lpage>955</lpage><volume>31</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28257136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/eye.2017.32</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5518837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Anxiety, depression, and quality of life in Turkish patients with glaucoma</article-title><source>Psychol Rep</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tastan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iyigun</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acikel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><volume>106</volume><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20524533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2466/pr0.106.2.343-357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The association between glaucoma and risk of depression: a nationwide population-based cohort study</article-title><source>BMC Ophthalmol</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>146</fpage><volume>18</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29929494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12886-018-0811-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6013853</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Psychiatric manifestations in patients with primary open-angle glaucoma (Article in German)</article-title><source>Ophthalmologe</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Erb</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Batra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Br&#246;mer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#252;ller-Schaaf</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiel</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>639</lpage><volume>90</volume><year>1993</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/8124026/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/8124026/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8124026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Anxiety and depression are more prevalent in primary angle closure glaucoma than in primary open-angle glaucoma</article-title><source>J Glaucoma</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><volume>24</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/IJG.0000000000000025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24240874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Depression and quality of life in patients with glaucoma: a cross-sectional analysis using the Geriatric Depression Scale-15, assessment of function related to vision, and the Glaucoma Quality of Life-15</article-title><source>J Glaucoma</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Skalicky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>546</fpage><lpage>551</lpage><volume>17</volume><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18854731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/IJG.0b013e318163bdd1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Depression in glaucoma patients: a review of the literature</article-title><source>Semin Ophthalmol</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stamatiou</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kazantzis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Theodossiadis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatziralli</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><volume>37</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33822676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/08820538.2021.1903945</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>