<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.--><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3211</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jamasd</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JAMA Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2168-622X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2168-6238</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>JAMA Network</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10483381</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10483381.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10483381</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10483381</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37672238</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2023.3145</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">yoi230067</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="domain" specific-use="print"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Investigation</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="online-first"><subject>Online First</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="allowCommenting"><subject>Comments</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Gabapentin Use Among Individuals Initiating Buprenorphine Treatment for Opioid Use Disorder</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="headline">Gabapentin Use With Buprenorphine Initiation for Opioid Use Disorder</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Gabapentin Use With Buprenorphine Initiation for Opioid Use Disorder</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names initials="MS">Matthew S.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="yoi230067aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="KY">Kevin Y.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="yoi230067aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tardelli</surname><given-names initials="VS">Vitor S.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MS</degrees><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="yoi230067aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="yoi230067aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fidalgo</surname><given-names initials="TM">Thiago M.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="yoi230067aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buttram</surname><given-names initials="ME">Mance E.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="yoi230067aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grucza</surname><given-names initials="RA">Richard A.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="yoi230067aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="yoi230067aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="yoi230067aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Psychiatry, Washington University in St Louis, School of Medicine, St Louis, Missouri</aff><aff id="yoi230067aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Psychiatry, Universidade Federal de S&#227;o Paulo, S&#227;o Paulo, Brazil</aff><aff id="yoi230067aff3"><label>3</label>Translational Addictions Research Laboratory, Centre for Addictions and Mental Health, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada</aff><aff id="yoi230067aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Health, Human Performance and Recreation, University of Arkansas, Fayetteville</aff><aff id="yoi230067aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Family and Community Medicine, St Louis University, St Louis, Missouri</aff><aff id="yoi230067aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Health and Outcomes Research, St Louis University, St Louis, Missouri</aff><author-notes><title>Article Information</title><p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> July 5, 2023.</p><p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published Online:</bold> September 6, 2023. doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2023.3145</uri></p><corresp id="yoi230067cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Matthew S. Ellis, PhD, Department of Psychiatry, Washington University in St Louis, School of Medicine, 660 S Euclid Ave, Box 8134, St Louis, MO 63110 (<email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ellism@wustl.edu">ellism@wustl.edu</email>).</corresp><p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Dr Xu had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. Drs Ellis and Xu contributed equally as co&#8211;first authors.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Concept and design:</italic> Ellis, Xu, Grucza.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> All authors.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Ellis, Xu.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> Ellis, Grucza.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Statistical analysis:</italic> Xu, Grucza.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Obtained funding:</italic> Grucza.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Xu, Grucza, Buttram.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Supervision:</italic> Ellis, Tardelli, Fidalgo.</p><p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Drs Ellis and Buttram reported receiving grant funding from the Denver Health and Hospital Authority outside the submitted work. Dr Fidalgo reported receiving a scholarship from Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cient&#237;fico e Tecnol&#243;gico (National Council for Scientific and Technological Development) outside the submitted work. Dr Grucza reported consulting for Janssen Pharmaceuticals without compensation and reviewing grants for the National Institutes of Health and Washington University in St Louis outside the submitted work. No other disclosures were reported.</p><p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> This project was supported by grant R21 DA044744 from the National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA; principal investigators [PIs]: Dr Grucza and Laura Bierut, MD). Effort for some personnel was supported by grant T32 DA015035 from the NIDA (Dr Xu; PIs: Kathleen Bucholz, PhD, and Jeremy Goldbach, PhD) and the Researched Abuse, Diversion, and Addiction-Related Surveillance System, the property of Denver Health and Hospital Authority, a political subdivision of the State of Colorado; these grants did not fund the analyses of the Merative MarketScan Commercial and Multi-State Medicaid Database data performed by Dr Xu. The Center for Administrative Data Research (CADR) is supported in part by the Washington University Institute of Clinical and Translational Sciences via grant UL1 TR002345 from the National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences of the National Institutes of Health.</p><p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The funders had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p><p><bold>Meeting Presentation:</bold> This work was presented at the 85th Annual Meeting of the College on Problems of Drug Dependence; June 19, 2023; Denver, Colorado.</p><p content-type="data-sharing-statement"><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> See <xref rid="note-YOI230067-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>.</p><p><bold>Additional Contributions:</bold> Davida Schiff, MD, MSc, Massachusetts General Hospital, assisted with the creation of the study&#8217;s forest plots. Laura Bierut, MD, Washington University in St Louis, provided thoughtful insights that contributed to this study. Jeremy Goldbach, PhD, and Kathleen Bucholz, PhD, the Transdisciplinary Training in Addictions Research T32 Program of Washington University in St Louis, obtained funding to support effort for personnel (Dr Xu). Matthew Keller, MS, John Sahrmann, MS, and Dustin Stwalley, MA, the CADR of Washington University in St Louis, provided technical support for the MarketScan Databases, and data acquisition, management, and storage. These individuals were not compensated for this work.</p></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-09-06T10:00"><day>6</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>80</volume><issue>12</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">444880</issue-id><fpage>1269</fpage><lpage>1276</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>06</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>06</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-09-06 00:25:58.463"><day>06</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright 2023 American Medical Association. All Rights Reserved.</copyright-statement></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jamapsychiatry-e233145.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamapsychiatry-e233145.pdf">jamapsychiatry-e233145.pdf</self-uri><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/archpsyc/fullarticle/10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2023.3145"/><abstract abstract-type="key-points"><title>Key Points</title><sec id="ab-yoi230067-1"><title>Question</title><p>What is the prevalence of gabapentin use in individuals filling buprenorphine prescriptions for opioid use disorder (OUD), and what are its associations with drug-related poisoning?</p></sec><sec id="ab-yoi230067-2"><title>Findings</title><p>In this case-control study with crossover analysis of 109&#8201;407 individuals diagnosed with OUD initiating buprenorphine treatment, gabapentin use was not associated with hospitalization for drug-related poisoning after accounting for between-person confounding.</p></sec><sec id="ab-yoi230067-3"><title>Meaning</title><p>These findings contribute to the evidence base on the use of gabapentin as an adjunctive medication in individuals filling buprenorphine with OUD.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" specific-use="electronic"><p>This case-control study with crossover analysis assesses the differences between patients receiving and not receiving gabapentin alongside buprenorphine in the treatment of opioid use disorder and the drug-related poisoning risk associated with gabapentin.</p></abstract><abstract><sec id="ab-yoi230067-4"><title>Importance</title><p>Gabapentin prescriptions have drastically increased in the US due to off-label prescribing in settings such as opioid use disorder (OUD) treatment to manage a range of comorbid conditions and withdrawal symptoms, despite a lack of evidence.</p></sec><sec id="ab-yoi230067-5"><title>Objective</title><p>To assess the purpose and associated risks of off-label gabapentin use in OUD treatment.</p></sec><sec id="ab-yoi230067-6"><title>Design, Setting, and Participants</title><p>This retrospective recurrent-event case-control study with a crossover design used administrative claims data from MarketScan Commercial and Multi-State Medicaid databases from January 1, 2006, to December 31, 2016. Individuals aged 12 to 64 years with an OUD diagnosis and filling buprenorphine prescriptions were included in the primary analysis conducted from July 1, 2022, through June 1, 2023. Unit of observation was the person-day.</p></sec><sec id="ab-yoi230067-7"><title>Exposures</title><p>Days covered by filled gabapentin prescriptions.</p></sec><sec id="ab-yoi230067-8"><title>Main Outcomes and Measures</title><p>Primary outcomes were receipt of gabapentin in the 90 days after initiation of buprenorphine treatment and drug-related poisoning. Drug-related poisonings were defined using codes from <italic toggle="yes">International Classification of Diseases, Ninth Revision</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems, Tenth Revision</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="ab-yoi230067-9"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 109 407 patients were included in the analysis (mean [SD] age, 34.0 [11.2] years; 60 112 [54.9%] male). Among the 29 967 patients with Medicaid coverage, 299 (1.0%) were Hispanic, 1330 (4.4%) were non-Hispanic Black, 23 112 (77.1%) were non-Hispanic White, and 3399 (11.3%) were other. Gabapentin was significantly less likely to be prescribed to Black or Hispanic patients, and more likely to be prescribed to female patients, those with co-occurring substance use or mood disorders, and those with comorbid physical conditions such as neuropathic pain. Nearly one-third of persons who received gabapentin (4336 [31.1%]) had at least 1 drug-related poisoning after initiating buprenorphine treatment, compared with 13&#8201;856 (14.5%) among persons who did not receive gabapentin. Adjusted analyses showed that days of gabapentin use were not associated with hospitalization for drug-related poisoning (odds ratio, 0.98 [95% CI, 0.85-1.13]). Drug-related poisoning risks did not vary based on dosage.</p></sec><sec id="ab-yoi230067-10"><title>Conclusions and Relevance</title><p>Gabapentin is prescribed in the context of a myriad of comorbid conditions. Even though persons receiving gabapentin are more likely to have admissions for drug-related poisoning, these data suggest that gabapentin is not associated with an increased risk of drug-related poisoning alongside buprenorphine in adjusted analyses. More data on the safety profile of gabapentin in OUD settings are needed.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front></article></pmc-articleset>