<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Gland Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Gland Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2506</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">glandsurg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Gland Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2227-684X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2227-8575</issn><publisher><publisher-name>AME Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11635573</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11635573.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11635573</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11635573</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39678408</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/gs-24-330</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gs-13-11-2010</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Risk factors for surgical site infection following thyroid surgery: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names initials="X">Xuanwei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="afn2" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>#</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names initials="K">Kaiyuan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="afn2" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>#</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="afn2" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>#</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="L">Linpo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="F">Fan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names initials="S">Shuoying</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names initials="D">Dingcun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>The Fourth School of Clinical Medicine, Zhejiang Chinese Medical University</institution>, <institution content-type="dept">Hangzhou First People&#8217;s Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <country country="cn">China</country>;</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Oncological Surgery, Affiliated Hangzhou First People&#8217;s Hospital, School of Medicine</institution>, <institution>Westlake University</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <country country="cn">China</country>;</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="dept">College of Mathematical Medicine</institution>, <institution>Zhejiang Normal University</institution>, <addr-line>Jinhua</addr-line>, <country country="cn">China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="afn1"><p><italic toggle="yes">Contributions:</italic> (I) Conception and design: X Huang, D Luo; (II) Administrative support: Y Zhang, D Luo; (III) Provision of study materials or patients: X Huang, K Huang, Y Zhang, L Zhou, F Wu; (IV) Collection and assembly of data: X Huang, K Huang, Y Zhang, L Zhou, F Wu, S Qian, Y Cai; (V) Data analysis and interpretation: X Huang, K Huang, L Zhou, F Wu, S Qian, Y Cai; (VI) Manuscript writing: All authors; (VII) Final approval of manuscript: All authors.</p></fn><fn id="afn2" fn-type="equal"><label>#</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work as co-first authors.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><italic toggle="yes">Correspondence to:</italic> Dingcun Luo, BM. Department of Oncological Surgery, Affiliated Hangzhou First People&#8217;s Hospital, School of Medicine, Westlake University, No. 261, Huansha Road, Hangzhou 310006, China; College of Mathematical Medicine, Zhejiang Normal University, Jinhua, China. Email: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ldc65@zju.edu.cn">ldc65@zju.edu.cn</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>11</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">476911</issue-id><fpage>2010</fpage><lpage>2022</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-12-17 16:25:16.470"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>2024 AME Publishing Company. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>AME Publishing Company.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><italic toggle="yes">Open Access Statement:</italic> This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 International License (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0), which permits the non-commercial replication and distribution of the article with the strict proviso that no changes or edits are made and the original work is properly cited (including links to both the formal publication through the relevant DOI and the license). See: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="gs-13-11-2010.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Thyroid surgery is a common surgical procedure for the treatment of thyroid diseases, such as thyroid nodules, thyroid cancer, and hyperthyroidism. Despite significant advancements in surgical techniques and perioperative care, surgical site infection (SSI) remains a frequent postoperative complication, which can lead to prolonged hospital stays, increased medical costs, and decreased quality of life for patients. Identifying risk factors for SSI is crucial for developing effective prevention strategies. This study aimed to systematically investigate and quantify the incidence and risk factors associated with SSI following thyroid surgery through a meta-analysis and systematic review.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>A comprehensive search strategy was employed across major databases [PubMed, Web of Science, Embase, Cochrane Library, China Biology Medicine (CBM), China National Knowledge Infrastructure (CNKI), Wanfang Data] up to June 15, 2024. Additionally, we conducted a supplementary search for relevant literature up to October 4, 2024. Studies were selected based on stringent inclusion and exclusion criteria focusing on SSI risk factors in patients undergoing thyroid surgery. The methodological quality of eligible studies was critically appraised. Statistical analyses were conducted using Stata 15.1 with meta-analytic techniques to estimate means and standard deviations, and calculating odds ratio (OR) with 95% confidence interval (CI) using appropriate effect models. Publication bias was assessed using Egger&#8217;s test.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The systematic review and subsequent meta-analysis included nine studies (eight case-control and two cohort) involving a total of 127,467 patients, with 703 cases of postoperative SSI documented. Key findings indicated that prolonged surgical duration greater than 2 hours [OR =4.50; 95% CI: (2.74, 7.37); P&lt;0.001], presence of comorbidities [OR =1.91; 95% CI: (1.16, 3.15); P=0.01], age greater than 50 years [OR =1.81; 95% CI: (1.24, 2.64); P=0.002], incision length greater than 5 cm [OR =2.79; 95% CI: (1.92, 4.04); P&lt;0.001], lymph node dissection [OR =1.90; 95% CI: (1.28, 2.80); P=0.001], and male [OR =1.78; 95% CI: (1.38, 2.29); P&lt;0.001] were significant risk factors for SSI after thyroid surgery. Conversely, male gender did not present a statistically significant association with SSI risk.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Surgical duration greater than 2 hours, presence of comorbidities, age greater than 50 years, incision length greater than 5 cm, lymph node dissection, and male emerge as critical risk factors for SSI in patients recovering from thyroid surgery. However, the small number of included articles and the lack of differentiation between OR, risk ratio (RR), and hazard ratio (HR) are limitations of this analysis.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords: </title><kwd>Thyroid surgery</kwd><kwd>surgical site infection (SSI)</kwd><kwd>risk factors</kwd><kwd>meta-analysis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="sp1">the Zhejiang Medical and Health Science and Technology Plan Project</funding-source><award-id rid="sp1">No. 2022KY939</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="sp2">the Project of Medical Scientific and Technology Program in Hangzhou</funding-source><award-id rid="sp2">No. A20200821</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="ba" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Highlight box</title></caption><sec><title>Key findings</title><p>&#8226; This meta-analysis is about the incidence and risk factors associated with surgical site infection (SSI) following thyroid surgery. Several factors have been identified as significant risk factors for the development of SSI following thyroid surgery.</p></sec><sec><title>What is known and what is new?</title><p>&#8226; There is currently no consensus among researchers regarding which specific factors contribute to the development of SSI following thyroid surgery.</p><p>&#8226; Incorporating findings from relevant literature, our analysis concludes that surgical duration greater than 2 hours, presence of comorbidities, age greater than 50 years, incision length greater than 5 cm, lymph node dissection, and male are significant risk factors for the development of SSI following thyroid surgery.</p></sec><sec><title>What is the implication, and what should change now?</title><p>&#8226; These findings underscore the importance of enhanced monitoring and the application of focused preventive strategies during the perioperative period to reduce the risk of SSI.</p></sec></boxed-text><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Surgical site infection (SSI) ranks among the most prevalent categories of postoperative complications (<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), posing significant threats to patient safety and imposing substantial economic burdens on healthcare systems. A recent large-scale investigation into patients undergoing thyroid surgery affirmed that superficial SSIs are amongst the primary types of postoperative complications (<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Adhering to contemporary clinical guidelines (<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), prophylactic antibiotics are conventionally prescribed for class II, III, and IV incisions given their heightened risk of infection; in contrast, for class I incisions (defined as clean, lacking signs of infection or inflammation), which typically exhibit lower infection rates, guidelines recommend against the routine use of prophylactic antibiotics. Nonetheless, thyroid surgery, predominantly categorized as clean surgery with class I incisions, has seen of an unexpectedly high rate of prophylactic antibiotic utilization, reaching up to 50% (<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Specifically, SSI affecting thyroid surgery, characterized as infection at the surgical incision site or within deeper tissues, is acknowledged as a major complication of thyroidectomy, with reported incidence rates primarily ranging from 0.09% to 2.9% (<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). It is significant to note that, despite its classification as clean surgery, the incidence of SSI in thyroid surgery remains substantial, especially in light of the increasing prevalence of thyroid diseases and the resultant uptick in the frequency of thyroid procedures. SSI can precipitate complications such as wound dehiscence, which prolongs the healing timeline (<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Moreover, they contribute to extended hospital stays, augment healthcare expenses, and escalate the risks associated with systemic infections and other severe complications. Research indicates that the SSI rate for head and neck surgeries stands at 0.37%, yet each case entails an approximate additional hospitalization cost of $20,000 (<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Consequently, the adoption of effective preventive measures becomes indispensable for mitigating the incidence of SSI post-thyroid surgery. Clinicians engaged in thyroidectomies must remain vigilant regarding the risks of SSI and judiciously consider the administration of prophylactic antibiotics to strike a balance between infection control and antibiotic stewardship.</p><p>Acknowledging that SSI is a pivotal determinant of surgical success and patient outcomes, this study endeavors to systematically explore the incidence and potential risk factors of SSI following thyroid surgery through a meta-analysis and systematic review. The objectives of this research are to ascertain and quantify the incidence of SSI post-thyroid surgery and to delineate the multifaceted risk factors impacting SSI occurrence. The overarching aim is to furnish evidence-based guidance for clinical practice, optimize SSI prevention protocols, thereby alleviating the strain on healthcare resources and accelerating patient recovery timelines. We present this article in accordance with the MOOSE reporting checklist (available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://gs.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/gs-24-330/rc" ext-link-type="uri">https://gs.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/gs-24-330/rc</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Literature search</title><p>An extensive literature search was conducted across multiple databases including PubMed, Embase, Cochrane Library, Web of Science, China Biology Medicine (CBM), China National Knowledge Infrastructure (CNKI), and Wanfang Data. The search was finalized on June 15, 2024. Additionally, we conducted a supplementary search for relevant literatures up to October 4, 2024.</p><p>The search strategy specifically sought out cohort studies and case-control studies that incorporated multivariate analyses to investigate risk factors for SSI pertinent to thyroid surgery. Keywords combined with free-text terms were utilized for the search strategy: &#8220;thyroid&#8221;, &#8220;surgical site infection&#8221;, and &#8220;risk factors&#8221;. The supplementary search strategy used keywords in combination with free text terms: &#8220;thyroid&#8221;, &#8220;surgical site infection&#8221;, and &#8220;predictive factors&#8221;. EndNote 21 was utilized for literature management.</p></sec><sec><title>Inclusion and exclusion criteria</title><p>Inclusion criteria: (I) studies must adhere to the diagnostic criteria for SSI (<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). (II) Peer-reviewed case-control studies and cohort studies investigating risk factors for SSI in patients undergoing thyroid surgery are eligible for inclusion. The research must feature multivariate analysis of SSI risk factors. Primary outcome measure: results of multivariate risk factor analysis. Secondary outcome measure: incidence rate of SSI in patients who have undergone thyroid surgery. Exclusion criteria: conference abstracts, meta-analyses, protocols, letters to the editor, duplicate publications, systematic reviews, articles without full-text availability, studies lacking accessible data, and animal experiments will not be considered.</p></sec><sec><title>Data extraction</title><p>Data extraction was conducted by two independent reviewers, both of whom are thyroid surgeons with extensive clinical experience, who systematically screened the literature. This process involved reading titles, abstracts, and full texts to select studies according to the predetermined inclusion and exclusion criteria. For any studies where there was uncertainty regarding eligibility, consultation with pertinent experts was sought to resolve discrepancies. Throughout the screening procedure, strict adherence to the inclusion and exclusion criteria was maintained. Pertinent indicators were extracted from the studies, and a cross-checking mechanism was implemented to ensure the consistency of the data extracted from the literature. The main contents of the data extraction included the first author&#8217;s name, publication year, country of origin, study design, sample size, gender, and age demographics.</p></sec><sec><title>Literature evaluation criteria</title><p>The Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (NOS) (<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) was employed to assess the quality of the studies, evaluating three domains: selection of study groups (up to 4 points), comparability between groups (up to 2 points), and ascertainment of exposure or outcome (up to 3 points). Disagreements during the assessment by the two researchers were discussed until consensus was reached, with consultation of a third party if necessary. The total score ranges from 0 to 9 points, with scores &#8804;4 indicating low quality, 5&#8211;6 points indicating moderate quality, and &#8805;7 points indicating high quality.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Statistical analysis was conducted using Stata version 15.1. Risk estimates across studies, regardless of whether they were reported as odds ratio (OR), risk ratio (RR), or hazard ratio (HR), were uniformly described as ORs. A pooled OR and its 95% confidence interval (CI) were calculated. Based on the results of heterogeneity tests (Q-test) and the I<sup>2</sup> statistic, an appropriate model was chosen for the calculation of the combined OR. Sensitivity analyses were conducted by sequentially removing individual studies when I<sup>2</sup>&gt;50% to assess the robustness of the findings. If I<sup>2</sup>&gt;50%, a random-effects model was applied; if I<sup>2</sup>&#8804;50%, a fixed-effects model was used. Publication bias was assessed using Egger&#8217;s test, with a significance level &#945;=0.05. A P value &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Literature search and selection process</title><p>A comprehensive literature search was conducted in databases (PubMed, Web of Science, Embase, Cochrane Library, CBM, CNKI, and Wanfang Data) targeting cohort studies and case-control studies that featured multivariate analyses of risk factors for SSI following thyroid surgery. EndNote 21 was utilized for efficient literature management. The initial search identified 297 records, from which 130 duplicates were removed, leaving 167 unique records. Applying the exclusion criteria and reviewing titles and abstracts led to the preliminary selection of 13 studies. Upon full-text review, four articles were excluded: one with a study population of head and neck surgery patients (<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>); one without multifactorial analysis (<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>); one focusing on non-SSIs (NSSIs) (<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>); and one deemed unsuitable for inclusion due to the quality of the literature after discussion (<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). And supplement search results identified 41 records, from which five duplicate studies were removed, leaving 36 records, exclude studies that do not involve predictive or risk factors. Ten studies met the inclusion criteria and were ultimately included in the analysis. The detailed methodology of the literature search and selection process, including the application of inclusion and exclusion criteria, is illustrated in <xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig"><italic toggle="yes">Figure 1</italic></xref>. The search records from the initial search in relevant databases are provided in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cdn.amegroups.cn/static/public/GS-24-330-Supplementary.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Tables S1-S6</ext-link>. The data from the supplementary search are provided in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cdn.amegroups.cn/static/public/GS-24-330-Supplementary.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Tables S7-S11</ext-link>.</p><fig position="float" id="f1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flow diagram of study selection. CBM, China Biology Medicine. CNKI, China National Knowledge Infrastructure.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gs-13-11-2010-f1.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Characteristics of included studies</title><p>A total of ten studies (<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>-<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) were included in the analysis, consisting of eight case-control studies and two cohort studies. These studies collectively encompassed 127,467 patients, of whom 703 developed postoperative SSI. Detailed characteristics of the included studies are delineated in <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 1</italic></xref>. All 10 studies, including both the case-control and cohort designs, underwent quality assessment using the NOS, with scores ranging from 7 to 9, which reflects a generally high quality of the included studies. The particular quality assessments are presented in <xref rid="t2" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 2</italic></xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="t1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Literature characterization table</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="19.87%" span="1"/><col width="14.12%" span="1"/><col width="18.16%" span="1"/><col width="9.36%" span="1"/><col width="9.28%" span="1"/><col width="14.61%" span="1"/><col width="7.54%" span="1"/><col width="7.06%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" style="border-bottom: solid 0.50pt" colspan="1">Study</th><th rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-bottom: solid 0.50pt" colspan="1">Country</th><th rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-bottom: solid 0.50pt" colspan="1">Study design</th><th valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-bottom: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1">Sample size</th><th rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-bottom: solid 0.50pt" colspan="1">Gender (M/F), n</th><th valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-bottom: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1">Mean age (years)</th></tr><tr><th valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1">SSI</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NSSI</th><th valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1">SSI</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.50pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NSSI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bures C, 2014</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Austria</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort study</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,746</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,575/5,203</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salem FA, 2018</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweden</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort study</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,494</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,833/7,661</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cai Y, 2013</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case-control study</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52/48</td><td colspan="2" valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1">40.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">De Palma M, 2013</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case-control study</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,898</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">653/2,273</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elfenbein DM, 2014</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case-control study</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49,326</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49,147</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chen Y, 2016</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case-control study</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">360</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190/210</td><td colspan="2" valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1">40.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wang Y, 2017</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case-control study</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">446</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128/352</td><td colspan="2" valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1">46</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myssiorek D, 2018</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case-control study</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57,143</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,539/45,604</td><td colspan="2" valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1">51.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wang F, 2019</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case-control study</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">324</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88/262</td><td colspan="2" valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1">44</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">He K, 2019</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case-control study</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">239</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55/187</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.67</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.31</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>SSI, surgical site infection; NSSI, non-surgical site infection; M, male; F, female; NA, not available.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="t2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>NOS for research</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="29.45%" span="1"/><col width="19.12%" span="1"/><col width="19.29%" span="1"/><col width="16.72%" span="1"/><col width="15.42%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Selection</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comparability</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exposure</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case control study</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Cai Y, 2013</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">****</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">***</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;De Palma M, 2013</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">****</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">***</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Elfenbein DM, 2014</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">****</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">***</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Chen Y, 2016</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">****</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">***</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Wang Y, 2017</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">****</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">***</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Myssiorek D, 2018</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">****</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">***</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Wang F, 2019</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">****</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">***</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;He K, 2019</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">****</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">***</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort study</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Bures C, 2014</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">****</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">***</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Salem FA, 2018</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">****</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">***</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>A &#8220;*&#8221; represents a score. NOS, Newcastle-Ottawa Scale.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Postoperative SSI incidence following thyroid surgery</title><p>Nine studies reported the incidence of postoperative SSI following thyroid surgery. Heterogeneity testing (I<sup>2</sup>=97.83%; P&lt;0.001) indicated substantial heterogeneity, prompting the use of a random-effects model for analysis. The results suggest a postoperative SSI incidence of [effect size (ES) =0.02; 95% CI: (0.02, 0.03)]. Due to the considerable heterogeneity of the metric, a sensitivity analysis was conducted by sequentially removing individual studies, which revealed minimal sensitivity and stable results. An Egger&#8217;s test was performed to assess publication bias, yielding a P=0.04, suggesting a higher likelihood of publication bias for this metric. See <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cdn.amegroups.cn/static/public/GS-24-330-Supplementary.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Figures S1,S2</ext-link> for further details.</p></sec><sec><title>Multivariate meta-analysis</title><sec><title>Surgical duration greater than 2 hours</title><p>Five studies mentioned surgical duration greater than 2 hours. Heterogeneity testing (I<sup>2</sup>=0.0%; P&gt;0.99) indicated no significant heterogeneity, leading to the use of a fixed-effects model for analysis. The analysis results suggest that a surgical duration greater than 2 hours is a risk factor for postoperative SSI in patients undergoing thyroid surgery, with statistically significant differences [OR =4.50; 95% CI: (2.74, 7.37); P&lt;0.001]. See <xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig"><italic toggle="yes">Figure 2</italic></xref> and <xref rid="t3" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 3</italic></xref> for details.</p><fig position="float" id="f2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Forest plot of the effect of surgical duration greater than 2 hours on SSI following thyroid surgery. OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval; SSI, surgical site infection.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gs-13-11-2010-f2.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Multivariate analysis</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="34.56%" span="1"/><col width="11.08%" span="1"/><col width="14.8%" span="1"/><col width="17.83%" span="1"/><col width="10.7%" span="1"/><col width="11.03%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk factors</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of studies</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterogeneity (I<sup>2</sup>), %</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Egger&#8217;s test</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgical duration greater than 2 hours</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.50 (2.74, 7.37)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presence of comorbidities</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91 (1.16, 3.15)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age greater than 50 years</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81 (1.24, 2.64)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incision length greater than 5 cm</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.79 (1.92, 4.04)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.057</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymph node dissection</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90 (1.28, 2.80)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78 (1.38, 2.29)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Presence of comorbidities</title><p>Seven studies reported on comorbidities, referring to chronic health conditions existing before undergoing thyroid surgery, such as diabetes and hypertension. One study differentiated between insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus (IDDM) and non-IDDM (NIDDM) among diabetic patients, and both types were included in the analysis. Heterogeneity testing (I<sup>2</sup>=79.0%; P&lt;0.001) indicated significant heterogeneity, leading to the use of a random-effects model for analysis. The analysis results suggest that the presence of comorbidities is associated with an increased risk of postoperative SSI in patients undergoing thyroid surgery, with statistically significant differences [OR =1.91; 95% CI: (1.16, 3.15); P=0.01]. See <xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig"><italic toggle="yes">Figure 3</italic></xref> and <xref rid="t3" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 3</italic></xref> for details.</p><fig position="float" id="f3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Forest plot of the effect of presence of comorbidities on SSIs following thyroid surgery. OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval; SSI, surgical site infection.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gs-13-11-2010-f3.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Age greater than 50 years</title><p>Four studies reported on age greater than 50 years. Heterogeneity testing (I<sup>2</sup>=52.5%; P=0.06) indicated no significant heterogeneity, leading to the use of a random-effects model for analysis. The analysis results suggest that age greater than 50 years is associated with an increased risk of postoperative SSI in patients undergoing thyroid surgery, with statistically significant differences [OR =1.81; 95% CI: (1.24, 2.64); P=0.002]. See <xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig"><italic toggle="yes">Figure 4</italic></xref> and <xref rid="t3" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 3</italic></xref> for details.</p><fig position="float" id="f4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Forest plot of the effect of age greater than 50 years on SSI following thyroid surgery. OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval; SSI, surgical site infection.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gs-13-11-2010-f4.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Incision length greater than 5 cm</title><p>Three studies reported on incision length greater than 5 cm. Heterogeneity testing (I<sup>2</sup>=0.0%; P=0.97) indicated no significant heterogeneity, leading to the use of a fixed-effects model for analysis. The analysis results suggest that incision length greater than 5 cm is associated with an increased risk of postoperative SSI in patients undergoing thyroid surgery, with statistically significant differences [OR =2.79; 95% CI: (1.92, 4.04); P&lt;0.001]. See <xref rid="f5" ref-type="fig"><italic toggle="yes">Figure 5</italic></xref> and <xref rid="t3" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 3</italic></xref> for details.</p><fig position="float" id="f5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Forest plot of the effect of incision length greater than 5 cm on SSI following thyroid surgery. OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval; SSI, surgical site infection.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gs-13-11-2010-f5.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Lymph node dissection</title><p>Three studies reported on lymph node dissection. Heterogeneity testing (I<sup>2</sup>=60.6%; P=0.08) indicated moderate heterogeneity, leading to the use of a random-effects model for analysis. The analysis results suggest that lymph node dissection is associated with an increased risk of postoperative SSI in patients undergoing thyroid surgery, with statistically significant differences [OR =1.90; 95% CI: (1.28, 2.80); P=0.001]. See <xref rid="f6" ref-type="fig"><italic toggle="yes">Figure 6</italic></xref> and <xref rid="t3" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 3</italic></xref> for details.</p><fig position="float" id="f6" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Forest plot of the effect of lymph node dissection on SSI following thyroid surgery. OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval; SSI, surgical site infection.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gs-13-11-2010-f6.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Male</title><p>Four studies reported sex differences. Heterogeneity testing (I<sup>2</sup>=10.5%; P=0.34) indicated no significant heterogeneity, and thus a fixed-effects model was used for the analysis. The analysis revealed that males were associated with an increased risk of postoperative SSI in thyroid surgery patients, and this difference was statistically significant [OR =1.78; 95% CI: (1.38, 2.29); P&lt;0.001]. See <xref rid="f7" ref-type="fig"><italic toggle="yes">Figure 7</italic></xref> and <xref rid="t3" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 3</italic></xref> for details.</p><fig position="float" id="f7" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Forest plot of male&#8217;s effect on SSIs following thyroid surgery. OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval; SSI, surgical site infection.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gs-13-11-2010-f7.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Sensitivity analyses</title><p>To assess the impact of each study on the aggregate findings, sensitivity analyses were performed by sequentially excluding one study at a time. The results indicated that the pooled ESs and their corresponding 95% CIs were not significantly altered by the exclusion of any single study. This suggests that the overall conclusions drawn from the meta-analysis are robust and reliable.</p></sec><sec><title>Publication bias</title><p>Egger&#8217;s test was applied to each risk factor to assess publication bias. Among the six risk factors with statistically significant differences, surgery time greater than 2 hours (P=0.03) and the presence of comorbidities (P=0.01) showed evidence of publication bias as risk factors for postoperative SSI in patients undergoing thyroid surgery. The remaining four risk factors, including age greater than 50 years (P=0.97), incision length greater than 5 cm (P=0.057), lymph node dissection (P=0.78), and male (P=0.57), had P values greater than 0.05, indicating no evidence of publication bias. See <xref rid="t3" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 3</italic></xref> for details.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>This meta-analysis explores risk factors for SSI following thyroid surgery. The incidence of SSI across the included studies ranged from 0.36% to 24%. Increased risk factors for SSI in thyroid surgery patients include surgical duration greater than 2 hours, presence of comorbidities, age greater than 50 years, incision length greater than 5 cm, lymph node dissection, and male.</p><p>Longer surgical procedures increase the exposure time of the incision, thereby increasing the opportunity for bacterial invasion and increasing the risk of postoperative SSI (<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Some surgeries can suppress the patient&#8217;s immune system, which is another potential reason for increased SSI risk (<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). One study has shown that laparoscopic radical nephrectomy with an operative time of more than 3 hours is an independent risk factor for postoperative SSI (<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). In addition, each 20-minute increase in operating time increases the risk of postoperative SSI by approximately 25% (<xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Another study showed that patients with surgery times longer than 120 minutes had a significantly higher rate of postoperative SSI than those with surgery times within 120 minutes, consistent with the above studies (<xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). To reduce the risk of SSIs, surgical teams should aim to control the duration of surgery, implement efficient workflows, minimize unnecessary delays and technical complexity, and maintain strict aseptic techniques to effectively prevent SSIs.</p><p>Age is one of the most important factors influencing the incidence of SSI. Studies have shown that the risk of postoperative infection increases significantly in patients over the age of 50 years (<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Another study showed a similar trend, with patients aged 65 years and older undergoing thyroidectomy having twice the risk of postoperative complications compared to those under 65 years, and this risk increasing to five times for patients aged 80 years and older (<xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). With advancing age, patients experience a decline in immune function and weakened tissue repair capacity, both of which contribute to a significantly increased risk of postoperative infection. Honig <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> also found (<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>) that aging increases the risk of delayed wound healing and skin necrosis, which exacerbates the risk of postoperative SSI.</p><p>Many studies examine the relationship between diabetes or hypertension and postoperative SSI separately, so we discuss these conditions separately. There is evidence that diabetic patients have a significantly higher incidence of postoperative SSI than non-diabetic patients (<xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). A study on diabetes and SSI (<xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) confirmed that perioperative prophylactic antibiotics are an independent protective factor against SSI. Hypertensive patients are also more prone to infection due to vascular dysfunction and impaired tissue repair. Studies suggest that hypertension is an independent risk factor for SSI (<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Therefore, medical teams should thoroughly assess patients&#8217; age and comorbidity status preoperatively and develop personalized preventive measures and treatment strategies to reduce the risk of SSIs, thereby improving patient safety and cure rates.</p><p>The length of the incision is a significant factor that influences the incidence of postoperative SSI. It is generally accepted that longer incisions are associated with an increased risk of infection. This is due to the fact that they are more susceptible to contamination from the surrounding environment and exposure to microbes. Furthermore, longer incisions necessitate a longer healing period, thereby extending the window of infection risk. Furthermore, the extent of exposure of long incisions is a significant consideration, as it increases the patient&#8217;s exposure to the external environment and potential microorganisms, thereby increasing the likelihood of infection. It is therefore imperative that the size of the incision and the protective measures employed during surgical planning and execution receive special attention, with a view to minimizing the occurrence of postoperative infections. It is incumbent upon surgeons to meticulously plan incision pathways, endeavor to minimize incision size and adhere rigorously to aseptic techniques in order to effectively mitigate the risk of SSI.</p><p>Lymph node dissection, a common procedure in thyroid surgery, increases the complexity and duration of surgery, thus elevating the risk of postoperative infections. A number of studies have demonstrated that patients who undergo lymph node dissection have a markedly elevated incidence of postoperative SSI in comparison to those who do not undergo this procedure (<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Additionally, another study has demonstrated that lymph node dissection is significantly associated with an elevated risk of postoperative infection, indicating that this procedure is an important risk factor for SSI (<xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Moreover, Jin <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (<xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>) discovered that prophylactic central neck dissection in clinically node-negative thyroid cancer patients undergoing total thyroidectomy markedly elevated the incidence of surgical site wound infections in comparison to total thyroidectomy alone. This indicates that for non-malignant surgical procedures, the unnecessary performance of prophylactic cervical lymph node dissections can be reduced in order to prevent potential SSIs. However, for curative surgeries for malignant tumors, more precise indicators are required to inform surgical decisions and ensure optimal patient outcomes. In instances where lymph node dissection is undertaken, it is imperative that efforts are made to minimize the duration of the surgical procedure in order to reduce the risk of postoperative infections.</p><p>With regard to the utilization of prophylactic antibiotics prior to surgical procedures, the extant research evidence is inconclusive. Some studies have demonstrated that there is no significant correlation between thyroid postoperative infection and the administration of prophylactic antibiotics. Consequently, the routine utilization of prophylactic antimicrobial therapy is not advised (<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>), which may be attributable to the specific antibiotic employed. However, other studies have indicated that prophylactic antimicrobial therapy is considered an appropriate course of action in cases where there is a potential risk of SSI, such as the use of 2 g of piperacillin or 1g of cefazolin (<xref rid="r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Conversely, there is evidence that preoperative use of chlorhexidine gluconate shower can effectively reduce the risk of postoperative SSI in patients (<xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Despite its limited application in clinical practice, this measure can be considered, particularly for planned surgery patients with relevant risk factors, to reduce the incidence of SSI after thyroid surgery.</p><p>Our findings indicate that males have a significantly higher risk of SSI following thyroid surgery compared to females. This finding is consistent with other studies on SSI related to various surgical procedures (<xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>), but the underlying mechanisms still require further investigation. One possible explanation for this difference lies in biological sex differences. For instance, males and females differ in immune responses, hormone levels, and skin microbiota, all of which may influence the incidence of SSI. Specifically, androgens have been shown to suppress certain functions of the immune system (<xref rid="r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>), potentially leading to weaker resistance to infection in males. In addition to biological factors, social behaviors, and lifestyle factors may also be involved. Males are more likely to engage in physical labor or high-risk activities, which can increase their exposure to pathogens. They may also be less stringent in adhering to preoperative hygiene guidelines compared to females. Furthermore, potential biases in the care provided by healthcare providers to different sexes are worthy of consideration. Despite the emphasis placed on equitable treatment in modern medicine, evidence suggests that sex bias may still exist in practice, affecting preoperative assessment, the execution of aseptic techniques during surgery, and the quality of postoperative care.</p><p>This study is limited in the following ways: firstly, the number of articles included is relatively small, with the majority of them originating from China, which may introduce selection bias; secondly, during the analysis process, we did not differentiate between OR, RR, and HR. Although the practical differences among these three are minimal, there are inherent distinctions in what they measure regarding disease risk, which may lead to some degree of bias in the results.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The incidence of SSI in patients who underwent thyroid surgery was found to be 2%. The risk factors for SSI in patients who underwent thyroid surgery include surgical duration greater than 2 hours, presence of comorbidities, age greater than 50 years, incision length greater than 5 cm, lymph node dissection, and male. It is recommended that surgeons pay close attention to patients who present with these risk factors and take preventive measures to prevent possible SSI. We look forward to more relevant research in the future to guide us in further reducing SSI after thyroid surgery.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary</title><supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><p>The article&#8217;s supplementary files as</p></supplementary-material><supplementary-material position="anchor" id="su1" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="gs-13-11-2010-rc.pdf" id="d67e1035" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/gs-24-330</object-id></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="gs-13-11-2010-coif.pdf" id="d67e1038" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/gs-24-330</object-id></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="gs-13-11-2010-supplementary.pdf" id="d67e1041" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/gs-24-330</object-id></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Funding:</italic> This work was supported by <funding-source rid="sp1">the Zhejiang Medical and Health Science and Technology Plan Project</funding-source> (<award-id rid="sp1">No. 2022KY939</award-id>) and <funding-source rid="sp2">the Project of Medical Scientific and Technology Program in Hangzhou</funding-source> (<award-id rid="sp2">No. A20200821</award-id>).</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><italic toggle="yes">Reporting Checklist:</italic> The authors have completed the MOOSE reporting checklist. Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://gs.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/gs-24-330/rc" ext-link-type="uri">https://gs.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/gs-24-330/rc</ext-link></p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><italic toggle="yes">Conflicts of Interest:</italic> All authors have completed the ICMJE uniform disclosure form (available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://gs.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/gs-24-330/coif" ext-link-type="uri">https://gs.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/gs-24-330/coif</ext-link>). All authors report that this work was supported by the Zhejiang Medical and Health Science and Technology Plan Project (No. 2022KY939) and the Project of Medical Scientific and Technology Program in Hangzhou (No. A20200821). The authors have no other conflicts of interest to declare.</p></fn></fn-group><notes><p content-type="note added in proof"><italic toggle="yes">Ethical Statement:</italic> The authors are accountable for all aspects of the work in ensuring that questions related to the accuracy or integrity of any part of the work are appropriately investigated and resolved.</p></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mielke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>"Prevention of Surgical Site Infections": Current recommendation of the German Commission of Hospital Hygiene and Infection Prevention.</article-title><source>Bundesgesundheitsblatt Gesundheitsforschung Gesundheitsschutz</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>371</fpage>-<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00103-018-2721-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29536112</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brauer</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burkey</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk Assessment in Thyroid Lobectomy and Total Thyroidectomy using Over 100 Thousand Cases.</article-title><source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>130</volume>:<fpage>1351</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/00034894211007219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33834878</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horan</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaynes</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martone</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CDC definitions of nosocomial surgical site infections, 1992: a modification of CDC definitions of surgical wound infections.</article-title><source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>1992</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>606</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1334988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosato</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avenia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernante</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Complications of thyroid surgery: analysis of a multicentric study on 14,934 patients operated on in Italy over 5 years.</article-title><source>World J Surg</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>271</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00268-003-6903-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14961204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Polistena</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prete</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avenia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of Antibiotic Prophylaxis on Surgical Site Infection in Thyroid and Parathyroid Surgery: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis.</article-title><source>Antibiotics (Basel)</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>290</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics11030290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35326753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8944446</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chetter</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oswald</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGinnis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patients with surgical wounds healing by secondary intention: A prospective, cohort study.</article-title><source>Int J Nurs Stud</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2018.09.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30343210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Qurayshi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Surgical Site Infection in Head and Neck Surgery: A National Perspective.</article-title><source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>161</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599819832858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30935264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Critical evaluation of the Newcastle-Ottawa scale for the assessment of the quality of nonrandomized studies in meta-analyses.</article-title><source>Eur J Epidemiol</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>603</fpage>-<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10654-010-9491-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20652370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moskalenko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beem</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Incidence of Surgical Site Infections after Thyroid and Parathyroid Surgery: No Role for Antimicrobial Prophylaxis.</article-title><source>Am Surg</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>897</fpage>-<lpage>901</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29981621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors of infections in patients after thyroid papillary carcinoma resection.</article-title><source>Chinese Journal of Nosocomiology</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>2766</fpage>-<lpage>7, 2770</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Huang YH, Liu ZY, Chen JP. Factors Related to Operating Room and Nursing Countermeasures for Incision Infections in Patients Undergoing Thyroid Surgery. Healthful Friend 2022;(22):160-1, 164.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for surgical sites infections in patients undergoing thyroidectomy.</article-title><source>Chinese Journal of Nosocomiology</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>5203</fpage>-<lpage>4, 5207</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of Antibiotic Prophylaxis and Surgical Sites Infections during Perioperative Period of Thyroid Surgery in A Hospital.</article-title><source>Anti-Tumor Pharmacy</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>226</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of Risk Factors and Pathogen Profiles for Incision Infection Following Thyroidectomy in Patients with Goiter.</article-title><source>Electronic Journal of Clinical Medical Literature</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>46</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk Management of Incision Infection and Subcutaneous Fluid Accumulation Following Thyroid Surgery.</article-title><source>World Latest Medicine Information</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>128</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salem</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Almquist</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordenstr&#246;m</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A Nested Case-Control Study on the Risk of Surgical Site Infection After Thyroid Surgery.</article-title><source>World J Surg</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>2454</fpage>-<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00268-018-4492-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29470699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6060833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elfenbein</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Surgical site infection after thyroidectomy: a rare but significant complication.</article-title><source>J Surg Res</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>190</volume>:<fpage>170</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jss.2014.03.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24739508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5125385</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bures</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klatte</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilhofer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A prospective study on surgical-site infections in thyroid operation.</article-title><source>Surgery</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>155</volume>:<fpage>675</fpage>-<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.surg.2013.12.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24502803</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Palma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grillo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borgia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibiotic prophylaxis and risk of infections in thyroid surgery: results from a national study (UEC-Italian Endocrine Surgery Units Association).</article-title><source>Updates Surg</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>213</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13304-013-0219-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23729319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Related factors for postoperative infection in patients undergoing subtotal thyroidectomy surgery.</article-title><source>Chinese Journal of Nosocomiology</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>2032</fpage>-<lpage>4, 2042</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Myssiorek</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parsikia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors predictive of the development of surgical site infection in thyroidectomy - An analysis of NSQIP database.</article-title><source>Int J Surg</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>273</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijsu.2018.11.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30453084</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for surgical site infection after percutaneous endoscopic lumbar discectomy.</article-title><source>Int Wound J</source><year>2024</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<elocation-id>e14605</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/iwj.14605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38149500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10961887</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC12011399"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudensky</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yinnon</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shutin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The cellular immunological responses of patients undergoing coronary artery bypass grafting compared with those of patients undergoing valve replacement.</article-title><source>Eur J Cardiothorac Surg</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>1056</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejcts.2009.12.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20171113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of surgical site infection and tumour-specific survival rate in patients with renal cell carcinoma after laparoscopic radical nephrectomy.</article-title><source>Int Wound J</source><year>2024</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<elocation-id>e14711</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/iwj.14711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38387886</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10834101</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC12011445"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goswami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shohat</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Longer Operative Time Results in a Higher Rate of Subsequent Periprosthetic Joint Infection in Patients Undergoing Primary Joint Arthroplasty.</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>947</fpage>-<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2019.01.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30765229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scigliano</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carender</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Operative Time and Risk of Surgical Site Infection and Periprosthetic Joint Infection: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis.</article-title><source>Iowa Orthop J</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>155</fpage>-<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35821941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9210401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilar-Compte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez de Iturbe</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;n-Onraet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hyperglycemia as a risk factor for surgical site infections in patients undergoing mastectomy.</article-title><source>Am J Infect Control</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>192</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajic.2007.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18371515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grogan</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitmaker</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A population-based prospective cohort study of complications after thyroidectomy in the elderly.</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>1645</fpage>-<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.2011-1162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22419716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Honig</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Habarth-Morales</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increased Patient Age as a Risk Factor Following Free Flap Reconstruction after Breast Cancer: A Single Institutional Review of 2,598 Cases.</article-title><source>J Reconstr Microsurg</source><year>2024</year>. [<comment>Epub ahead of print</comment>]. doi: .<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0044-1787728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38866038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comprehensive analysis of risk factors for postoperative wound infection following radical mastectomy in breast cancer patients.</article-title><source>Int Wound J</source><year>2024</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<elocation-id>e14848</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/iwj.14848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38578050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10996372</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11964519"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Extensive analysis of risk factors associated with surgical site infections post-cardiothoracic open surgery.</article-title><source>Int Wound J</source><year>2024</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<elocation-id>e14842</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/iwj.14842</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38484717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10940006</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11964610"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Protective effect of intraoperative re-dose of prophylactic antibiotics on surgical site infection in diabetic patients: a retrospective cohort study.</article-title><source>Ann Transl Med</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>96</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/atm.2019.01.35</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31019946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6462642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of surgical site infection and risk factors in patients after foot and ankle surgery: A systematic review and meta-analysis.</article-title><source>Int Wound J</source><year>2024</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<elocation-id>e14350</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/iwj.14350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37606302</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10781588</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11875662"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCall</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beitsch</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Surgical complications associated with sentinel lymph node dissection (SLND) plus axillary lymph node dissection compared with SLND alone in the American College of Surgeons Oncology Group Trial Z0011.</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>3657</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2006.07.4062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17485711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of prophylactic central neck dissection following total thyroidectomy on surgical site wound infection, hematoma, and haemorrhage in subjects with clinically node-negative papillary thyroid carcinoma: A meta-analysis.</article-title><source>Int Wound J</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>251</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/iwj.13867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35702946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9885457</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11964505"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dionigi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rovera</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Surgical site infections after thyroidectomy.</article-title><source>Surg Infect (Larchmt)</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>7</volume><issue>Suppl 2</issue>:<fpage>S117</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/sur.2006.7.s2-117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16895492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwatani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Surgical site infections in thyroid and parathyroid surgery in Japan: An analysis of the Japan Nosocomial Infections Surveillance database from 2013 to 2020.</article-title><source>Int Wound J</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1874</fpage>-<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/iwj.14046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36504428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10333034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ammanuel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for deep surgical site infection following thoracolumbar spinal surgery.</article-title><source>J Neurosurg Spine</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>292</fpage>-<lpage>301</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/2019.8.SPINE19479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32011834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Update on risk factors of surgical site infection in colorectal cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis.</article-title><source>Int J Colorectal Dis</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>2147</fpage>-<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00384-020-03706-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32748113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edmiston</surname><given-names>CE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunja</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Longitudinal rates, risk factors, and costs of superficial and deep incisional surgical-site infection (SSI) after primary and revision total knee arthroplasty: A US retrospective claims database analysis.</article-title><source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>1587</fpage>-<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/ice.2023.10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36726345</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ainslie</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simitsidellis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirkwood</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RISING STARS: Androgens and immune cell function.</article-title><source>J Endocrinol</source><year>2024</year>;<volume>261</volume>:<elocation-id>e230398</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1530/JOE-23-0398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38579776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11103679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article id="gs-13-11-2010-prf" article-type="reviewer-report"><front-stub><title-group><article-title>Peer Review File</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><p>Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://gs.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/gs-24-330/prf" ext-link-type="uri">https://gs.amegroups.com/article/view/10.21037/gs-24-330/prf</ext-link></p><fig id="d67e2299" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="gs-13-11-2010-prf.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></fig></body></sub-article></article></pmc-articleset>