<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Psychol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Psychol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2645</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcpsychol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Psychology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2050-7283</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11022322</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11022322.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11022322</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11022322</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38632660</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40359-024-01726-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1726</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Four-year follow-up of psychiatric and psychosomatic profile in patients with Inflammatory Bowel Disease (IBD)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5828-4654</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Gostoli</surname><given-names initials="S">Sara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrara</surname><given-names initials="F">Francesco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quintavalle</surname><given-names initials="L">Ludovica</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tommasino</surname><given-names initials="S">Sara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gigante</surname><given-names initials="G">Graziano</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Montecchiarini</surname><given-names initials="M">Maria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Urgese</surname><given-names initials="A">Alessia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guolo</surname><given-names initials="F">Francesco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Subach</surname><given-names initials="R">Regina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#8217;Oronzo</surname><given-names initials="A">Angelica</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Polifemo</surname><given-names initials="A">Annamaria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buonfiglioli</surname><given-names initials="F">Federica</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cennamo</surname><given-names initials="V">Vincenzo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3025-7918</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Rafanelli</surname><given-names initials="C">Chiara</given-names></name><address><email>chiara.rafanelli@unibo.it</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01111rn36</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.6292.f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1757 1758</institution-id><institution>Department of Psychology &#8220;Renzo Canestrari&#8221;, </institution><institution>University of Bologna, </institution></institution-wrap>Bologna, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.414090.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1763 4974</institution-id><institution>Gastroenterology and Interventional Endoscopy Unit, </institution><institution>AUSL Bologna, </institution></institution-wrap>Bologna, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.414090.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1763 4974</institution-id><institution>Division of Cardiology, Bellaria Hospital, </institution><institution>AUSL Bologna, </institution></institution-wrap>Bologna, Italy </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">452076</issue-id><elocation-id>211</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>17</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>17</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-04-25 03:25:15.423"><day>25</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="40359_2024_Article_1726.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Psychological characterization of patients affected by Inflammatory Bowel Disease (IBD) focuses on comorbidity with psychiatric disorders, somatization or alexithymia. Whereas IBD patients had higher risk of stable anxiety and depression for many years after the diagnosis of the disease, there is a lack of studies reporting a comprehensive psychosomatic assessment addressing factors of disease vulnerability, also in the long-term. The objective of this investigation is to fill this gap in the current literature. The aims were thus to assess: a) changes between baseline and a 4-year follow-up in psychiatric diagnoses (SCID), psychosomatic syndromes (DCPR), psychological well-being (PWB-I), lifestyle, gastrointestinal symptoms related to IBD and Irritable Bowel Syndrome (IBS)-like symptoms b) stability of psychiatric and psychosomatic syndromes at 4-year follow-up. A total of 111 IBD outpatients were enrolled; 59.5% of them participated at the follow-up. A comprehensive assessment, including both interviews and self-report questionnaires, was provided at baseline and follow-up. Results showed increased psychiatric diagnoses, physical activity, consumption of vegetables and IBS-like symptoms at follow-up. Additionally, whereas psychiatric diagnoses were no longer present and new psychopathological pictures ensued at follow-up, more than half of the sample maintained psychosomatic syndromes (particularly allostatic overload, type A behavior, demoralization) from baseline to follow-up. Long-term presence/persistence of such psychosocial burden indicates the need for integrating a comprehensive psychosomatic evaluation beyond traditional psychiatric nosography in IBD patients. Moreover, since psychosomatic syndromes represent vulnerability factors of diseases, further studies should target subgroups of patients presenting with persistent psychosomatic syndromes and worse course of the disease.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Diagnostic Criteria for Psychosomatic Research (DCPR)</kwd><kwd>Inflammatory Bowel Disease (IBD)</kwd><kwd>Lifestyle behaviors</kwd><kwd>Psychological well-being</kwd><kwd>Psychiatric diagnoses</kwd><kwd>Psychosomatic syndromes</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Inflammatory Bowel Diseases (IBD), including ulcerative colitis (UC) and Crohn's disease (CD), are chronic diseases that exhibit an unpredictable clinical course, with alternating active phases and periods of variable duration of remission [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The epidemiology of IBD is rapidly changing worldwide. The estimated prevalence continues to rise in Western countries, with a high burden of IBD in North America, Oceania, and Europe [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], reaching approximately 2.2 million of IBD patients in USA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. In Northern Italy, the average incidence of IBD registered in the period 2016&#8211;2021 was 18 per 100.000 inhabitants/year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. IBD specific symptoms are fever, weight and appetite loss, bloody stool, vomiting and anemia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. A high percentage of other symptoms such as abdominal pain, bloating, diarrhea and watery stools, transversally exhibited in IBD and Irritable Bowel Syndrome (IBS) patients are reported. IBD may be complicated by extra-intestinal systemic manifestations such as rheumatological, ocular, dermatological, hepatobiliary, pulmonary, cardiac, and hematological [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. There is also an increased risk of neoplasms, mainly colorectal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. An intimate connection between the central nervous and the enteric nervous systems (gut-brain axis) was observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Indeed, psychiatric comorbidity in IBD is well known and higher than in matched cohorts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. It is increasingly acknowledged that both psychological and biological pathways play a role in stress-induced alterations in IBD expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. On the one hand, psychiatric disorders such as anxiety and depressive disorders may trigger and exacerbate intestinal inflammation or contribute to relapse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. On the other hand, both active physical symptoms and the chronic and severe nature of IBD can negatively impact an individual's mental health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Furthermore, subclinical manifestations, such as somatization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] and alexithymia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], affecting IBD patients&#8217; clinical disease activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] and quality of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] were observed. In IBD patients, healthy lifestyle such as regular physical exercise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], a personalized dietary approach, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], avoidance of smoking [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] and light or no alcohol consumption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] are recommended. However, some of these recommendations are contrary to what is often practiced by IBD patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Whereas Bisgaard and colleagues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] found that patients with IBD had higher risk of anxiety and depression starting at least five years before and continuing until at least ten years after IBD diagnosis, there is a lack of studies reporting a comprehensive psychosomatic assessment, addressing different factors of disease vulnerability in IBD patients, also in the long-term, despite the advocated need for a thorough evaluation and management of IBD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. In order to fill the gaps in the existing literature, the present study aimed to conduct a more extensive investigation of the clinical and subclinical psychological profile of IBD outpatients at baseline and at a 4-year follow-up. Additionally, our study aimed to verify the long-term stability of psychosomatic syndromes in IBD patients. Specifically, the present study had two objectives: a) to assess changes between baseline and a 4-year follow-up in psychiatric profile according to DSM-5 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], psychosomatic syndromes on the basis of Diagnostic Criteria for Psychosomatic Research (DCPR) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], psychological well-being (PWB) according to PWB-Interview (PWB-I) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] and lifestyle, as well as in IBD-related symptoms and IBS-like symptoms b) to assess the stability of psychiatric and psychosomatic syndromes at 4-year follow-up.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Participants and procedure</title><p id="Par3">Consecutive outpatients with IBD in remission phase, including Crohn&#8217;s disease and ulcerative colitis, were recruited at the Unit of Gastroenterology of Local Unit Health (AUSL) of Bologna (Italy), after a check-up visit. The diagnosis of CD and UC were based on clinical history, blood and fecal tests, endoscopic, histologic and radiologic findings, following the ECCO-ESGAR Guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>].</p><p id="Par4">Patients were recruited at baseline between December 2018 and January 2020. After the check-up visit, patients were asked to join the study and the informed consent document was provided. The interview was conducted soon after obtaining patients&#8217; written informed consent. Participants were subsequently contacted again, approximately four years later, to set an appointment for the follow-up interview, which was conducted by phone. The local ethics committee approved the longitudinal study. All procedures involved in the present investigation adhere to the ethical standards set by the relevant national and institutional committees on human experimentation and with the Helsinki Declaration of 1975, as revised in 2008.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Assessment</title><p id="Par5">The interviews followed the same procedure at baseline and follow-up. Patients were assessed by three clinical psychologists trained to conduct the interviews. During the baseline assessment, patients underwent face-to-face interviews, whereas, during the follow-up, interviews were conducted via telephone. At both assessments, sociodemographic data, including gender, age, education level, occupation, marital status were collected, as well as regularly taken medications.</p><p id="Par6">Participants underwent three validated clinical interviews for the assessment of psychiatric disorders, psychosomatic syndromes and psychological well-being. Information about lifestyle such as physical activity, diet, alcohol consumption, and smoking were collected as well. Additional ad hoc questions about the presence of IBD related symptoms and IBS-like symptoms were introduced. On average, the interview lasted 45 minutes.</p><sec id="Sec5"><title>Psychiatric diagnoses</title><p id="Par7">The Italian adaptation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] of the Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-5, clinician version (SCID-5-CV) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], to assess the presence of various psychiatric conditions, including depressive disorders (major depression), anxiety disorders (panic disorder, generalized anxiety disorder, agoraphobia and social anxiety), eating disorders (bulimia, binge eating disorder, and anorexia nervosa), and other disorders such as obsessive-compulsive disorder, somatic symptom disorders and illness anxiety, was employed. Moreover, current minor depression from the DSM-IV-TR appendix was assessed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. The SCID-5-CV demonstrated exceptional reliability, notable specificity, and clinical validity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. These findings substantiate its utility and appropriateness for routine clinical application [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Psychosomatic syndromes</title><p id="Par8">The Italian version of the Semi-Structured Interview, which is based on the revised Diagnostic Criteria for Psychosomatic Research (DCPR-R) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], was employed for the identification of psychosomatic syndromes. The updated version of DCPR was developed based on insights derived from its extensive use in many patients and various clinical settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], encompassing diagnostic criteria for two additional syndromes such as allostatic overload and hypochondriasis. The interview protocol, grounded in DCPR-R, has already demonstrated its utility within medical settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. It comprises a set of dichotomous (yes or no) items, complemented with screening questions that refer to the essential criteria of the disorders. This assessment instrument enables the examination of psychosomatic syndromes, which are delineated into four distinct domains: stress, personality, illness behavior, and psychological manifestations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. The stress domain includes allostatic overload. In the personality domain, type A behavior and alexithymia are considered. Illness behavior encompasses hypochondriasis, disease phobia, thanatophobia, health anxiety, persistent somatization, conversion symptoms, anniversary reaction and illness denial. The cluster regarding the psychological manifestations covers demoralization, demoralization with hopelessness, irritable mood and somatic symptoms secondary to a psychiatric disorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. These criteria have been meticulously developed with the aim of operationalizing the spectrum of manifestations of illness behavior and sub-threshold distress within both psychiatric and medical contexts. They can be utilized independently of, or in conjunction with, the DSM criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. The interview has demonstrated excellent interrater reliability, construct validity, and predictive validity concerning psychosocial functioning and treatment outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Psychological well-being</title><p id="Par9">The Italian version (PWB-I) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] of the semi-structured interview based on the Psychological Well-Being (PWB) scales items [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>] was employed. This instrument was utilized to evaluate the psychological well-being and resilience of individuals in clinical populations, aligning with the multidimensional model proposed by Ryff [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. The original version of the PWB scale has exhibited favorable psychometric properties, including robust internal consistency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] and this adaptation shows test-retest reliability in prior research endeavors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. It was used to facilitate tailoring of interventions and support strategies to address specific psychological needs of patients affected by IBD. The adapted questionnaire consists of 18 questions, in which respondents are asked to provide dichotomous responses in the form of "Yes" or "No" to each of these questions that encompass the six fundamental dimensions of PWB (environmental mastery, personal growth, purpose in life, autonomy, self-acceptance and positive relationship with others) as conceptualized by Ryff [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Lifestyle-related behaviors</title><p id="Par10">An adapted version of the GOSPEL questionnaire to assess lifestyle-related behaviors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>] was used. This particular adaptation was specifically crafted to surmount the inherent limitations posed by comprehensive questionnaires typically employed for the evaluation of dietary habits and leisure time physical activity. The assessment instrument is multifaceted and includes lifestyle dimensions such as physical activity, dietary habits (vegetables, fruits, fish and dairy products consumption), alcohol consumption and tobacco smoking. Respondents were asked to rate their habits on a 4-point Likert scale, indicating the frequency of each specific habit per week. This measure is frequently well-suited for real-world clinical environments marked by time limitations and practical constraints [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. This modified questionnaire has demonstrated its efficacy in previous investigations focused on patients affected by various medical conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>IBD-related symptoms, IBS-like symptoms</title><p id="Par11">In order to assess IBD-related symptoms (fecal blood) and IBS-like symptoms (e.g. constipation/diarrhea, mild abdominal pain, bloating) both at baseline and follow-up, five ad hoc questions were asked.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par12">Data were entered into SPSS 20.0 for Windows (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). Descriptive analyses were used to outline socio-demographic data, pharmacological treatment, psychiatric/psychosomatic diagnoses (DSM-5 and DCPR-R), well-being scores (PWB-I), lifestyle-related behaviors, IBD symptoms and IBS-like symptoms of the sample both at baseline and follow-up. Normal distribution of data was assessed with Shapiro-Wilk test and, when not confirmed (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .05), median and interquartile range was reported.</p><p id="Par13">For both first and second aim, analyses were conducted on the subgroup of patients who underwent follow-up assessment.</p><p id="Par14">Regarding the first aim, differences in the frequencies of current psychiatric diagnoses (DSM) and psychosomatic syndromes (DCPR) between baseline and follow-up were evaluated using the McNemar test. Wilcoxon signed-rank test was applied to underline differences between the number of DCPR syndromes and the number of SCID diagnoses at baseline and follow-up. Next, differences in well-being scores (PWB-I) and lifestyle-related behaviors from baseline to follow-up, were studied using the Sign test. Additionally, to assess differences in the distribution of smokers and non-smokers between baseline and follow-up, a McNemar test was employed. Finally, a McNemar test with the aim of comparing the presence of IBD related and IBS-like symptoms in the two evaluations was applied.</p><p id="Par15">Regarding the second aim, to determine which DSM and DCPR diagnoses were maintained between baseline and follow-up, contingency tables were used. Significance level for all the analyses was set to 0.05, two-tailed.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Results</title><p id="Par16">At baseline, the sample consisted of 111 patients: 44 males (39.6%) and 67 females (60.4%). The distribution of age (<italic toggle="yes">W</italic> = .974, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .029) and duration of the disease (<italic toggle="yes">W</italic> = .895, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001) did not approximate a normal distribution. Patients had a median age of 49 years (<italic toggle="yes">IQR</italic> = 22) and have been living with the disease for a median of 9 years (<italic toggle="yes">IQR</italic> = 12).</p><p id="Par17">Out of the 111 patients contacted to be assessed in the follow-up study, 59.5% agreed to participate. 36.4% were males and 63.6% females. The distribution of age (<italic toggle="yes">W</italic> = .963, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .044) and duration of the disease (<italic toggle="yes">W</italic> = .863, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;.001) did not approximate a normal distribution. Participants had a median age of 50 years (<italic toggle="yes">IQR</italic> = 23) and have been living with the disease for a median of 13 years (<italic toggle="yes">IQR</italic>= 12). Out of the 111 patients, 45 (40.5%) did not participate due to time constraints (33.4%) and inability to be contacted (6%); among them, 20 (44.4%) were males and 25 (55.6%) females with a mean age (W = .967, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> =.217) of 55.3 years (<italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 13.20). Patients&#8217; sociodemographic data and pharmacological treatment of baseline and follow-up are described in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Socio-demographic data and pharmacological treatment of the sample&#160;at baseline and follow-up (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>= 66)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sample characteristics</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Baseline</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Follow-up</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">%</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">%</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.4%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.4%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.6%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.6%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Disease</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Ulcerative colitis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.1%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.1%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Crohn&#8217;s disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.9%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.9%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Marital status</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Single</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.8%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.8%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Married</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.1%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.2%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Divorced</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.1%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.1%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Widowed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Employment status</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Retired</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.6%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.7%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Manual labor</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.8%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.7%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Sedentary work</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.5%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Unemployed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.1%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.1%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Education</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Primary school certificate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;8th grade diploma</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.8%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.8%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Diploma</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.4%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Bachelor&#8217;s degree</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.6%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Master degree</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.2%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.2%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;PhD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Pharmacological Treatment</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Antidepressants</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.6%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.1%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;TCA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;SSRI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.6%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Other antidepressants</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Antipsychotics</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Anxiolytics</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.6%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Azathiaprina</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.1%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Biological</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.5%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.8%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Cortisone</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.6%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.2%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Mesalazine</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86.4%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.7%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Anticoagulant</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.1%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Antidyslipidemics</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.6%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Antidiabetics</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Antihypertensive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.1%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.1%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">PhD</italic> Philosophiae Doctor, <italic toggle="yes">TCA</italic> Tricyclic Antidepressant, <italic toggle="yes">SSRI</italic> Selective Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitors</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par18">Regarding the first aim of the study, the frequency of DSM diagnoses from baseline to follow-up showed a significant increase (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001). Indeed, 6.1% of IBD patients presented with DSM diagnoses at baseline, whereas 31.8% at follow-up (frequencies associated with each diagnosis, both at the baseline and follow-up assessments, are delineated in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Frequency of psychiatric and psychosomatic diagnoses at baseline and follow-up, compared using the McNemar test.&#160;Frequency of maintenance and development of diagnoses between baseline and follow-up is also outlined</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Baseline</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Maintained</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Developed</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Follow-up</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Psychiatric diagnoses</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current major depression</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.03%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (6.06%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (7.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.375</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current minor depression</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (15.15%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (15.15%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current panic disorder</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.03%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.03%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Agoraphobia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (4.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (4.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Social Anxiety</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (7.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (7.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Generalized anxiety disorder</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (12.12%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (12.12%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (6.06%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (6.06%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bulimia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Binge Eating Disorder</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.03%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.03%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anorexia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Somatic Symptoms disorder</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (7.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (7.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.219</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Illness Anxiety</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (7.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (7.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.219</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Psychosomatic syndromes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Allostatic overload</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (27.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (19.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (18.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (37.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.143</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alexithymia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (25.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (7.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (28.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (36.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.281</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Health Anxiety</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (4.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.625</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Type A behavior</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (28.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (16.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (9.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (25.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.791</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Disease phobia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.03%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hypochondriasis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.03%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.03%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Thanatophobia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Illness denial</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.03%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Persistent somatization</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (6.06%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (22.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (24.24%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.008**</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Demoralization</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (13.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (7.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (13.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (21.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.267</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Demoralization with hopelessness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.03%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (6.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (7.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.375</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Irritable mood</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (12.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.03%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (6.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (9.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.754</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Conversion symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (7.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (7.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Functional somatic symptoms secondary to a psychiatric disorder</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anniversary reaction</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.03%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (3.03%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par19">Regarding psychosomatic syndromes, the frequency of DCPR diagnoses between baseline and follow-up did not show a significant increase (<italic toggle="yes">p =</italic> .<italic toggle="yes">086</italic>). 71.2% of IBD patients presented at least one DCPR syndrome at baseline, whereas 75.5% at follow-up. The only significant change was the increase in persistent somatization: 6.06% at baseline and 24.24% at follow-up (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .008) (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par20">No significant results emerged from the comparisons of PWB-I scores between baseline and follow-up (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>)<italic toggle="yes">.</italic>
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>PWB-I median scores and relative interquartile ranges of participants at baseline compared with follow-up using Sign test</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">PWB-I Scores</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Baseline</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Follow-up</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Mdn</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">IQR</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Mdn</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">IQR</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PWB-I environmental mastery</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.664</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PWB-I personal growth</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PWB-I purpose in life</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PWB-I autonomy</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.241</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PWB-I self-acceptance</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.152</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PWB-I positive relations</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.860</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PWB-I tot</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.596</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">PWB-I</italic>&#160;Psychological Well-Being Interview</p><p><sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par21">The analysis of lifestyle-related behaviors showed few significant differences between baseline and follow-up. In particular, the frequency of physical activity (<italic toggle="yes">Z</italic> = - 2.09, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .037) and the consumption of vegetables (<italic toggle="yes">Z</italic> = - 2.96, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .003) increased, while no significant changes between baseline and follow-up were observed for the remaining habits. Lifestyle data and comparisons are reported in Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref><italic toggle="yes">.</italic>
<table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of lifestyle habits between baseline and follow-up, using Sign Test</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Lifestyle habit</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Median Frequency</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Baseline</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Follow-up</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Z</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vegetables consumption</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Two / Three times a week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Two / Three times a week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">- 2.96</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.003**</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fruit consumption</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Everyday</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Everyday</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">- 0.86</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.391</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fish consumption</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Two / Three times a week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Two / Three times a week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">- 0.39</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.700</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dairy products consumption</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Two / Three times a week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Two / Three times a week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">- 1.46</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.144</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yogurt consumption</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Never / Occasionally</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Never / Occasionally</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alcohol consumption</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Never / Occasionally</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Never / Occasionally</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">- 0.17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.864</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Physical activity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Never / Occasionally</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Once / Twice a week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">- 2.09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.037*</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par22">Concerning IBD related symptoms, results did not show any significant change. 7.6% presented IBD related symptoms at baseline, whereas 16.7% at follow-up (no one maintained these symptoms). About IBS-like symptoms, patients showed a significant increase between baseline and follow-up (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .001). Indeed, 9.1% at baseline presented IBS-like symptoms, whereas 56.1% at follow-up (4.5% maintained the symptoms) (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>IBD-related symptoms and IBS-like symptoms at baseline and follow-up, compared using the McNemar test.&#160;Frequency of maintenance and development of symptoms between baseline and follow-up is also outlined</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Baseline</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Maintained</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Developed</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Follow-up</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n (%)</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IBD-related symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (7.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (16.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (16.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.210</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IBS-like symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (9.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (4.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (51.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37 (56.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001**</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>IBD Inflammatory Bowel Disease, <italic toggle="yes">IBS</italic> Irritable Bowel Syndrome</p><p><sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .01</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par23">Regarding the second aim, 1.5% of the sample maintained at least one DSM diagnosis and 30.3% developed new DSM diagnoses. On the contrary, the percentage of IBD patients who maintained at least one DCPR syndrome was 54.5% whereas 21.2% developed new DCPR syndromes. The DCPR syndromes that were found to persist to some extent in IBD patients were allostatic overload (19.7% of the total sample), type A behavior (16.7%), alexithymia (7.6%), and demoralization (7.6%) (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). In particular, the DCPR syndromes that persisted in more than half of the cases from baseline to follow-up were allostatic overload, Type A behavior and demoralization (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par24">The current study aimed to conduct an integrated assessment approach that encompasses the clinical and subclinical psychological profile of IBD outpatients in a longitudinal perspective, in order to provide a more comprehensive characterization of IBD patients.</p><p id="Par25">Regarding psychiatric diagnoses, findings of the present study revealed a significant increase at follow-up, as only 4 (6.1%) patients had at least one DSM diagnosis at baseline, whereas 21 (31.8%) at follow-up. Among the most commonly observed diagnoses at follow-up, minor depression and generalized anxiety disorder were detected. Indeed, it was reported that anxiety and depressive disorders are prevalent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>] and can affect patients&#8217; quality of life, as well as the course of IBD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Moreover, in a review by Arp and colleagues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>] the prevalence of psychiatric comorbidities was high in patients with IBD and higher than in the background population. Further, a retrospective study by Marrie and colleagues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] reported that individuals with Immune Mediated Inflammatory Disease (IMID), including IBD, have a non-specifically increased risk of psychiatric comorbidity with a cumulative incidence of depression of 20% five years after the IBD diagnosis.</p><p id="Par26">About psychosomatic syndromes, the majority of the sample both at baseline and follow-up (71.2% and 75.5%, respectively) presented at least one DCPR syndrome. Among them, allostatic overload, alexithymia, type A behavior and demoralization were frequently observed both at baseline and follow-up in IBD patients, whereas persistent somatization was the only DCPR syndrome increased at follow-up. It is well known the relevance of the DCPR system in detecting psychological distress in medical disease settings, in comparison or integrated with the current psychiatric system. Indeed, DCPR syndromes were found to be transversally represented in most medical settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], even though in IBD patients had never been described. From the present study findings, it seems that more than a quarter of IBD patients present with allostatic overload, alexithymia or Type A behavior, both at baseline and follow-up. Patients with allostatic overload are thus characterized by feelings of being overwhelmed by the demands of daily life and may also present sleep disturbances, irritability, impaired social or occupational functioning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Psychological stress has long been reported anecdotally to increase disease activity in IBD. Studies have confirmed that adverse life events and chronic stress increase the likelihood of relapse in patients with quiescent IBD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. IBD patients with alexithymia are inhibited concerning the experience and expression of emotions and show difficulties in communication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Elevated levels of alexithymia were commonly observed in patients with IBD, especially in females [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>], and this appeared to be associated with an increased likelihood of experiencing unfavorable clinical outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. IBD patients with Type A behavior are characterized by impatience and a sense of time-related pressure, irritability, and a competitive drive. The high frequency of Type A behavior in IBD patients and not only in cardiology settings, suggests that it might be considered as a relevant psychosomatic factor across a variety of clinical and preclinical conditions requiring a careful evaluation by clinicians [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Demoralized IBD patients present a feeling state characterized by their consciousness of having failed to meet their own expectations (or those of others) or being unable to cope with some pressing problems. Demoralized patients also experience prolonged and generalized feelings of helplessness. This phenomenon should not be ascribed to a normative reaction to stress or the presence of mood disorders in a subdued form [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. In the literature, findings suggest a high prevalence of demoralization in the medically ill and the feasibility of a differentiation between demoralization and depression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. In the current study, the only diagnosis that had a significant increase at follow-up was persistent somatization. Indeed, 4 patients (6.1%) at baseline and 16 patients (24.2%) at follow-up presented this syndrome. Patients presenting persistent somatization complain about functional symptoms, such as IBS-like symptoms, causing distress, repeated medical care or impaired quality of life; they also exhibit additional symptoms of autonomic arousal also involving other organ systems and exaggerated side effects from medical therapy, indicating low sensations or pain thresholds and high suggestibility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Consistently with the tendency of these patients to have difficulties expressing psychological distress, leading to its translation into physical symptoms, psychological comorbidity including somatization and perceived stress were found to be common in IBD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>].</p><p id="Par27">The comparison of well-being scores, as measured by the PWB-I at baseline and follow-up, did not show any significant results. However, in comparison with the PWB-I scores of a screening population for fecal occult blood test in a study conducted by Gostoli and colleagues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>], in the present investigation, the PWB-I scores of IBD patients without DCPR syndromes were similar to those of the screening population without DCPR syndromes, whereas the PWB-I scores of IBD patients with DCPR syndromes were slightly lower than those of the screening population with DCPR syndromes.</p><p id="Par28">Concerning lifestyle-related behaviors, a notable and statistically significant increase in physical activity and the consumption of vegetables was detected. This could be the result of healthy lifestyle promoting prescriptions given&#160;by the gastroenterologist during the scheduled visits and followed by the patients, contrary to the literature contributions, which instead reported IBD patients&#8217; difficulty in adhering to them [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. It has been reported that physical activity represents a protective factor against IBD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The literature also provides some guidelines on the optimal diet for these patients, suggesting that low-fiber diets may encourage intestinal inflammation, while high-fiber diets may provide protection against the inflammatory process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. In the present study, other healthy lifestyle behaviors were maintained, probably because most patients had been living with the disease for many years, before the first assessment, and thus&#160;they might have already adjusted some aspects of their habits. Consequently, at follow-up, the majority have continued to uphold these changes. This finding is in contrast with the study by Lo et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], where IBD outpatients were found to not practice such recommendations. As said before, it is likely that the gastroenterologists involved in the present study posed a great attention on healthy lifestyle.</p><p id="Par29">Concerning the IBD related symptoms and IBS-like symptoms, whilst nearly all the patients were asymptomatic at baseline, only IBS-like symptoms such as abdominal pain, bloating, diarrhea and watery stools showed a significant increase after 4-year follow-up. On the same line, contributions in literature showed a higher prevalence of IBS-like symptoms in patients with IBD than in the general population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. Such symptoms were associated with psychological comorbidity, such as anxiety and depression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. According to Spiller and Major [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>], a dysregulated interaction between peripheral factors (i.e.,&#160;microbiota and&#160;post-inflammatory changes) and central factors (stress, psychological comorbidity), might generate such gastrointestinal symptoms. Furthermore, in the present study, findings of increased persistent somatization at follow-up might result in a higher burden of IBS-like symptoms.</p><p id="Par30">Regarding the second aim, it was observed that only 1.5% of the IBD patients maintained at least one DSM diagnosis, despite in the literature Bisgaard and colleagues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] found that patients with IBD had higher risk of anxiety and depression continuing until at least ten years after IBD diagnosis. On the other hand, our findings showed that more than half of the patients maintained psychosomatic syndromes between baseline and follow-up. The most stable DCPR syndromes included allostatic overload, type A behavior and demoralization. To the best of our knowledge, there is a lack of literature specifically addressing this topic but there are some notable contributions in other medical settings. For example, patients with post-coronary artery bypass grafting and those with Implantable Cardioverter Defibrillators (ICD) showed sustained DCPR syndromes over time. The 1-month and 6/8-year post-surgery assessments for bypass patients confirmed stability in type A behavior, irritable mood, demoralization and persistent somatization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. The latter syndromes persisted over a year in ICD patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. In line with our findings, DCPR categories remained stable in individuals over time in both cases. The stability of DCPR syndromes might as well have resulted in increased burden of IBS-like symptoms along the follow-up period, as previously described. Moreover, unlike depression, demoralization was found to rarely persist as an uninterrupted condition for any substantial duration, in different medical settings (e.g.,&#160;gastroenterology, cardiology, endocrinology, and oncology) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. However, this is in contrast with the findings of the present study, where more than half of the patients affected by demoralization at baseline presented with persistent demoralization at follow-up.</p><p id="Par31">The current study shows some limitations such as small sample size, absence of a control group, distinction between IBD- and IBS-like symptoms not always possible and data collection method, which changed between the initial and follow-up assessments. Indeed, during the baseline assessment, interviews were performed face-to-face, while follow-up assessments were conducted over the phone. This variation in data collection methods might have introduced factors such as participants&#8217; fatigue, especially given the overall length of the interviews, potentially leading to less attentive responses. In addition, the telephone-based approach and the absence of in-person contact could have influenced the relationship between the interviewer and the patients, especially with older participants.</p><p id="Par32">Despite the mentioned limitations, the strengths of this study include the presence of a comprehensive assessment of clinical and sub-clinical aspects of IBD patients, the longitudinal design of the study and the use of measure according to clinimetric validity.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par33">These longitudinal study findings revealed clinical and persistent subclinical distress in a sample of IBD outpatients longitudinally assessed. It seems that, whereas psychiatric conditions are more changeable over time, psychosomatic syndromes such as allostatic overload, type A behavior, alexithymia and demoralization represent persistent unhealthy attitudes in IBD patients at a long-term follow. These findings, together with the development of persistent somatization at follow-up, might have an impact on the increase of IBS-like symptoms, whereas after 4-year follow-up IBD symptoms were managed. Since it has been advocated the need for a comprehensive assessment and management of IBD, in order to develop more targeted treatment, an integrated assessment through the DCPR system enables the identification of subclinical aspects not detected by traditional tools, as vulnerability factors of the disease. From a secondary prevention perspective, studying the persistence over time of certain DCPR syndromes in patients with IBD could be useful to monitor the psychophysical conditions of IBD patients.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#8217;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>S.G.: conceptualization and methodology, validation, visualization, writing&#8212;original draft, writing&#8212;review and editing; F.F.: conceptualization and methodology, validation, resources, project administration, writing&#8212;review and editing; L.Q.: validation, formal analysis, investigation, data curation, visualization, writing&#8212;original draft, writing&#8212;review and editing; S.T.: validation, formal analysis, investigation, data curation, visualization, writing&#8212;original draft, writing&#8212;review and editing; G.G.: formal analysis, writing&#8212;review and editing; M.M.: resources; A.U.: resources; F.G.: formal analysis, writing&#8212;review and editing; R.S.: writing&#8212;review and editing; A.D.: visualization, writing&#8212;review and editing; A.P.: resources, writing&#8212;review and editing; F.B.: resources, writing&#8212;review and editing; V.C.: supervision, resources, writing&#8212;review and editing; C.R.: conceptualization and methodology, validation, visualization, supervision, project administration, writing&#8212;original draft, writing&#8212;review and editing.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are available on request from the corresponding author. The data are not publicly available due to privacy or ethical restrictions.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par34">The ethics committee of the local health authority (AUSL Bologna, Italy) approved the longitudinal study (Ref: 530/2018/OSS/AUSLBO). All participants involved in the study provided written informed consent to participate in the current research. Participants were informed from the outset of their right to withdraw from the study at any time.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par35">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par36">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henriksen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jahnsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lygren</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aadland</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vatn</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical course in Crohn&#8217;s disease: Results of a five-year population-based follow-up study (the IBSEN study)</article-title><source>Scand J Gastroenterol</source><year>2007</year><volume>42</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>602</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00365520601076124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17454881</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colonnello</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agostini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disease course, stress, attachment, and mentalization in patients with inflammatory bowel disease</article-title><source>Med Hypotheses</source><year>2020</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>109665</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mehy.2020.109665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32155541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Windsor JW, Kaplan GG. Evolving Epidemiology of IBD. Curr Gastroenterol Rep. 2019;21(8). Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11894-019-0705-6">https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11894-019-0705-6</ext-link>. 
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11894-019-0705-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31338613</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coward</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benchimol</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avina-Zubieta</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bitton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hazlewood</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jelinski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deardon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuenzig</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leddin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McBrien</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otley</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panaccione</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezaie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenfeld</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pe&#241;a-S&#225;nchez</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Targownik</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Past and Future Burden of Inflammatory Bowel Diseases Based on Modeling of Population-Based Data</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2019</year><volume>156</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1345</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2019.01.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30639677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caviglia</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertolino</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bretto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poshnjari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tribocco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armandi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Astegiano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saracco</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertolusso</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribaldone</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of inflammatory bowel diseases: a population study in a healthcare District of North-West Italy</article-title><source>J Clin Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>641</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm12020641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36675570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9860659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McDowell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farooq</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haseeb</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Inflammatory Bowel Disease</source><year>2023</year><publisher-loc>In StatPearls</publisher-loc><publisher-name>StatPearls Publishing</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29262182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sza&#322;wi&#324;ska</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>W&#322;odarczyk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spinelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fichna</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>W&#322;odarczyk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IBS-Symptoms in IBD patients&#8212;manifestation of concomitant or different entities</article-title><source>J Clin Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>31</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm10010031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33374388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7794700</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kilic</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaffar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sriranganathan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quraishi</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of extraintestinal manifestations in inflammatory bowel disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Inflamm Bowel Dis</source><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ibd/izad061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37042969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faye</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holmer</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Axelrad</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer in inflammatory bowel disease</article-title><source>Gastroenterol Clin North Am</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gtc.2022.05.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36153115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gracie</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guthrie</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamlin</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bi-directionality of brain-gut interactions in patients with inflammatory bowel disease</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2018</year><volume>154</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1635</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2018.01.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29366841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marrie</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walld</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolton</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sareen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patten</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lix</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hitchon</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Gabalawy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisk</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased incidence of psychiatric disorders in immune-mediated inflammatory disease</article-title><source>J Psychosom Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2017.07.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28867419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fousekis FS, Katsanos AH, Kourtis G, Saridi M, Albani E, Katsanos KH, Christodoulou DK. Inflammatory Bowel Disease and Patients With Mental Disorders: What Do We Know? J Clin Med Res. 2021;13(9):466-73. 10.14740/jocmr4593. 
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14740/jocmr4593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8510650</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34691320</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nass</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dibbets</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Markus</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on inflammatory bowel disease: The role of emotional stress and social isolation</article-title><source>Stress Health</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/smi.3080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34273129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8420478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eldridge</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raine</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding and addressing the psychological burden of IBD</article-title><source>J Crohn&#8217;s Colitis</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ecco-jcc/jjab130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34468698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tavakoli P, Vollmer-Conna U, Hadzi-Pavlovic D, Grimm MC. A review of inflammatory bowel disease: a model of microbial, immune and neuropsychological integration. Public Health Rev. 2021; 42. 10.3389/phrs.2021.1603990. 
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/phrs.2021.1603990</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8386758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34692176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eugenicos</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychological factors associated with inflammatory bowel disease</article-title><source>Br Med Bullett</source><year>2021</year><volume>138</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bmb/ldab010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8361235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34057462</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitropoulou</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fradelos</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsaras</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christodoulou</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Papathanasiou</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality of life in patients with inflammatory bowel disease: importance of psychological symptoms</article-title><source>Cureus</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.28502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36185946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9514670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gracie</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sood</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mumtaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bholah</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamlin</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Poor correlation between clinical disease activity and mucosal inflammation, and the role of psychological comorbidity, in inflammatory bowel disease</article-title><source>Off J Am Coll Gastroenterol</source><year>2016</year><volume>111</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ajg.2016.59</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27002800</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vigan&#242; CA, Beltrami MM, Bosi MF, Zanello R, Valtorta M, Maconi G. Alexithymia and Psychopathology in patients suffering from inflammatory bowel disease: arising differences and correlations to tailoring therapeutic strategies. Front Psychiatry. 2018;9. 10.3389/fpsyt.2018.00324. 
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpsyt.2018.00324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6088187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30127753</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iglesias-Rey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barreiro-de Acosta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caama&#241;o-Isorna</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>V&#225;zquez Rodr&#237;guez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenzo Gonz&#225;lez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bello-Paderne</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dom&#237;nguez-Mu&#241;oz</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of alexithymia on health-related quality of life in inflammatory bowel disease: are there any related factors?</article-title><source>Scand J Gastroenterol</source><year>2012</year><volume>47</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/00365521.2012.654403</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22300356</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bogut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinac</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pravdi&#263;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Personality Traits and Health Related Quality of Life in Patients with Irritable Bowel Sindrome and Inflammatory Bowel Disease</article-title><source>Psychiatria Danubina</source><year>2022</year><volume>34</volume><issue>Suppl 10</issue><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36752243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gatt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schembri</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katsanos</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christodoulou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karmiris</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kopylov</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pontas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koutroubakis</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foteinogiannopoulou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fabian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molnar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zammit</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fragaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balomenos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zingboim</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ben Horin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mantzaris</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellul</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inflammatory Bowel Disease [IBD] and physical activity: a study on the impact of diagnosis on the level of exercise amongst patients with IBD</article-title><source>J Crohn&#8217;s Colit</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>686</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ecco-jcc/jjy214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30561568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lautenschlager SA, Barry MP, Rogler G, Biedermann L, Schreiner P, Siebenh&#252;ner AR, Abdelrahman K, Ademi G, Aepli P, Thomas A, Anderegg C, Antonino AT, Archanioti E, Arrigoni E, de Jong DB, Balsiger B, Bast&#252;rk P, Bauerfeind P, Becocci A, Belli D, Bengoa JM, Binek J, Blattmann M, Boehm S, Boldanova T, Borovicka J, BellBraeggeri CP, Brand S, Br&#252;gger L, Brunner S, B&#252;hr P, Burnand B, Burk S, Burri E, Buyse S, Cao DT, Carstens O, Cao DT, Criblez DH, Cunningham S, D&#8217;Angelo F, de Saussure P, Degen L, Delarive J, Doerig C, Dora B, Drerup S, Egger M, El-Wafa A, Zimmermann D. Lifestyle factors associated with inflammatory bowel disease: data from the Swiss IBD cohort study. BMC Gastroenterol. 2023;23(1). 10.1186/s12876-023-02692-9. 
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12876-023-02692-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10008613</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36907848</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morys</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kacz&#243;wka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Je&#380;ewska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of selected psychological factors in patients with inflammatory bowel disease</article-title><source>Gastroenterol Rev</source><year>2016</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5114/pg.2015.52560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4814534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27110311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexakis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chhaya</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cecil</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Majeed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pollok</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Smoking status at diagnosis and subsequent smoking cessation: associations with corticosteroid use and intestinal resection in crohn&#700;s disease</article-title><source>Off J Am Coll Gastroenterol</source><year>2018</year><volume>113</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1689</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41395-018-0273-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30323269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rozich JJ, Holmer A, Singh S. Effect of lifestyle factors on outcomes in patients with inflammatory bowel diseases. Am J Gastroenterol. 2020;115(6):832-40. 10.14309/ajg.0000000000000608. 
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14309/ajg.0000000000000608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7274876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32224703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalili</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lochhead</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giovannucci</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ananthakrishnan</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Healthy lifestyle is associated with reduced mortality in patients with inflammatory bowel diseases</article-title><source>Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><year>2021</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cgh.2020.02.047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32142939</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7483199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bisgaard TH, Poulsen G, Allin KH, Keefer L, Ananthakrishnan AN, Jess T. Longitudinal trajectories of anxiety, depression, and bipolar disorder in inflammatory bowel disease: a population-based cohort study. eClinicalMedicine. 2023;59:101986. Disponibile all'indirizzo: 10.1016/j.eclinm.2023.101986. 
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.eclinm.2023.101986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10184046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37197708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">American Psychiatric Association. Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders. 5th ed. 2013.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cosci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sonino</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current PSYCHOSOMATIC PRACTICE</article-title><source>Psychother Psychosom</source><year>2016</year><volume>86</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000448856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27884006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomba</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increasing Psychological Well-Being and Resilience by Psychotherapeutic Methods</article-title><source>J Personal</source><year>2009</year><volume>77</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1903</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-6494.2009.00604.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19807860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maaser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sturm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vavricka</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kucharzik</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiorino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Annese</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calabrese</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baumgart</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bettenworth</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borralho Nunes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burisch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castiglione</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eliakim</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellul</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez-Lama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halligan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katsanos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kopylov</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kotze</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krusti&#326;&#353;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laghi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Limdi</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rieder</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rimola</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Rheenen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verstockt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ECCO-ESGAR Guideline for Diagnostic Assessment in IBD Part 1: initial diagnosis, monitoring of known IBD, detection of complications</article-title><source>J Crohn&#8217;s Colitis</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ecco-jcc/jjy113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30137275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sturm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maaser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calabrese</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Annese</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiorino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kucharzik</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vavricka</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verstockt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Rheenen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rimola</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rieder</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Limdi</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laghi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krusti&#326;&#353;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kotze</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kopylov</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katsanos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halligan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez Lama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellul</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eliakim</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castiglione</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burisch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borralho Nunes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bettenworth</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baumgart</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ECCO-ESGAR Guideline for Diagnostic Assessment in IBD Part 2: IBD scores and general principles and technical aspects</article-title><source>J Crohn&#8217;s Colitis</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ecco-jcc/jjy114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30137278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">First, M. B., Williams, J. B. W., Karg, R. S. &amp; Spitzer, R. L. SCID-5-CV.&#160;Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-5 Disorders. Clinician Version. 2017. Raffaello Cortina Editore.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">First, M. B., Williams, J. B. W., Karg, R. S. &amp; Spitzer, R. L. SCID-5-CV.&#160;Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-5 Disorders. Clinician Version American Psychiatric Association. 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>American Psychiatric Association</collab></person-group><source>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders Fourth Edition Text Revision (DSM-IV-TR)</source><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>American Psychiatric Association</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Os&#243;rio</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loureiro</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallak</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Machado-de-Sousa</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ushirohira</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baes</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apolinario</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donadon</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolsoni</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guimar&#227;es</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fracon</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva-Rodrigues</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pizeta</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanches</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin-Santos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crippa</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical validity and intrarater and test&#8211;retest reliability of the Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-5 &#8211; Clinician Version (SCID-5-CV)</article-title><source>Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</source><year>2019</year><volume>73</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>754</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pcn.12931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31490607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shabani A, Masoumian S, Zamirinejad S, Hejri M, Pirmorad T, Yaghmaeezadeh H. Psychometric properties of Structured Clinical Interview for DSM&#8208;5 Disorders&#8208;Clinician Version (SCID&#8208;5&#8208;CV). Brain Behav. 2021;11(5). 10.1002/brb3.1894. 
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/brb3.1894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8119811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33729681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Porcelli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rafanelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Criteria for Psychosomatic Research (DCPR) in the Medical Setting</article-title><source>Curr Psychiatry Rep</source><year>2010</year><volume>12</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11920-010-0104-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20425288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Offidani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rafanelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gostoli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marchetti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roncuzzi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allostatic overload in patients with atrial fibrillation</article-title><source>Int J Cardiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>165</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijcard.2012.08.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22974727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guidi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucente</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sonino</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allostatic Load and Its Impact on Health: A Systematic Review</article-title><source>Psychother Psychosom</source><year>2020</year><volume>90</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000510696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32799204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cosci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The clinical inadequacy of the DSM-5 classification of somatic symptom and related disorders: an alternative trans-diagnostic model</article-title><source>CNS Spectrum</source><year>2015</year><volume>21</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>310</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/s1092852915000760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26707822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galeazzi</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mackinnon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rigatelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interrater reliability, prevalence, and relation to ICD-10 diagnoses of the diagnostic criteria for psychosomatic research in consultation-liaison psychiatry patients</article-title><source>Psychosomatics</source><year>2004</year><volume>45</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>386</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.psy.45.5.386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15345783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guidi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piolanti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berrocal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gostoli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrozzino</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incremental Validity Of The Diagnostic Criteria For Psychosomatic Research &#8211; Revised (DCPR-R) to clinical assessment in primary care</article-title><source>Psychiatry Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>291</volume><fpage>113233</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32563748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryff</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Happiness is everything, or is it? Explorations on the meaning of psychological well-being</article-title><source>J Personal Soc Psychol</source><year>1989</year><volume>57</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1069</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0022-3514.57.6.1069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Internet addiction and psychological well-being among college students: a cross-sectional study from Central India</article-title><source>J Fam Med Prim Care</source><year>2018</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>147</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_189_17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5958557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29915749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giannuzzi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Secondary prevention through cardiac rehabilitation position paper of the working group on cardiac rehabilitation and exercise physiology of the european society of cardiology</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><year>2003</year><volume>24</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>1273</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0195-668x(03)00198-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12831822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giannuzzi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Temporelli</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maggioni</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ceci</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chieffo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gattone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marchioli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schweiger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tavazzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urbinati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valagussa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanuzzo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GlObal Secondary Prevention strategiEs to Limit event recurrence after myocardial infarction: the GOSPEL study. A trial from the Italian Cardiac Rehabilitation Network: rationale and design</article-title><source>Eur J Prev Cardiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>12</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>555</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.hjr.0000186623.60486.26</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16319545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gostoli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roncuzzi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urbinati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morisky</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rafanelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unhealthy behaviour modification, psychological distress, and 1-year survival in cardiac rehabilitation</article-title><source>Br J Health Psychol</source><year>2016</year><volume>21</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>894</fpage><lpage>916</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bjhp.12204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27316556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giannuzzi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Temporelli</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marchioli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maggioni</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balestroni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ceci</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chieffo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gattone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schweiger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tavazzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urbinati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valagussa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanuzzo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global secondary prevention strategies to limit event recurrence after myocardial infarction</article-title><source>Arch Internal Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>168</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>2194</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.168.20.2194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19001195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drossman</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The psychosocial aspects of inflammatory bowel disease</article-title><source>Stress Med</source><year>1986</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/smi.2460020209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hu S, Chen Y, Chen Y, Wang C. Depression and anxiety disorders in patients with inflammatory bowel disease. Front Psychiatry. 2021;12. 10.3389/fpsyt.2021.714057. 
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpsyt.2021.714057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8531580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34690829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Arp L, Jansson S, Wewer V, Burisch J. Psychiatric disorders in adult and paediatric patients with inflammatory bowel diseases &#8211; a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Crohn's Colitis. 2022;1933&#8211;1945. 10.1093/ecco-jcc/jjac095. 
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ecco-jcc/jjac095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35775920</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mawdsley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychological stress in IBD: new insights into pathogenic and therapeutic implications</article-title><source>Gut</source><year>2005</year><volume>54</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1481</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gut.2005.064261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16162953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1774724</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">La Barbera D, Bonanno B, Rumeo MV, Alabastro V, Frenda M, Massihnia E, Morgante MC, Sideli L, Crax&#236; A, Cappello M, Tumminello M, Miccich&#232; S, Nastri L. Alexithymia and personality traits of patients with inflammatory bowel disease. Sci Rep. 2017;7(1). 10.1038/srep41786. 
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/srep41786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5288771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28150800</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mangelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grandi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grassi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ottolini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Porcelli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rafanelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rigatelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sonino</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing demoralization and depression in the setting of medical disease</article-title><source>J Clin Psychiatry</source><year>2005</year><volume>66</volume><issue>03</issue><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4088/jcp.v66n0317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15766307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gracie</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Irritable bowel syndrome-type symptoms are associated with psychological comorbidity, reduced quality of life, and health care use in patients with inflammatory bowel disease</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2017</year><volume>153</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>324</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2017.05.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28572008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Savarese&#160;M, Castellini&#160;G, Leone&#160;S, Previtali&#160;E, Armuzzi&#160;A, Graffigna&#160;G. Psychological reaction to Covid-19 of Italian patients with IBD. BMC Psychol. 2021;9(1). 10.1186/s40359-021-00622-6. 
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s40359-021-00622-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8343359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34362456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gostoli S, Montecchiarini M, Urgese A, Ferrara F, Polifemo AM, Ceroni L, Gasparri A, Rafanelli C, Cennamo V. The clinical utility of a comprehensive psychosomatic assessment in the program for colorectal cancer prevention: a cross-sectional study. Sci Rep. 2021;11(1). 10.1038/s41598-021-95171-8. 
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-021-95171-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8329196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34341444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutritional and dietary strategy in the clinical care of inflammatory bowel disease</article-title><source>J Formosan Med Assoc</source><year>2020</year><volume>119</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1742</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jfma.2019.09.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31624009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strid</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of IBS-type symptoms in IBD</article-title><source>Lancet Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><year>2020</year><volume>5</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1029</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s2468-1253(20)30291-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33010813</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fairbrass</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costantino</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gracie</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of irritable bowel syndrome-type symptoms in patients with inflammatory bowel disease in remission: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Lancet Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><year>2020</year><volume>5</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1053</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s2468-1253(20)30300-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33010814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spiller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Major</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IBS and IBD &#8212; separate entities or on a spectrum?</article-title><source>Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><year>2016</year><volume>13</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrgastro.2016.141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27667579</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rafanelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roncuzzi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milaneschi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Minor Depression as a Cardiac Risk Factor After Coronary Artery Bypass Surgery</article-title><source>Psychosomatics.</source><year>2006</year><volume>47</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.psy.47.4.289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16844886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Banihashemian</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fakhri</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moazzen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Obsessive-compulsive disorder as a risk factor in patients with implantable cardioverter defibrillator</article-title><source>Iran Red Crescent Med J</source><year>2011</year><volume>13</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>514</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22737521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3371984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guidi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical characterization of demoralization</article-title><source>Psychother Psychosom.</source><year>2023</year><volume>92</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000530760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37231894</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>