<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Obstet Gynecol MFM</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am J Obstet Gynecol MFM</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3815</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">pheelsevier</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>American Journal of Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology Mfm</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2589-9333</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Elsevier - PMC COVID-19 Collection</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10268810</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10268810.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10268810</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10268810</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37330010</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajogmf.2023.101057</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2589-9333(23)00199-4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101057</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Relationship between COVID-19 Vaccination Status in Pregnancy and Birth Weight</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaur</surname><given-names initials="P">Priyanka</given-names></name><degrees>MD MPH</degrees><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">&#8270;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002"><name name-style="western"><surname>Darwin</surname><given-names initials="KC">Kristin C.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0003"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names initials="JR">Jaden R.</given-names></name><degrees>MD MPH</degrees><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0004"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uribe</surname><given-names initials="K">Katelyn</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shippey</surname><given-names initials="E">Ernie</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0006"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eke</surname><given-names initials="A">Ahizechukwu</given-names></name><degrees>MD PhD MPH</degrees><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>Department of Gynecology and Obstetrics, The Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland, USA</aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label>Division of Maternal Fetal Medicine, Department of Gynecology and Obstetrics, The Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland, USA</aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label>Division of Clinical Pharmacology, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland, USA.</aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label>Vizient &#174; Inc, Irvine, Texas, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor0001"><label>&#8270;</label>Corresponding author: Priyanka Gaur MD MPH, Department of Gynecology &amp; Obstetrics, Johns Hopkins Hospital, 600 N. Wolfe Street, Phipps 228, Baltimore, MD 21287. Phone: 410-955-8436</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">438208</issue-id><elocation-id>101057</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>4</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>15</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-06-21 23:25:09.980"><day>21</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Published by Elsevier Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0001"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Despite findings that maternal COVID-19 infection in pregnancy is associated with low birth weight (LBW; weight &lt; 2,500 grams), previous studies demonstrate no difference in LBW risk between COVID-19 vaccinated and unvaccinated pregnant persons. Few studies, however, have examined the association of unvaccinated, incomplete, and complete vaccination on LBW, and they have been limited by small sample sizes and lack of adjustment for covariates.</p></sec><sec><title>Objective</title><p>We sought to address key limitations of prior work and evaluate this association between unvaccinated, incomplete, and complete COVID-19 vaccination status in pregnancy and LBW. We predicted a protective association of vaccination on LBW that varies by number of doses received.</p></sec><sec><title>Study design</title><p>We performed a population-based retrospective study using the Vizient&#174; clinical database, which included data from 192 hospitals in the United States. Our sample included pregnant persons who delivered between January 2021 and April 2022 at hospitals that reported maternal vaccination data and birth weight at delivery. Pregnant persons were categorized into three groups: unvaccinated; incompletely vaccinated (one dose of Pfizer or Moderna); or completely vaccinated (one dose of Johnson &amp; Johnson or &#8805; two doses of Moderna or Pfizer). Demographics and outcomes were analyzed using standard statistical tests. We performed multivariable logistic regression to account for potential confounders between vaccination status and LBW in the original cohort. Propensity score matching was used to reduce bias related to likelihood of vaccination, and the multivariable logistic regression model was then applied to the propensity score matched cohort. Stratification analysis was performed for gestational age and race/ethnicity.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Of the 377,995 participants, 31,155 (8.2%) had LBW, and these participants were more likely to be unvaccinated than those without LBW (98.8% versus 98.5%, p &lt; 0.001). Incompletely vaccinated pregnant persons were 13% less likely to have LBW neonates compared to unvaccinated persons (odds ratio 0.87, 95% confidence interval 0.73-1.04), and completely vaccinated persons were 21% less likely to have LBW neonates (odds ratio 0.79, 95% confidence interval 0.79-0.89). After controlling for maternal age, race/ethnicity, hypertension, diabetes, lupus, tobacco use, multifetal gestation, obesity, use of assisted reproductive technology, and maternal/neonatal COVID-19 infections in the original cohort, these associations remained significant for only complete vaccination (adjusted odds ratio 0.80, 95% confidence interval 0.70-0.91) and not incomplete vaccination (adjusted odds ratio 0.87, 95% confidence interval 0.71-1.04). In the propensity score matched cohort, pregnant persons who were completely vaccinated against COVID-19 were 22% less likely to have LBW neonates compared to unvaccinated and incompletely vaccinated individuals (aOR 0.78, 95% CI 0.76-0.79).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Pregnant persons who were completely vaccinated against COVID-19 were less likely to have LBW neonates compared to unvaccinated and incompletely vaccinated individuals. This novel association was observed among a large population after adjusting for confounders of LBW and factors influencing the likelihood of receiving the COVID-19 vaccine.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="keys0001"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>cesarean delivery</kwd><kwd>COVID-19 infection</kwd><kwd>low birth weight</kwd><kwd>NICU admission</kwd><kwd>prematurity</kwd><kwd>primary series</kwd><kwd>unvaccinated</kwd><kwd>vaccine hesitancy</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="para9001">
<boxed-text id="tbox0002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>AJOG at a Glance:</title></caption><p id="para0012"><bold>Why was this study conducted?</bold> Despite findings that maternal COVID-19 infection in pregnancy is associated with low birth weight (LBW; weight &#8804; 2,500 grams), previous studies are conflicting regarding LBW risk between vaccinated and unvaccinated pregnant persons.</p><p id="para0013"><bold>Key findings?</bold> Compared to unvaccinated and incompletely vaccinated pregnant persons, completely vaccinated individuals were less likely to have LBW neonates.</p><p id="para0014"><bold>What does this add to what is known?</bold> We describe an association between complete COVID-19 vaccination status in pregnancy and neonatal weight at delivery. Complete COVID-19 vaccination may be protective against LBW.</p><notes notes-type="alt-text" specific-use="for-accessibility" id="alte1"><p>Alt-text: Unlabelled box</p></notes></boxed-text>
</p><sec id="sec0001"><title>Introduction</title><p id="para0015">Untreated COVID-19 infection in unvaccinated pregnant persons continues to be a cause of maternal, fetal, and neonatal morbidity in the United States.<sup>1-3</sup> Following the emergence of data from several studies demonstrating the efficacy and safety of the COVID-19 vaccine, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (ACOG) and the Society for Maternal Fetal Medicine (SMFM) recommended vaccination for all pregnant persons to prevent significant maternal and neonatal morbidity.<sup>4</sup> As of March 2023, 70% of pregnant people ages 18-49 in the United States were completely vaccinated against COVID-19 before or during pregnancy.<sup>5</sup> While the majority of pregnant persons accept the vaccine, recent studies project that 30-50% of those who accept a COVID-19 vaccine cite safety concerns.<sup>6</sup> Vaccine hesitancy persists among pregnant persons, mainly due to fetal and neonatal concerns, necessitating studies to understand the effects of COVID-19 vaccinations on neonatal outcomes when compared to unvaccinated groups.</p><p id="para0016">Low birth weight (LBW; weight &#8804; 2,500 grams at birth) is an outcome associated with several maternal infectious diseases in pregnant persons,<sup>7-9</sup> and hence a potential concern for pregnancies impacted by COVID-19 infection. According to the CDC National Vital Statistics Reports, the LBW rate among singleton births in the United States was 8.2% in 2020.<sup>10</sup> LBW is associated with several significant risks to the neonate in the short- and long-term. Immediate risks include respiratory distress syndrome, hypothermia, sepsis, intracranial hemorrhage, and admission to a neonatal intensive care unit.<sup>11-12</sup> Infants are also at increased risk of developmental delays and chronic conditions such as hypertension, diabetes, and heart disease.<sup>13-15</sup>
</p><p id="para0017">Most, though not all, studies have shown higher LBW rates in pregnant persons infected with COVID-19 as high as 17%.<sup>16-23</sup> Recent studies demonstrate no difference in LBW risk between vaccinated and unvaccinated persons against COVID-19.<sup>24-28</sup> These studies were limited by smaller sample sizes and lacked adjustment of covariates.<sup>25-26</sup> In addition, vaccination status was dichotomized as unvaccinated or having received at least one vaccine, rather than stratifying by incomplete and complete vaccination. Only one report by the United Kingdom Government with longitudinal data from 2021-2023 identified a higher proportion of LBW infants in unvaccinated individuals (8.6%, 95% CI 8.5-8.7) compared to those with at least one vaccine dose (8.1%, 95% CI 8.0-8.2), and we suspect this may be attributable to larger sample sizes (thousands versus hundreds).<sup>29</sup> Very few studies have explored the association between unvaccinated, incomplete, and complete vaccination status and LBW among a large population while accounting for prematurity and maternal comorbidities that are known contributors to birth weight. Therefore, we evaluated this association and predicted a protective association of vaccination on LBW that varies by number of doses received.</p></sec><sec id="sec0002"><title>Methods</title><p id="para0018">Approval from the Institutional Review Board was obtained, and this study was deemed exempt due to use of de-identified data. We performed a population-based retrospective study of 377,995 pregnancies to examine associations between COVID-19 vaccination status and LBW. We utilized the claims-based Vizient&#174; clinical database/Resource Manager (CDB; Vizient Inc), which included data from 192 hospitals across 38 states in the United States.<sup>30</sup> The Vizient clinical database is a healthcare analytics platform for tracking clinical performance measures and has been used successfully to study outcomes in COVID-19 vaccinated persons.<sup>31-33</sup>
</p><p id="para0019">Individuals met inclusion criteria if they were greater than 4 weeks of gestational age in the current pregnancy; between the ages of 13-55 years of age; delivered between January 2021 and April 2022 at hospitals that reported patient vaccination data; and had neonatal birth weight recorded at the time of delivery. Pregnant persons were categorized into three groups: unvaccinated; incompletely vaccinated (one dose of Pfizer or Moderna); or completely vaccinated (one dose of Johnson &amp; Johnson or &#8805; two doses of Moderna or Pfizer). People who also received booster immunizations were included in the completely vaccinated group. Pregnant persons were excluded if vaccination status was not recorded; they were vaccinated postpartum; gestational age at birth was less than 20 weeks or greater than 42 weeks; birth weight was less than 1,000 grams; or they had abnormal pregnancies (ectopic and molar pregnancies) (<xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>
).<fig id="fig0001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) diagram of how participants were selected</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0004">Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1_lrg.jpg"/></fig></p><sec id="sec0003"><title>Definition of Exposure and Outcome</title><p id="para0020">Our primary outcome of interest was LBW among pregnant women who were completely, incompletely, or unvaccinated against COVID-19. Our secondary outcomes were maternal demographic variables (age, race, region, and insurance payer type), multifetal gestation, parity, gestational age at delivery, maternal and neonatal COVID-19 infection, NICU admission, mode of delivery, comorbid conditions in pregnancy, and use of assistive reproductive technology. Birth weight at delivery was extracted from claims records. The Vizient clinical database only records COVID-19 vaccination status for persons vaccinated in an inpatient setting. COVID-19 infection was identified as a diagnosis in a facility or physician claim, positive test, or electronic health record data at any time in pregnancy. Birth weight was identified from either claims or electronic health records and not self-reported by patients.</p></sec><sec id="sec0004"><title>Covariates</title><p id="para0021">For this study, several covariates of interest were extracted. Self-reported race was collected as Asian, Black, White, or other. Hispanic/Latino was not reported in the database. Age was categorized as less than or equal to 20 years, between 20 and 35 years, or greater than or equal to 35 years old. Parity was classified as nulliparous or multiparous. Maternal comorbidities were also extracted using ICD-10 codes and included chronic hypertension, pregestational diabetes, lupus, tobacco use, multifetal gestation, obesity (BMI &gt; 30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), use of assisted reproductive technology, and COVID-19 infection in pregnancy. Presence of these comorbidities was recorded as &#8216;yes&#8217; if present and &#8216;no&#8217; if absent. Other covariates extracted from the medical records were neonatal COVID-19 infection and gestational age at delivery.</p></sec><sec id="sec0005"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p id="para0022">An assessment of the data was done at the time of exploratory data analysis, and our data was checked for omitted variables, distributional assumptions, and outliers. Variables were incorporated for analysis if they were at least 90% completely reported. Several sociodemographic and clinical characteristics were compared, and their frequencies were determined between the exposed groups (unvaccinated versus incomplete vaccination versus complete vaccination). Differences between groups were assess with Chi-square or T-tests as appropriate for type of variable. We identified confounders for LBW a priori based on prior literature and used variables available in the database.<sup>34</sup> Multivariable logistic regression was used to estimate the odds of LBW and account for potential confounders. Unadjusted and adjusted odds ratios were reported. Controls included maternal age, race/ethnicity, chronic hypertension, pregestational diabetes, lupus, tobacco use, multifetal gestation, obesity, assisted reproductive technology, and maternal/neonatal COVID infections.</p><p id="para0023">After identifying an association between COVID-19 vaccination and LBW, we sought to reduce biases related to likelihood of vaccination with the use of propensity score matching (PSM). Propensity scores were estimated from the multivariable logistic regression model with COVID-19 vaccination as the outcome. The treated group was classified as completely vaccinated, and the untreated group was classified as incompletely vaccinated or unvaccinated. Covariates included in the PSM model were determined by multivariable logistic regression. Variables that were statistically associated with vaccination and included as covariates were maternal age, race/ethnicity, region, insurance, parity, chronic hypertension, pregestational diabetes, lupus, and tobacco use. PSM with replacement was performed on a 1:1 basis using the nearest neighbor method. We analyzed the treatment effect of COVID-19 vaccination on LBW among the PSM cohort. The propensity score weighted frequencies between the two groups were fit to the multivariable logistic regression models, and unadjusted and adjusted odds ratios were reported.</p><p id="para0024">Stratification analysis was performed among late preterm (34 0/7 &#8211; 36 6/7 weeks) and term (37 0/7 weeks and greater) deliveries by repeating the previously described multivariable logistic regression models with the appropriate gestational ages. We also tested for effect modification by creating two-way interaction terms between vaccination status and race/ethnicity, as both vaccination uptake and birth weight are known to vary by this variable.<sup>35,36</sup> For all models, statistical significance was set at P &lt; 0.05, and odds ratios and adjusted odds ratios were calculated with 95% confidence intervals. Assuming a power of 80%, alpha of 0.05, medium effect size of 0.15, and twelve predictors in the multivariable regression model, a sample size of at least 130 persons was required in each exposure group. All analysis was performed in Stata SE 17 (StataCorp, College Station, TX; 2022).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0006"><title>Results</title><p id="para0025">Of the 377,995 eligible pregnant persons who met the inclusion criteria, 31,155 (8.2%) had LBW, and these patients were more likely to be unvaccinated (<xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
). LBW infants were also more likely to be associated with maternal COVID-19 infection during pregnancy compared to non-LBW infants (3.9% versus 2.9%, p &lt; 0.001). More LBW infants required NICU admission (36.7% versus 6.6%, p &lt; 0.001) and cesarean delivery (52.2% versus 31.0%, p &lt; 0.001) compared to infants without LBW. After controlling for maternal age, race/ethnicity, chronic hypertension, pregestational diabetes, lupus, tobacco use, multifetal gestation, obesity, use of assisted reproductive technology, and COVID-19 infections (maternal and fetal), LBW infants were 35% more likely to be impacted by maternal COVID-19 infection in pregnancy (aOR 1.35, 95% CI 1.26-1.43). Furthermore, the LBW rate among maternal COVID-19 infections was 10.8% compared to 8.2% in those uninfected (p &lt; 0.001).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics and differences for pregnant persons between birth weight groups less than or equal to 2,500 grams and greater than 2,500 grams</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0001">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Birth weight &#8804; 2500g</bold></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Birth weight &gt; 2500g</bold></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>P value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Number (%)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31,155 (8.24)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">346,840 (91.76)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age (years, %)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Less than 20</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,497 (4.81)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,078 (3.77)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 to 35</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22,140 (71.07)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">252,982 (72.84)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Over 35</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7,515 (24.12)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80,763 (23.29)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Race (%)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Black</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8,074 (25.92)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57,322 (16.53)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">White</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,567 (49.97)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">202,958 (58.52)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asian</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,846 (5.93)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20,396 (5.88)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,668 (18.19)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66,164 (19.08)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Nulliparous (%)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,464 (11.12)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48,100 (13.87)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>GA at delivery (weeks, %)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20w0d-23w6d</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51 (0.16))</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">151 (0.04)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24w0d-27w6d</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">524 (1.68)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">245 (0.07)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28w0d-33w6d</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,488 (20.82)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,546 (0.45)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34w0d-36w6d</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9,893 (31.75)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16,083 (4.64)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37w0d-42w0d</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,199 (45.58)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">328,815 (94.80)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Vaccination status (%)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unvaccinated</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30,771 (98.77)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">341,591 (98.49)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Incompletely vaccinated</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">127 (0.41)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,622 (0.47)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Completely vaccinated</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">257(0.82)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,627 (1.05)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>COVID-19 infection (%)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Maternal</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,209(3.88)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9,992 (2.88)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neonatal</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36 (0.12)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">179 (0.05)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>NICU admission (%)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11,446 (36.74)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23,031 (6.64)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Mode of delivery (%)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cesarean section</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16,248 (52.21)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">107,297 (30.94)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vaginal delivery</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,870 (47.79)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">239,507 (69.06)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Comorbid conditions (%)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Obesity</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,374 (20.46)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67,635 (19.50)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chronic hypertension</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,850 (12.36)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19,158 (5.52)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pregestational diabetes</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,063 (3.41)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7,323 (2.11)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lupus</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">233 (0.75)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,035 (0.30)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tobacco use</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,116 (10.00)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17,238 (4.97)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Conceived by ART (%)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">808 (2.59)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,546 (1.60)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Multifetal gestation (%)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,779 (12.13)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,471 (1.00)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Region (%)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Midwest</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8,762 (30.12)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104,012 (32.62)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Northeast</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,910 (13.44)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34,354 (10.77)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">South</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,812 (37.16)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">122,844 (38.52)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">West</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,068 (19.28)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57,682 (18.09)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Insurance payer (%)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Private</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,281 (45.84)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">188,506 (54.35)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Public</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,380 (49.37)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">141,211 (40.71)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,235 (3.96)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,116 (3.78)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Self-pay</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">259 (0.83)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,007 (1.16)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="para0026">Regarding inpatient vaccination rates, 0.8% and 0.4% of the LBW group were completely and incompletely vaccinated, respectively; and 1.1% and 0.5% of the non-LBW group were completely and incompletely vaccinated, respectively (p &lt; 0.001 for both). Compared to unvaccinated persons, completely vaccinated persons were 21% less likely to have LBW neonates (OR 0.79, 95% CI 0.69-0.89,), while incompletely vaccinated pregnant persons were 13% less likely to have LBW neonates (OR 0.87, 95% CI 0.73-0.1.04). In multivariable regression analysis, completely vaccinated and incompletely vaccinated pregnant persons were less likely to have LBW neonates compared to unvaccinated pregnant persons by 20% (aOR 0.80, 95% CI 0.70-0.91) and 13% (aOR 0.87, 95% CI 0.71-1.04), respectively (<xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0002" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Unadjusted and adjusted odds of LBW by COVID-19 vaccination status and other known contributors to LBW</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0002">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>OR</bold></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>95% CI</bold></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>aOR</bold></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>95% CI</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Vaccination status</bold>, reference unvaccinated</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Incomplete vaccination</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.87</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.73-1.04</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.87</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.71-1.04</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Complete vaccination</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.79</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.69-0.89</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.80</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.70-0.91</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Maternal COVID-19 infection</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.36</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.28-1.45</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.35</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.26-1.43</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Neonatal COVID-19 infection</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.24</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.57-3.21</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.75</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.20-2.54</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age</bold>, reference 20-35</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age &lt; 20</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.31</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.24-1.38</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.35</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.28-1.43</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age &gt; 35</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.06</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03-1.09</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.99-1.05</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Race</bold>, reference White</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Black</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.84</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.78-1.89</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.72</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.68-1.78</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asian</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.18</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12-1.24</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.31</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.25-1.38</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.08-1.15</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.19</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.15-1.22</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Chronic Hypertension</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.41</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.32-2.50</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.16</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.07-2.25</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Pregestational Diabetes</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.64</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.53-1.75</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.31</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.24-1.40</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Lupus</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.52</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.18-2.90</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.20</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.89-2.56</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Tobacco use</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.12</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.04-2.21</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.03</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.94-2.11</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Multifetal gestation</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.66</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.02-14.32</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.12</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.45-14.83</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Obesity</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.06</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03-1.09</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.83-0.88</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Assisted Reproductive Technology</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.64</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.52-1.77</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.28</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.18-1.40</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="para0027">Propensity score overlap weighting created &#8220;treated&#8221; (completely vaccinated) and &#8220;untreated&#8221; (incompletely vaccinated or unvaccinated) groups that were balanced with respect to confounding variables (<xref rid="tbl0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>
). In the PSM cohort, which contained 3,640 matches, pregnant persons who were completely vaccinated against COVID-19 were 22% less likely to have LBW neonates compared to unvaccinated or incompletely vaccinated individuals (aOR 0.78, 95% CI 0.76-0.79). This adjusted odds ratio was close to the 20% decreased odds of LBW estimated in the previously described multivariable regression model of the original cohort prior to PSM.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0003" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Demographics of exposed and unexposed COVID-19 vaccinated groups after propensity score matching</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0003">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Unvaccinated or Incomplete Vaccination</bold></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Complete Vaccination</bold></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>P value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age (%)</bold>, reference 20-35</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Less than 20</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.22</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.28</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.88</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Over 35</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.43</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.43</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Race (%),</bold> reference White</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Black</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.05</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.05</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asian</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.67</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.62</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.40</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.45</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Nulliparous (%)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.26</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.26</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Comorbid conditions (%)</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chronic hypertension</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.52</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.54</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pregestational diabetes</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.19</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.24</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.89</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lupus</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.30</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.41</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.43</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tobacco use</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.30</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.27</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Region (%)</bold>, reference Midwest</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Northeast</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.94</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.94</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">South</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.71</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.71</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">West</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.66</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.64</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.98</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Insurance payer (%)</bold>, reference private</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.37</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Public</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.40</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.40</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.37</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.37</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Self-pay</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.75</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.75</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="para0028">When stratifying by gestational age, the association between COVID-19 vaccination status and LBW remained significant for term and late preterm infants with only complete vaccination. Completely vaccinated persons were 18% less likely to have term neonates with LBW (aOR 0.82, 95% CI 0.68-0.99 for complete vaccination; aOR 0.96, 95% CI 0.74-1.25 for incomplete vaccination). Completely vaccinated persons were 17% less likely to have preterm neonates with LBW (aOR 0.83, 95% CI 0.76-0.96 for complete vaccination; aOR 0.90, 95% CI 0.72-1.11 for incomplete vaccination).</p><p id="para0029">There was evidence of effect modification by race/ethnicity. As compared to White unvaccinated or incompletely vaccinated persons, White vaccinated individuals were 43% less likely to have LBW neonates (aOR 0.57, 95% CI 0.55-0.60), Black vaccinated individuals were not less likely to have LBW neonates (aOR 0.99, 95% CI 0.92, 1.05), and Asian vaccinated individuals were 13% less likely to have LBW neonates (aOR 0.87, 95% CI 0.81-0.93).</p></sec><sec id="sec0007"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="sec0008"><title>Principal Findings</title><p id="para0030">From this study, pregnant persons who were completely vaccinated against COVID-19 were less likely to have LBW neonates compared to unvaccinated and incompletely vaccinated individuals. Complete vaccination status may be protective against LBW after adjusting for confounders of LBW and factors influencing the likelihood of receiving the COVID-19 vaccine. This association was significant for term and late preterm deliveries, and there was a difference in the odds of LBW by race/ethnicity.</p></sec><sec id="sec0009"><title>Results</title><p id="para0031">This finding supports a study from the United Kingdom;<sup>28</sup> however, it differs from two previous studies demonstrating no difference between COVID-19 vaccination status and LBW.<sup>25-26</sup> Theiler et al. (2021) compared 121 vaccinated and 11 unvaccinated pregnant persons and reported no significant difference in LBW risk between vaccinated groups, but this outcome was underpowered (OR 0.34, 95% CI 0.01-3.91).<sup>25</sup> Goldshtein et al. (2022) compared 352 unvaccinated against 705 vaccinated pregnant persons and found the vaccinated group was 11% less likely to experience LBW after propensity adjustment though the authors did not control for confounders of LBW (RR 0.89, 95% CI 0.78-1.01).<sup>26</sup> These two primary studies are the main contributors to LBW outcomes research in recent systematic reviews and meta-analyses.<sup>24,27-28</sup> In addition, related literature on small for gestational age (SGA) neonates and COVID-19 vaccination has also not revealed a significant difference between vaccinated groups.<sup>37-38</sup>
</p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><title>Clinical Implications</title><p id="para0032">The findings of our study are significant because they describe the impact of complete, incomplete, and unvaccinated COVID-19 maternal status on neonatal weight at delivery. The few existing studies have been limited by smaller sample sizes, limited covariate adjustment for exposure and outcome, and lack of stratification analysis for COVID-19 vaccination status, infection, and prematurity. Obtaining this level of granular data in a very large population allowed us to detect a novel association between the COVID-19 vaccine and LBW.</p><p id="para0033">We also found that LBW infants were more likely to be associated with COVID-19 infection during pregnancy than infants without LBW. This aligns with theories that COVID-19 may act like other maternal viral illnesses, such as influenza virus, in modulating birth weight.<sup>7-8</sup> Studies have shown that pregnant patients with COVID-19 infection give birth to infants with lower birth weights,<sup>16-23</sup> offering a plausible biological mechanism for our observed association. In a review of 111 studies, the rate of LBW was higher in mothers infected to COVID-19 (16.7%, 95% CI 12.8-21.5).<sup>17</sup> The rate of LBW in those with maternal COVID-19 infection in our study was also significantly higher than the background national rate.</p><p id="para0034">Studies have demonstrated that pregnant persons with COVID-19 infection are at increased risk of iatrogenic and spontaneous preterm birth and fetal growth restriction,<sup>3</sup> known contributors to low birth weight; therefore, it is possible that preventing or mitigating infection with vaccination may result in lower LBW rates among vaccinated individuals. We propose a relationship between COVID-19 vaccination and LBW in <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>
and hypothesize that reduction of COVID-19 disease may be in the pathway between the exposure and outcome.<fig id="fig0002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Directed Acyclic Graph (DAG) showing the association between exposure (COVID-19 vaccination), outcome (LBW), and confounding variables</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0005">Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2_lrg.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="para0035">Greater understanding of the influence of COVID-19 infection on LBW is important as it is likely to have short- and long-term consequences in the perinatal period, infancy, and into adulthood.<sup>12</sup> For example, we found that LBW infants were more likely to require cesarean delivery and NICU admission. Notably, the association between COVID-19 vaccination status and LBW remained significant even after controlling for maternal and neonatal COVID-19 infections in pregnancy, suggesting there may be other factors influencing this association. A possible mediating variable may be prematurity. In our cohort, the association between complete vaccination and LBW was significant for late preterm and term deliveries. To our knowledge, there is no clear biological mechanism as to how the vaccine contributes to LBW, and current literature demonstrates no difference in preterm birth based on vaccination status.<sup>35</sup>
</p></sec><sec id="sec0011"><title>Research Implications</title><p id="para0036">These associations will require further prospective validation but raise important potential to decrease vaccine hesitancy and the incidence of LBW infants through vaccination efforts. Additional research questions are how the timing of vaccine administration impacts birth weight and whether there is an association with other clinical metrics, such as gestational age at delivery, mode of delivery, and length of NICU stay. Further identification of modifiable and non-modifiable factors influencing proclivity to receive the COVID-19 vaccine may also aid in more effective public health interventions promoting vaccination in pregnancy. As an example, unvaccinated status has been associated with younger age, current smoking, lower BMI, and race.<sup>39</sup>
</p><p id="para0037">
<italic toggle="yes">Strengths and Limitations:</italic>
</p><p id="para0038">Several strengths of our study are the very large sample size, high-quality data, and generalizability. The nationally representative database included 377,995 pregnant participants with diverse socioeconomic representation, mirroring that of the reproductive-aged U.S. population.<sup>40</sup> We explored race/ethnicity as a modifying factor for the association between COVID-19 vaccination and LBW, though this finding was limited by lack of reporting of Hispanic/Latino groups. We highlight the complexity of determining factors influencing LBW and vaccine acceptance across the spectrum of race and ethnicity. The impact of vaccination on LBW was significantly modified by racial and ethnic groups in our study, calling for the need to address sociodemographic determinants of health in addition to encouraging complete vaccination among vulnerable groups.</p><p id="para0039">Claims-based data has inherent biases of miscoding and missing data. While we were unable to ascertain the accuracy of coding, we had access to comprehensive reporting of variables of interest and possible confounding variables for rigorous analyses. Majority of variables were greater than 95% completely reported, and all variables were greater than 90% completely reported. Of importance, birth weight was identified from a claim or electronic health record instead of self-reported.</p><p id="para0040">A limitation of our claims data is the large unvaccinated population due to lack of reporting by hospitals when outpatient vaccinations were administered to participants. It is likely that many pregnant individuals within our unvaccinated cohort were incompletely or completely vaccinated. Although vaccination status was unaccounted for in cases of outpatient immunization, we argue that underestimated vaccination numbers would bias our results toward the null and that our associations remained significant. Multivariable logistic regression and propensity score matching also served to strengthen the validity of our findings though residual confounders may exist due to the study's observational design and assumptions of propensity score matching.</p><p id="para0041">Lastly, we were unable to account for when COVID-19 vaccination or infection occurred in pregnancy due to lack of available information in the Vizient clinical database. Better understanding of this temporal exposure is critical in understanding if a protective association of vaccination on LBW persists in iterations of this study. Another pertinent variable of interest is history of preterm birth, which was also not reported in the Vizient database.</p></sec><sec id="sec0012"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="para0042">In conclusion, this study demonstrated an association between maternal COVID-19 vaccination status and LBW. Completely vaccinated pregnant persons were less likely to have LBW neonates compared to those with incomplete and unvaccinated COVID-19 status in the late preterm and term period.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0013"><title>Glossary</title><p id="para0043"><italic toggle="yes">Low birth weight:</italic> weight less than or equal to 2,500 grams at birth</p><p id="para0044"><italic toggle="yes">Incomplete COVID-19 vaccination:</italic> 1 dose of Pfizer or Moderna</p><p id="para0045">Reference</p><p id="para0046"><italic toggle="yes">Complete COVID-19 vaccination:</italic> 1 dose of Johnson &amp; Johnson or &#8805; 2 doses of Moderna or Pfizer<list list-type="simple" id="celist0001"><list-item id="celistitem0001"><label>1</label><p id="para0047">Seasely AR, Blanchard CT, Arora N, Battarbee AN, Casey BM, Dionne-Odom J, Leal Jr SM, Moates DB, Sinkey RG, Szychowski JM, Tita AT. Maternal and perinatal outcomes associated with the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) Delta (B. 1.617. 2) variant. Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology. 2021 Dec 1;138(6):842-4.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0002"><label>2</label><p id="para0048">Metz TD, Clifton RG, Hughes BL, Sandoval G, Saade GR, Grobman WA, Manuck TA, Miodovnik M, Sowles A, Clark K, Gyamfi-Bannerman C. Disease severity and perinatal outcomes of pregnant patients with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). Obstetrics and gynecology. 2021 Apr;137(4):571.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0003"><label>3</label><p id="para0049">Regan, A.K., Arah, O.A., Fell, D.B. and Sullivan, S.G., 2022. SARS-CoV-2 infection during and associated perinatal health outcomes: a national US cohort study. <italic toggle="yes">The Journal of infectious diseases, 225</italic>(5), pp.759-767.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0004"><label>4</label><p id="para0050">Rasmussen SA, Kelley CF, Horton JP, Jamieson DJ. Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) vaccines and pregnancy: what obstetricians need to know. Obstetrics and gynecology. 2021 Mar;137(3):408.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0005"><label>5</label><p id="para0051">COVID-19 vaccination among pregnant people aged 18-49 years overall, by race and ethnicity, and date reported to CDC &#8211; Vaccine Safety Datalink,* United States. Accessed March 2023. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker/#vaccinations-pregnant-women" id="interref0001">https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker/#vaccinations-pregnant-women</ext-link>.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0006"><label>6</label><p id="para0052">Bhattacharya O, Siddiquea BN, Shetty A, Afroz A, Billah B. COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy among pregnant women: a systematic review and meta-analysis. BMJ open. 2022 Aug 1;12(8):e061477.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0007"><label>7</label><p id="para0053">Dor&#233;lien A. The effects of in utero exposure to influenza on birth and infant outcomes in the US. Population and development review. 2019 Sep;45(3):489</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0008"><label>8</label><p id="para0054">Yu W, Hu X, Cao B. Viral infections during pregnancy: The big challenge threatening maternal and fetal health. Maternal-Fetal Medicine. 2022 Jan 25;4(01):72-86.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0009"><label>9</label><p id="para0055">Manjunathachar HV, Singh KN, Chouksey V, Kumar R, Sharma RK, Barde PV. Prevalence of torch infections and its associated poor outcome in high-risk pregnant women of central India: time to think for prevention strategies. Indian journal of medical microbiology. 2020 Jul 1;38(3-4):379-84.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0010"><label>10</label><p id="para0056">Osterman MJ, Hamilton BE, Martin JA, Driscoll AK, Valenzuela CP. Births: final data for 2020.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0011"><label>11</label><p id="para0057">Eichenwald EC, Stark AR. Management and outcomes of very low birth weight. New England Journal of Medicine. 2008 Apr 17;358(16):1700-11.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0012"><label>12</label><p id="para0058">De Bernab&#233; JV, Soriano T, Albaladejo R, Juarranz M, Calle ME, Mart&#237;nez D, Dom&#237;nguez-Rojas V. Risk factors for low birth weight: a review. European Journal of Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology and Reproductive Biology. 2004 Sep 10;116(1):3-15.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0013"><label>13</label><p id="para0059">Sacchi C, Marino C, Nosarti C, Vieno A, Visentin S, Simonelli A. Association of intrauterine growth restriction and small for gestational age status with childhood cognitive outcomes: a systematic review and meta-analysis. JAMA pediatrics. 2020 Aug 1;174(8):772-81.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0014"><label>14</label><p id="para0060">Bianchi ME, Restrepo JM. Low Birthweight as a Risk Factor for Non-communicable Diseases in Adults. Frontiers in Medicine. 2021;8.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0015"><label>15</label><p id="para0061">de Mendon&#231;a EL, de Lima Mac&#234;na M, Bueno NB, de Oliveira AC, Mello CS. Premature birth, low birth weight, small for gestational age and chronic non-communicable diseases in adult life: A systematic review with meta-analysis. Early human development. 2020 Oct 1;149:105154.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0016"><label>16</label><p id="para0062">Piekos SN, Roper RT, Hwang YM, Sorensen T, Price ND, Hood L, Hadlock JJ. The effect of maternal SARS-CoV-2 infection timing on birth outcomes: a retrospective multicentre cohort study. The Lancet Digital Health. 2022 Feb 1;4(2):e95-104.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0017"><label>17</label><p id="para0063">Marchand G, Patil AS, Masoud AT, Ware K, King A, Ruther S, Brazil G, Calteux N, Ulibarri H, Parise J, Arroyo A. Systematic review and meta-analysis of COVID maternal and neonatal clinical features and pregnancy outcomes to June 3rd 2021. AJOG global reports. 2022 Jan 3:100049.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0018"><label>18</label><p id="para0064">Yoon SH, Kang JM, Ahn JG. Clinical outcomes of 201 neonates born to mothers with COVID-19: a systematic review. Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci. 2020 Jul 1;24(14):7804-15.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0019"><label>19</label><p id="para0065">Villar J, Ariff S, Gunier RB, Thiruvengadam R, Rauch S, Kholin A, Roggero P, Prefumo F, Do Vale MS, Cardona-Perez JA, Maiz N. Maternal and neonatal morbidity and mortality among pregnant women with and without COVID-19 infection: the INTERCOVID multinational cohort study. JAMA pediatrics. 2021 Aug 1;175(8):817-26</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0020"><label>20</label><p id="para0066">Smith V, Seo D, Warty R, Payne O, Salih M, Chin KL, Ofori-Asenso R, Krishnan S, da Silva Costa F, Vollenhoven B, Wallace E. Maternal and neonatal outcomes associated with COVID-19 infection: A systematic review. Plos one. 2020 Jun 4;15(6):e0234187.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0021"><label>21</label><p id="para0067">Martin JA, Osterman MJ, Valenzuela CP. Maternal and Infant Characteristics and Outcomes Among Women With Confirmed or Presumed COVID-19 During Pregnancy: 14 States and the District of Columbia.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0022"><label>22</label><p id="para0068">Dileep A, ZainAlAbdin S, AbuRuz S. Investigating the association between severity of COVID-19 infection during pregnancy and neonatal outcomes. Scientific Reports. 2022 Feb 22;12(1):1-7.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0023"><label>23</label><p id="para0069">Simon E, Gouyon JB, Cottenet J, Bechraoui&#8208;Quantin S, Rozenberg P, Mariet AS, Quantin C. Impact of SARS&#8208;CoV&#8208;2 infection on risk of prematurity, birthweight and obstetric complications: A multivariate analysis from a nationwide, population&#8208;based retrospective cohort study. BJOG: An International Journal of Obstetrics &amp; Gynaecology. 2022 Jun 1.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0024"><label>24</label><p id="para0070">Prasad S, Kalafat E, Blakeway H, Townsend R, O'Brien P, Morris E, Draycott T, Thangaratinam S, Le Doare K, Ladhani S, von Dadelszen P. Systematic review and meta-analysis of the effectiveness and perinatal outcomes of COVID-19 vaccination in pregnancy. Nature communications. 2022 May 10;13(1):1-8.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0025"><label>25</label><p id="para0071">Theiler RN, Wick M, Mehta R, Weaver AL, Virk A, Swift M. Pregnancy and birth outcomes after SARS-CoV-2 vaccination in pregnancy. American journal of obstetrics &amp; gynecology MFM. 2021 Nov 1;3(6):100467.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0026"><label>26</label><p id="para0072">Goldshtein I, Steinberg DM, Kuint J, Chodick G, Segal Y, David SS, Ben-Tov A. Association of BNT162b2 COVID-19 vaccination during pregnancy with neonatal and early infant outcomes. JAMA pediatrics. 2022 May 1;176(5):470-7.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0027"><label>27</label><p id="para0073">Hameed I, Khan MO, Nusrat K, Mahmood S, Nashit M, Malik S, Siddiqui OM, Samad SA, Marsia S, Usman MS, Siddiqi TJ. Is it safe and effective to administer COVID-19 vaccines during pregnancy? A systematic review and meta-analysis. American Journal of Infection Control. 2022 Aug 22.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0028"><label>28</label><p id="para0074">Kalafat E, Heath P, Prasad S, Pat O, Khalil A. COVID-19 vaccination in pregnancy. American journal of obstetrics and gynecology. 2022 May 11.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0029"><label>29</label><p id="para0075">GOV. UK. COVID-19 vaccine weekly surveillance reports (12 January 2022). Accessed January 2023. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/1128632/Vaccine-surveillance-report-week-2-2023.pdf" id="interref0002">https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/1128632/Vaccine-surveillance-report-week-2-2023.pdf</ext-link>.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0030"><label>30</label><p id="para0076">Vizient, Inc. 2022 Vizient Clinical Data Base/Resource Manager. Accessed June 2022. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.vizientinc.com/what-we-do/operations-and-quality/clinical-data-base" id="interref0003">https://www.vizientinc.com/what-we-do/operations-and-quality/clinical-data-base</ext-link>. Accessed June 2022.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0031"><label>31</label><p id="para0077">Phillips MC, Sarff L, Banerjee J, Coffey C, Holtom P, Meurer S, Wald&#8208;Dickler N, Spellberg B. Effect of mortality from COVID&#8208;19 on inpatient outcomes. Journal of medical virology. 2022 Jan;94(1):318-26.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0032"><label>32</label><p id="para0078">de Havenon A, Ney JP, Callaghan B, Delic A, Hohmann S, Shippey E, Esper GJ, Stulberg E, Tirschwell D, Frontera J, Yaghi S. Impact of COVID-19 on outcomes in ischemic stroke patients in the United States. Journal of Stroke and Cerebrovascular Diseases. 2021 Feb 1;30(2):105535.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0033"><label>33</label><p id="para0079">Nguyen NT, Chinn J, De Ferrante M, Kirby KA, Hohmann SF, Amin A. Male gender is a predictor of higher mortality in hospitalized adults with COVID-19. PLoS One. 2021 Jul 9;16(7):e0254066.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0034"><label>34</label><p id="para0080">American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists. ACOG Practice Bulletin No. 227: fetal growth restriction. Obstetrics and gynecology. 2021 Feb;137(2):e16-28.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0035"><label>35</label><p id="para0081">Na, L., Banks, S., &amp; Wang, P. P. (2023). Racial and ethnic disparities in COVID-19 vaccine uptake: A mediation framework. <italic toggle="yes">Vaccine, 41</italic>(14), 2404-2411.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0036"><label>36</label><p id="para0082">Ro, A., Goldberg, R. E., &amp; Kane, J. B. (2019). Racial and ethnic patterning of low birth weight, normal birth weight, and macrosomia. <italic toggle="yes">Preventive medicine, 118</italic>, 196-204.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0037"><label>37</label><p id="para0083">Lipkind HS, Vazquez-Benitez G, DeSilva M, Vesco KK, Ackerman-Banks C, Zhu J, Boyce TG, Daley MF, Fuller CC, Getahun D, Irving SA. Receipt of COVID-19 vaccine during pregnancy and preterm or small-for-gestational-age at birth&#8212;Eight Integrated Health Care Organizations, United States, December 15, 2020&#8211;July 22, 2021. Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report. 2022 Jan 1;71(1):26.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0038"><label>38</label><p id="para0084">Fell DB, Dimanlig-Cruz S, Regan AK, H&#229;berg SE, Gravel CA, Oakley L, Alton GD, T&#246;r&#246;k E, Dhinsa T, Shah PS, Wilson K. Risk of preterm birth, small for gestational age at birth, and stillbirth after covid-19 vaccination during pregnancy: population based retrospective cohort study. bmj. 2022 Aug 17;378.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0039"><label>39</label><p id="para0085">Morgan, J. A., Biggio Jr, J. R., Martin, J. K., Mussarat, N., Chawla, H. K., Puri, P., &amp; Williams, F. B. (2022). Maternal outcomes after severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection in vaccinated compared with unvaccinated pregnant patients. <italic toggle="yes">Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology, 139</italic>(1), 107-109.</p></list-item><list-item id="celistitem0040"><label>40</label><p id="para0086">U.S. Census Bureau QuickFacts. Accessed June 2023. Available from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.census.gov/table" id="interref0004">https://data.census.gov/table</ext-link>.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="d36e1107"><p id="notep0001"><italic toggle="yes">Disclosure statement:</italic> The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p></fn><fn id="d36e1111"><p id="notep0002"><italic toggle="yes">Funding</italic>: Overall support for this work was provided by the Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD) of the National Institutes of Health (NIH) under the Award Number K23HD104517 (Dr. Eke). The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the NIH.</p></fn><fn id="d36e1115"><p id="notep0003"><italic toggle="yes">Presentation:</italic> This paper was presented as a poster at the 43<sup>rd</sup> Annual Pregnancy Meeting in San Francisco, California on February 6<sup>th</sup>-11<sup>th</sup> 2023.</p></fn><fn id="d36e1128"><p id="notep0004"><italic toggle="yes">Acknowledgements</italic><bold>:</bold> We acknowledge Vizient &#174; for use of its clinical database for this project.</p></fn><fn id="d36e1133"><p id="notep0005"><italic toggle="yes">Condensation:</italic><bold>Completely vaccinated pregnant persons were least likely to have low birth weight neonates compared to unvaccinated and incompletely vaccinated pregnant persons.</bold></p></fn><fn id="d36e1137"><p id="notep0006"><italic toggle="yes">Blinded Conflict of Interest Statement:</italic><bold>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</bold></p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>