<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1753</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">frontendo</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Endocrinol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Endocrinology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-2392</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10235694</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10235694.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10235694</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10235694</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37274346</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2023.1159055</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Endocrinology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Association between weight-adjusted-waist index with hepatic steatosis and liver fibrosis: a nationally representative cross-sectional study from NHANES 2017 to 2020</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn003" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2176034"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yahui</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn003" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names initials="M">Minghan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2281325"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names initials="K">Kai</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="J">Jinsheng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
<institution>Department of Pathology, Heping Hospital Affiliated to Changzhi Medical College</institution>, <addr-line>Changzhi, Shanxi</addr-line>, <country>China</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
<institution>Department of Pathology, Changzhi Medical College the First Clinical College</institution>, <addr-line>Changzhi, Shanxi</addr-line>, <country>China</country>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
<institution>Key Laboratory of Esophageal Cancer Basic Research and Clinical Transformation, Heping Hospital Affiliated to Changzhi Medical College</institution>, <addr-line>Changzhi, Shanxi</addr-line>, <country>China</country>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Takefumi Kimura, Shinshu University, Japan</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Shun-ichi Wakabayashi, Shinshu University Hospital, Japan; Debjyoti Kundu, Indiana University Bloomington, United States</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Jinsheng Wang, <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mailto:jshwang@czmc.edu.cn">jshwang@czmc.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn003"><p>&#8224;These authors have contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">427503</issue-id><elocation-id>1159055</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>05</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>03</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-06-05 17:25:09.640"><day>05</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 Shen, Wu, Fu, Zhu and Wang</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Shen, Wu, Fu, Zhu and Wang</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fendo-14-1159055.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The negative effects of obesity on hepatic steatosis and fibrosis have received considerable attention in recent years. The weight-adjusted-waist index (WWI) reflects weight-independent centripetal obesity. Herein, we provide the first investigation of a link between WWI, hepatic steatosis, and liver fibrosis.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We used data from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey 2017-2020 to conduct a cross-sectional study. The linear relationship between WWI, controlled attenuation parameters, and liver stiffness measurements (LSM) was investigated using multivariate linear regression models. The nonlinear relationship was described using fitted smoothed curves and threshold effect analyses. Subgroup analyses were performed based on gender, age, body mass index, diabetes, hypertension, drinking, and smoking.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>This population-based study included 7,594 people, 50.74% of whom were men and 49.26% of whom were women. Multivariate linear regression analysis revealed a significant positive relationship between WWI and hepatic steatosis [CAP, &#946;=7.60, 95% confidence interval (CI) (4.42, 10.78), P&lt;0.0001]. This positive association was stronger when excessive alcohol intake was present compared to when it was absent (P for interaction&#8201;=&#8201;0.031), and when hypertension was present compared to when it was not (P for interaction&#8201;=&#8201;0.014). The linear relationship between WWI and liver fibrosis was not statistically significant on multiple regression analysis [LSM, &#946;=0.03, 95% CI (-0.26, 0.32), P=0.84]. However, a U-shaped association was seen between WWI and LSM, with a negative correlation when WWI&lt; 10.92 and a positive correlation when WWI &gt; 10.92.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>We report a strong association between WWI and hepatic steatosis, and suggest that it may potentially be used as a simple anthropometric index to predict hepatic steatosis.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>WWI</kwd><kwd>steatosis</kwd><kwd>and fibrosis weight-adjusted-waist index</kwd><kwd>hepatic steatosis</kwd><kwd>liver fibrosis</kwd><kwd>NAFLD</kwd><kwd>NHANES</kwd><kwd>VCTE</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001"><institution-wrap><institution>Health Commission of Shanxi Province
</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100017949</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Key Research and Development Projects in Shanxi Province (201903D321032) and the Scientific Research Project of Shanxi Provincial Health Commission (2019142). The study was funded by the Four &#8220;Batches&#8221; Innovation Project of Invigorating Medical through Science and Technology of Shanxi Province (Key Laboratory of Esophageal Cancer Basic Research and Clinical Transformation, Heping Hospital Affiliated to Changzhi Medical College, 2020SYS22).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="1"/><ref-count count="34"/><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="3791"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Obesity</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) is the most common chronic liver disease worldwide, which affects up to 40% of adults and children (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). NAFLD can progress from simple hepatic steatosis to non-alcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH) and then to liver fibrosis, cirrhosis, and hepatocellular carcinoma (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). NAFLD has been linked to obesity and obesity-related metabolic disorders such as glucose intolerance, type 2 diabetes (T2D), and dyslipidemia (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).</p><p>Excessive hepatic fat accumulation not only leads to local changes, such as hepatocyte dysfunction, proinflammatory immune response activation, and fibrogenesis, but also triggers a series of extrahepatic metabolic disorders, including cardiovascular events and T2D. Furthermore, observational studies have highlighted that both hepatic steatosis and fibrosis are associated with a higher risk of all-cause mortality. Therefore, determining the level of liver steatosis is critical in the evaluation and clinical prognosis of patients with NAFLD (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Although pathological biopsy remains the gold standard for evaluating the severity of hepatic steatosis and liver fibrosis, vibration controlled transient elastography (VCTE) is a non-invasive alternative that is increasingly being used. Recent observational studies have suggested that VCTE has robust accuracy in estimating the grade of hepatic steatosis and the stage of liver fibrosis (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). However, the use of VCTE is limited by its popularity and high learning curve (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p><p>Weight-adjusted-waist index (WWI) was first postulated in 2018 as an anthropometric measure of central obesity that reflects both fat and muscle mass components, regardless of the body mass index (BMI) (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). The links between WWI and various cardiovascular events have since been well established (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). However, the relationship between WWI and these hepatic indicators has not been defined.</p><p>In the present study, we used the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES) to investigate the relationship between WWI and hepatic steatosis and liver fibrosis in the US population.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s2_1"><label>2.1</label><title>Data and sample sources</title><p>The NHANES is a cross-sectional survey conducted every two years to assess the nutritional and physical health of the general public in the United States (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Through interviews and related tests, demographics, dietary, and health-related information are collected (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). The survey is approved by the Center for Disease Control and Prevention Research Ethics Review Board, and all survey participants provide written informed consent to participate (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>).</p><p>In the present study, we used the 2017&#8211;2020 pre-coronavirus-19 pandemic data from the NHANES database. Out of the 15,560 individuals who participated, we excluded those with hepatitis B or C infection (n=215), missing VCTE data (n=434), unreliable VCTE estimation (liver stiffness interquartile range/median&#8805;30%, n&#8201;=&#8201;201), those younger than 18 years old (n=4,123), and incomplete data on weight and waist circumference (WC) (n=2993). The final analyses included 7,594 participants (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#160;1</bold>
</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="f1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure&#160;1</label><caption><p>Flowchart of the sample selection from NHANES 2017&#8211;2020. NHANES, National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey; HBV/HCV, participants with infection of hepatitis B virus and hepatitis C virus; VCTE, vibration controlled transient elastography.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fendo-14-1159055-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_2"><label>2.2</label><title>Definition of weight-adjusted-waist index</title><p>WWI is a novel index that estimates central obesity based on WC and weight. WC and weight were measured in a mobile examination center (MEC), where laboratory tests were carried out under controlled conditions (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). WWI was included as an exposure variable in our study and calculated as follows:</p><disp-formula><mml:math id="M1" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>WWI</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cm</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>kg</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>WC</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Weight</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></sec><sec id="s2_3"><label>2.3</label><title>Measurement of hepatic steatosis and liver fibrosis</title><p>Hepatic steatosis and liver fibrosis was detected with VCTE. Specifically, controlled attenuation parameter (CAP) and liver stiffness measurement (LSM) represented the levels of steatosis and fibrosis, respectively. We only included participants with a reliable VCTE estimation (interquartile range/median of LSM &#8804; 30%).</p></sec><sec id="s2_4"><label>2.4</label><title>Covariates</title><p>Based on a review of the literature, we summarized potential confounding covariates between WWI and hepatic steatosis and liver fibrosis in our multivariable-adjusted model (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Gender, age, race, family income-to-poverty ratio, and education level were all demographic covariates in our study. Anthropometric and laboratory covariates included BMI, direct high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL, mmol/L), low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL, mmol/L), triglycerides (TG, mmol/L), total cholesterol (TC, mmol/L), serum uric acid (&#956;mol/L), alanine aminotransferase (ALT, IU/L), alkaline phosphatase (ALP, IU/L), and aspartate aminotransferase (AST, IU/L). Medical history covariates included the presence or absence of T2D, excess alcohol consumption (&#8805; 4 drinks per day), smoking, or cardiovascular disease (CVD, defined as history of coronary artery disease, congestive heart failure, heart attack, stroke, or angina pectoris).</p></sec><sec id="s2_5"><label>2.5</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Weighted Student&#8217;s t-tests for continuous variables and weighted chi-squared tests for categorical variables were used to assess differences between WWI quartiles. The NHANES used an inferential statistics method to represent a large, nationally representative sample due to its complex multistage probability sampling design. Thus, using linear regression analyses, we summarized continuous variables as means with standard errors (SE) and categorical parameters as proportions using logistic regression analyses. Weighted multivariable regression models were used in three different models to investigate the relationship between WWI and hepatic steatosis and liver fibrosis. No covariates were adjusted in Model 1. Model 2 was adjusted for gender, age, and race. Model 3 was adjusted for gender, age, race, education level, BMI, excess alcohol consumption, HDL, LDL, TG, total cholesterol, serum uric acid, ALT, ALP, AST, CVD, and T2D status.</p><p>We performed a sensitivity analysis after categorizing the WWI into quartiles to assess robustness. A generalized additive model (GAM) and smooth curve fitting were used to address non-linearity. When a non-linear correlation was observed, a two-piecewise linear regression model (segmented regression model) was used to fit each interval and calculate the threshold effect. Subgroup analyses were then performed based on gender, age, BMI, T2D, hypertension, excess alcohol consumption, smoking, and CVD. A log-likelihood ratio test was used to determine whether a threshold existed by comparing a one-line model (non-segmented) to a two-piecewise linear regression model. The inflection point (K) was determined using a two-step recursive method (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Furthermore, a subgroup analysis of the correlations between WWI and hepatic steatosis and liver fibrosis was carried out using stratified multivariable logistic regression models with stratified covariates such as gender, age, BMI, and T2D. A two-sided P value &#8804; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. R (version 4.1.3) and EmpowerStats, two statistical computing and graphical programs, were used to conduct the statistical studies (version 2.0).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="s3_1"><label>3.1</label><title>Baseline characteristics</title><p>
<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">
<bold>Table&#160;1</bold>
</xref> summarizes the demographic profiles of the 7,594 participants. These participants had a mean &#177; SD age of 42.59 &#177; 20.99&#8201;years; 50.74% were men, and 49.26% were women. The WWI ranges for the first, second, third, and fourth quartiles were 8.04-10.45, 10.45-11.05, 11.05-11.64, and 11.64-14.14, respectively. Compared with participants in the lowest WWI quartile, those in the highest quartile were more likely to be male, older, excess alcohol consumers, or have CVD, lower education level, lower socioeconomic status, higher TG levels, higher BMI, higher total cholesterol, higher LDL, higher ALT, higher ALP, and higher serum uric acid.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;1</label><caption><p>Weighted characteristics of the study population based on controlled attenuated parameter (CAP) and median liver stiffness measurement (LSM).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight-adjusted-waist index (WWI)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q1<break/>N=1,899 (8.04-10.44)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q2<break/>N=1,898 (10.44-11.05)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q3<break/>N=1,898 (11.05-11.64)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q4<break/>N=1,899 (11.64-14.14)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years), (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,263<break/>(67%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">693<break/>(37%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">433<break/>(23%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266<break/>(14%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40-59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184<break/>(9.7%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">444<break/>(23%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">775<break/>(41%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,098<break/>(58%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">452<break/>(24%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">761<break/>(40%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">690<break/>(36%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">535<break/>(28%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex, (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">754<break/>(40%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">857<break/>(45%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">963<break/>(51%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,279<break/>(67%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,145<break/>(60%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,041<break/>(55%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">935<break/>(49%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">620<break/>(33%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race, (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mexican American</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">155 (8.2%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">227 (12%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">293 (15%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256 (13%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other Hispanic</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162 (8.5%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204 (11%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202 (11%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226 (12%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Hispanic White</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">576 (30%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">603 (32%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">642 (34%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">785 (41%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Hispanic Black</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">632 (33%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">487 (26%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">450 (24%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">391 (21%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other Races</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">374 (20%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">377 (20%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">311 (16%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241 (13%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education level, (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Less than high school</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182<break/>(9.6%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">284<break/>(15%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">392<break/>(21%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">435<break/>(23%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High school or above high school</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,460<break/>(77%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,541<break/>(81%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,471<break/>(78%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,439<break/>(76%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">257<break/>(14%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73<break/>(3.8%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35<break/>(1.8%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25<break/>(1.3%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>), (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal weight</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,061<break/>(56%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">522<break/>(28%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">321<break/>(17%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169<break/>(8.9%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overweight</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">243<break/>(13%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">674<break/>(36%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">930<break/>(49%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,246<break/>(66%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obese</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">594<break/>(31%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">698<break/>(37%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">644<break/>(34%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">482<break/>(25%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes, (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61<break/>(0.8%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">239<break/>(3.1%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">436<break/>(5.7%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">681<break/>(8.9%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,838<break/>(24.2%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,659<break/>(21.8%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,462<break/>(19.3%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,218<break/>(16.3%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension, (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">267<break/>(14%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">581<break/>(31%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">806<break/>(42%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,038<break/>(55%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,632<break/>(86%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,317 (69.02%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,091<break/>(57.01%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">861<break/>(45.02%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking, (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,307<break/>(69%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,160<break/>(61%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,067<break/>(56%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,089<break/>(57%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">592<break/>(31%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">738<break/>(39%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">831<break/>(44%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">810<break/>(43%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excess Alcohol Consumption, (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,463 (88.08%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,378 (83.21%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,261 (77.08%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,073 (68.08%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198<break/>(11.92%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">278 (16.79%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">375<break/>(22.92%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">503 (31.92%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CVD, (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61<break/>(3.72%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">153<break/>(8.37%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203<break/>(10.89%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">345<break/>(18.36%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,580<break/>(96.28%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,675<break/>(91.63%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,661<break/>(89.11%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,534<break/>(81.64%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Income to poverty ratio</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40<break/>(1.18, 4.66)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64<break/>(1.27, 4.67)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.31<break/>(1.18, 4.16)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91<break/>(1.11, 3.55)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">Laboratory features</th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total cholesterol (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">172<break/>(150, 198)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185<break/>(161, 214)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">187<break/>(161, 216)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">183<break/>(156, 211)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglyceride (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70<break/>(0.52, 1.05)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96<break/>(0.67, 1.49)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14<break/>(0.80, 1.61)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24<break/>(0.88, 1.70)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL- cholesterol (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56<break/>(2.07, 3.13)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.79<break/>(2.30, 3.41)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.90<break/>(2.25, 3.49)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.69<break/>(2.15, 3.34)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL- cholesterol (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42<break/>(1.19, 1.71)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29<break/>(1.09, 1.60)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27<break/>(1.06, 1.55)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27<break/>(1.06, 1.53)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT (IU/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15<break/>(12, 22)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19<break/>(13, 27)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19<break/>(14, 27)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18<break/>(13, 25)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALP (IU/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76<break/>(56, 80)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71<break/>(59, 86)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76<break/>(64, 92)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82<break/>(67, 99)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST (IU/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19<break/>(16, 23)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19<break/>(16, 24)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19<break/>(16, 24)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19<break/>(16, 23)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSM (kPa)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.70<break/>(4.00, 5.70)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80<break/>(4.00, 5.90)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.10<break/>(4.10, 6.38)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.30<break/>(4.30, 6.90)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAP (dB/m)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215<break/>(190, 248)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">257<break/>(218, 297)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">278<break/>(238, 318)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">295<break/>(253, 336)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum uric acid (&#956;mol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">297<break/>(244, 351)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">315<break/>(256, 381)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">321<break/>(262, 381)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">321<break/>(262, 381)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Mean and interquartile range for continuous variables: P value was calculated by weighted linear regression model.</p></fn><fn><p>% for categorical variables: P value was calculated by weighted chi-square test.</p></fn><fn><p>BMI, body mass index; LDL- cholesterol, low-Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol; HDL- cholesterol, high-Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol; ALT, alanine transaminase; ALP, alkaline phosphatase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase; LSM, liver stiffness measure; CAP, controlled attenuation parameter; CVD, cardiovascular disease; WWI, weight-adjusted-waist index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3_2"><label>3.2</label><title>Association between the weight-adjusted-waist index and hepatic steatosis (CAP)</title><p>We first estimated the association between WWI and the severity of liver fibrosis without adjusting for any covariates. Higher WWI was associated with a higher grade of hepatic steatosis. After full adjustment (see Methods), each unit with a higher WWI score was found to be associated with 7.60 dB/m increased units of CAP [&#946;=7.60, 95% CI (4.42, 10.78), P&lt;0.001]. Sensitivity analysis was conducted after treating the WWI as a categorical variable (quartile). In the fully adjusted model, compared with the lowest WWI quartile (first quartile), the adjusted &#946; for participants in the second quartile, third quartile, and fourth quartile were 6.51, 11.03, and 14.06, respectively (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">
<bold>Table&#160;2</bold>
</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;2</label><caption><p>The association between WWI with CAP and LSM.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight-adjusted-waist index</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude model<break/>(Model 1) <xref rid="fnT2_1" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimally adjusted model (Model 2) <xref rid="fnT2_2" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fully adjusted model (Model 3) <xref rid="fnT2_3" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAP &#946; (95% CI) <xref rid="fnT2_4" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>d</sup>
</xref>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.21 (29.77, 32.65)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.97 (35.26, 38.68)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.60 (4.42, 10.78)&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">WWI group</th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quartile 1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quartile 2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.55 (33.98, 41.13)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.48 (35.88, 43.09)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.51 (1.08, 11.94) 0.0188</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quartile 3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.95 (53.37, 60.53)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.73 (56.92, 64.54)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.03 (4.89, 17.10) 0.0005</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quartile 4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.75 (69.17, 76.33)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.61 (77.51, 85.72)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.06 (6.95, 21.17) 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for trend</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.37 (33.69, 37.05)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.44 (37.49, 41.39)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.88 (3.50, 10.26)&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>LSM &#946; (95% CI)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 (0.61, 0.84)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 (0.77, 1.04)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 (-0.26, 0.32) 0.8419</td></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">WWI group</th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quartile 1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quartile 2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 (-0.10, 0.45) 0.219</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24 (-0.05, 0.53) 0.099</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.44 (-0.94, 0.05) 0.0773</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quartile 3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.66, 1.22)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.75, 1.36)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.25 (-0.81, 0.31) 0.3825</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quartile 4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61 (1.33, 1.89)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87 (1.54, 2.19)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 (-0.62, 0.67) 0.9314</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for trend</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (0.69, 0.95)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.79, 1.10)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 (-0.26, 0.35) 0.7835</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>In sensitivity analysis, Weight-adjusted-waist index was converted from a continuous variable to a categorical variable (quartile).</p></fn><fn id="fnT2_1"><label>a</label><p>Model 1: no covariates were adjusted.</p></fn><fn id="fnT2_2"><label>b</label><p>Model 2: adjusted for sex, age, and race.</p></fn><fn id="fnT2_3"><label>c</label><p>Model 3: adjusted for sex, age, race, education level, family income to poverty ratio, BMI, Diabetes, hypertension, smoking, drinking, family income to poverty ratio, Total calcium, Total cholesterol, Triglyceride, LDL- cholesterol, HDL- cholesterol, ALT, ALP, AST, Serum uric acid, drinking, and cardiovascular diseases.</p></fn><fn id="fnT2_4"><label>d</label><p>95% CI: 95% confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3_3"><label>3.3</label><title>Association between the weight-adjusted-waist index and liver fibrosis (LSM)</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">
<bold>Table&#160;2</bold>
</xref>, in the unadjusted model, each unit of higher WWI score was found to be associated with 0.72 kPa increased units of LSM [&#946;=0.72, 95% CI (0.61, 0.84), P&lt;0.0001]. However, after adjusting for all covariates, the relationship between WWI and LSM was not significant in Model 3 [&#946;=0.03, 95% CI (-0.26, 0.32), P=0.84].</p></sec><sec id="s3_4"><label>3.4</label><title>Subgroup analysis</title><p>We used stratified weighted multivariate regression analysis to investigate the association between WWI and CAP and LSM in different population settings, stratified by gender, age, BMI, T2D, hypertension, excess alcohol consumption, smoking, and CVD.</p><p>As displayed in <xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#160;2</bold>
</xref>, a stronger positive association between WWI and CAP was observed in participants with excess alcohol consumption and hypertension (P&lt; 0.05). However, the correlation between WWI and CAP was similar in the population with different subgroups of gender, age, smoking, BMI, T2D, and CVD. Furthermore, A significant correlation between WWI and LSM was observed in participants with BMI&gt;30 and experience CVD (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#160;3</bold>
</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="f2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure&#160;2</label><caption><p>Subgroup analysis for the association between WWI and hepatic steatosis.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fendo-14-1159055-g002.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="f3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure&#160;3</label><caption><p>Subgroup analysis for the association between WWI and liver fibrosis.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fendo-14-1159055-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3_5"><label>3.5</label><title>Non-linear relationship between WWI with hepatic steatosis and liver fibrosis</title><p>After adjusting for all variables, a non-linear association between WWI and LSM levels was found (<xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#160;4</bold>
</xref>). We observed a U-shaped relationship between the WWI and LSM (inflection point: 10.92) (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">
<bold>Table&#160;3</bold>
</xref>). Specifically, LSM was negatively associated with WWI&lt;10.92 [&#946;=-0.57, 95% CI (-1.06, -0.08), P=0.022], and positively association with WWI &gt;10.92 [&#946;=0.44, 95% CI (0.05, 0.84), P=0.028].</p><fig position="float" id="f4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure&#160;4</label><caption><p>Smooth curve fitting for WWI and LSM. The solid red line represents the smooth curve fit between variables. Blue bands represent the 95% confidence interval from the fit. WWI, weight-adjusted-waist index; LSM, liver stiffness measurement.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fendo-14-1159055-g004.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;3</label><caption><p>Threshold effect analysis of WWI on LSM and CAP using a two-piecewise linear regression model.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WWI</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAP<break/>Adjusted &#946; (95% CI) P value</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSM<break/>Adjusted &#946; (95% CI) P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitting by the standard linear model</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.60 (4.42, 10.78)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 (-0.26, 0.32)<break/>0.8419</td></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Fitting by the two-piecewise linear model</th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inflection point</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.92</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;K segment effect</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.98 (7.01, 18.95)&lt;0.0001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.57 (-1.06, -0.08)<break/>0.0219</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;K segment effect</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.88 (0.80, 8.95)<break/>0.0191</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44 (0.05, 0.84)<break/>0.0280</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Log likelihood ratio</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Adjusted for sex, age, race, education level, BMI, Diabetes, hypertension, smoking, drinking, family income to poverty ratio, Total calcium, Total cholesterol, Triglyceride, LDL- cholesterol, HDL- cholesterol, ALT, ALP, AST, Serum uric acid, drinking, and cardiovascular diseases.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>As with the linear association, we also observed a positive correlation between WWI and CAP when conducting the non-linear model. We found consistent positive association between WWI and CAP. Notably, the association was much stronger when WWI&gt;10.75 [WWI&gt;10.75: &#946;=12.98, 95% CI (7.01, 18.95), P&lt;0.0001]; WWI&lt;10.75: [&#946;=4.88, 95% CI (0.80, 8.95), P=0.02] (<xref rid="f5" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#160;5</bold>
</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="f5" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure&#160;5</label><caption><p>Smooth curve fitting for WWI and CAP. The solid red line represents the smooth curve fit between variables. Blue bands represent the 95% confidence interval from the fit. WWI, weight-adjusted-waist index; CAP, controlled attenuation parameter.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fendo-14-1159055-g005.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>The present study aimed to evaluate the relationship between WWI and hepatic steatosis and liver fibrosis among civilians in the United States. In our cross-sectional study comprising 7,594 participants, we found a significant positive linear association between WWI and hepatic steatosis. Furthermore, we identified a U-shaped relationship between WWI and liver fibrosis (inflection point 10.92). By performing subgroup analyses, a stronger association between WWI and hepatic steatosis was demonstrated in participants with hypertensive disorders and excessive alcohol consumption. Additionally, we saw evidence of a strong correlation between WWI and liver fibrosis in participants with BMI&gt;30 or CVD.</p><p>Accumulating evidence has supported the leading role of obesity in the pathogenesis of NAFLD. Given a strong link with dysregulated lipid metabolism, obesity not only contributes to the evolution of hepatic steatosis and inflammation, but also poses a threat to cardiovascular events and metabolic syndromes (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Currently, BMI is widely used to determine the severity of obesity. However, obese patients, especially NAFLD patients, tend to demonstrate both fat accumulation and loss of skeletal muscle mass due to physical inactivity, which further increases the risk of hospitalization for NAFLD patients (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). In addition, central obesity, specifically the accumulation of adipose in deep subcutaneous tissue, has been identified as the critical driver for NASH progression, insulin resistance, and cardiovascular events (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Therefore, BMI, using total weight, may not accurately reflect the health status of obese individuals, particularly NAFLD patients. In contrast, WWI, calculated by normalizing WC with body weight, primarily reflects pure central obesity and can assess high fat mass and low muscle mass (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). For this study, we evaluated the association of WWI with estimated liver histology. We found a significant positive correlation between WWI and CAP. Additionally, we have identified a U-shaped association between WWI and LSM.</p><p>WWI was first used to better evaluate the morbidity and mortality of cardiovascular and metabolic diseases in the Korean population (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Furthermore, trans-ethnic studies have revealed that WWI was positively associated with higher risks of hyperuricemia and multiple kinds of cardiovascular events, including heart failure, abdominal aortic calcification, and left ventricular hypertrophy (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>).</p><p>WWI was thought to represent the severity of central obesity rather than general obesity. As a sign of metabolic syndromes, a series of studies have suggested that central obesity is a risk factor for NAFLD, cardiovascular diseases, and other metabolic diseases for both obese and non-obese populations (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Specifically, central obesity is characterized by the accumulation of abdominal adipose tissue, especially visceral adipose tissue. Mechanically, visceral adipose tissue could constantly secrete proinflammatory stimuli, which could further lead to systematic inflammation, metabolic disorders, and histological progression in the liver of obese patients. Moreover, during the expansion of visceral adipose tissue, proinflammatory macrophages in the adipose further contribute to immune-infiltration in the liver (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). In addition, some subtypes of adipose-derived ceramidases could desensitize insulin activity and contribute to insulin resistance (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Our study has further highlighted and qualified the critical role central obesity in liver steatosis. In the future, WWI may be a liver fibrosis predictor.</p><p>This study has several limitations which should be mentioned. First, the cross-sectional study design did not allow us to determine any causal relationships. Second, the severity of hepatic steatosis and liver fibrosis in this study was determined using VCTE, which needs to be further validated in biopsy-proven cohorts. Furthermore, although the NHANES was conducted in the United States in a multi-ethnic adult population, our results may not reflect other geographic areas or ethnic groups.</p><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s4_1"><label>4.1</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, our study found strong link between WWI and hepatic steatosis, and suggested that it may potentially be used as a simple anthropometric index to predict hepatic steatosis.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s5"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/supplementary material. Further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s6"><title>Author contributions</title><p>YS and YW contributed equally to the research&#8217;s conception and design. YS performed the study and wrote the draft. YS contributed to the acquisition and analysis of the data. MF and KZ conducted the statistical analysis. YS wrote the initial drafts of the manuscript. JW reviewed and revised the later drafts of the manuscript. All authors critically reviewed the manuscript, agreed to be fully accountable for ensuring the integrity and accuracy of the work, and read and approved the final manuscript. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s8"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s9"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koyama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Liver inflammation and fibrosis</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>127</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>55</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI88881</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28045404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5199698</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neuschwander-Tetri</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rinella</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanyal</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanisms of NAFLD development and therapeutic strategies</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>24</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<page-range>908&#8211;22</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-018-0104-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6553468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29967350</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Imajo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoneda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nozaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Hyperresponsivity to low-dose endotoxin during progression to nonalcoholic steatohepatitis is regulated by leptin-mediated signaling</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>44</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2012.05.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22768838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meex</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoy</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Fetuin b is a secreted hepatocyte factor linking steatosis to impaired glucose metabolism</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>22</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>1078&#8211;89</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2015.09.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26603189</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhir</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Hepatic Hdac3 promotes gluconeogenesis by repressing lipid synthesis and sequestration</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>18</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>934&#8211;42</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.2744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3411870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22561686</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Imajo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kessoku</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomeno</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mawatari</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Magnetic resonance imaging more accurately classifies steatosis and fibrosis in patients with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease than transient elastography</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>150</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>626</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>37.e7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2015.11.048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26677985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vuppalanchi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Natta</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallinan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kowdley</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelmalek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Vibration-controlled transient elastography to assess fibrosis and steatosis in patients with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease</article-title>. <source>Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>156</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63.e2</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cgh.2018.04.043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29705261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6203668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eddowes</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsochatzis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anstee</surname><given-names>QM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheridan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Accuracy of FibroScan controlled attenuation parameter and liver stiffness measurement in assessing steatosis and fibrosis in patients with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>156</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>1717&#8211;30</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2019.01.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30689971</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vuppalanchi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Natta</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallinan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kowdley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Performance characteristics of vibration-controlled transient elastography for evaluation of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>67</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<page-range>134&#8211;44</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.29489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5739967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28859228</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosserhoff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hellerbrand</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Obesity and fatty liver are &#8216;grease&#8217; for the machinery of hepatic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Dig Dis</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<page-range>377&#8211;83</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000329800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21894008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tutunchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naeini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebrahimi-Mameghani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Najafipour</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mobasseri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ostadrahimi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Metabolically healthy and unhealthy obesity and the progression of liver fibrosis: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>Clin Res Hepatol Gastroenterol</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>45</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>101754</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinre.2021.101754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34303827</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ware</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Landy</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hennekens</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hecht</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Interrelationships between self reported physical health and health behaviors among healthy US adults: from the NHANES 2009-2016</article-title>. <source>Public Health Pract (Oxf)</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>100277</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.puhip.2022.100277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36570399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9773046</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The association between serum cadmium and diabetes in the general population: a cross-sectional study from NHANES (1999-2020)</article-title>. <source>Front Nutr</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<elocation-id>966500</elocation-id>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnut.2022.966500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36570173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9768494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Association between the weight-adjusted-waist index and abdominal aortic calcification in united states adults: results from the national health and nutrition examination survey 2013-2014</article-title>. <source>Front Cardiovasc Med</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<elocation-id>948194</elocation-id>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcvm.2022.948194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36186965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9515490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Elevated serum uric acid is associated with cognitive improvement in older American adults: a large, population-based-analysis of the NHANES database</article-title>. <source>Front Aging Neurosci</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<elocation-id>1024415</elocation-id>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnagi.2022.1024415</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36570535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9772611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Race and gender differences in the associations between cadmium exposure and bone mineral density in US adults</article-title>. <source>Biol Trace Elem Res</source> (<year>2022</year>). doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12011-022-03521-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36508128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Associations of phthalates with NAFLD and liver fibrosis: a nationally representative cross-sectional study from NHANES 2017 to 2018</article-title>. <source>Front Nutr</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<elocation-id>1059675</elocation-id>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnut.2022.1059675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36483930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9723339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hohenester</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wimmer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Artmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Denk</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Lifestyle intervention for morbid obesity: effects on liver steatosis, inflammation, and fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>315</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<page-range>G329&#8211;g38</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpgi.00044.2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29878845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lassailly</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caiazzo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buob</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pigeyre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verkindt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Labreuche</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Bariatric surgery reduces features of nonalcoholic steatohepatitis in morbidly obese patients</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>149</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>379&#8211;88</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2015.04.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25917783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Polyzos</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kountouras</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mantzoros</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Obesity and nonalcoholic fatty liver disease: from pathophysiology to therapeutics</article-title>. <source>Metabolism</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>97</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.metabol.2018.11.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30502373</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinn</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guallar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease and accelerated loss of skeletal muscle mass: a longitudinal cohort study</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>76</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>1746&#8211;54</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.32578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35588190</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petermann-Rocha</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sattar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Celis-Morales</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Associations of muscle mass and grip strength with severe NAFLD: a prospective study of 333,295 UK biobank participants</article-title>. <source>J Hepatol</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>76</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<page-range>1021&#8211;9</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2022.01.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35085594</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Middleton</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gamst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in abdominal adipose tissue depots assessed by MRI correlate with hepatic histologic improvement in non-alcoholic steatohepatitis</article-title>. <source>J Hepatol</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>78</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>238&#8211;46</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2022.10.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9852022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36368598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Weight-adjusted waist index reflects fat and muscle mass in the opposite direction in older adults</article-title>. <source>Age Ageing</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>50</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<page-range>780&#8211;6</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ageing/afaa208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33035293</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A novel adiposity index as an integrated predictor of cardiometabolic disease morbidity and mortality</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>16753</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-35073-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30425288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6233180</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Association between weight-adjusted-waist index and heart failure: results from national health and nutrition examination survey 1999-2018</article-title>. <source>Front Cardiovasc Med</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<elocation-id>1069146</elocation-id>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcvm.2022.1069146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36588556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9794568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The association between weight-adjusted-waist index and abdominal aortic calcification in adults aged &gt;/= 40 years: results from NHANES 2013-2014</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>20354</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-24756-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36437292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9701694</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The relationship between the weight-adjusted-waist index and left ventricular hypertrophy in Chinese hypertension adults</article-title>. <source>Hypertens Res</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>46</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<page-range>253&#8211;60</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41440-022-01075-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36319736</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Positive association between weight-adjusted-waist index and hyperuricemia in patients with hypertension: the China h-type hypertension registry study</article-title>. <source>Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<elocation-id>1007557</elocation-id>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2022.1007557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36277696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9582276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fahed</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aoun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bou Zerdan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bou Zerdan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouferraa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Metabolic syndrome: updates on pathophysiology and management in 2021</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>1&#8211;38</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms23020786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8775991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35054972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahakyan</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez-Escudero</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hodge</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sochor</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Normal-weight central obesity: implications for total and cardiovascular mortality</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>163</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<page-range>827&#8211;35</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M14-2525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4995595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26551006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pacifico</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Martino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Merulis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bezzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osborn</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Left ventricular dysfunction in obese children and adolescents with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>59</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>461&#8211;70</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.26610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23843206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bijnen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Josefs</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuijpers</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maalsen</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van de Gaar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vroomen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Adipose tissue macrophages induce hepatic neutrophil recruitment and macrophage accumulation in mice</article-title>. <source>Gut</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>67</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<page-range>1317&#8211;27</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2016-313654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29074725</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaben</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scherer</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Adipogenesis and metabolic health</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>20</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<page-range>242&#8211;58</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41580-018-0093-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30610207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>