<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Surg Neurol Int</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Surg Neurol Int</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1278</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">sni</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Surgical Neurology International</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2229-5097</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2152-7806</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Scientific Scholar</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11544477</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11544477.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11544477</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11544477</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39524602</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.25259/SNI_991_2023</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.25259/SNI_991_2023</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Interictal gamma oscillation regularity analysis and susceptibility-weighted imaging on focal epilepsy cases with alcohol use disorders</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yoshihito</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="tanunpas@gmail.com">tanunpas@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yosuke</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="yanda2011@gmail.com">yanda2011@gmail.com</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Matsubara Tokushukai Hospital, Matsubara, Osaka, Japan</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Brain Function Analysis and Digital Medicine Research Institute, Showa University, Hatanodai, Japan</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Showa University School of Medicine, Shinagawa-ku, Japan</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Yosuke Sato, Brain Function Analysis and Digital Medicine Research Institute, Showa University, Hatanodai Shinagawa-ku, Tokyo, Japan. <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="yanda2011@gmail.com">yanda2011@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>04</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">455634</issue-id><elocation-id>361</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>04</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>08</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-11-13 17:25:35.300"><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#169; 2024 Surgical Neurology International</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncsalicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-Share Alike 4.0 License, which allows others to remix, transform, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as the author is credited and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="SNI-15-361.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Background: </title><p>There has been no clear consensus on the clinical markers to distinguish alcohol-related seizures (ARSs) from epileptic seizures. We have reported the usefulness of gamma oscillation (30&#8211;70 Hz) regularity (GOR) analysis using interictal electroencephalography (EEG) data to evaluate epileptogenic focus. We conducted interictal GOR analysis using scalp EEG and susceptibility-weighted imaging (SWI) to visualize the epileptogenic focus in two cases initially suspected to have ARS.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Case Description: </title><p>In each case, a significantly high GOR area suggestive of epileptogenic focus was detected and that area was consistent with that where SWI showed hemosiderin deposit. In one patient, seizures were well controlled with the introduction of anti-seizure medication (ASM). In another patient, ASM was introduced but is refractory, and epilepsy surgery is being considered in the future.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Conclusion: </title><p>The interictal GOR analysis and SWI can successfully contribute to identify the patients suspected to have ARS who may have epileptogenic focus and can be treated with ASM and epilepsy surgery.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Alcohol-related seizures</kwd><kwd>Anti-seizure medication</kwd><kwd>Epilepsy surgery</kwd><kwd>Gamma oscillation regularity</kwd><kwd>Susceptibility-weighted imaging</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>
<inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="SNI-15-361-inline001.jpg"/>
</p><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Although alcohol-related seizure (ARS) is a significant symptom of alcohol abuse, little is known about its mechanism.[<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] There has been no clear consensus on clinical markers to distinguish ARS from epileptic seizures.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] Recently, we reported interictal gamma oscillation regularity (GOR) with electroencephalography (EEG), and could help determine the epileptogenic focus in epilepsy patients.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>-<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] The GOR analysis calculates the average of gamma band sample entropy scores using multi-scale entropy analysis. Lower sample entropy scores represent a higher regularity of gamma oscillations, which we define as high GOR. One of the benefits of GOR analysis is that it may identify epileptogenic focus not very accurately detectable with conventional EEG findings.</p><p>We also focused on whether susceptibility-weighted imaging (SWI) can illustrate the unknown epileptogenic focus in patients with ARS. The SWI is an MRI technique that can distinguish hemosiderin deposit rich lesions, which often cause epilepsy. The SWI has been widely used as a standard protocol in addition to routine MRI after mild traumatic brain injury (TBI),[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] which is reported to be associated with alcohol abuse.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] We hypothesized that some patients in the group of patients treated as ARS may have epilepsy triggered by TBI. For such patients, anti-seizure medication (ASM) and epilepsy surgery may improve the course of the disease.</p><p>In this report, we present our experience with patients with suspected ARS, where interictal GOR analysis and SWI allowed us to evaluate the epileptogenic focus and give appropriate treatment.</p></sec><sec id="sec1-2"><title>CLINICAL PRESENTATION</title><sec id="sec2-2_1"><title>Case 1</title><p>A 50-year-old female patient with alcohol abuse was admitted to our department with general convulsion and refractory seizures, such as an illusion of her left eye field and numbness in her left arm. There was a history of TBI in her 30s, and she often hit her left shoulder on the surroundings. T2-weighted image demonstrated low-signal intensity in the right occipital lobe [<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1a</xref>]. The SWI showed a hemosiderin deposit in the right occipital lobe [<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1b</xref>], which could explain the hemianopsia of frequent hitting of the left shoulder. In EEG, very small potential sharp transients were identified on the right occipital region. The interictal GOR analysis demonstrated significantly high GOR in the right occipital lobe [<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1c</xref>]. Oral levetiracetam of 1000 mg was started, but 2 months later, she was admitted to our department with general convulsion again. Since the addition of 100 mg of lacosamide orally, seizures have been well controlled.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1:</label><caption><p>Results of Cases 1 and 2. (a) In Case1, T2-weighted image demonstrates low signal intensity in the right occipital lobe. (b) SWI shows hemosiderin deposits in the right occipital lobe. (c) Interictal GOR analysis shows epileptogenic focus in the right occipital lobe. (d) In Case 2, T2-weighted image demonstrates low signal intensity in the left temporal lobe. (e) SWI shows hemosiderin deposits in the left temporal lobe. (f) Interictal GOR analysis shows epileptogenic focus in the left temporal lobe. Note that the lower the entropy score, the higher the GOR, and vice versa. GOR: Gamma oscillation regularity</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="SNI-15-361-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-2_2"><title>Case 2</title><p>A 40-year-old male patient with a history of alcohol abuse was admitted to the outpatient clinic complaining of severe anxiety, lightning sensation in the visual field, and refractory loss of consciousness. The patient had been treated in other psychiatric clinics with a diagnosis of depression and had taken oral antidepressants for many years. He had refractory seizures, but those were diagnosed as ARS in other clinics. The patient had a history of several mild TBIs. T2-weighted image demonstrated low-signal intensity in the left temporal lobe and mild brain atrophy [<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1d</xref>]. The SWI clearly showed a hemosiderin deposit in the left temporal lobe [<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1e</xref>]. In EEG, interictal spike waves were observed mainly on the left temporal region. The interictal GOR analysis demonstrated significantly high GOR in the left temporal lobe [<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1f</xref>]. He was introduced to several ASMs but is refractory, and epilepsy surgery is being considered in the future.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2_3"><title>EEG data recordings</title><p>EEG data were recorded using the Nihon-Kohden EEG system at 17 electrode sites (Fp1, Fp2, F3, F4, C3, C4, P3, P4, O1, O2, F7, F8, T3, T4, T5, T6, and Fz), in accordance with the international 10&#8211;20 system, with the two ear lobes jointly forming the reference. The EEG signals were recorded with a sampling rate of 500 Hz, a 1&#8211;60 Hz bandpass filter, and a time constant of 0.3 s. A 60-Hz notch filter was applied to all channels. All selected EEG data were inspected to ensure that artifacts did not contaminate them.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2_4"><title>SWI protocol</title><p>For MRI for SWI sequence, the following parameters were used: TR 29 ms, TE 20 ms, Matrix 288 &#215; 288, and flip angle 10&#176;.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2_5"><title>GOR analysis</title><p>The detailed algorithm for GOR analysis using the sample entropy method is described in our previous study.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>-<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-3"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Previous reports show alcohol intake promotes iron accumulation in the brain.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] Considering that mild TBI is associated with alcohol abuse,[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] we speculate that SWI should be performed for patients with ARS not only at the time of TBI onset but also at the time of admission of seizures even after a long period of their trauma. We suppose that SWI can be considered a routine MRI techniques to evaluate alcohol abuse patients because some pathological lesions may not be diagnosed with previous CT scans or routine MRI.</p><p>In this report, interictal GOR analysis could illustrate the epileptogenic focus in both two patients. To distinguish ARS from epileptic seizures, it may be desirable that those patients stay in the hospital for several days to be analyzed with video EEG monitoring and are observed for a sufficient period with ASMs in the outpatient department. However, alcoholic patients often refuse to be hospitalized or fail to follow their physicians&#8217; advice. As interictal GOR analysis can be performed within 1 h in an outpatient department, we suppose that this new method may be highly compatible with such patients.</p><p>Although it is widely accepted that ASMs are not effective for patients with ARS,[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] we would like to emphasize that true epileptic patients, like the patients in this report, may be concealed among those diagnosed with ARS and that such epileptic patients should be appropriately treated with ASM, and epileptic surgery should be considered in the case of drug resistance. Furthermore, to accomplish this, we recommend that an interictal GOR analysis and SWI be performed on alcohol users with ARS. It is also reported that the mortality risk is very high in epilepsy patients who take alcohol.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] Therefore, we assume that further analysis by interictal GOR analysis will be necessary among alcohol abuse patients with or without seizures.</p><p>In both two patients, the epileptogenic foci that were detected by interictal GOR analysis were directly related to the hemosiderin deposit lesion detected by SWI. Past mild TBI likely caused hemosiderin deposition and epileptogenic formation. Hemosiderin deposition and subsequent reactive gliosis can develop into epileptogenicity by facilitating neuronal synchrony.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] We assume that the interictal GOR analysis may detect such neuronal synchrony as a significantly high GOR.</p><p>This study had some limitations. First, it was a retrospective study. Second, the number of patients is small. Third, it is single institutional. Although the data obtained from these two cases were insufficient to convincingly suggest a role for interictal GOR in the identification of epileptogenic foci, it could highlight efficient use in isolating potential candidates who may be worthy of detailed evaluation for intractable seizures. We will continue to study this topic and provide more cases.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec1-4"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>Interictal GOR analysis and SWI may be helpful in distinguishing some patients with ARS who may have epileptogenic lesions that can be treated with ASM or epilepsy surgery.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><bold>How to cite this article:</bold> Tsuji Y, Sato Y. Interictal gamma oscillation regularity analysis and susceptibility-weighted imaging on focal epilepsy cases with alcohol use disorders. Surg Neurol Int. 2024;15:361. doi: 10.25259/SNI_991_2023</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec1-5"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The raw data supporting this article will be made available by the authors without undue reservation.</p></sec><sec id="sec1-6"><title>Ethical approval</title><p>The research/study approved by the Institutional Review Board at the Department of Neurosurgery, Matsubara Tokushukai Hospital, Osaka, Japan, number #20&#8211;06, dated August 17, 2022.</p></sec><sec id="sec1-7"><title>Declaration of patient consent</title><p>The authors certify that they have obtained all appropriate patient consent.</p></sec><sec sec-type="financial-disclosure" id="sec1-8"><title>Financial support and sponsorship</title><p>Nil.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec1-9"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec><sec id="sec1-10"><title>Use of artificial intelligence (AI)-assisted technology for manuscript preparation</title><p>The authors confirm that there was no use of artificial intelligence (AI)-assisted technology for assisting in the writing or editing of the manuscript and no images were manipulated using AI.</p></sec><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bob</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jasova</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bizik</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raboch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epileptiform activity in alcohol dependent patients and possibilities of its indirect measurement</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e18678</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21541318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0018678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3082533</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goddard</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leech</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A permanent change in brain function resulting from daily electrical stimulation</article-title><source>Exp Neurol</source><year>1969</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4981856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0014-4886(69)90128-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hageman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hof</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nihom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Susceptibility-weighted MRI and microbleeds in mild traumatic brain injury: Prediction of posttraumatic complaints?</article-title><source>Eur Neurol</source><year>2022</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35038701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000521389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Juh&#225;s</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacKay</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Deep grey matter iron accumulation in alcohol use disorder</article-title><source>Neuroimage</source><year>2017</year><volume>148</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28065850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2017.01.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalk</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effectiveness and tolerability of anti-seizure medication in alcohol withdrawal syndrome: A systematic review, meta-analysis and GRADE of the evidence</article-title><source>Addiction</source><year>2022</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33822427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/add.15510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mclean</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pace</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorton</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alcohol-specific mortality in people with epilepsy: Cohort studies in two independent population-based datasets</article-title><source>Front Neurol</source><year>2021</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>623139</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fneur.2020.623139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7859425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33551978</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ochi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doesburg</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otsubo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatiotemporal changes in regularity of gamma oscillations contribute to focal ictogenesis</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>9362</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28839247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-017-09931-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5570997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ochi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizutani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otsubo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low entropy of interictal gamma oscillations is a biomarker of the seizure onset zone in focal cortical dysplasia type II</article-title><source>Epilepsy Behav</source><year>2019</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31150993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.yebeh.2019.01.030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shirasawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interictal high gamma oscillation regularity as a marker for presurgical epileptogenic zone localization</article-title><source>Oper Neurosurg</source><year>2022</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1227/ons.0000000000000245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35486873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins-Bach</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alfaro-Almagro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Douaud</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Llera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phenotypic and genetic associations of quantitative magnetic susceptibility in UK Biobank brain imaging</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2022</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>818</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35606419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41593-022-01074-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9174052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Derry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mild traumatic brain injury and epilepsy: Alcohol misuse may underpin the association</article-title><source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source><year>2014</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>593</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23892406</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/jnnp-2013-306267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol consumption on unprovoked seizure and epilepsy: An updated meta-analysis</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source><year>2022</year><volume>232</volume><fpage>109305</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35042100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2022.109305</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="sec1-11"><title>Disclaimer</title><p>The views and opinions expressed in this article are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the official policy or position of the Journal or its management. The information contained in this article should not be considered to be medical advice; patients should consult their own physicians for advice as to their specific medical needs.</p></sec></back></article></pmc-articleset>