<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">36</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcid</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Infectious Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2334</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11457331</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11457331.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11457331</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11457331</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39375590</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-024-09993-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9993</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Bedaquiline <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> injectable containing regimens for rifampicin-resistant and multidrug-resistant tuberculosis in a reference center in Brazil &#8211; a real-world evidence study using a retrospective design</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5226-4372</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names initials="AP">Ana Paula</given-names></name><address><email>anapsantos.ip@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0009-0002-9977-063X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Benace Jr</surname><given-names initials="CJ">Crist&#243;v&#227;o Jorge</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6015-9628</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>de Medeiros Leung</surname><given-names initials="JA">Janaina Aparecida</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5900-6007</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Kritski</surname><given-names initials="AL">Afr&#226;nio Lineu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3250-6738</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>de Queiroz Mello</surname><given-names initials="FC">Fernanda Carvalho</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03490as77</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8536.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2294 473X</institution-id><institution>Thorax Diseases Institute, </institution><institution>Federal University of Rio de Janeiro, </institution></institution-wrap>Rio de Janeiro, Brazil </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">452052</issue-id><elocation-id>1112</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>07</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>07</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-10-09 12:25:14.647"><day>09</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12879_2024_Article_9993.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Drug resistance (DR) is one of the several challenges to global tuberculosis (TB) control. The implementation of bedaquiline (BED) for DR-TB after more than 40 years was expected to improve treatment outcomes as well as microbiologic conversion and adverse events (AE) occurrence.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Retrospective cohort study based on secondary data of patients with rifampicin-resistant (RR) or multidrug-resistant (MDR) TB reported to the Outpatient Clinic of Mycobacterial Diseases of the Thorax Diseases Institute &#8211; Federal University of Rio de Janeiro - Brazil, between 2016 and 2023. We aimed to evaluate microbiologic conversion, AE and TB treatment outcomes and compare them according to the treatment regimen used for RR/MDR-TB patients under routine conditions [Injectable Containing Regimens (ICR) <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> BED Containing Regimens (BCR)]. Logistic regression and survival analysis using Cox regression and Kaplan Meier curve were used for statistical analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Of the 463 DR-TB patients notified during the study period, 297 (64.1%) were included for analysis (ICR&#8201;=&#8201;197 and BCR&#8201;=&#8201;100). Overall AEs were more frequent (83.7 vs. 16.3%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001) and occurred earlier in the ICR group (15 days vs. 65 days, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.003). There were no cases of cardiotoxicity requiring interruption of BED treatment. None of the regimens of treatment tested were associated with smear or culture conversion on Cox regression analysis (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.60 and 0.88, respectively). BED-containing regimens were also associated with favorable outcomes in multivariable logistic regression [adjusted odds ratio (aOR)&#8201;=&#8201;2.63, 95% confidence interval (CI)1.36&#8211;5.07, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.004], as higher years of schooling, primary drug resistance, and no previous TB treatment. In the survival analysis, BCR was inversely associated with the occurrence of AE during treatment follow-up (aHR 0.24, 95% CI 0.14&#8211;0.41, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001). In addition, TB treatment regimens with BED were also associated with favorable outcomes (aHR 2.41, 95% CI 1.62&#8211;3.57, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001), along with no illicit drug use and primary drug resistance.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">The implementation of a fully oral treatment for RR/MDR-TB in a reference center in Brazil was safe and associated with favorable outcomes under routine conditions, despite social, demographic, and behavioral factors that may influence TB treatment completion.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12879-024-09993-8.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Tuberculosis</kwd><kwd>Bedaquiline</kwd><kwd>Adverse events</kwd><kwd>Microbiological conversion</kwd><kwd>Treatment outcome</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par7">Tuberculosis (TB) affects more than 10&#160;million people worldwide each year, yet it is preventable and mostly curable. Despite the effective treatment of latent and active TB, we are still far from achieving the goals of the End TB Strategy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">Drug resistance is one of many challenges that must be overcome before the alarming number of TB cases can be reduced. According to WHO, the estimated proportion of people with TB who had multidrug-resistant (MDR) or rifampicin-resistant (RR) TB was 3.3% among new cases and 17% among those previously treated cases in 2022 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">Bedaquiline (BED) was the first new clinically approved TB drug developed in more than 40 years and quickly became the <italic toggle="yes">core</italic> of regimens for RR/MDR-TB in combination with linezolid (LNZ), levofloxacin (LFX), terizidone (TRZ) and clofazimine (CFZ) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p><p id="Par10">In 2014, a phase IIb clinical trial demonstrated the efficacy and safety of BED, with a significant improvement in treatment outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The drug was then used under a compassionate use agreement by several national TB programs until it was recommended by the WHO in 2016 and implemented globally for drug-resistant TB (DR-TB) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p><p id="Par11">One of the main concerns with BED-Containing Regimens (BCR) was cardiovascular safety because of the potential for QT interval prolongation on electrocardiogram, leading to arrhythmias [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><p id="Par12">Several scientific publications have evaluated drug-resistant TB regimens containing bedaquiline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. From observational studies to randomized clinical trials, all of them contributed to the current WHO recommendations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par13">Since 2021, the Brazilian Ministry of Health implemented the new regimen for RR/MDR-TB with bedaquiline in combination with LNZ, LFX and TRZ (BCR), in substitution of amikacin (Am) (and previously capreomycin) in combination with LFX, TRZ, ethambutol and pyrazinamide [Injectable Containing Regimens (ICR)]. Although both regimens share the same long duration of 18 months, the former is a totally oral regimen, while the latter includes 8 months of a parenteral drug [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par14">We aimed to evaluate microbiologic conversion, adverse events (AE) and TB treatment outcomes before and after the implementation of BCR in RR/MDR-TB patients under routine conditions at the Newthon Bethlem Outpatients Clinic of the Thorax Diseases Institute &#8211; Federal University of Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, the city with the highest incidence of drug-resistant TB in Brazil.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par15">A real-world evidence study with a retrospective cohort design was conducted based on secondary data extracted from the database of the <italic toggle="yes">Sistema de Tratamentos Especiais - TB</italic> (SITE-TB), where patients with DR-TB reported between 2016 and 2023 were registered (Ethics Committee approval # 5.959.943).</p><p id="Par16">SITE-TB is a Brazilian Internet platform implemented in 2013 in all Brazilian states, with the aim of routinely monitoring all persons with drug-resistant tuberculosis in Brazil, as well as qualifying tuberculosis drug control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. The online website also allows physicians to report drug-resistant TB cases in the country and to register patients` follow-up, including microbiological curve, radiological evolution and AE occurrence. All drug changes during TB treatment need to be registered in the platform, making it an effective way to manage and supply TB drugs for the different national reference centers for DR-TB.</p><p id="Par17">All patients with RR/MDR-TB reported and treated at our clinic during the study period were eligible. To be included, TB treatment regimens must have included amikacin or capreomycin, used in Brazil until 2021 (ICR), or bedaquiline (BCR) according to the recommendations of the Brazilian Ministry of Health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Patients with a change of diagnosis and those transferred to another health center were excluded. Patients who were later found to be rifampicin-monoresistant based on phenotypic drug susceptibility testing were still included in the analysis if the treatment regimen using injectable drugs or bedaquiline was maintained.</p><p id="Par18">Favorable outcomes of TB treatment were considered to be cure, completion of treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] and patients who were still on treatment but had completed at least 6 months of treatment with good adherence. Unfavorable outcomes included loss to follow-up, failure, resistance evolution, death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] or change of regimen due to AEs. Adverse event data were collected as described in the SITE-TB database during the patient follow-up visits to the outpatient clinic. Times to smear and culture conversion were calculated based on the first day of treatment and the day the next negative biologic specimen was obtained.</p><p id="Par19">Descriptive analysis was performed through estimates of median and interquartile range (IQR) of the quantitative variables and simple and relative frequencies of the qualitative variables.</p><p id="Par20">For the quantitative variables, the Shapiro-Wilk test was performed to test for normal distribution. For the variables with an abnormal distribution, the Mann-Whitney test was used to compare the medians of two independent variables. The Chi-square test was used to test the association between the qualitative variables.</p><p id="Par21">For the multiple logistic regression analysis, the covariates in the model were selected according to the p-value of the test in the corresponding Chi-square tests, considering values less than 0.2 as possible predictors of the outcome variable in the BCR and ICR groups. The process of selecting the final model was done by the stepwise (backward) method until all variables were considered significant with p-values below 0.05. Variables with statistical significance in the regression analysis were tested for interactions.</p><p id="Par22">The Cox regression model was used to estimate the hazard ratio (HR) for comparing the two TB treatment regimens used (BCR and ICR) over time. Simple models were constructed to estimate HR without adjustment, and then models with all covariates were adjusted to estimate the adjusted hazard ratio (aHR).</p><p id="Par23">Kaplan-Meier curves were constructed with the event of interest, i.e., adverse events, smear and culture conversions or TB treatment outcomes, and the time (in days) until its occurrence. The log-rank test was used to compare two or more curves.</p><p id="Par24">The significance level used was 5%, and all analyses were performed in the R 4.1.0 environment (R Core Team, 2021).</p></sec><sec id="Sec3" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p id="Par25">During the study period, 463 patients were diagnosed with drug-resistant TB and 166 were excluded from the analysis (151 had other drug-resistance patterns, 9 were treated with other regimens, 6 had a change of diagnosis or were transferred).</p><p id="Par26">The study population was predominantly men (63%), aged between 26 and 50 years (56%), non-white (68%), and with a low level of education (&lt;&#8201;7 years) (53%). Regarding social habits associated with TB risk, 25% had a history of alcoholism, 30% were smokers and 28% reported illicit drug use. 75% had MDR-TB, 26% had a previous history of any DR-TB and 48% had primary resistant TB. Demographic and clinical data and social habits characteristics of the 297 patients included for analysis are summarized in Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, according to TB treatment groups. There was no statistically significant difference in demographic and clinical characteristics between them.</p><p id="Par27">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>General characteristics of the study population according to the regimen of treatment used (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;297)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Regimen of treatment</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Injectable Containing Regimens<break/>
<bold>(</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>
<bold>&#8201;=&#8201;197)</bold>
</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Bedaquiline Containing Regimens<break/>
<bold>(</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>
<bold>&#8201;=&#8201;100)</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>Variable</bold>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>N</bold>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>%</bold>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>N</bold>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>%</bold>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">p-value*</italic></bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>Sex</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">124</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 96</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>Age (Years)</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 52</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26&#8211;50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;&#8201;50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><p>
<bold>Ethnicity</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>(</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>
<bold>&#8201;=&#8201;292)</bold>
</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non &#8211; White</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">129</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">White</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><p>
<bold>Years of education</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>(</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>
<bold>&#8201;=&#8201;263)</bold>
</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8804;&#8201;7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">109</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 55</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;&#8201;7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Comorbidities</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diabetes Mellitus</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mental illness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 89</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hepatitis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1. 00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Renal failure</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 55</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cancer</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 65</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Use of CTC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Use of immunobiologics</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 87</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>HIV</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Negative</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">118</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">0. 21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unknown</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Positive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Social habits</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alcoholism</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Drug Use</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>TB presentation</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Disseminate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">0. 84</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Extrapulmonary</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pulmonary</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">183</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>Resistance Pattern</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other R resistance</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0. 06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MDR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">155</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>Type of Resistance</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Acquired</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0. 87</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Primary</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>Previous DR-TB</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">140</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0. 09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="7" colspan="1">
<bold>Treatment Outcomes</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cure</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="7" colspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Completed Treatment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">On treatment (&#8805;&#8201;6&#160;m)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lost to follow up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Death</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Failure</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Resistance Evolution</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>Outcome Categories</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unfavorable</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Favorable</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Chi-square test</p><p>Legend: N&#8201;=&#8201;Number of observations; %= relative frequency; CI&#8201;=&#8201;Confidence interval; CTC&#8201;=&#8201;Corticosteroids; HIV&#8201;=&#8201;Human Immunodeficiency virus; TB&#8201;=&#8201;Tuberculosis; R&#8201;=&#8201;Rifampicin; MR&#8201;=&#8201;Multidrug; DR-TB&#8201;=&#8201;Drug Resistant Tuberculosis</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par28">Although overall AEs were more frequent (83.7 vs. 16.3%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001) and occurred earlier in the ICR group (15 days vs. 65 days, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.003), we did not observe a statistically significant difference in the presentation of AE requiring treatment interruption between the groups of interest (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par29">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Adverse events according to regimen of treatment</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Treatment Regimen</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Injectable Containing Regimen</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Bedaquiline Containing Regimen</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Adverse Event</bold>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>N</bold>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>%</bold>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>N</bold>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>%</bold>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">p-value*</italic></bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overall AE</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83. 7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16. 3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time in days until first AE, days (IQR)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>15</p><p>(31.7)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>65</p><p>(93)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hepatitis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100. 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1. 00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Peripheral neuropathy</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70. 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30. 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Optic neuropathy</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60. 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40. 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arthralgia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84. 4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15. 6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 97</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nephrotoxicity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100. 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 70</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ototoxicity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100. 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rash</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100. 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Psychiatric symptoms</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100. 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hypothyroidism</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100. 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1. 00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Myelotoxicity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50. 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50. 0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 74</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Chi-square test</p><p>Legend: N&#8201;=&#8201;absolute frequency; %= Relative frequency; AE&#8201;=&#8201;Adverse event; IQR&#8201;=&#8201;Interquartile range</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par30">White ethnicity, higher years of education (&gt;&#8201;7 years), not smoking and not using illicit drugs were associated with favorable TB treatment outcomes in the bivariate regression analysis, along with primary (vs. acquired drug resistance) and having (vs. not having) previous DR-TB. MDR-TB was inversely associated with favorable outcomes when compared with RR-TB or rifampicin-monoresistant TB (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><p id="Par31">
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Bivariate and multivariate logistic regression analysis of factors associated with favorable tuberculosis treatment outcomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value*</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aOR</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value*</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Ethnicity (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;292)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-White</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">White</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.91</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14&#8211;3.21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Education (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;263)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Up to 7 years</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">More than 7 years</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.54&#8211;4.36</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.30&#8211;4.09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Diabetes Mellitus</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.77&#8211;1.18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Alcoholism</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97&#8211;2.79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.88</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14&#8211;3.19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Illicit drugs</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.82</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.09&#8211;3.03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Tuberculosis Presentation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Both</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Extrapulmonary</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05&#8211;2.37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pulmonary</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08&#8211;1.09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Resistance Pattern</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other R resistance</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MDR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.48</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.27&#8211;0.84</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Type of Resistance</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Acquired</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Primary</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.90&#8211;4.96</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.90</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.05&#8211;3.45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Previous DR-TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.60&#8211;8.10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14&#8211;4.79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Regimen of Treatment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Injectable Containing Regimens</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bedaquiline Containing Regimens</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.46</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.89&#8211;2.38</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.63</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.36&#8211;5.07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Adverse Events</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18&#8211;0.49</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18&#8211;0.60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Legend: OR&#8201;=&#8201;Odds Ratio; CI&#8201;=&#8201;Confidence Interval; aOR&#8201;=&#8201;Adjusted Odds Ratio; R&#8201;=&#8201;Rifampicin; MR&#8201;=&#8201;Multidrug; DR-TB&#8201;=&#8201;Drug Resistant Tuberculosis</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par32">In multivariate logistic regression, when adjusted for ethnicity, years of education, comorbidities (diabetes mellitus, corticosteroid and immunobiologic use), alcoholism, smoking, illicit drug use, TB presentation, type of drug resistance, drug resistance pattern, previous DR-TB treatment, treatment regimen and AE (included in the model because they had a level of significance&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.20), only higher years of education (&gt;&#8201;7 years), primary (vs. acquired drug resistance), no history of previous DR-TB treatment and BCR persisted in the final model and were associated with favorable outcomes (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The absence of AE was inversely associated with favorable outcomes, even after adjustment for possible confounders (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><p id="Par33">Survival analysis of time until microbiologic conversion in days showed that smoking was inversely associated with smear conversion. On the other hand, primary resistance showed a positive association with microbiologic conversion when compared with those with acquired resistance (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). None of the TB treatment regimens were associated to smear or culture conversion (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par34">
<table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Cox regression analysis of time in days until favorable tuberculosis treatment outcomes, adverse events occurrence and microbiologic conversion</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HR</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CI (95%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aHR</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CI (95%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">
<bold>Favorable outcome</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Illicit drugs</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.08&#8211;2.27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.66</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.35&#8211;5.24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Resistance Pattern</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other R resistance</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MDR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.38&#8211;0.74</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.002</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.35&#8211;0.81</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Type of Resistance</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Acquired</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Primary</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03&#8211;1.93</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.58</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.63&#8211;1.06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Regimen of Treatment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Injectable Containing Regimens</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bedaquiline Containing Regimens</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.68&#8211;3.25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.62&#8211;3.57</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">
<bold>Adverse events</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;26 years</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26&#8211;50 years</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.76&#8211;1.88</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.94</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.15&#8211;3.28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;&#8201;50 years</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.67</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00&#8211;2.79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03&#8211;3.92</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Previous DR-TB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.36</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.22&#8211;0.61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.19&#8211;0.62</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Regimen of Treatment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Injectable Containing Regimens</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bedaquiline Containing Regimens</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.16&#8211;0.42</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14&#8211;0.41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">
<bold>Smear conversion</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.74</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.52&#8211;1.10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.57</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.34&#8211;0.97</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Resistance Pattern</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other R resistance</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MDR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.37&#8211;0.85</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.006</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.46</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.27&#8211;0.79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Type of Resistance</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Acquired</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Primary</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02&#8211;1.94</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02&#8211;2.37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Regimen of Treatment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Injectable Containing Regimens</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bedaquiline Containing Regimens</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.74&#8211;1.42</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.89</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.89</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.57&#8211;1.38</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">
<bold>Culture Conversion</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Regimen of Treatment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Injectable Containing Regimens</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bedaquiline Containing Regimens</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.85&#8211;1.61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.69&#8211;1.53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.88</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Legend: HR&#8201;=&#8201;Hazard Ratio; CI&#8201;=&#8201;Confidence Interval; aHR&#8201;=&#8201;Adjusted Hazard Ratio; R&#8201;=&#8201;Rifampicin; MR&#8201;=&#8201;Multidrug; DRTB&#8201;=&#8201;Drug Resistant Tuberculosis</p><p>Legend: ICR&#8201;=&#8201;Injectable Containing Regimens; BCR&#8201;=&#8201;Bedaquiline Containing Regimens</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par35">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Kaplan Meier curve of time in days until favorable tuberculosis treatment outcomes, adverse events occurrence and microbiologic conversion</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2093" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12879_2024_9993_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par36">Age groups above 26 years showed a higher risk ratio for AE occurrence over time, but previously treated DR-TB was inversely associated with it when compared to those who had never had DR-TB (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p><p id="Par37">Bedaquiline-containing regimens were inversely associated with the occurrence of AE in Cox regression analysis (aHR 0.24, 95% CI 0.14&#8211;0.41, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001). TB treatment with BCR was also associated with favorable outcomes (aHR 2.41, 95% CI 1.62&#8211;3.57, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001), as were no illicit drug use and primary drug resistance, even after adjustment for potential confounders (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Kaplan-Meier&#8217;s curves shown in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> register significant associations of BCR with time in days to AE occurrence and to treatment outcome (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001 for both variables), while microbiologic conversion did not show statistically significant differences between TB treatment groups.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par38">In this cohort of patients, followed at a reference center in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, BCR was associated with favorable TB treatment outcomes and a lower risk of AEs, although no benefit was seen in terms of microbiologic conversion.</p><p id="Par39">To our knowledge, this is the first study to analyze bactericidal activity, AE occurrence and TB treatment outcomes after the implementation of bedaquiline for RR/MDR-TB under routine conditions in Brazil. We registered an overall favorable treatment outcome of 55.9%, a level lower than the globally reported 63% by WHO in 2020 <sup>1</sup>, the frequency of favorable outcomes was almost 10% higher in our center after the implementation of BCR (61% vs. 52,8%) (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In addition, the association between bedaquiline regimens and favorable treatment outcomes was demonstrated in multivariate and survival analysis.</p><p id="Par40">A recent meta-analysis including observational cohorts and experimental studies found that the pooled treatment success rate of BCR was 78.4% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. This success rate is likely related to the inclusion of patients from different countries, which may make comparison with our results difficult. In addition, experimental studies, including randomized clinical trials, although being considered the highest level of evidence to establish causal associations in clinical research, are usually conducted under idealized and tightly controlled conditions, which may affect their external validity and can also influence the results of the meta-analysis and comparison with our results.</p><p id="Par41">In a large global cohort, 74.2% of patients treated with BCR had treatment success, 6.5% died, 2.9% failed and 16.5% were lost to follow-up [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Their numbers were better than ours (treatment success&#8201;=&#8201;62%, death&#8201;=&#8201;5%, failure&#8201;=&#8201;7% and loss to follow up =&#8201;26%), probably because the inclusion of patients from countries with better socioeconomic and quality of life indicators may affect adherence and treatment conclusions.</p><p id="Par42">Social aspects presented in our casuistic deserve attention, such as level of education, alcoholism, smoking and illicit drug use. These characteristics have already been identified as risk factors for TB in general and for adverse treatment outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. In our study, these variables were statistically associated with a negative impact on treatment outcome and smear conversion. Our data are consistent with the finding that patients without a history of DR-TB are more likely to complete TB treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], i.e., those who have previously discontinued resistant TB treatment may repeat the behavior, with a higher risk of a new discontinuation, failure, resistance development, or even death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p><p id="Par43">Another worrying finding is the percentage of primary drug resistance in our sample of RR/MDR-TB patients (almost 50%), which represents a public health problem and has been highlighted by other authors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Fortunately, these patients tend to have more favorable outcomes, as shown by another study in a Brazilian scenario [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p><p id="Par44">Curiously, the absence of AE was inversely associated with favorable outcomes, unlike previous studies that found an association between drug side effects and loss to follow-up [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. We suggest that this could be explained by the fact that only those who continued and completed treatment could complain of AE. On the other hand, patients with unfavorable outcomes, with a poor adherence to medical appointments, did not complain about them.</p><p id="Par45">In addition, the time to first presentation of AE was longer in the BCR group compared the ICR group. In the meta-analysis by Hatami et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], the most common AE potentially attributable to bedaquiline regimens were gastrointestinal symptoms (15.3%), peripheral neuropathy (13.8%), and hematologic disorders (13.6%). In our cohort, the most common serious adverse events in the BCR group were arthralgia, optic neuropathy, peripheral neuropathy and myelotoxicity, but no nephrotoxicity or ototoxicity occurred in the ICR group.</p><p id="Par46">Since the first clinical trials with bedaquiline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], prolongation of the QT interval on the electrocardiogram has been a concern, but later, studies conducted under routine conditions have not reproduced this finding, mainly because cardiac monitoring is not reported systematically and in sufficient detail to allow for easy comparisons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. While some studies show an increased risk of cardiotoxicity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], none of our patients showed QT interval prolongation, results similar to those published by Chesov et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p><p id="Par47">Our study did not have sufficient power to show statistically significant differences in time to smear or culture conversion between TB treatment regimens, as did Charan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. However, more recent studies have found an association of higher sputum culture conversion rates with BCR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p><p id="Par48">Our main limitation, besides those inherent to retrospective studies, was the impossibility of attributing neither TB treatment outcomes nor AE occurrence specifically to bedaquiline, as treatment regimens include several drugs, but this is a problem common to all similar studies. In addition, although we wanted to contribute to the research gap in reliable scientific data on AEs, our routine registries were not conducted in a standardized or structured way, as details were not recorded in the medical records or in the instrument used as a source document, making it difficult for us to assess and grade them. Finally, not all patients presented microbiological results at follow-up because they could not produce spontaneous or induced sputum, which could justify our lack of power for this analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par49">In this study, we demonstrated that the implementation of a fully oral bedaquiline-based regimen was safe and associated with a favorable outcome under routine conditions, despite social, demographic, and behavioral factors that may influence TB treatment completion.</p><p id="Par50">Despite rapid changes regarding in RR/MDR-TB treatment in recent years, including the recommendation of the bedaquiline-pretomanide-linezolid (BPaL) regimens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], real-world evidence studies evaluating regimens still recommended in different settings are important to show the behavior of the disease and its treatment in relation to social and clinical variables under routine conditions and at specific points in history.</p><p id="Par51">The results of the present study made it possible to highlight the positive evolution of Brazilian public institutions over the years, and why not say of global health institutions, leading to the adoption of safer and more effective treatments over the years. In addition, we expect that these data can help the health managers to improve TB care by anticipating the identification of patients at higher risk of adverse TB treatment outcomes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12879_2024_9993_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#8217;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We appreciate Camila Marinelli for their technical assistance during the statistical analysis.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>APS conceived and supervised the study. CBJ and JAML collected data e filled the database. APS and FCQM analyzed all the data. AK provided advice during the design of the study. APS wrote the manuscript, which has been critically reviewed for intellectual content by AK and FCQM. All authors have read and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was funded by the own authors.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par52">The study was submitted to Clementino Fraga Filho &#8211; UFRJ Ethics Committee and was approved under # 5.959.943. Because of the retrospective design of the study and the total anonymity of patient&#8217;s identification, the IRB mentioned above waived the need of informed consent.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par53">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par54">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">The Global Plan to End TB 2023&#8211;2030. Geneva, Switzerland. Stop TB Partnership. 2022. Available: file:///C:/Users/Z728352/Downloads/global_plan_to_end_tb_2023&#8211;2030.pdf</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Global tuberculosis report 2023</collab></person-group><source>Licence: CC BY-NC-SA 3.0 IGO</source><year>2023</year><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="book">Global tuberculosis report 2023. Licence: CC BY-NC-SA 3.0 IGO. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2023.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">WHO treatment guidelines for drug-resistant tuberculosis, WHO/HTM/TB/2016.04. 2016 update. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/250125/1/9789241549639-eng.pdf?ua=1">http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/250125/1/9789241549639-eng.pdf?ua=1</ext-link>. World Health Organization: 2016.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27748093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diacon</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pym</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grobusch</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de los Rios</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gotuzzo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasilyeva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><collab>TMC207-C208 Study Group</collab><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multidrug-resistant tuberculosis and culture conversion with bedaquiline</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>371</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1313865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25140958</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Diacon AH, Pym A, Grobusch MP, de los Rios JM, Gotuzzo E, Vasilyeva I, TMC207-C208 Study Group, et al. Multidrug-resistant tuberculosis and culture conversion with bedaquiline. N Engl J Med. 2014;371(8):723&#8211;32.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25140958</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMoa1313865</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pawara</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pawara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shirkhedkar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Surana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A structural insight of bedaquiline for the cardiotoxicity and hepatotoxicity</article-title><source>Tuberculosis</source><year>2019</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tube.2019.06.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31378273</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Patel H, Pawara R, Pawara K, Ahmed F, Shirkhedkar A, Surana S. A structural insight of bedaquiline for the cardiotoxicity and hepatotoxicity. Tuberculosis. 2019;117:79&#8211;84.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31378273</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.tube.2019.06.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pym</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diacon</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conradie</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danilovits</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bedaquiline in the treatment of multidrug- and extensively drug-resistant tuberculosis</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2016</year><volume>47</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>564</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.00724-2015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26647431</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Pym AS, Diacon AH, Tang SJ, Conradie F, Danilovits M, et al. Bedaquiline in the treatment of multidrug- and extensively drug-resistant tuberculosis. Eur Respir J. 2016;47(2):564&#8211;74.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26647431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/13993003.00724-2015</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirzayev</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Viney</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linh</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>World Health Organization recommendations on the treatment of drug-resistant tuberculosis, 2020 update</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2021</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>200330</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.03300-2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8176349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33243847</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Mirzayev F, Viney K, Linh NN, et al. World Health Organization recommendations on the treatment of drug-resistant tuberculosis, 2020 update. Eur Respir J. 2021;57:200330.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/13993003.03300-2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8176349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33243847</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Padayatchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bionghi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naidu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ndjeka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Master</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Treatment outcomes in patients with drug-resistant TB-HIV co-infection treated with bedaquiline and linezolid</article-title><source>Int J Tuberc Lung Dis</source><year>2020</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1024</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5588/ijtld.20.0048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33126934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8141513</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Padayatchi N, Bionghi N, Osman F, Naidu N, Ndjeka N, Master I, et al. Treatment outcomes in patients with drug-resistant TB-HIV co-infection treated with bedaquiline and linezolid. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis. 2020;24:1024&#8211;31.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33126934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5588/ijtld.20.0048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8141513</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insignificant difference in culture conversion between bedaquiline-containing and bedaquiline-free all-oral short regimens for multidrug-resistant tuberculosis</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis</source><year>2021</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2021.08.055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34454119</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Fu L, Weng T, Sun F, Zhang P, Li H, Li Y, et al. Insignificant difference in culture conversion between bedaquiline-containing and bedaquiline-free all-oral short regimens for multidrug-resistant tuberculosis. Int J Infect Dis. 2021;111:138&#8211;47.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34454119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijid.2021.08.055</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of adverse reactions of bedaquiline containing regimen in the treatment of drug-resistant pulmonary tuberculosis</article-title><source>Chin J Antituberc</source><year>2022</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>45</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Zhang Y, Xiong Y, Chang T, Liu F. Analysis of adverse reactions of bedaquiline containing regimen in the treatment of drug-resistant pulmonary tuberculosis. Chin J Antituberc. 2022;44:239&#8211;45.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brasil</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Minist&#233;rio Da Sa&#250;de. Departamento De Vigil&#226;ncia em Sa&#250;de. Departamento De Vigil&#226;ncia das Doen&#231;as Transmiss&#237;veis. Coordena&#231;&#227;o-Geral do Programa Nacional De Controle Da Tuberculose</article-title><source>Nota Informativa N&#186; 9/2021. Atualiza&#231;&#227;o das recomenda&#231;&#245;es do tratamento da tuberculose drogarresistente com a disponibiliza&#231;&#227;o da bedaquilina e delamanida</source><year>2021</year><publisher-loc>Bras&#237;lia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Minist&#233;rio da Sa&#250;de</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="book">Brasil. Minist&#233;rio Da Sa&#250;de. Departamento De Vigil&#226;ncia em Sa&#250;de. Departamento De Vigil&#226;ncia das Doen&#231;as Transmiss&#237;veis. Coordena&#231;&#227;o-Geral do Programa Nacional De Controle Da Tuberculose. Nota Informativa N&#186; 9/2021. Atualiza&#231;&#227;o das recomenda&#231;&#245;es do tratamento da tuberculose drogarresistente com a disponibiliza&#231;&#227;o da bedaquilina e delamanida. Bras&#237;lia: Minist&#233;rio da Sa&#250;de; 2021.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartholomay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pelissari</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arakaki-Sanchez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dockhorn</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Special Tuberculosis Treatment Information System (SITE-TB) in Brazil: background, description and perspectives</article-title><source>Epidemiol Serv Saude</source><year>2019</year><volume>28</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e2018158</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31271632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5123/S1679-49742019000200002</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Bartholomay P, Pinheiro RS, Pelissari DM, Arakaki-Sanchez D, Dockhorn F, Rocha JL, et al. Special Tuberculosis Treatment Information System (SITE-TB) in Brazil: background, description and perspectives. Epidemiol Serv Saude. 2019;28(2):e2018158.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31271632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5123/S1679-49742019000200002</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. Meeting Report of the WHO Expert Consultation on Drug-resistant tuberculosis treatment outcome definitions, 17&#8211;19 November 2020. Geneva, World Health Organization,; 2021.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ur Rehman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fatima</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akram</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nashwan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yunus</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy and safety of bedaquiline containing regimens in patients of drug-resistant tuberculosis: an updated systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Clin Tuberc Other Mycobact Dis</source><year>2023</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>100405</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jctube.2023.100405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38152568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10750101</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Ur Rehman O, Fatima E, Ali A, Akram U, Nashwan A, Yunus F. Efficacy and safety of bedaquiline containing regimens in patients of drug-resistant tuberculosis: an updated systematic review and meta-analysis. J Clin Tuberc Other Mycobact Dis. 2023;34:100405.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38152568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jctube.2023.100405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10750101</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koirala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borisov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danila</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mariandyshev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shrestha</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lukhele</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Outcome of treatment of MDR-TB or drug-resistant patients treated with bedaquiline and delamanid: results from a large global cohort</article-title><source>Pulmonology</source><year>2021</year><volume>27</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pulmoe.2021.02.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33753021</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Koirala S, Borisov S, Danila E, Mariandyshev A, Shrestha B, Lukhele N, et al. Outcome of treatment of MDR-TB or drug-resistant patients treated with bedaquiline and delamanid: results from a large global cohort. Pulmonology. 2021;27(5):403&#8211;12.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33753021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pulmoe.2021.02.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chenciner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Annerstedt</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pescarini</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wingfield</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Social and health factors associated with unfavourable treatment outcome in adolescents and young adults with tuberculosis in Brazil: a national retrospective cohort study</article-title><source>Lancet Glob Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>9</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e1380</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(21)00300-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34534486</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Chenciner L, Annerstedt KS, Pescarini JM, Wingfield T. Social and health factors associated with unfavourable treatment outcome in adolescents and young adults with tuberculosis in Brazil: a national retrospective cohort study. Lancet Glob Health. 2021;9(10):e1380&#8211;90.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34534486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2214-109X(21)00300-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguipdop-Djomo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abubakar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mangtani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug misuse, tobacco smoking, alcohol and other social determinants of tuberculosis in UK-born adults in England: a community-based case-control study</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>5639</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-62667-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32221405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7101386</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Nguipdop-Djomo P, Rodrigues LC, Smith PG, Abubakar I, Mangtani P. Drug misuse, tobacco smoking, alcohol and other social determinants of tuberculosis in UK-born adults in England: a community-based case-control study. Sci Rep. 2020;10(1):5639.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32221405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-020-62667-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7101386</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scholze</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berra</surname><given-names>TZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>ACV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pieri</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pillon</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tuberculosis among people living on the Street and using Alcohol, Tobacco, and illegal drugs: analysis of territories in Extreme Vulnerability and trends in Southern Brazil</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>7721</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph19137721</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35805377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9265499</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Scholze AR, Alves JD, Berra TZ, Ramos ACV, Pieri FM, Pillon SC, et al. Tuberculosis among people living on the Street and using Alcohol, Tobacco, and illegal drugs: analysis of territories in Extreme Vulnerability and trends in Southern Brazil. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(13):7721.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35805377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph19137721</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9265499</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Savioli</surname><given-names>MTG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrone</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary bacillary resistance in multidrug-resistant tuberculosis and predictive factors associated with cure at a referral center in S&#227;o Paulo, Brazil</article-title><source>J Bras Pneumol</source><year>2019</year><volume>45</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e20180075</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1806-3713/e20180075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30864608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6733733</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Savioli MTG, Morrone N, Santoro I. Primary bacillary resistance in multidrug-resistant tuberculosis and predictive factors associated with cure at a referral center in S&#227;o Paulo, Brazil. J Bras Pneumol. 2019;45(2):e20180075.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30864608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/1806-3713/e20180075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6733733</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teferi</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Khatib</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boltena</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andualem</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asamoah</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biru</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adane</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tuberculosis treatment outcome and predictors in Africa: a systematic review and Meta-analysis</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>18</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>10678</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph182010678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34682420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8536006</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Teferi MY, El-Khatib Z, Boltena MT, Andualem AT, Asamoah BO, Biru M, Adane HT. Tuberculosis treatment outcome and predictors in Africa: a systematic review and Meta-analysis. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18(20):10678.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34682420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph182010678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8536006</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhering</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kritski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary and acquired multidrug-resistant tuberculosis: predictive factors for unfavorable treatment outcomes in Rio De Janeiro, 2000&#8211;2016</article-title><source>Rev Panam Salud Publica</source><year>2020</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>e178</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26633/RPSP.2020.178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33417644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7778465</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Bhering M, Kritski A. Primary and acquired multidrug-resistant tuberculosis: predictive factors for unfavorable treatment outcomes in Rio De Janeiro, 2000&#8211;2016. Rev Panam Salud Publica. 2020;44:e178.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33417644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.26633/RPSP.2020.178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7778465</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Birhane</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mekonnen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dingeta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teklemariam</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loss to follow-up tuberculosis treatment and associated factors among adults attending at public health facilities in Warder District, Somali Regional State, Eastern Ethiopia</article-title><source>Front Public Health</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1151077</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2023.1151077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37234759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10208408</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Birhane M, Mekonnen S, Dingeta T, Teklemariam Z. Loss to follow-up tuberculosis treatment and associated factors among adults attending at public health facilities in Warder District, Somali Regional State, Eastern Ethiopia. Front Public Health. 2023;11:1151077.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37234759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpubh.2023.1151077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10208408</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nigam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lingala</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reasons for loss to follow-up (LTFU) of pulmonary TB (PTB) patients: a qualitative study among Saharia, a particularly vulnerable tribal group of Madhya Pradesh, India</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>e0261152</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0261152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34941885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8699669</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Mishra P, Sharma RK, Yadav R, Rao VG, Nigam S, Lingala MA, Bhat J. Reasons for loss to follow-up (LTFU) of pulmonary TB (PTB) patients: a qualitative study among Saharia, a particularly vulnerable tribal group of Madhya Pradesh, India. PLoS ONE. 2021;16(12):e0261152.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34941885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0261152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8699669</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pontali</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sotgiu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiberi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardiac safety of bedaquiline: a systematic and critical analysis of the evidence</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2017</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>1701462</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.01462-2017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29146605</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Pontali E, Sotgiu G, Tiberi S, et al. Cardiac safety of bedaquiline: a systematic and critical analysis of the evidence. Eur Respir J. 2017;50:1701462.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29146605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/13993003.01462-2017</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sotgiu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bostanghadiri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abadi</surname><given-names>SSD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mesgarpour</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goudarzi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bedaquiline-containing regimens and multidrug-resistant tuberculosis: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Bras Pneumol</source><year>2022</year><volume>48</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e20210384</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.36416/1806-3756/e20210384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35649043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8836629</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Hatami H, Sotgiu G, Bostanghadiri N, Abadi SSD, Mesgarpour B, Goudarzi H, et al. Bedaquiline-containing regimens and multidrug-resistant tuberculosis: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Bras Pneumol. 2022;48(2):e20210384.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35649043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.36416/1806-3756/e20210384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8836629</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The efficacy and safety of Bedaquiline in the treatment of pulmonary tuberculosis patients: a systematic review and Meta-analysis</article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1389</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics12091389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37760686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10525131</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Tong E, Wu Q, Chen Y, Liu Z, Zhang M, Zhu Y, Wu K, Pan J, Jiang J. The efficacy and safety of Bedaquiline in the treatment of pulmonary tuberculosis patients: a systematic review and Meta-analysis. Antibiotics. 2023;12:1389.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37760686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antibiotics12091389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10525131</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chesov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heyckendorf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexandru</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of bedaquiline on treatment outcomes of multidrug-resistant tuberculosis in a high-burden country</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2021</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>2002544</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.02544-2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33334942</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Chesov D, Heyckendorf J, Alexandru S, et al. Impact of bedaquiline on treatment outcomes of multidrug-resistant tuberculosis in a high-burden country. Eur Respir J. 2021;57:2002544.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33334942</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/13993003.02544-2020</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reljic</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bedaquiline versus placebo for management of multiple drug-resistant tuberculosis: a systematic review</article-title><source>Indian J Pharmacol</source><year>2016</year><volume>48</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0253-7613.178839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27127322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4825437</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Charan J, Reljic T, Kumar A. Bedaquiline versus placebo for management of multiple drug-resistant tuberculosis: a systematic review. Indian J Pharmacol. 2016;48(2):186&#8211;91.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27127322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/0253-7613.178839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4825437</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kempker</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikiashvili</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benkeser</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbakadze</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bablishvili</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical outcomes among patients with drug-resistant tuberculosis receiving bedaquiline- or delamanid-containing regimens</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2020</year><volume>71</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2336</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31712809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/cid/ciz1107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7713674</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Kempker RR, Mikiashvili L, Zhao Y, Benkeser D, Barbakadze K, Bablishvili N, et al. Clinical outcomes among patients with drug-resistant tuberculosis receiving bedaquiline- or delamanid-containing regimens. Clin Infect Dis. 2020;71(9):2336&#8211;44.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31712809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/cid/ciz1107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7713674</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Putra</surname><given-names>ON</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yulistiani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soedarsono</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Subay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Favorable outcome of individual regimens containing bedaquiline and delamanid in drug-resistant tuberculosis: a systematic review</article-title><source>Int J Mycobacteriol</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijmy.ijmy_217_22</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36926755</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Putra ON, Yulistiani Y, Soedarsono S, Subay S. Favorable outcome of individual regimens containing bedaquiline and delamanid in drug-resistant tuberculosis: a systematic review. Int J Mycobacteriol. 2023;12(1):1&#8211;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36926755</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/ijmy.ijmy_217_22</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabur</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brode</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low-dose amikacin in the treatment of Multidrug-resistant tuberculosis (MDR-TB)</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>254</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-021-05947-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33691624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7945371</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Sabur NF, Brar MS, Wu L, Brode SK. Low-dose amikacin in the treatment of Multidrug-resistant tuberculosis (MDR-TB). BMC Infect Dis. 2021;21(1):254.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33691624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12879-021-05947-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7945371</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>WHO consolidated guidelines on tuberculosis</collab></person-group><source>Module 4: treatment - drug-resistant tuberculosis treatment, 2022 update</source><year>2022</year><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36630546</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="book">WHO consolidated guidelines on tuberculosis. Module 4: treatment - drug-resistant tuberculosis treatment, 2022 update. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2022. Licence: CC BY-NC-SA 3.0 IGO.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36630546</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>