<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Trauma Surg Acute Care Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Trauma Surg Acute Care Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3432</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">tsaco</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">tsaco</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Trauma Surgery &amp; Acute Care Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2397-5776</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11253739</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11253739.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11253739</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11253739</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39021730</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/tsaco-2024-001364</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">tsaco-2024-001364</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1506</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Opioid and non-opioid analgesic regimens after fracture and risk of serious opioid-related events</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names initials="K">Kyle</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><email>kyle.hart@lmunet.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1918-1329</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Medvecz</surname><given-names initials="AJ">Andrew J</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><email>andrew.j.medvecz@vumc.org</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaidya</surname><given-names initials="A">Avi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><email>avi.u.vaidya@vumc.org</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dusetzina</surname><given-names initials="S">Stacie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><email>s.dusetzina@Vanderbilt.Edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leech</surname><given-names initials="AA">Ashley A</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><email>ashley.leech@Vanderbilt.Edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0699-4224</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiese</surname><given-names initials="AD">Andrew D</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><email>andrew.d.wiese.1@vumc.org</email></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Health Policy</institution>, <institution>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Nashville</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Tennessee</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Surgery</institution>, <institution>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Nashville</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Tennessee</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>Supplemental material This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise.</p></fn><fn id="fn1"><p>Additional supplemental material is published online only. To view, please visit the journal online (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1136/tsaco-2024-001364" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1136/tsaco-2024-001364</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn5"><p>None declared.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1">DrAndrew JMedvecz; <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="andrew.j.medvecz@vumc.org">andrew.j.medvecz@vumc.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">454016</issue-id><elocation-id>e001364</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>14</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>17</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-08-24 00:25:30.370"><day>24</day><month>08</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2024. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See:&#160;<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="tsaco-9-1.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="tsaco-9-1.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="companion" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="article-commentary" journal-id="Trauma Surg Acute Care Open" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11331901"><article-title>Navigating pain management in orthopedic trauma: the unintended consequences of combined analgesic regimens</article-title><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><date><day>9</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date><elocation-id>e001537</elocation-id><source>Trauma Surgery &amp; Acute Care Open</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/tsaco-2024-001537</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11331901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39161371</pub-id></related-article><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec><title>Background</title><p>Non-opioid analgesics are prescribed in combination with opioids among patients with long bone fracture to reduce opioid prescribing needs, yet evidence is limited on whether they reduce the risk of serious opioid-related events (SOREs). We compared the risk of SOREs among hospitalized patients with long bone fracture discharged with filled opioid prescriptions, with and without non-opioid analgesics.</p></sec><sec><title>Design</title><p>We identified a retrospective cohort of analgesic-na&#239;ve adult patients with a long bone fracture hospitalization using the Merative MarketScan Commercial Database (2013&#8211;2020). The exposure was opioid and non-opioid analgesic (gabapentinoids, muscle relaxants, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, acetaminophen) prescriptions filled in the 3 days before through 42 days after discharge. The outcome was the development of new persistent opioid use or opioid use disorder during follow-up (day 43 through day 408 after discharge). We used Cox proportional hazards regression with inverse probability of treatment weighting with overlap trimming to compare outcomes among those that filled an opioid and a non-opioid analgesic to those that filled only an opioid analgesic. In secondary analyses, we used separate models to compare those that filled a prescription for each specific non-opioid analgesic type with opioids to those that filled only opioids.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Of 29 489 patients, most filled an opioid prescription alone (58.4%) or an opioid and non-opioid (22.0%). In the weighted proportional hazards regression model accounting for relevant covariates and total MME, filling both a non-opioid analgesic and an opioid analgesic was associated with 1.63 times increased risk of SOREs compared with filling an opioid analgesic only (95% CI 1.41 to 1.89). Filling a gabapentin prescription in combination with an opioid was associated with an increased risk of SOREs compared with those that filled an opioid only (adjusted HR: 1.84 (95% CI1.48 to 2.27)).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Filling a non-opioid analgesic in combination with an opioid was associated with an increased risk of SOREs after long bone fracture.</p></sec><sec><title>Level of evidence</title><p>Level III, prognostic/epidemiological.</p></sec><sec><title>Study type</title><p>Retrospective cohort study.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Analgesics, Opioid</kwd><kwd>Substance-Related Disorders</kwd><kwd>Fractures, Bone</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000026</institution-id><institution>National Institute on Drug Abuse</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>K01DA050740</award-id><award-id>K01DA051683</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><sec><title>WHAT IS ALREADY KNOWN ON THIS TOPIC</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>Though non-opioid analgesics are increasingly prescribed after traumatic injuries to reduce overall opioid prescribing needs, there is growing evidence that the concomitant prescribing of non-opioid analgesics in combination with opioids is associated with an increased risk of persistent opioid use and opioid use disorder.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title>WHAT THIS STUDY ADDS</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>In this retrospective cohort study, compared with those filling an opioid analgesic prescription only, those that filled a non-opioid analgesic prescription had an elevated risk of developing persistent opioid use or an opioid use disorder after adjusting for all relevant covariates, include total MME dose. The elevated risk was highest for those filling a gabapentin prescription in combination with opioids.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title>HOW THIS STUDY MIGHT AFFECT RESEARCH, PRACTICE OR POLICY</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>Clinical guidelines regarding postsurgery analgesia should indicate that caution may be warranted when prescribing multimodal or high-dose opioid medications as they may increase the risk of serious opioid-related harms.</p></list-item></list></sec></boxed-text><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p> The quadrupling of opioid prescriptions since 1999 has coincided with the increase in opioid-related harms globally, including over 100 000 overdose deaths in the USA.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Opioid prescribing after surgical procedures and traumatic injuries, especially at high doses, has been associated with increased risk of subsequent opioid-related harms, including development of persistent opioid use and opioid use disorder (OUD) as well as opioid-related overdoses and deaths.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Though intraoperative (eg, spinal and regional anesthesia) and postoperative pain management (eg, ketorolac administration) strategies during hospitalization have shown potential benefits at reducing subsequent opioid-related harms, beneficial outpatient pain management strategies remain less well understood.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8 9</sup></xref></p><p>Long bone fracture is a common and costly traumatic injury requiring hospitalization in the USA.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Patients hospitalized for long bone fracture often require opioid use for appropriate pain management, which could potentially lead to a higher risk for experiencing serious opioid-related harms compared with non-trauma patients.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Risk factors for opioid-related harms after traumatic injury include male sex, preoperative opioid use, payer type, American Society of Anesthesiologists score and injury severity score.<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> The use of multimodal analgesia (ie, opioid and non-opioid analgesics) is one potential strategy to reduce risk through the reduction in postdischarge opioid requirements or by lowering perceived pain in certain surgical populations.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">220</xref><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> However, it remains unclear whether the use of non-opioid analgesics, alone or in combination with opioids, protects against the development of serious opioid-related events (SORE) after traumatic injury.</p><p>We sought to compare the risk of developing SOREs (including persistent opioid use, coded diagnosis or treatment for OUD, or opioid-related hospitalization) among previously analgesic na&#239;ve patients hospitalized for long bone fracture that filled opioid analgesics in combination with at least one non-opioid analgesic prescription (muscle relaxants, gabapentin, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), acetaminophen) at discharge compared with patients who filled only an opioid analgesic prescription.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Data sources and study cohort</title><p>We identified opioid na&#239;ve patients aged 18&#8211;65 years hospitalized for long bone fracture in the USA from July 1, 2013, through December 31, 2019, using the Merativ MarketScan Commercial Database. We focused solely on long bone fracture to limit confounding due to different pain management guidelines and potential differences in the underlying risks for SOREs for different injury types. The Merative MarketScan Commercial Database encompasses deidentified enrollment data, inpatient and outpatient claims and outpatient filled prescription drug claims for a population of more than 215 million individuals with employer-sponsored private insurance health plans, including employees, covered spouses and dependents. The study was approved by the authors&#8217; institutional review board.</p><p>We identified patients hospitalized with evidence of a long bone fracture based on a primary or secondary diagnosis claim of humerus (ICD9: 812.00&#8211;812.59; ICD10: S42.201-S42.929), femur (ICD9: 820.00&#8211;821.39; ICD10: S72.001-S72.929) or tibia fracture (ICD9: 823.00&#8211;824.99; ICD10: S82.101-S82.929). Patients entered the cohort on day 43 after discharge (t<sub>0</sub>) if they were continuously enrolled (no gaps &gt;30 days) in the health plan at least 6 months before through 42 days after discharge (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>). We excluded patients with evidence of OUD (coded diagnosis, opioid-related hospitalization or use of medication-assisted therapy (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental appendix table 1</xref>)) during baseline. To focus on patients who were analgesic-na&#239;ve prior to hospitalization, we excluded patients with evidence of outpatient prescriptions for opioids, gabapentinoids, muscle relaxants, NSAIDs and acetaminophen in the 6 months prior to admission through 3 days prior to discharge. We also excluded patients with severe injuries hospitalized for longer than 14 days. Hospitalizations with a one calendar day gap or less between discharge and subsequent readmission were considered the same hospitalization. We also did not include any hospitalizations for the same individual that occurred during the follow-up period (eg, additional injuries, removal of hardware, revision) to remove overlapping follow-up periods for the same individual and to reduce correlated observations within the same individual. For the primary analysis, we restricted the study population to only those individuals who received at least one discharge opioid prescription in the 3 days before through 42 days after discharge from the fracture hospitalization to remove potential bias from including those that did not fill any analgesic in the exposure period.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Study design overview. SORE, serious opioid-related event.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="tsaco-9-1-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>Patient follow-up continued from day 43 after discharge through the earliest of the following: day 408 after discharge (365 days after day 42 after discharge), loss of enrollment, death, or evidence of a SORE (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Exposure</title><p>We identified use of opioids and non-opioid analgesics using National Drug Classification codes for filled prescriptions 3 days before through 42 days after discharge. The Merative Marketscan Commerical Database does not include information on inpatient analgesic administration and dosing and so was not assessed. Opioid-combination drugs, (eg, hydrocodone-acetaminophen, oxycodone-acetaminophen) were classified as opioid prescriptions only. Non-opioid analgesics included single-entity prescriptions for muscle relaxants, gabapentin, NSAIDs and acetaminophen. We excluded combined-entity prescriptions for NSAIDs and acetaminophen intended to manage symptoms of cold, influenza or allergies (eg, acetaminophen-dextromethorphan, acetaminophen phenylephrine, ibuprofen-pseudoephedrine). We further calculated the total dose of all opioids filled in this period as the total morphine milligram equivalents (MME) filled (MME=strength per tablet &#215; quantity &#215; MME conversion factor) to be accounted for as a covariate in the model (see below). In the primary analysis among individuals filling an opioid prescription, the exposure of interest was the filling of any non-opioid analgesic prescription compared with the opioid only group as reference. Secondary analyses focused specifically on individual non-opioid analgesic prescriptions (eg, gabapentin, muscle relaxants, NSAIDs, acetaminophen) compared with the opioid only group as reference.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Serious opioid-related events</title><p>The primary SORE outcome was a composite measure identified on the earliest date either of the following was detected: (1) persistent opioid use, defined as the earliest date a patient fills a greater than 90-day supply of opioids within a 180-day window,<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> (2) evidence of OUD based on coded diagnoses for OUD, (3) opioid-related hospitalization or (4) use of medication-assisted therapy (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental appendix table 1</xref>). Importantly, only opioid prescriptions filled on or after t<sub>0</sub> (day 43 after discharge) were included in the determination of persistent opioid use during follow-up.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Covariates</title><p>We identified covariates <italic toggle="yes">a priori</italic> as potential confounders in the association between postdischarge analgesic use and SOREs. We identified patient demographics from the trauma hospitalization, including study year, age at admission, health plan type (employer, health plan), sex (male, female), employee classification (union/non-union/other), employee status (full-time, part-time, retiree, COBRA/long-term disability, other) and US geographic region of residence. We further identified characteristics of the trauma hospitalization, including length of stay, surgery during the hospitalization, fracture type (primary fracture, secondary fracture, more than one fracture type), evidence of multiple traumas as identified by the diagnosis-related group, and the number of readmissions from discharge through day 42 after discharge. Furthermore, we identified comorbidities among patients in the baseline period using coded diagnoses, including back pain, headache, musculoskeletal pain, psychogenic pain, neuropathic pain, sickle cell/hemolytic anemia, arthritis pain, depression, frailty and malignancy. We further calculated each patient&#8217;s Elixhauser comorbidity index using inpatient hospitalization data in the baseline period, excluding conditions measured separately (eg, depression).</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>For descriptive analyses of demographics and baseline covariates, we categorized opioid-exposure groups based on the median MME among opioid users (eg, no opioid, opioid only with total MME&#8804;675, opioid only with total MME&gt;675, both non-opioid and opioid with total MME&#8804;675, non-opioid and opioid-with total MME&gt;675). For the primary analysis, we used Cox proportional hazard regression with inverse probability of treatment weighting (IPTW) with overlap trimming to compare outcomes among those that filled an opioid and a non-opioid analgesic to those that filled only an opioid analgesic. Those that did not fill a discharge opioid were not included in the primary analysis. The probability of filling a non-opioid was calculated using a logistic regression model including all relevant covariates, including total opioid dose (using restricted cubic splines).<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> We then calculated an adjusted HR (aHR) with 95% CIs using robust SEs comparing opioid and non-opioid users to opioid only users. In preplanned secondary analyses, we used separate Cox proportional hazard regression models with separate IPTW to compare those that filled each non-opioid analgesic type (gabapentin, muscle relaxants, NSAIDs, acetaminophen) with opioids to those that filled opioids without that specific non-opioid type. The use of the other non-opioid analgesics was subsequently included in IPTW model as a covariate for each secondary analysis. We also conducted a post hoc comparison among those that filled an opioid and one of the two most common muscle relaxant prescriptions (cyclobenzaprine, methocarbamol). Statistical analyses were completed using SAS Enterprise Guide, V.8.2.9.4 (SAS Institute, Cary, North Carolina) and Stata statistical software (release V.17.0; Stata-Corp LLC, College Station, Texas).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>We identified 29 489 patients aged 18&#8211;65 years with evidence of a long bone fracture that met all inclusion and exclusion criteria (2013&#8211;2020) (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2</xref>). Of these patients, 76.1% were identified with a primary diagnosis for at least one long bone fracture type while 23.9% were identified with a secondary diagnosis (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Population flow diagram.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="tsaco-9-1-g002.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Baseline and follow-up characteristics of adult patients discharged to home after hospitalization for long bone fracture, stratified by discharge pain regimen type, Merative MarketScan Commercial Database (2013&#8211;2020), n=29 489</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="bottom" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No analgesic</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-opioid only</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Opioid only&#8212;low dose</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Opioid only&#8212;high dose</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Opioid and non-opioid&#8212;low opioid dose</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Opioid and non-opioid&#8212;high opioid dose</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=5358</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=427</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=8882</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=8347</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=2617</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=3858</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Sex, female</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2820 (53%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208 (49%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4578 (52%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3885 (47%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1157 (44%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1566 (41%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Health plan type</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Employer</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3764 (70%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">348 (81%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6939 (78%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5990 (72%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2006 (77%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2917 (76%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Health plan</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1594 (30%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (19%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1943 (22%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2357 (28%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">611 (23%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">941 (24%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Employee type</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Union</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2034 (38%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174 (41%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3975 (45%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3307 (40%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1137 (43%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1626 (42%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Non-union</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">879 (16%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (19%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1388 (16%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1260 (15%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">379 (14%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">609 (16%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Other/unknown</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2445 (46%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">172 (40%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3519 (40%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3780 (45%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1101 (42%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1623 (42%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Employee status</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Active</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2671 (50%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">283 (66%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5359 (60%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4827 (58%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1773 (68%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2478 (64%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Retiree</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">962 (18%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (12%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1389 (16%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1018 (12%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">244 (9%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">321 (8%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;COBRA/LTD</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205 (4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (5%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">311 (4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">278 (3%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88 (3%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160 (4%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Other/unknown</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1520 (28%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (17%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1823 (21%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2224 (27%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">512 (20%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">899 (23%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitalization characteristics</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Surgery during hospitalization</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2139 (40%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165 (39%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4713 (53%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4742 (57%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1251 (48%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1983 (51%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Type of fracture</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Primary fracture&#8212;one type</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3534 (66%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247 (58%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6835 (77%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6425 (77%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1809 (69%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2642 (68%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Secondary fracture&#8212;one type</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">967 (18%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (20%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1060 (12%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1002 (12%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">406 (16%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">642 (17%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Primary fracture -&gt;one type</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176 (3%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (6%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198 (2%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241 (3%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">119 (5%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195 (5%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Secondary fracture -&gt;one type</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">681 (13%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (16%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">789 (9%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">679 (8%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">283 (11%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">379 (10%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discharge prescribing characteristics</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Muscle relaxants</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170 (40%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1340 (51%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2297 (60%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Gabapentin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">159 (37%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">900 (34%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1483 (38%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;NSAIDs</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178 (42%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">966 (37%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1012 (26%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Acetaminophen</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (74%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Opioid type</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Any hydrocodone</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3467 (39%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3817 (46%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">822 (31%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1607 (42%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Any oxycodone</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5073 (57%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5804 (70%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1659 (63%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2913 (76%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Any other opioid</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1064 (12%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2339 (28%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">473 (18%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1462 (38%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline comorbidities<xref rid="T1_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">&#8224;</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Back pain</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">742 (14%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (16%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000 (11%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">992 (12%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">412 (16%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">664 (17%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Dental pain</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (1%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (0%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Headache</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241 (4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">329 (4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">333 (4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140 (5%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">193 (5%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Musculoskeletal pain</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3906 (73%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">313 (73%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5895 (66%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5556 (67%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1892 (72%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2829 (73%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Psychogenic pain</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1499 (28%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134 (31%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2397 (27%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2351 (28%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">870 (33%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1405 (36%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Neuropathic pain</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">601 (11%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (11%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">607 (7%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">565 (7%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">272 (10%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">434 (11%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Sickle cell/hemolytic anemia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (0%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Arthritis pain</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212 (4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (2%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">167 (2%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138 (2%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (1%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (1%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Depression</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">654 (12%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (13%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">796 (9%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">772 (9%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">235 (9%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">362 (9%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Frailty</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1730 (32%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (22%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1651 (19%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1984 (24%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">438 (17%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">856 (22%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Malignancy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">381 (7%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (7%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">397 (4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">342 (4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122 (5%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">164 (4%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Multiple trauma-related diagnosis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">462 (9%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (15%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">484 (5%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">592 (7%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">355 (14%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">578 (15%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Year of admission</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;2013</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">519 (10%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">663 (7%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">940 (11%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115 (4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266 (7%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;2014</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1130 (21%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (9%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1793 (20%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2108 (25%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266 (10%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">710 (18%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;2015</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">814 (15%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (9%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1345 (15%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1728 (21%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">231 (9%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">652 (17%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;2016</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">780 (15%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (12%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1287 (14%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1493 (18%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">310 (12%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">735 (19%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;2017</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">684 (13%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (15%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1265 (14%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1083 (13%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">400 (15%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">670 (17%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;2018</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">744 (14%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 (26%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1315 (15%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">621 (7%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">590 (23%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">505 (13%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">687 (13%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103 (24%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1214 (14%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">374 (4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">705 (27%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">320 (8%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Region</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Northeast</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1237 (23%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (18%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1905 (21%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1161 (14%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">406 (16%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">412 (11%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;North Central</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1107 (21%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (18%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1879 (21%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1920 (23%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500 (19%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">785 (20%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;South</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1780 (33%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">153 (36%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3038 (34%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2975 (36%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1048 (40%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1686 (44%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;West</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">827 (15%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (18%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1345 (15%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1433 (17%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">368 (14%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">611 (16%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Other</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">407 (8%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (10%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">715 (8%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">858 (10%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">295 (11%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">364 (9%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean (SD)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean (SD)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean (SD)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean (SD)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean (SD)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean (SD)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD) for continuous variables</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Age at admission (years)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.3 (14.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.1 (14.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.8 (15.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.9 (14.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.7 (15.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7 (14.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Length of initial hospital stay, days</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5 (3.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8 (3.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2 (2.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 (2.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 (2.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5 (3.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Total MME in 42 days after discharge</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">382.4 (170.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3965.9 (43083.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">385.9 (172.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4098.4 (35363.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;MME per day in 42 days after discharge</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.2 (28.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">240.2 (2288.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.9 (26.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180.3 (1738.6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Elixhauser comorbidity score</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (1.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 (0.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (0.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (0.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (0.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (0.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Hospitalizations between discharge and cohort entry</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Hospitalization days between discharge and cohort entry</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Follow-up, days</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">277.4 (123.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286.7 (121.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">297.3 (113.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">291.1 (116.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">294.1 (114.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">273.3 (125.5)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T1_FN1" fn-type="other"><label>*</label><p>Patients could only enter cohort starting 1 July 1, 2013.</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN2" fn-type="other"><label>&#8224;</label><p>Baseline comorbidities measured over entirety of baseline period (day 180 before admission through day 42 after discharge).</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN3" fn-type="other"><label>&#8225;</label><p>Elixhauser comorbidity score<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> only calculated from inpatient hospitalization encounters during the baseline period.</p></fn><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>COBRAConsolidated Omnibus Budget Reconciliation ActLTDlong-term disabilityMMEmorphine milligram equivalentNSAIDsnon-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The most common discharge pain regimen was opioids only with total MME &#8804;675 (30.1%), followed by opioid only with total MME &gt;675 (28.3%), no analgesic (18.2%), both opioid and non-opioid analgesics with MME &gt;675 (13.1%) and MME &#8804;675 (8.9%) and non-opioids only (1.5%). Muscle relaxants were the most prescribed non-opioid analgesic (12.9%), followed by gabapentin (8.6%), NSAIDs (7.3%) and acetaminophen (0.1%), while 5.0% filled a prescription for more than one non-opioid analgesic.</p><p>The crude rate for SOREs was highest in those filling a non-opioid analgesic in combination with an opioid analgesic with a total dose &gt;675 MME (13.37 per 100 person-years) and lowest in those filling an opioid only with a total dose &#8804;675 MME (0.93 per 100 person-years) (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>). Among the 1039 patients with SOREs during the period, the earliest SORE was persistent opioid use for 849 patients and evidence of OUD for 190 patients (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>). In the unadjusted Cox proportional hazard model, filling a non-opioid analgesic with an opioid was associated with a 2.58 times increased risk of SORE compared with filling an opioid only (95% CI 2.26 to 2.95). In the weighted proportional hazard regression model accounting for all relevant covariates and total MME (with standardized differences &lt;0.024 for all covariates (<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental appendix table 2</xref>)), filling a non-opioid analgesic with an opioid analgesic was associated with 1.63 times increased risk of SORE compared with filling an opioid analgesic only (95% CI 1.41 to 1.89).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Serious opioid-related events (SORE)1 associated with opioid and non-opioid pain regimens filled after discharge from trauma hospitalization, Merative MarketScan (2013&#8211;2020)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Pain regimen</td><td rowspan="2" valign="bottom" colspan="1">N</td><td rowspan="2" valign="bottom" colspan="1">SORE</td><td rowspan="2" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Follow-up, years</td><td rowspan="2" valign="bottom" colspan="1">SORE/100 py</td><td rowspan="2" valign="bottom" colspan="1">95%&#8201;CI</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent use<xref rid="T2_FN1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOUD/OUD diagnosis</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Loss of enrollment</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No opioid or non-opioid</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5358</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4069</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.78</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.23 to 4.43</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112 (2.09)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (0.78)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5204 (97.13)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-opioid only</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">427</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">335</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 to 3.98</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (1.17)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.23)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">421 (98.59)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Opioid only</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Total dose&#8804;650 MME</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8882</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7229</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 to 1.18</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (0.54)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (0.21)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8815 (99.25)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Total dose&gt;650 MME</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8347</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">385</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6652</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.79</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.24 to 6.4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">330 (3.95)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (0.66)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7962 (95.39)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Opioid and non-opioid</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Total dose&#8804;650 MME</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2617</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2107</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43 to 2.64</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (1.07)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (0.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2576 (98.43)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Total dose&gt;650 MME</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3858</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">386</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2887</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.37</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1 to 14.77</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">326 (8.45)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (1.56)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3472 (89.99)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T2_FN1" fn-type="other"><label>*</label><p>Persistent opioid use (&gt;90 days&#8217; supply in 180-day window), opioid use disorder diagnosis or buprenorphine/methadone prescription fill or evidence of opioid overdose diagnosis.</p></fn><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>MOUDmedication for opioid use disorderOUDopioid use disorderPYperson-years</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In drug-specific comparisons among only individuals that filled an opioid analgesic, filling a gabapentin prescription was associated with a higher risk compared with those that did not in the unadjusted (HR: 3.25 (95% CI 2.80 to 3.79) and adjusted models (aHR: 1.84 (95% CI 1.48 to 2.27)). We observed similar findings for filling a muscle relaxant (crude HR: 2.42 (95% CI 2.09 to 2.80) and aHR: 1.37 (95% CI 1.15 to 1.62)) or NSAID prescription (crude HR: 2.41 (95% CI 2.09 to 2.79) and aHR: 1.36 (95% CI 1.08 to 1.71)) compared with those that did not. In the post hoc comparison by muscle relaxant type, we did not observe a significant difference among those that filled an opioid with cyclobenzaprine versus an opioid with methocarbamol (aHR: 0.92; 95% CI 0.68 to 1.24). The low number of individuals (n=28) that filled a non-combination acetaminophen prescription precluded a secondary analysis in this subgroup. The log&#8211;log survival plots indicated no major deviations from parallel for each exposure group.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="s4-1"><title>Summary of findings</title><p>We observed a significantly elevated risk of SOREs associated with filling a non-opioid analgesic in combination with an opioid analgesic compared with those that filled an opioid analgesic only, even after accounting total opioid dose (and other relevant covariates). Importantly, the highest risk was associated with the concomitant filling of gabapentin and opioid prescriptions, though significantly elevated risks were associated with the filling of muscle relaxant and NSAID prescriptions as well.</p><p>Prior literature has demonstrated that opioid prescribing after surgical procedures is associated with SOREs. For example, several studies have demonstrated that patients filling prescriptions for higher initial opioid doses after cesarean delivery have a higher risk of SOREs compared with patients who filled prescriptions for opioids at low doses or who did not fill an opioid prescription at all.<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25 27 30</sup></xref> In a meta-analysis by Lawal <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> including 33 different studies, the authors reported that approximately 1 in 10 patients with a surgical procedure subsequently develop prolonged opioid use.<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> Specific to patients with traumatic injury, Alghnam and Castillo showed that patients with traumatic injuries are approximately 1.4 times more likely to become persistent opioid users compared with those without a traumatic injury.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref></p><p>Due to the recognized risk of SOREs among patients using high-dose opioids after surgery or traumatic injury, increased prescribing of non-opioid analgesic medications has been observed and recommended as an option to reduce overall opioid prescribing in these populations.<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">2131</xref><xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> These recommendations were based on prior work that has demonstrated equivocal perceived pain intensity and decreased opioid use among patients receiving multimodal analgesia. For example, Hamrick <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> demonstrated that the total prescribed opioid dose among adult trauma ICU patients was reduced with the implementation of a multimodal order set without any change to overall pain scores before and after multimodal treatment.<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> Additionally, Elia <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> performed a meta-analysis that showed that multimodal treatment reduced the use of morphine and the intensity of pain in a surgery population.<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> Cramer <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> evaluated the use of opioids in combination with non-opioids and showed that the use of multimodal analgesia was more effective in postoperative pain control than that of an opioid regimen.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Additionally, the conclusions from the meta-analysis by Lawal <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> were that patients at risk for prolonged opioid use should transition to non-opioid interventions.<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref></p><p>Though these updated recommendations have led to decreased opioid prescribing and increased non-opioid prescribing in the USA, there is a growing concern that the concomitant use of opioid and non-opioid analgesics, though intended to reduce prescribed opioids, could potentially increase the risk of SOREs after surgery or traumatic injury. In a population-based case&#8211;control study among opioid users in Canada (1997&#8211;2013), the coprescribing of gabapentin and opioids was associated with a nearly twofold increased odds of opioid-related death compared with the prescribing of opioids alone.<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> Similarly, in a nested case&#8211;control study among Medicare beneficiaries (2013&#8211;2016), at least one overlapping day of gabapentin and opioid use was associated with an increased odds of opioid-related overdose (aOR:1.74; 95% CI 1.25 to 2.41) compared with those with opioid use alone.<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> Additionally, a recent examination of 62 652 overdose deaths reported to the State Unintentional Drug Overdose Reporting System, which found a near doubling in the absolute number of drug overdose deaths for which gabapentin was detected in 2020 compared with 2019.<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39 40</sup></xref> Thus, our study contributes to the growing concerns around concomitant opioid and gabapentin use, as we found that the coprescribing of opioids with non-opioids (including gabapentin) after long bone fracture hospitalization was not associated with a lower risk of SOREs, but rather a potentially elevated risk for developing persistent opioid use, OUD and opioid-related overdose. Importantly, this association was observed even after accounting for the total opioid dose in the 42-day baseline postdischarge period.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Strengths/limitations</title><p>The findings from our retrospective study should be considered in the context of several strengths and limitations. We used the Merative MarketScan Commercial Database to have sufficient power to detect significant differences in the risk of SOREs among patients with different discharge analgesic regimens. However, this likely reduces the generalizability of our findings to the entire population of patients with traumatic injury in the USA. Furthermore, we are unable to detect potentially fatal opioid-related overdose events, nor do we have inpatient hospitalization data to account for the severity of the injury. However, we attempt to account for the severity of injury by restricting to patients with a length of stay &lt;14 days, identifying any evidence of surgical procedures during the hospitalization, and controlling for total opioid dose prescribed in the discharge period. Additionally, we required continuous enrollment during baseline and follow-up to allow for complete ascertainment of covariates, exposure groups and outcomes but recognize the potential for bias due to differential loss to follow-up in our study population despite the use of Cox proportional hazards regression.</p><p>We implemented a definition for persistent opioid use that has been used in prior work to study serious opioid-related harms in other populations but recognize our study findings may differ with the use of a different definition of persistent opioid use. Importantly, the algorithm used to identify medication for OUD treatment as evidence of OUD diagnosis did not distinguish between buprenorphine and methadone administered for pain and OUD treatment. Although we adjusted for many <italic toggle="yes">a priori</italic> confounders, we cannot rule out potential misclassification of certain key covariates in the study population due to the use of a 6-month baseline period and the inability to consider information not captured in the claims record. As this study is retrospective, despite our attempt to account for a long list of possible confounders using IPTW, we cannot rule out the possibility of unmeasured confounding.</p><p>Finally, though pharmacy fill data have reliably been used to identify opioid use in prior retrospective cohort studies, we recognize we were unable to measure actual analgesic use in our study, including drugs paid for out of pocket and the misuse of illicit opioids. Beaulieu-Bonneau <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> identified significant alcohol and recreational drug use at 8 and 12 months following admission for TBI, many of whom also met criteria for substance use disorder.<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref> To address this concern, we excluded all individuals with prior opioid use or evidence of OUD at baseline, whereas the development of OUD in the year after admission was a component of composite outcome. However, it is possible that we underestimated non-prescribed or illicit opioid use during the baseline period. Similarly, we were unable to account for differences in the use of other over the counter analgesics (eg, acetaminophen, NSAIDs). Importantly, many prescription drug plans do not cover acetaminophen, leading many patients to purchase acetaminophen over the counter, a practice that may explain why so few individuals had evidence of a filled single-entity acetaminophen prescription during the exposure period. Furthermore, as it is difficult to separate the therapeutic benefit of acetaminophen and opioids in combination, and since our exposure of interest was filling a standalone non-opioid prescription in addition to an opioid-analgesic prescription (single-entity or combination), we classified combination opioid-acetaminophen drugs as opioids only in our analysis. An additional limitation is that Merative MarketScan Commercial Database does not include information on inpatient analgesic administration and dosing and so we were unable to account for inpatient analgesic use in the analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Compared with those that filled only an opioid analgesic prescription after a long bone fracture hospitalization, patients who filled both opioid and non-opioid analgesics in the discharge period were at an increased risk of developing a SORE. Thus, the concomitant prescribing of non-opioid analgesics with opioids did not lower the risk of subsequent SOREs.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="SP1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/tsaco-2024-001364</object-id><label>online supplemental file 1</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="tsaco-9-1-s001.docx" id="d67e1601" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This work was supported by the National Institute on Drug Abuse (grant number: K01DA051683; grant number: K01DA050740).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; internally peer-reviewed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient consent for publication:</bold> Not applicable.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Data availability free text:</bold> Data were obtained from a third party (Merative Marketscan) are not publicly available.</p></fn><fn fn-type="presented-at"><p><bold>Presented at:</bold> Partial findings from this manuscript were presented in August 2023 at the International Conference on Pharmacoepidemiology (ICPE) in Halifax, Canada.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethics approval:</bold> The Vanderbilt University Institutional Review Board reviewed and approved the study protocol (VU IRB: 181007) with a waiver of informed consent as study data were retrospective and deidentified.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenfeld</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tunkel</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multimodal analgesia as first-line therapy after otolaryngology operations: primer on nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs)</article-title><source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source><year>2021</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>712</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599820947013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32806991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jivraj</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raghavji</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bethell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wijeysundera</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ladha</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wunsch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Persistent postoperative opioid use: a systematic literature search of definitions and population-based cohort study</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Anesthesiology</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>1528</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ALN.0000000000003265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32243330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8202398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanz</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinwiddie</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Donnell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug overdose deaths among persons aged 10-19 years - United States, July 2019-December 2021</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>1576</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7150a2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36520659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9762908</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brummett</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waljee</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goesling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Englesbe</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohnert</surname><given-names>ASB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kheterpal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nallamothu</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New persistent opioid use after minor and major surgical procedures in US adults</article-title><source>JAMA Surg</source><year>2017</year><volume>152</volume><elocation-id>e170504</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2017.0504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28403427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7050825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skojec</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanak</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacomis</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruminski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Persistent post-discharge opioid prescribing after traumatic brain injury requiring intensive care unit admission: a cross-sectional study with longitudinal outcome</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>e0225787</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0225787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31774864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6880998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peahl</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>Y-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waljee</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rates of new persistent opioid use after vaginal or cesarean birth among US women</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2019</year><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>e197863</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.7863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31348508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6661716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darnall</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mackey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidence of and risk factors for chronic opioid use among opioid-naive patients in the postoperative period</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Intern Med</italic></source><year>2016</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>1286</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2016.3298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27400458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6684468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Badin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortiz-Babilonia</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leland</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Musharbash</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parrish</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aiyer</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prescription patterns, associated factors, and outcomes of opioids for operative foot and ankle fractures: a systematic review</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Orthop Relat Res</italic></source><year>2022</year><volume>480</volume><fpage>2187</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CORR.0000000000002307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35901447</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10476710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwok</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Hara</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pollak</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Hara</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slobogean</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are injured workers with higher rehabilitation service utilization less likely to be persistent opioid users? A cross-sectional study</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Health Serv Res</italic></source><year>2019</year><volume>19</volume><elocation-id>32</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12913-019-3879-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30642319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6332665</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hornik</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thode</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analgesic use in ED patients with long-bone fractures: a national assessment of racial and ethnic disparities</article-title><source>Am J Emerg Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajem.2023.03.054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37027957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alghnam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castillo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traumatic injuries and persistent opioid use in the USA: findings from a nationally representative survey</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Inj Prev</italic></source><year>2017</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/injuryprev-2016-042059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27597400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gossett</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finney</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waljee</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brummett</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New persistent opioid use and associated risk factors following treatment of ankle fractures</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Foot Ankle Int</italic></source><year>2019</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1043</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1071100719851117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31132877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anoushiravani</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roof</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Connor</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vigdorchik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarzkopf</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors associated with persistent chronic opioid use following THA</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Orthop Surg Traumatol</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>681</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00590-019-02618-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31897709</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mackelprang</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abshire</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivara</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vavilala</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rural-urban disparities in health care costs and health service utilization following pediatric mild traumatic brain injury</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Health Serv Res</italic></source><year>2019</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1475-6773.13096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30507042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6407359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inacio</surname><given-names>MCS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roughead</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for persistent and new chronic opioid use in patients undergoing total hip arthroplasty: a retrospective cohort study</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ Open</italic></source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e010664</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010664</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4853994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27130165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawal</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruchi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bavry</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hume</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewkowitz</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brothers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rate and risk factors associated with prolonged opioid use after surgery: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Netw Open</italic></source><year>2020</year><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e207367</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.7367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32584407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7317603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Genel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patanwala</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassett</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luckie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Penm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naylor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of pharmacological-based interventions, including education and prescribing strategies, to reduce subacute pain after total hip or knee arthroplasty: a systematic review of randomized controlled trials</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Pain Med</italic></source><year>2022</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1476</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pm/pnac052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35325201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9434276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seal</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertenthal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Byers</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rife</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yaffe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><collab>Chronic Effects of Neurotrauma Consortium Study Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Traumatic brain injury and receipt of prescription opioid therapy for chronic pain in Iraq and Afghanistan veterans: do clinical practice guidelines matter</article-title><source>J Pain</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>931</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpain.2018.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29597083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>von Oelreich</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brattstr&#246;m</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sj&#246;lund</surname><given-names>K-F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Discacciati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oldner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors and outcomes of chronic opioid use following trauma</article-title><source>Br J Surg</source><year>2020</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bjs.11507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32031251</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lysakowski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tram&#232;r</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does Multimodal analgesia with acetaminophen, nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs, or selective cyclooxygenase-2 inhibitors and patient-controlled analgesia morphine offer advantages over morphine alone? Meta-analyses of randomized trials</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Anesthesiology</italic></source><year>2005</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>1296</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000542-200512000-00025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16306743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamrick</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beyer</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cocanour</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duby</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multimodal analgesia and opioid use in critically ill trauma patients</article-title><source>J Am Coll Surg</source><year>2019</year><volume>228</volume><fpage>769</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2019.01.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30797081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Polomano</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fillman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vallerand</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicely</surname><given-names>KLW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jungquist</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multimodal analgesia for acute postoperative and trauma-related pain</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Nurs</italic></source><year>2017</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>S12</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.NAJ.0000513527.71934.73</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28212146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gedda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nygren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garpenbeck</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffstr&#246;m</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soop</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multimodal analgesia bundle and postoperative opioid use among patients undergoing colorectal surgery</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Netw Open</italic></source><year>2023</year><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e2332408</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.32408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37672272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10483316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasotakis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haut</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenboehler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoegler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantrell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Efficacy and safety of non-Steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) for the treatment of acute pain after orthopedic trauma: a practice management guideline from the Eastern Association for the Surgery of Trauma and the Orthopedic Trauma Association</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Trauma Surg Acute Care Open</italic></source><year>2023</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e001056</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/tsaco-2022-001056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36844371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9945020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Osmundson</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Min</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiese</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawley</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samuels</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grijalva</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Opioid prescribing after childbirth and risk for serious opioid-related events: a cohort study</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>412</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M19-3805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32510992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8081555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiese</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osmundson</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adgent</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samuels</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grijalva</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prescription opioid dose after vaginal delivery and the risk of serious opioid-related events: a retrospective cohort study</article-title><source>Womens Health Issues</source><year>2021</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>376</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.whi.2021.03.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33865673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8260443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiese</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osmundson</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adgent</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spieker</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grijalva</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The risk of serious opioid-related events associated with common opioid prescribing regimens in the postpartum period after cesarean delivery</article-title><source>Am J Obstet Gynecol MFM</source><year>2021</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>100475</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajogmf.2021.100475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34455101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8599660</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becher</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sauerbrei</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling continuous covariates with a &#8220;spike&#8221; at zero: bivariate approaches</article-title><source>Biom J</source><year>2016</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bimj.201400112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27072783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sauerbrei</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becher</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling variables with a spike at zero: examples and practical recommendations</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Epidemiol</italic></source><year>2017</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>650</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kww122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28369154</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bykov</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avorn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shrank</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Landon</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rathmell</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huybrechts</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Persistent opioid use following cesarean delivery: patterns and predictors among opioid-na&#239;ve women</article-title><source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source><year>2016</year><volume>215</volume><fpage>353</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajog.2016.03.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5003640</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26996986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohnert</surname><given-names>ASB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Losby</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Opioid prescribing in the United States before and after the centers for disease control and prevention&#8217;s 2016 opioid guideline</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Intern Med</italic></source><year>2018</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M18-1243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30167651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6176709</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Encinosa</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selden</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Opioid and non-opioid analgesic prescribing before and after the CDC&#8217;s 2016 opioid guideline</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Health Econ Manag</italic></source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10754-021-09307-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33963977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8105705</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bazargan-Hejazi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heidari Zadie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Euasobhon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ketumarn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karbasfrushan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amini-Saman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pain management in trauma: a review study</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">J Inj Violence Res</italic></source><year>2016</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5249/jivr.v8i2.707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27414816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4967367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>DRW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faulkner</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forget</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><collab>On Behalf Of The Score Collaborative</collab></person-group><article-title>Opioid prescription following wrist and ankle fracture fixation in Scotland-tradition prevails</article-title><source>J Clin Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>468</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm11020468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35054162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8781195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karamchandani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klick</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linskey Dougherty</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonavia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pain management in trauma patients affected by the opioid epidemic: a narrative review</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">J Trauma Acute Care Surg</italic></source><year>2019</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>430</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/TA.0000000000002292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30939572</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajput</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shergill</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vadivelu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhanced recovery after surgery: opioid sparing strategies after discharge: a review</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Pain Headache Rep</italic></source><year>2022</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11916-022-01009-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35072920</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juurlink</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antoniou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mamdani</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Brink</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gabapentin, opioids, and the risk of opioid-related death: a population-based nested case-control study</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS Med</italic></source><year>2017</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>e1002396</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1002396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28972983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5626029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olopoenia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Camelo-Castillo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qato</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adekoya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palumbo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sera</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simoni-Wastila</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adverse outcomes associated with concurrent gabapentin, opioid, and benzodiazepine utilization: a nested case-control study</article-title><source>Lancet Reg Health Am</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>100302</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lana.2022.100302</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36777316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9904085</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuehn</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growing role of gabapentin in opioid-related overdoses highlights misuse potential and off-label prescribing practices</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2022</year><volume>328</volume><fpage>1283</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2022.13659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36069924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilson</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Notes from the field: trends in Gabapentin detection and involvement in drug overdose deaths - 23 States and the District of Columbia, 2019-2020</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>664</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7119a3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35552367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9098248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beaulieu-Bonneau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>St-Onge</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackburn</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banville</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paradis-Giroux</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ouellet</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol and drug use before and during the first year after traumatic brain injury</article-title><source>J Head Trauma Rehabil</source><year>2018</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>E51</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/HTR.0000000000000341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28926484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Walraven</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A modification of the Elixhauser Comorbidity measures into a point system for hospital death using administrative data</article-title><source>Medical Care</source><year>2009</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>626</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MLR.0b013e31819432e5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19433995</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>Data may be obtained from a third party and are not publicly available.</p></sec></back></article></pmc-articleset>