<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">503</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">neurodist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ndt</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1176-6328</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1178-2021</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10239234</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10239234.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10239234</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10239234</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37274139</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NDT.S408812</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">408812</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Electrocardiogram Abnormalities and Associated Factors Among People with and without Epilepsy Attending the Outpatient Department at Referral Hospitals in Amhara Regional State, Northern Ethiopia, 2022: Institutional-Based Comparative Cross-Sectional Study</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Adane et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Adane et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8199-1859</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Adane</surname><given-names initials="T">Tadegew</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Melese</surname><given-names initials="M">Mihret</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6273-7727</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Tesfaye</surname><given-names initials="E">Ephrem</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ambelu</surname><given-names initials="A">Adugnaw</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7553-1429</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Getnet</surname><given-names initials="M">Mihret</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinamaw</surname><given-names initials="D">Deresse</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8968-4917</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Esubalew</surname><given-names initials="D">Dereje</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1042-497X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Yismaw</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yibeltal</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Biomedical Science, School of Medicine, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, Debre Markos University</institution>, <addr-line>Debre Markos</addr-line>, <country>Ethiopia</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Human Physiology, School of Medicine, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, University of Gondar</institution>, <addr-line>Gondar</addr-line>, <country>Ethiopia</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Biomedical Sciences, School of Medicine, Madda Walabu University Goba Referral&#160;Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Bale- Goba</addr-line>, <country>Southeast Ethiopia</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Biomedical Science, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, Ambo University</institution>, <addr-line>Ambo</addr-line>, <country>Ethiopia</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Tadegew Adane Abebe, Email tadegeada0975@gmail.com</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">425720</issue-id><fpage>1285</fpage><lpage>1302</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>30</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>04</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-06-05 17:25:09.640"><day>05</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2023 Adane et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Adane et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution &#8211; Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="ndt-19-1285.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Epilepsy&#160;is&#160;a&#160;brain&#160;disease&#160;that is associated with electrocardiographic (ECG) abnormalities.&#160;However, this evidence is limited in Ethiopia. Studying ECG abnormality in epileptic patients could help minimize the cardiac problems and death of epileptic patients by early screening. This study was aimed to assess electrocardiogram abnormalities and associated factors among people with and without epilepsy at referral hospitals in Amhara Regional State (ARS), northern Ethiopia, 2022.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Institutional-based comparative cross-sectional study was conducted from April 20 to June 20, 2022. Three referral hospitals in ARS were selected by simple random sampling.&#160;Epileptic patients were selected by systematic random sampling, and 403 age- and sex-matched participants were selected from attendants&#160;of patients&#160;in the outpatient department.&#160;Interviewer-administered questionnaire&#160;and&#160;digital electrocardiograph were used for data collection. Data were entered to EpiData version 4.6 and exported to stata version&#160;14 for analysis. Variables with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value &lt;0.25 in bivariable analysis were entered to multivariable binary logistic regression. Strength of association was determined by adjusted odds ratio with a 95%&#160;confidence interval (CI).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The prevalence of ECG abnormality was 40.0% (95% CI = 34.7&#8211;46.8) and 29.0% (95% CI =&#160;23.2&#8211;34.3) in epileptic and non-epileptic subjects, respectively. The odds of ECG abnormality was 58% higher among epileptic patients. Divorce, duration of epilepsy, uncontrolled epilepsy,&#160;former/current smoker, adequate physical activity, hypertension, and overweight/obesity were associated with ECG abnormality among epileptic patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion and Recommendations</title><p>The proportion of ECG abnormality was higher among the epileptic than the non-epileptic group.&#160;This should be a wake-up call for stakeholders to establish appropriate measurements to reduce cardiac issues of epileptic patients.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>electrocardiographic abnormality</kwd><kwd>epilepsy</kwd><kwd>Ethiopia</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="7"/><ref-count count="57"/><page-count count="18"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Epilepsy is a brain disease characterized by at least two seizures that occur 24 hours apart without precipitating factors.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></p><p>Cardiovascular problems, the leading cause of mortality globally in the general population,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> are significantly more common in epileptic patients than in non-epileptic individuals.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> However, most patients remain asymptomatic until the occurrence of arrhythmia, myocardial infarction, and sudden cardiac arrest.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Since the traditional cardiac screening methods like age, diabetes status, hypertension, and smoking status could not fully identify cardiac problems,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> electrocardiography remains the best method of early screening before severe cardiac disturbance and death.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> The risk of sudden cardiac death increases three-fold in epileptic patients compared to non-epileptics due to an already existing increased risk of congenital or acquired heart disease among epileptic patients.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></p><p>Electrocardiographic&#160;abnormalities, which indicate problems in the heart or its vasculature, are common among epileptic patients.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#160;The prevalence of abnormal electrocardiogram (ECG) finding in epileptic patients in the Caucasian population is 31.8%.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>&#160;In&#160;India, 9.4% of epileptic patients had abnormal QTc intervals,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> and&#160;in Egypt 51% of temporal lobe epileptic patients had prolonged QTc intervals.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Moreover, abnormalities in ECG among epileptic patients is associated with a higher risk of death.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p><p>Electrocardiographic&#160;abnormalities in people with epilepsy are caused by depolarization and repolarization defects due to disruption of ion channels by anti-epileptic drugs (AEDs), myocardial ischemia due to prolonged contraction in repeated autonomic stimulation of the heart, and as a result of genetic mutation of ion channels found both in the brain and the heart.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> These electrocardiographic changes are associated with age,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> gender,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> alcohol, cigarette smoking,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> chat chewing,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> overweight and/or obesity,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> hypertension,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> antiepileptic drugs (AEDs),<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> duration of epilepsy,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> and frequency of seizure.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></p><p>The current epilepsy management is targeted mainly at symptomatic&#160;treatment with AEDs&#160;and fails&#160;to screen ECG abnormalities.&#160;Atenolol is effective in the management of long-standing cardiac electrical disturbances after seizure in animal studies.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> However, to decrease cardiac issues neither atenolol nor any other intervention has been practised as part of epilepsy follow-up in Ethiopia. This is due to limited research-based evidence in this country. Even globally, previous studies were done either in small sample sizes, not based on matched age and sex groups, or did not show factors associated with ECG abnormality. Our study attempts to fill these gaps.</p><p>Electrocardiographic screening is a cost-effective and non-invasive method to decrease the risk of sudden unexpected death of epileptic patients by detecting cardiac repolarization and depolarization problems early.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> This study is intended to evaluate the ECG abnormalities and associated factors in people with epilepsy and attendants of patients in outpatient departments in referral hospitals found in Amhara Regional State.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Objectives</title><sec id="s0002-s2001"><title>General Objective</title><p>To assess the prevalence and factors associated with electrocardiogram abnormalities among people with and without epilepsy in the outpatient department at referral hospitals in Amhara Regional State, northern Ethiopia, 2022.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002"><title>Specific Objectives</title><p>To compare the prevalence of electrocardiogram abnormality between epileptic and non-epileptic individuals in referral hospitals in Amhara Regional State, northern Ethiopia, 2022.</p><p>To determine the association between epilepsy and ECG abnormality among epileptic patients who attend outpatient follow-up and attendants of patients in outpatient departments at referral hospitals in Amhara Regional State, northern Ethiopia, 2022.</p><p>To identify factors associated with ECG abnormality among epileptic patients who attend outpatient follow-up at referral hospitals in Amhara Regional State, northern Ethiopia, 2022.</p><p>To establish factors associated with ECG abnormality among attendants of patients in outpatient departments at referral hospitals in Amhara Regional State, northern Ethiopia, 2022.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s0003-s2001"><title>Study Setting, Design, and Period</title><p>This was an institutional-based comparative cross-sectional study conducted from April 20 to June 20, 2022 in referral hospitals found in Amhara Regional State (ARS).&#160;There are eight referral hospitals in the region, namely University of Gondar Comprehensive Specialized Referral Hospital,&#160;Tibebe Gion Comprehensive Referral Hospital, Felegehiwot Comprehensive Referral Hospital, Dessie, Woldia, Debre Markos,&#160;Debre Tabor, and Debre Birhan Referral Hospital.&#160;These hospitals have been serving about 2064 adult epileptic patients in the outpatient department. Of these, Debre Markos, Felegehiwot, and Dessie Referral Hospitals were the actual randomly selected study sites, which serve 364, 309, and 304 adult epileptic patients, respectively.</p><p>Felegehiwot Referral Hospital is found in Bahir Dar, the capital city of ARS. It is located 565&#8201;kilometers (km) northwest of Addis Ababa, the capital city of Ethiopia.&#160;It&#160;is currently serving 309 adult epileptic patients.</p><p>Dessie Referral Hospital is found in Dessie town in North Wollo Zone in Amhara Region. Dessie town is found 401 km northeast of Addis Ababa and 471 km from Bahir Dar. Debre Markos Referral Hospital is found at Debre Markos town located 256&#8201;km from Bahir Dar and 300&#8201;km from Addis Ababa.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002"><title>Population and Eligibility Criteria</title><p>All epileptic patients aged 18 years or more and on follow-up at referral hospitals found in ARS were our source population, and those who visited follow-up clinic at selected hospitals during the study period were our study population for the epileptic group. The other source population for the second group was attendants of patients in the outpatient department at referral hospitals found in ARS. Those attendants of patients in outpatient departments at referral hospitals found in ARS during the study period were the second study population. For the first group, all epileptic patients aged 18 or more years who visited follow-up clinics, and for the second group, sex and age (within a range of 5 years with the first group) matched attendants aged 18 years or above who assisted outpatients at the selected hospitals during the study period were included in this study. However, patients with seizures within the day of data collection were excluded. Patients with lesions over the chest, hands, and feet were also excluded since electrodes were put around these areas which may irritate them, making them unable to be calm during the procedure, and also to decrease the risk of infection for the subsequent study subjects.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2003"><title>Sample Size Determination and Sampling Procedures</title><p>The sample size was determined in Epi Info-7 based on the prevalence of ECG abnormality in terms of QTc interval abnormality between epileptic (8.4%) and non-epileptic (2%) groups studied in Egypt.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Considering equal sample size, 95% confidence interval, and power of 80%, it yielded a sample size of 188 for each group.</p><p>Since staging exists in selecting hospitals, we used a design effect and multiplied&#160;each&#160;sample&#160;size&#160;by&#160;2, giving&#160;376.&#160;By&#160;Considering&#160;a&#160;10%&#160;non-response&#160;rate,&#160;the&#160;required&#160;sample&#160;size&#160;was&#160;414 for each group. Therefore, the total sample size was 828.</p><p>Three hospitals were selected by a simple random sampling method. These were Felegehiwot, Dessie, and Debre Markos referral hospitals. Through reading two months of the chronic follow-up logbook, we found that 309, 364, and 304 adult epileptic patients aged 18 years or above were having follow-up at Felegehiwot, Debre Markos, and Dessie comprehensive referral hospitals, respectively, during&#160;February and March 2022. These hospitals served a total of 977 adult epileptic patients. Proportionate allocation was done to select 414 samples in this population so that 131, 154, and 129 were the actual sample sizes, respectively, in these hospitals. Then, systematic random sampling was executed to select epileptic patients after the Kth interval, calculated as: K = total study population/sample size, and was found to be two. Lottery was drawn independently for the selected hospitals to select either one or two. In this way, number one for Felegehiwot and number two for Dessie and Debre Markos hospitals were drawn. Finally, using these numbers as a starting point in the order of patients card in the follow-up clinic, the next participants were selected every second interval until the required sample size was met.</p><p>Participants for the second (non-epileptic) group were selected among volunteers from attendants of patients in outpatient departments that absolutely matched for sex and within 5 years range in age&#160;with the epileptic group from each hospital.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2004"><title>Operational Definitions</title><p>Epileptic patient: any patient diagnosed with epilepsy and having follow-up in the respective referral hospital.</p><p>ECG abnormality: any deviation in wave, segment, or interval based on the Minnesota criteria.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></p><p>Defined daily dose for antiepileptic drugs: according to WHO, an average dose of the drug that should be taken per day to attain maintenance for adults with the main indication,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> which is as follows: carbamazepine = 1000 mg, clonazepam = 8 mg, ethosuxamide = 1250 mg, phenobarbital = 100 mg, phenytoin = 300 mg, pyrimidine = 1250 mg, lamotrigine = 300 mg, valproate = 1500 mg.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></p><p>Combination therapy: consumption of more than one AED per day.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></p><p>Uncontrolled epilepsy: if there is seizure within the last six months despite treatment with AEDs.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></p><p>Adequate physical activity: according to CDC criteria, having a brisk walk for 150&#8211;300 minutes, or running/ jogging 75&#8211;150 minutes, or any muscle strengthening activity of at least two times per week.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></p><p>Smoking status: current smoker, a person who smoked at least 100 cigarettes in his/her life time and currently smoking; former smoker, a person who smoked 100 or more cigarettes but not currently; never smoker, a person who has smoked less than 100 cigarettes or not at all.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></p><p>Current chat chewer: a person who chewed chat in the last three months of data collection; ever chat chewer, at least once in a life time; non-chewer, no history of any chat chewing.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></p><p>Hypertension: a systolic and/or diastolic blood pressure of &#8805;140 mmHg and &#8805;90 mmHg, respectively, or being on anti-hypertensive drugs.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></p><p>Alcohol consumption: frequent drinker, more than three times per week; moderate drinker, three or less times per week; and abstainer, none at all.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></p><p>Weight: underweight, BMI &lt;18.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; normal, BMI 18.5&#8211;24.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; overweight, BMI 25&#8211;29.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; and obese, BMI &#8805;30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2005"><title>Data Collection Instruments and Procedures</title><p>An interviewer-administered structured questionnaire was used to collect sociodemographic, behavioural, and clinical factors considering the WHO stepwise approach for surveillance.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Secondary data were also used to collect drug-related data. Mercury sphygmomanometer, weight balance, and height measuring board were used to measure blood pressure, weight, and height, respectively. A digital electrocardiograph was used to measure electrocardiographic parameters.</p><p>Epileptic patients' data were collected from those who fulfil the inclusion criteria. Sociodemographic, behavioural, and clinical information, as well as height and weight measurement were collected by three trained clinical&#160;nurses.&#160;First, blood pressure was measured by mercury sphygmomanometer according to the WHO guideline.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></p><p>Then, height and weight were measured according to the WHO guideline.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>&#160;Body mass index was calculated as weight in kilogram divided by height squared in meter in STATA. Then, data of the sex- and age-matched (maximum of five years above or below the age of each epileptic group) non-epileptic group were collected.</p><p>Next, sociodemographic, behavioural, and clinical factors were collected. Lastly, electrocardiography was done by three experts of the respective hospital using a 12-lead digital electrocardiograph with a paper speed of 25 mm per second. A paper horizontally calibrated with large boxes representing 0.2 seconds, divided into 5 small boxes that represent 0.04 seconds and vertically with 10 mm representing 1 millivolt was used. The study participant was made to resume supine position, 45 degrees tilted upward, after having removed his/her clothes over the chest, bracelets, and any other electromagnetic substances from his/her body. Then 10 electrodes, 4 on each forearm and legs and 6 on the chest were applied. After completing the required data from individuals, a mark which says &#8220;ECG&#8221;, followed by signature of the data collector, was signed from epileptic patients to avoid duplication in their next follow-up. For the non-epileptic group, they were orally informed not to be part of this study within the next two months.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2006"><title>Data Quality Control</title><p>The questionnaire was prepared in English version and translated to Amharic version by a language expert. Then this was again translated back to English version by another language expert to check for consistency. Data collectors were trained for a day about the purpose of the research, the ethical issues, the questionnaire, and the measurement procedures.&#160;Pre-test was done among 10 epileptic and seven non-epileptic subjects at Woldia referral hospital. Sociodemographic, behavioural, and clinical data were collected under close supervision by supervisors in each hospital. Electrocardiography was done by three experts of the hospital. Electrocardiographic parameters were interpreted by a senior cardiologist. The cardiologist was allowed to interpret the cardiogram only without knowing the epileptic status of the study participant.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2007"><title>Study Variables</title><sec id="s0003-s2007-s3001"><title>Dependent Variable</title><p>Electrocardiogram abnormality (Yes/ No).</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2007-s3002"><title>Independent Variables</title><p>Sociodemographic variables: age, sex, marital status, residence, educational status, occupation, and income.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2007-s3003"><title>Behavioural Variables</title><p>Alcohol, smoking, chat chewing, and physical activity.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2007-s3004"><title>Clinical Variables</title><p>Epilepsy, body mass index, hypertension, and for the epileptic group (duration of epilepsy, type of drug for the disease, frequency of seizure in the last 3 months, epilepsy control, and&#160;the ratio of prescribed daily dose to defined daily dose).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003-s2008"><title>Data Processing and Analysis</title><p>The collected data were checked for completeness and entered into EpiData version 4.6 and exported to stata-14 for analysis. Normality of continuous independent variables was checked by histogram. Median &#177; interquartile range (IQR) was used for descriptive statistics for variables with no normal distribution. The epileptic and non-epileptic groups were compared based on their sociodemographic, behavioural, and clinical factors (hypertension and BMI) to check whether they are different populations or not. Wilcoxon rank sum test was used to compare continuous variables without normal distribution. These groups were considered different when the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value was &#8804;0.05.&#160;Two groups proportion test and <italic toggle="yes">X</italic><sup>2</sup>-test were applied to compare the magnitude of ECG abnormality between groups. The association between ECG abnormality and epilepsy was checked by chi-square test statistics.</p><p>Binary logistic regression was executed three times. The first regression was done in all 806 study participants to determine the strength of association between ECG abnormality and epilepsy. The mean and individual variance inflation factor as well as the Hosmer&#8211;Lemeshow goodness of fit were done. Crude odds ratio of variables was determined in bivariable logistic regression. Then, those with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value less than 0.25 were entered to multivariate binary logistic regression to check the factors associated with ECG abnormality among all study participants. Decision of association was done at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value &#8804;0.05. Strength of association was expressed in adjusted odds ratio with 95% confidence interval. The same procedure was done for the next two models. The second regression was done to determine factors associated with ECG abnormality among non-epileptic patients. Finally, binary logistic regression was done to determine the factors associated with ECG abnormality among epileptic patients.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0004-s2001"><title>Sociodemographic Characteristics of Study Participants</title><p>In this study, a total of 403 epileptic and 403 non-epileptic study subjects were recruited, with a response rate of 97.3% for each group. There was no statistically significant difference between these two groups of study participants in their sociodemographic characteristics (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Sociodemographic Status of Epileptic and Non-Epileptic Groups in ARS Referral Hospitals, Ethiopia, 2022</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Categories</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Group Frequency, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epileptic</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Epileptic</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Marital status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">154 (38.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">184 (46.7)</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.39</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unmarried</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">207 (51.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">189 (46.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Divorced</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (7.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (5.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Widowed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (3.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (2.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Residence</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (20.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (19.1)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.80</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">322 (79.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">326 (80.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Income, median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2000 (2000)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2000 (1400)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Educational status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unable to read/ write</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97 (24.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (23.6)</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;Grade 8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98 (24.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (21.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 9&#8211;12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125 (31.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113 (28.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diploma or above</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (20.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 (27.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="8" colspan="1">Occupation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Farmer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">119 (29.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125 (31.0)</td><td rowspan="8" colspan="1">0.47</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Student</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 (30.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">115 (28.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Government employee</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (9.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (11.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Merchant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (5.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (7.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daily labourer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (10.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (7.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">House wife</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (3.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (3.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Private employee</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (7.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (6.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (5.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (4.7)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Note</bold>: Other (pensioner, prisoner, driver).</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: IQR, interquartile range.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>The median age of epileptic and non-epileptic subjects was 28&#177;(IQR 11) and 25&#177;(IQR 8) years, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value in the Wilcoxon rank sum test = 0.35). The age of epileptic patients ranges from 18 to 53 years, and it was 18 to 54 years in the non-epileptic group. In each group, 214 (53.1%) of the study participants were males.</p><p>The median monthly personal income of epileptic participants was 2000&#177;(IQR 2000) Ethiopian birr, with minimum and maximum of 200 and 10,000 Ethiopian birr, respectively. The median monthly income of the non-epileptic participants was 2000&#177;(IQR 1400) Ethiopian birr, with minimum and maximum of 600 and 11,000 Ethiopian birr, respectively (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0004-s2002"><title>Behavioural Characteristics of Study Participants</title><p>Epileptic patients were more frequently chat chewers and smokers than were non-epileptic subjects. About 7.9% of epileptic and 4.9% of non-epileptic participants were either former or current smokers. Similarly, 16.6% of epileptic and 12.9% of non-epileptic subjects had history of either ever or current chat chewing. There was no significant difference between them in status of physical activity and alcohol drinking (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of Behavioural Factors Between Epileptic and Non-Epileptic Subjects in ARS, Ethiopia, 2022</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Category</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Group, Total (%)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epileptic</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Epileptic</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">371 (92.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">383 (95.1)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.01*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Former/current</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (7.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (4.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Chat chewing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">336 (83.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">351 (87.1)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.047*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ever/current</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (16.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (12.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Alcohol drinking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abstainer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (7.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (8.5)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.26</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">274 (68.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">288 (71.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (24.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (20.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Physical activity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adequate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">142 (35.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">161 (40.0)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.47</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inadequate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">261 (64.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">242 (60.0)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Note</bold>: *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value &#8804;0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0004-s2003"><title>Clinical Profile of Study Participants</title><p>About 8.4% and 7.4% of epileptic and non-epileptic groups, respectively, were hypertensive (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value = 0.09). More than half (58.8%) of hypertensive epileptic patients and nearly half (50.7%) of hypertensive non-epileptic subjects had ECG abnormality. In addition, there was no significant difference between these groups in BMI (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value = 0.31). Nearly 7.4% and 9.4% of epileptic and non-epileptic subjects, respectively, were either overweight or obese. In the epileptic group, 56.7% of overweight/obese people had ECG abnormality; in the non-epileptic group, 56.9% of overweight/obese people had the condition.</p><p>The median duration of illness with epilepsy was 9&#177;(IQR 7) years. The median duration of epilepsy among those with and without ECG abnormality was 10&#177;7 and 8&#177;6, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.013). More than half (61.0%) of them were having combined drug therapy (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Clinical Profile of Non-Epileptic and Epileptic Patients at ARS Referral Hospitals, Ethiopia, 2022</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Category</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Total (%)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">ECG Abnormality</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">X</italic><sup>2</sup>/ Wilcoxon (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes in %</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No in %</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Epileptic group</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (8.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.2</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.002*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">369 (91.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">BMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Underweight</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (3.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.003*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">361 (89.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overweight/ obese</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (7.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of epilepsy, median &#177;IQR (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9&#177;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#177;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8&#177;6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Epilepsy control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controlled</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">286 (81.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.0</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncontrolled</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117 (29.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Type&#160;of AED</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carbamazepine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (16.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.8</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.735</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenobarbital</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (18.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (4.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Combined</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">246 (61.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">PDD&#160;to DDD ratio</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;One</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">280 (69.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.1</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.245</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">One</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">123 (30.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Seizure within 3 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">336 (83.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.5</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.005*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">One</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (9.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;One</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (7.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.6</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Non-epileptic group</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (7.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.3</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.03*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">373 (92.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">BMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Underweight</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (2.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.01*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">357 (88.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overweight/ obese</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (9.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Note</bold>: *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value &#8804;0.05.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: IQR, interquartile range; BMI, body mass index; AED, anti-epileptic drug; PDD, prescribed daily dose; DDD, defined daily dose.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0004-s2004"><title>Comparison of ECG Abnormality Among the Epileptic and the Non-Epileptic Group</title><p>Among all study participants, 34.5% (95% CI = 30&#8211;39.3%) were having at least one pattern of ECG abnormality.</p><p>The prevalence of ECG abnormality was 40.0% (95% CI = 34.7&#8211;46.8%) among the epileptic group, while it was about 29.0% (CI = 23.2&#8211;34.3%) in the non-epileptic group. The magnitude of ECG abnormality among female epileptic patients was 43.75%, while it was 27.6% among non-epileptic study participants (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0358). In males, the prevalence of ECG abnormality was 36.3% and 29.9% in the epileptic and non-epileptic group, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.244).</p><p>In particular, abnormal Q wave (8.9% of epileptic and 2.5% of non-epileptic group, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.005) and BBB (7.4% of epileptic and 2% of non-epileptic group, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.01) were significantly more prevalent in the epileptic group than in the non-epileptic group. Abnormal QTc accounted for 3.5% and 1.5% in the epileptic and non-epileptic group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.042). Similarly, 3.5% and 1.2% of the epileptic and the non-epileptic group, respectively, had abnormal ST segment (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.040). The most frequently observed ECG abnormalities were axis deviation (epileptic 10.4%, non-epileptic 8.9%) and abnormal heart rate (epileptic 10.4%; non-epileptic 7.4%) (<xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0004" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Patterns of ECG Abnormality Among the Epileptic and the Non-Epileptic Group in ARS Referral Hospitals, Ethiopia, 2022</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Category</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Total Number (%)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Groups in Number (%)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epileptic</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Epileptic</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">ECG abnormality</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">278 (34.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">161 (40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117 (29.0)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.022*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">528 (65.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">242 (60.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">286 (71.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Heart rate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">734 (91.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">361 (89.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">373 (92.6)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.295</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abnormal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (8.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (10.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (7.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">P wave</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">786 (97.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">394 (97.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">392 (97.3)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.461</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abnormal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (2.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (2.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">PR interval</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">787 (97.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">391 (97)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">396 (98.3)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.053</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abnormal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (2.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (3.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (1.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">QRS wave</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">781 (96.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">388 (96.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">393 (97.5)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.398</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abnormal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (3.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (3.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (2.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">QTc interval</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">786 (97.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">389 (96.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">397 (98.5)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.042</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abnormal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (3.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (1.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">BBB (R/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (4.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (7.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (2.0)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.01*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">768 (95.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">373 (92.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">395 (98.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Axis deviation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (9.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (10.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (8.9)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.613</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">728 (90.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">361 (89.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">367 (91.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Right/left&#160;atrial hypertrophy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (3.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (3.5)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.703</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">782 (97.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">393 (97.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">389 (96.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Right&#160;ventricular hypertrophy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (3.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (2.0)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.522</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">786 (97.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">391 (97.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">395 (98.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Left&#160;ventricular hypertrophy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (3.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (3.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (4.0)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.610</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">775 (96.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">389 (96.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">386 (96.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Abnormal Q wave</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (8.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.005*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">760 (94.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">367 (91.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">393 (97.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Abnormal T wave</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (3.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (5.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (2.0)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.103</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">778 (96.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">383 (95.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">395 (98.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Abnormal ST segment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (2.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (3.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (1.2)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.040</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">787 (97.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">389 (96.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">398 (98.8)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value &#8804;0.05.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0007"><p><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: BBB (R/L), right and/or left bundle branch block.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0004-s2005"><title>Association of Epilepsy with ECG Abnormality</title><p>Regression was done in the total study participants (for the 806 study participants). Epilepsy (yes/no) was considered as one of the determinants. Being epileptic was positively associated with ECG abnormality (<italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sup>2</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.022, COR = 1.63, 95% CI =&#160;1.07&#8211;2.45). After the effect of smoking, physical exercise, hypertension, and BMI had been adjusted, the odds of ECG abnormality was 58% higher among people with epilepsy than without epilepsy (AOR 1.01&#8211;2.48). Being former/current smoker (AOR = 3.06, 95% CI = 1.71&#8211;5.59), having adequate physical activity (AOR = 0.4, 95% CI = 0.09&#8211;0.89), being overweight/obese (AOR = 3.16, 95% CI = 1.99&#8211;5.72), and having hypertension (AOR = 3.48, 95% CI = 1.02&#8211;6.37) were associated with ECG abnormality (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Factors Associated with ECG Abnormality Among Non-Epileptic and Epileptic Patients in ARS Referral Hospitals, Ethiopia, 2022</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">ECG Abnormality (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 806)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">COR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">AOR (95% CI)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (median &#177; IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 &#177; 9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 &#177; 9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01 (0.76&#8211;3.24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95 (0.74&#8211;3.02)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Residence</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Urban</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Rural</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">222</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">426</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.22&#8211;1.340)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38 (0.18&#8211;1.04)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Marital status</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">228</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Unmarried</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">264</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.51&#8211;1.92)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.63&#8211;2.04)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Divorced</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.33 (1.29&#8211;4.33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 (0.97&#8211;3.91)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Widowed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55 (0.21&#8211;2.35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 (0.48&#8211;2.12)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Smoking</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">243</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">511</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Former/current</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.33 (1.80&#8211;6.01)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.06 (1.71&#8211;5.59)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Chat chewing</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">225</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">462</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Ever/current</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65 (0.51&#8211;2.58)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58 (0.39&#8211;2.13)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Physical activity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Adequate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">226</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 (0.19&#8211;0.91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.09&#8211;0.89)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Inadequate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">201</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">302</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Epilepsy</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">161</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">242</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63 (1.07&#8211;2.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58 (1.01&#8211;2.48)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">286</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">BMI</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Underweight</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.52&#8211;2,99)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.95&#8211;2.60)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">224</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">494</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Overweight/ obese</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.31 (2.09&#8211;7.02)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.16 (1.99&#8211;5.72)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Hypertension</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.78 (2.56&#8211;7.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48 (2.02&#8211;6.37)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">234</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">508</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0008"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: IQR, interquartile range; <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>, total number of participants (epileptic and non-epileptic).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0004-s2006"><title>Factors Associated with ECG Abnormality Among Epileptic Patients</title><p>The association of ECG abnormality with age, sex, residence, marital status, education, occupation, income, physical activity, smoking status, chat chewing, BMI, hypertension, duration of disease, treatment outcome, type of AED, PDD to DDD ratio, and number of seizures in the last three months was checked in bivariate binary logistic analysis. Residence, marital status, educational status, physical activity, sex, chat chewing, smoking, BMI, hypertension, duration of illness, status of seizure control, PDD to DDD ratio, and number of seizures in the last three months had significant association with ECG abnormality in COR at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value less than 0.25. Marital status, physical activity, smoking, hypertension, BMI, and disease-specific factors (uncontrolled epilepsy and duration of epilepsy) had statistically significant association with ECG abnormality in multivariate analysis. Being divorced (AOR = 2.39, 95% CI = 1.04&#8211;6.96), duration of epilepsy (AOR = 1.15, 95% CI = 1.05&#8211;1.27), uncontrolled seizure (AOR = 3.64, 95% CI = 1.57&#8211;5.86), being a former/current smoker (AOR = 4.66, 95% CI = 2.89&#8211;6.68), adequate physical activity (AOR = 0.6, 95% CI = 0.12&#8211;0.91), being hypertensive (AOR = 5.41, 95% CI = 2.82&#8211;9.31), and overweight/obesity (AOR = 3.11, 95% CI = 2.14&#8211;4.96) were associated with ECG abnormality (<xref rid="t0006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>).
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0006" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Factors Associated with ECG Abnormality Among Epileptic Patients at ARS Referral Hospitals, Ethiopia, 2022</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">ECG Abnormality (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 403)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">COR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AOR (95% CI)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Residence</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Urban</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Rural</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">199</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 (0.32&#8211;1.26)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 (0.22&#8211;1.08)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Marital status</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Unmarried</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.51&#8211;1.72)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36 (0.49&#8211;1.34)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Divorced</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.86 (1.33&#8211;6.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39 (1.04&#8211;6.96)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Widowed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66 (0.31&#8211;4.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46 (0.40&#8211;3.14)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Educational status</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Unable to read/ write</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8804;Grade 8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.54&#8211;2.38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.42&#8211;1.63)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Grade 8&#8211;12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.52&#8211;1.73)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 (0.25&#8211;1.52)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Diploma and above</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 (0.34&#8211;1.67)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 (0.34&#8211;1.36)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Chat chewing</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">208</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Ever/current</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58 (0.42&#8211;2.59)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.35&#8211;1.93)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Smoking</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">234</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Former/current</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.12 (3.11&#8211;7.72)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.66 (2.89&#8211;6.68)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Physical activity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Adequate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 (0.14&#8211;0.97)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 (0.12&#8211;0.91)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Inadequate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">BMI</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Underweight</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69 (0.44&#8211;2.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41 (0.35&#8211;2.63)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">227</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Overweight/ obese</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.95 (2.29&#8211;5.02)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.11 (2.14&#8211;4.96)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Hypertension</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.63 (2.92&#8211;9.01)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.41 (2.82&#8211;9.31)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">234</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of epilepsy (median&#177;IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#177;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8&#177;6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.99 (1.22&#8211;2.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 (1.05&#8211;1.27)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Epilepsy control</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Controlled</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">196</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Uncontrolled</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.36 (1.83&#8211;6.47)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.64 (1.57&#8211;5.86)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">PDD to DDD ratio</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&lt;One</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">177</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;=One</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53 (0.77&#8211;2.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 (0.64&#8211;1.90)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Number of seizures in the last 3 months</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">206</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;One</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 (0.38&#8211;2.96)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.31&#8211;2.35)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&gt;One</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58 (0.80&#8211;3.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 (0.23&#8211;5.97)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0009"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: IQR, interquartile range; <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>, total number of epileptic participants.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0004-s2007"><title>Factors Associated with ECG Abnormality Among the Non-Epileptic Group</title><p>In the non-epileptic group, age, sex, marital status, smoking, chat chewing, physical activity, BMI, and hypertension were associated with ECG abnormality in bivariate analysis at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value less than 0.25. From these, former/current smoking (AOR = 1.09, 95% CI = 1.03&#8211;2.09), adequate physical activity (AOR = 0.23, 95% CI = 0.01&#8211;0.68), overweight/obesity (AOR = 3.00, 95% CI = 1.01&#8211;5.04), and hypertension (AOR = 2.99, 95% CI = 1.94&#8211;5.03) were factors associated with ECG abnormality in multivariate analysis (<xref rid="t0007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>).
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0007" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Factors Associated with ECG Abnormality Among Outpatient Attendants of ARS Referral Hospitals, Ethiopia, 2022</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">ECG Abnormality (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 403)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">COR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">AOR (95% CI)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (median&#177; IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23&#177;8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28&#177;9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01 (0.76&#8211;3.24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95 (0.74&#8211;3.02)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 (0.46&#8211;1.72)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.43&#8211;1.69)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Marital status</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Unmarried</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.49&#8211;1.74)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (0.53&#8211;1.84)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Divorced</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.77&#8211;1.73)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.66&#8211;1.91)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Widowed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 (0.32&#8211;2.35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 (0.35&#8211;2.22)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Smoking</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">277</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Former/current</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.19 (1.40&#8211;5.11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (1.03&#8211;2.09)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Chat chewing</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">254</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Ever/current</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.64 (0.71&#8211;3.01)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 (0.21&#8211;2.99)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Physical activity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Adequate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 (0.02&#8211;0.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 (0.01&#8211;0.68)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Inadequate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">BMI</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Underweight</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78 (0.32&#8211;2,18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 (0.81&#8211;2.14)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">267</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Overweight/ obese</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.10 (2.02&#8211;6.91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00 (1.04&#8211;5.04)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Hypertension</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.15 (1.96&#8211;6.01)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.99 (1.94&#8211;5.03)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">274</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0010"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: IQR, interquartile range; <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>, total number of non-epileptic participants.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0005"><title>Discussion</title><p>The aim of the current study was to determine the prevalence and associated factors of ECG abnormality for epileptic patients and non-epileptic attendants of patients in outpatient departments.</p><p>In this study, 34.5% of the total study participants had at least one pattern of ECG abnormality which was comparable with a study done in Caucasian population, 31.8%.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> About 8.9% of them had abnormal heart rate (bradycardia or tachycardia), which is higher than a study conducted in China.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> This may be due to the difference in sociodemographic characteristics between the two populations.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> The proportion with abnormal Q wave in this study was 5.7%. This result is higher than the studies from Spain (3.5%),<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> China (1.28%),<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> and Angola (0.71%).<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> This may be because half of the study participants in the current study were epileptic patients which may raise the proportion of Q wave abnormality. This study revealed that 3.8% of study participants had left ventricular hypertrophy. This was consistent with a study in Spain, 3.2%.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></p><p>The proportion of overall ECG abnormality in epileptic patients, 40.0% (95% CI = 34.7&#8211;46.8%), was significantly higher than in the non-epileptic group, 29.0% (95% CI = 23.2&#8211;34.3%). This could be an indicator of the higher prevalence of unnoticed cardiovascular risks in epileptic patients.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Therefore, epileptic patients are more likely to experience sudden unexpected death.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Exceptionally, the proportions with BBB and abnormal Q wave, QTc, and ST segment were higher in epileptic patients than non-epileptic subjects. This result is in line with a global systematic review which found a higher proportion of pathologic Q wave in epileptic patients than in non-epileptic individuals.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> This may signify higher occurrence of previous myocardial ischemia in epileptic patients.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> The proportion was more specifically higher among female epileptic patients. This higher proportion of ECG abnormality in female epileptic patients may be as a result of interaction between AEDs and female hormones.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Anti-epileptic drugs increase the metabolism of female sex hormones<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> and production of female sex hormone binding globulins,<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> which decreases the bioavailability of these hormones in blood. Therefore, the cardiovascular health-promoting effect of female sex hormones is decreased, leading to the increased risk of heart disease among female epileptic patients.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> The other reason for the higher proportion of ECG abnormality among epileptic patients could be the effect of smoking. As indicated in the results section, the proportion of smokers among epileptic patients, 7.9%, was higher than in the non-epileptic group, 4.9% (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.04). Again, the present study indicated that smoking was associated with ECG abnormality that could increase the magnitude of ECG abnormality in epileptic patients.</p><p>While a study conducted in the Netherlands found higher heart rate abnormality of epileptic patients than in controls,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> the finding of this study revealed no difference in heart rate. This may be due to the fact that the Netherlands study might not have matching of groups based on age, sex, and other sociodemographic status, which our study did.</p><p>Factors associated with ECG abnormality among the whole group of 806 study participants were determined. Being epileptic, former/current smoker, adequate physical activity, overweight and/or obesity, and hypertension were associated with ECG abnormality. The odds of ECG abnormality among epileptic patients was 58% higher than the odds of ECG abnormality in the non-epileptic group (AOR = 1.58, 95% CI = 1.01&#8211;2.48). This may be due to the effect of genetic or seizure-induced changes to structure, autonomic function, and ion channels of the heart.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> The focus of epilepsy may arise from the area of the brain that controls the activity of the heart. During seizure stimulation, it may therefore suppress or overactivate the heart.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Sometimes, the focus of seizure may also be on cortical areas that directly control autonomic nervous system, and firing of these areas cause undesired stimulation of autonomic nerves which affect the heart.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> The effect of AEDs could also be responsible for the ECG abnormality by blocking ion channels of the heart.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> Furthermore, congenital or acquired channelopathies that are found both in the heart and brain may be responsible for the mutual occurrence of epilepsy and ECG abnormality.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></p><p>Smoking was associated with ECG abnormality among the whole group of study participants, the epileptic group and the non-epileptic group. From total participants, the odds of ECG abnormality among smokers was 3.06 times (AOR 3.06, 95% CI = 1.71&#8211;5.59) higher than among non-smokers. This finding was supported by a study in Angola.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> The harmful components of cigarette smoke like nicotine may be responsible for this difference. Nicotine is capable of altering the normal function of inward and delayed rectifier potassium channels, channels important for excitability and maintenance of membrane potential stability.<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> In another way, components of cigarette increase endogenous release of free radicals, decrease oxygen availability to the heart, favour inflammation and deposition of atherosclerotic plaque in coronary arteries, and finally lead to myocardial infarction.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> Moreover, in the present study, the strength of association between former/current smoking and ECG abnormality was higher in the epileptic group (AOR = 4.66, 95% CI = 2.89&#8211;6.68) than in the non-epileptic group (AOR = 1.09, 95% CI = 1.03&#8211;2.09). This may be due to increased sympathetic activity due to smoking and therefore increase the severity of epilepsy,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> which was associated with ECG abnormality in our study. In addition, both smoking and anti-epileptic drugs may have a synergistic effect for ECG abnormality by increasing the blood level of low-density lipoproteins and atherosclerosis.<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></p><p>The other factor that was significantly associated with ECG abnormality in both the epileptic and the non-epileptic group was adequate physical activity. The odds of ECG abnormality was 40% in the epileptic group (AOR = 0.6, 95% CI = 0.12&#8211;0.91) and 90% in the non-epileptic group (AOR = 0.23, 95% CI = 0.01&#8211;0.68) lower among those with adequate physical activity than non-adequate physical activity. This may be due to the effect of physical activity in decreasing the risk factors of cardiac problems like dyslipidaemia, obesity, and insulin resistance.<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></p><p>Among the 806 participants, being overweight and/or obese was associated with 3.16 times (AOR = 3.16, 95% CI = 1.99&#8211;5.72) higher odds of ECG abnormality than being of normal weight. Being overweight or obese was also associated with ECG abnormality in epileptic and non-epileptic groups separately. The strength of association between overweight/obesity and ECG abnormality was comparable in the epileptic and non-epileptic group (AOR = 3.11 versus 3.00). Among the epileptic group, the odds of ECG abnormality in overweight and/or obese subjects was 3.11 times (AOR = 3.11, 95% CI = 1.14&#8211;4.96) higher than among those with normal BMI. The odds of ECG abnormality was three times (AOR = 3.00, 95% CI = 1.04&#8211;5.04) higher than among normal BMI subjects in the non-epileptic group. First, accumulation of fat in the viscera of those people may physically displace the structure of the heart, so that the electrical axis is changed.<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> Second, overweight/obesity is associated with metabolic alterations like dyslipidaemia and the associated immune response of hyperlipidaemia.<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></p><p>Besides, hypertension was associated with ECG abnormality. Among the whole group of study participants, the odds of ECG abnormality among people with hypertension was 3.48 times (AOR = 3.48, 95% CI = 2.02&#8211;6.37) higher than among those without hypertension. This finding was consistent with the result of previous studies from Spain,<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Caucasian population,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> and Angola.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> Hypertension could be associated with ECG abnormality due to functional or structural changes.<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> Structural remodelling of the heart to compensate the load of increased blood pressure triggers re-placement of ion channels and dysfunction of gap junctions.<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></p><p>Being divorced was significantly associated with ECG abnormality among epileptic patients only. The odds of having ECG abnormality was 2.39 (AOR = 2.39, 95% CI = 1.04&#8211;6.96) times higher among divorced epileptic patients than among married epileptic patients. Being divorced and epileptic could be related with heart problems by its psychosocial implications. Psychological problems lead to excessive secretions of cortisol which is complicated by dyslipidaemia, insulin resistance, and catecholamine hypersensitivity, finally resulting in damage of the cardiovascular system.<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></p><p>A one-unit increase in the duration of epilepsy increased the odds of having ECG abnormality by 15% (AOR = 1.15, 95% CI = 1.05&#8211;1.27). This result was supported by a study done in Iran which indicated an increased risk of one of the components of ECG abnormality, the QRS wave, when duration of epilepsy increased.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> This condition could be a result of prolonged exposure of the heart to AEDs which block ion channels of the heart or increase existence of cardiovascular risks like dyslipidaemia and insulin resistance.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></p><p>The odds of ECG abnormality among epileptic patients with uncontrolled seizure were 3.64 (AOR = 3.64 with 95% CI = 1.57&#8211;5.86) times higher than the odds of ECG abnormality among epileptic patients with controlled seizure. This evidence was supported by a study done in Egypt in which patterns of ECG abnormality were associated with uncontrolled epilepsy.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> This could occur due to repetitive sympathetic stimulation of the heart during repetitive seizure.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Therefore, the heart contracts strongly to accomplish its duty. Due to severe muscular contraction, the vasculatures of the heart could be ischemic and the electrical bundles of the heart damaged. The other reason could be an uncontrolled surge of catecholamines that damage the heart during seizure activity.<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0006"><title>Strength and Limitation of the Study</title><p>This study has some strengths and limitations. Its strength was that the study was conducted in a multi-centre setting, which is more representative of the study population. Second, since it is a comparative study, it tells us the extent of ECG abnormality between epileptic and non-epileptic study participants.</p><p>The limitations of this study were, first, that study participants did not undergo laboratory screening for thyroid function test, random blood sugar, lipid profile, electrolyte level, complete blood count, and organ function tests. Therefore, such undiagnosed problems could be more likely in either group and thus could disrupt the findings. Second, the study failed to address those epileptic patients who did not start AED treatment. Therefore, ECG abnormalities were not compared between those who did or did not take AEDs.</p></sec><sec id="s0007"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The prevalence of ECG abnormality was higher in the epileptic group than in the non-epileptic group. Among patterns of ECG abnormality, BBB, abnormal QTc, ST segment, and Q wave were more common in the epileptic group. From the whole group of study participants, former or current smoking, overweight or obesity, hypertension, and epilepsy were factors that increase the odds of ECG abnormality, whereas adequate physical activity was associated with a decrease in the odds of ECG abnormality. Among the factors, hypertension and former or current smoking were more strongly associated with ECG abnormality in the epileptic group than in the non-epileptic group. Furthermore, being divorced, having a longer duration of epilepsy and uncontrolled epilepsy were associated with ECG abnormality among the epileptic group.</p></sec><sec id="s0008"><title>Recommendations</title><p>Policy makers are expected to design a strategy considering cardiovascular health assessment of epileptic patients for early detection of cardiac issues.</p><p>The government authorities are suggested to lead smoking cessation campaign.</p><p>Future studies are recommended to match study participants with body mass index and smoking status.</p><p>Health care providers need to pay attention to epileptic patients by full cardiovascular examination for earlier detection of cardiovascular problems.</p><p>Furthermore, epileptic patients as well as the general population are advised to establish cardiovascular health-promoting practices like physical exercise.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>We would like to express our gratitude to the University of Gondar for giving the chance for the study. We are so grateful to the study participants for their contribution in providing appropriate data. We would like to thank Felegehiwot, Dessie, and Debre Markos referral hospitals for their cooperation in the conduct of the study. Lastly, we are grateful to the data collectors and supervisors for their participation in collecting quality data.</p></ack><sec id="s0009"><title>Abbreviations</title><p>AED, antiepileptic drug; ARS, Amhara Regional State; BBB, bundle branch block; BMI, body mass index; CI, confidence interval; DDD, defined daily dose; ECG, electrocardiogram; IQR, interquartile range; ms, millisecond; OPD, outpatient department; PDD, prescribed daily dose; QTc, corrected QT; WHO, World Health Organization.</p></sec><sec id="s0010"><title>Data Sharing Statement</title><p>We included all the relevant information, but further datasets can be obtained from the corresponding author if required.</p></sec><sec id="s0011"><title>Ethical Approval and Consent to Participate</title><p>First, ethical approval was obtained from the ethical review board in the School of Medicine and Health Science, University of Gondar (Ref No. SOM/1482/2022). Letter of cooperation was written to the selected hospitals from University of Gondar, College of Medicine and Health Science, Department of Human Physiology. Letter of permission was asked&#160;of&#160;the manager and department of internal medicine in all&#160;selected hospitals.&#160;The purpose of the study was explained to the study participants.&#160;They were assured confidentiality, as information obtained will not be disclosed to anyone, and written informed consent was done. Study participants were asked to sign the consent form to declare that the study was done based on their free decision. The study was conducted in compliance with the Declaration of Helsinki. Those study participants with ECG abnormality were linked to outpatient department of internal medicine for further inspection.</p></sec><sec id="s0012"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis, and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising, or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0013"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Acevedo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Arzimanoglou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>ILAE official report: a practical clinical definition of epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsia</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>475</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>482</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/epi.12550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24730690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abajobir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Global, regional, and national burden of cardiovascular diseases for 10 causes, 1990 to 2015</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>25</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2017.04.052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28527533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5491406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>CDC</collab>. <article-title>Comorbidity in adults with epilepsy-United States</article-title>; <year>2013</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/preview/mmwrhtml/mm6243a2.htm#Tab1" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/preview/mmwrhtml/mm6243a2.htm#Tab1</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>May</month><day>18</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Christopher Jones</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pothier</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Blackstone</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lauer</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prognostic importance of presenting symptoms in patients undergoing exercise testing for evaluation of known or suspected coronary disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Med</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>117</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>380</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>389</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjmed.2004.06.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15380494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McClelland</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Budoff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>10-year coronary heart disease risk prediction using coronary artery calcium and traditional risk factors: derivation in the mesa (multi-ethnic study of atherosclerosis) with validation in the HNR (Heinz Nixdorf Recall) study and the DHS (Dallas Heart Study)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1643</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1653</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2015.08.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26449133</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4603537</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jimenez-Corona</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sievers</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Knowler</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Electrocardiographic abnormalities predict deaths from cardiovascular disease and ischemic heart disease in Pima Indians with type 2 diabetes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am Heart J</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>151</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1080</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1086</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ahj.2005.06.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16644339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bardai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lamberts</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Blom</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Epilepsy is a risk factor for sudden cardiac arrest in the general population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e42749</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0042749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22916156</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3419243</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lamberts</surname><given-names>RJBM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Novy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Novy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Increased prevalence of ECG markers for sudden cardiac arrest in refractory epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>86</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>309</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>313</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jnnp-2014-307772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24946773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4345521</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ioannou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Papageorgiou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Missouris</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Registry report of the prevalence of ECG abnormalities and their relation to patient characteristics in an asymptomatic population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">QJM</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>875</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>879</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/qjmed/hcy212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30239921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Suna</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Suna</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gutmane</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Electrocardiographic abnormalities and mortality in epilepsy patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Medicina</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>504</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/medicina57050504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34065703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8156797</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nasef</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gaber</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelhamid</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bastawy</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelhady</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wahid El Din</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Corrected QT interval and QT dispersion in temporal lobe epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Egypt J Neurol Psychiatry Neurosurg</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41983-020-00257-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>MCH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Brien</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Todaro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Acquired cardiac channelopathies in epilepsy: evidence, mechanisms, and clinical significance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsia</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1753</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1767</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/epi.16301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31353444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goit</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pant</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Alteration of cardiac autonomic function in patients with newly diagnosed epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Report</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e12826</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14814/phy2.12826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4908501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27273881</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>de Sousa</surname><given-names>JMB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fialho</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Walz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Determining factors of electrocardiographic abnormalities in patients with epilepsy: a case-control study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Res</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>129</volume>:<fpage>106</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>116</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eplepsyres.2016.12.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28043059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gon&#231;alves</surname><given-names>MAA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pedro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Magalh&#227;es</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence of major and minor electrocardiographic abnormalities and their relationship with cardiovascular risk factors in Angolans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">IJC Heart Vasc</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>100965</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijcha.2022.100965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8842030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35198725</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jayed</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Huthi</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Khat chewing induces cardiac arrhythmia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Open Access Library J</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of age, sex, body size and ethnicity with electrocardiographic values in community-based older asian adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Heart Lung Circ</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>705</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>711</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.hlc.2016.01.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26935158</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee&#8208;Lane</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Torabi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lacey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Epilepsy, antiepileptic drugs, and the risk of major cardiovascular events</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsia</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1604</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1616</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/epi.16930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34046890</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Asadollahi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shahidi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ramezani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sheibani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Interictal electrocardiographic alternations in patients with drug-resistant epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Seizure</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.seizure.2018.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30952092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kishk</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sharaf</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ebraheim</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Interictal cardiac repolarization abnormalities in people with epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Behav</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>106</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>111</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2017.10.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29274604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Read</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sammut</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Atenolol offers better protection than clonidine against cardiac injury in kainic acid-induced status epilepticus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br J Pharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>172</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>4626</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4638</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bph.13132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25765931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4594268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Proietti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Farcomeni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goethals</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cost-effectiveness and screening performance of ECG handheld machine in a population screening programme: the Belgian Heart Rhythm Week screening programme</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Prev Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>964</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>972</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2047487319839184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30935219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Prineas</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Crow</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The Minnesota Code Manual of Electrocardiographic Findings</italic></source>. <edition>2nd</edition> ed. Vol. <volume>2</volume>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer Science &amp; Business Media</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <article-title>Defined Daily Dose (DDD)</article-title>; <year>2021</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/tools/atc-ddd-toolkit/about-ddd" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/tools/atc-ddd-toolkit/about-ddd</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>February</month><day>27</day>, 2022</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>St Louis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Truly &#8220;rational&#8221; polytherapy: maximizing efficacy and minimizing drug interactions, drug load, and adverse effects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Neuropharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>96</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>105</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/157015909788848929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19949567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2730011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kwong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>So</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Early predictors of Medical intractability in epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>46</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0887-8994(03)00028-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13679121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <article-title>Physical activity</article-title>; <year>2020</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/physical-activity" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/physical-activity</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>May</month><day>18</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>CDC</collab>. <article-title>Smoking, general concepts</article-title>; <year>2017</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhis/tobacco/tobacco_glossary.htm#:~:text=Every%252520day%252520smoker%25253A%252520An%252520adult.at%252520the%252520time%252520of%252520interview" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhis/tobacco/tobacco_glossary.htm#:~:text=Every%20day%20smoker%3A%20An%20adult.at%20the%20time%20of%20interview</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>May</month><day>18</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abate</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tareke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tirfie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Semachew</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Amare</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ayalew</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chewing khat and risky sexual behavior among residents of Bahir Dar City administration, Northwest Ethiopia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Gen Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12991-018-0194-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5996492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29942341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gudina</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Assegid</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence of hypertension and its risk factors in southwest Ethiopia: a hospital-based cross-sectional survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Integr Blood Press Control</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>117</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IBPC.S47298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23986649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3753877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tumwesigye</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mutungi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bahendeka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Alcohol consumption, hypertension and obesity: relationship patterns along different age groups in Uganda</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prev Med Rep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>101141</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pmedr.2020.101141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32685360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7358719</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <article-title>Obesity and overweight</article-title>; <year>2022</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/obesity-and-overweight" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/obesity-and-overweight</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>May</month><day>18</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The WHO STEPwise Approach to Surveillance</italic></source>. <publisher-name>World Health Organization. Regional Office for Europe</publisher-name>; <year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <article-title>Guide to physical measurements</article-title>; <year>2021</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/ncds/surveillance/steps/Section%2525204%252520Step%2525202%252520Physical%252520Measurements.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/ncds/surveillance/steps/Section%204%20Step%202%20Physical%20Measurements.pdf</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>May</month><day>18</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalences and associated factors of electrocardiographic abnormalities in Chinese adults: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Cardiovasc Disord</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12872-020-01698-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32917144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7488680</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0036"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Awamleh Garc&#237;a</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso Mart&#237;n</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jim&#233;nez Hern&#225;ndez</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Abnormal electrocardiographic findings in the population older than 40 years. prevalence and clinical significance. Results of the OFRECE Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Rev Esp Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>820</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>826</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.recesp.2018.10.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30773471</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0037"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brigo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lochner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nardone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Manganotti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lattanzi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Increased risk of stroke and myocardial infarction in patients with epilepsy: a systematic review of population-based cohort studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Behav</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>106307</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2019.05.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31182394</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0038"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ostrowska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bellwon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adamski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Pathological Q waves as an indicator of prior myocardial infarction in patients with coronary artery disease and diabetes mellitus: a comparison of the prevalence and diagnostic accuracy according to present and former criteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med Res J</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>72</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5603/MRJ.2016.0012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0039"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Katsiki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mikhailidis</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effects of antiepileptic drugs on vascular risk factors: a narrative review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Seizure</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>677</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>684</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.seizure.2014.05.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25028247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0040"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Svalheim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sveberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mochol</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Taub&#248;ll</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Interactions between antiepileptic drugs and hormones</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Seizure</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.seizure.2015.02.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25797888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0041"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dutton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Foldvary&#8208;Schaefer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Contraception in women with epilepsy: pharmacokinetic interactions, contraceptive options, and management</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int Rev Neurobiol</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>134</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18929078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0074-7742(08)00006-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0042"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dos Santos</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stefanon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sex hormones in the cardiovascular system</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Horm Mol Biol Clin Investig</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>89</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>103</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/hmbci-2013-0048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25390005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0043"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Druschky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hilz</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hopp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Interictal cardiac autonomic dysfunction in temporal lobe epilepsy demonstrated by [(123)I]metaiodobenzylguanidine-SPECT</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>124</volume>(<issue>Pt 12</issue>):<fpage>2372</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2382</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/124.12.2372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11701592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0044"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zack</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Luncheon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Adults with an epilepsy history, notably those 45&#8211;64 years old or at the lowest income levels, more often report heart disease than adults without an epilepsy history</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Behav</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>208</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>210</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2018.05.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29908906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6113097</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0045"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Glasscock</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Klassen</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Noebels</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Arrhythmia in heart and brain: KCNQ1 mutations link epilepsy and sudden unexplained death</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Transl Med</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>2ra6</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2ra6</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.3000289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2951754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20368164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0046"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>B&#233;barov&#225;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ho&#345;&#225;kov&#225;</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kula</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Addictive drugs, arrhythmias, and cardiac inward rectifiers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">EP Europace</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>346</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>355</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/europace/euw071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27302393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0047"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Salahuddin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Prabhakaran</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pathophysiological mechanisms of tobacco-related CVD</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Glob Heart</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>113</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>120</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gheart.2012.05.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25691307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0048"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Neunteufl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kostner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Contribution of nicotine to acute endothelial dysfunction in long-term smokers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>251</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>256</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0735-1097(01)01732-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11788216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0049"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McLeish</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shear</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sheth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Privitera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The role of cigarette smoking in epilepsy severity and epilepsy-related quality of life</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Behav</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>38</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2019.01.041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30831400</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0050"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of cigarette smoking on HDL quantity and function: implications for atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cell Biochem</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>114</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2431</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2436</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcb.24581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23852759</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0051"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McMurray</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bo Andersen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The influence of exercise on metabolic syndrome in youth: a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Lifestyle Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>176</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>186</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1559827609351234</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0052"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bacharova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nikolopoulos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zamanis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Krivos&#237;kova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stef&#237;kova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gajdos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A different effect of obesity on ECG in premenopausal and postmenopausal women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Electrocardiol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1085</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1089</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jelectrocard.2018.09.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30497735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0053"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The negative effects of obesity on heart, especially the electrophysiology of the heart</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Artif Cells Nanomed Biotechnol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1055</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1062</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21691401.2020.1770269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32696673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0054"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yildiz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Oktay</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Milani</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ventura</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lavie</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Left ventricular hypertrophy and hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prog Cardiovasc Dis</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>10</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pcad.2019.11.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31759953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0055"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lip</surname><given-names>GYH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Coca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kahan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Hypertension and cardiac arrhythmias: a consensus document from the European Heart Rhythm Association (EHRA) and ESC Council on Hypertension, endorsed by the Heart Rhythm Society (HRS), Asia-Pacific Heart Rhythm Society (APHRS) and Sociedad Latinoamericana de Estimulaci&#243;n Card&#237;aca y Electrofisiolog&#237;a (SOLEACE)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">EP Europace</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>891</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>911</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/europace/eux091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28881872</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0056"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab>. <article-title>Heart disease and mental health disorders</article-title>; <year>2020</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/heartdisease/mentalhealth.htm" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/heartdisease/mentalhealth.htm</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>May</month><day>18</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0057"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Verrier</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nearing</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schachter</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Epileptic Heart: concept and clinical evidence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Behav</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>106946</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2020.106946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32109857</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>