<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">CMAJ Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">CMAJ Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2389</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cmajopen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">cmajo</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>CMAJ Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2291-0026</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Canadian Medical Association</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10558240</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10558240.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10558240</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10558240</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37788865</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9778/cmajo.20230006</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">cmajo.20230006</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>M&#233;tis health in Canada: a scoping review of M&#233;tis-specific health literature</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gmitroski</surname><given-names initials="KL">Krysta-Leigh</given-names></name><degrees>BSc</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastings</surname><given-names initials="KG">Katherine G.</given-names></name><degrees>MPH</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Legault</surname><given-names initials="G">Gabrielle</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbic</surname><given-names initials="S">Skye</given-names></name><degrees>PhD OT</degrees></contrib><aff id="af1-cmajo.20230006">Faculty of Medicine (Gmitroski, Barbic), and School of Population and Public Health (Hastings), University of British Columbia; Foundry (Hastings, Barbic), Vancouver, BC; Department of Community, Culture, and Global Studies (Legault), University of British Columbia Okanagan, Kelowna, BC; Department of Occupational Science and Occupational Therapy (Barbic), University of British Columbia; Providence Research (Barbic); Centre for Health Evaluation &amp; Outcome Sciences (Barbic), Vancouver, BC</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1-cmajo.20230006">Correspondence to: Krysta-Leigh Gmitroski, <email>klgmi@student.ubc.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Sep-Oct</season><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">444841</issue-id><fpage>E884</fpage><lpage>E893</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>09</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>07</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-01-25 19:25:14.493"><day>25</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2023 CMA Impact Inc. or its licensors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>CMA Impact Inc. or its licensors</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0) licence, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided that the original publication is properly cited, the use is noncommercial (i.e., research or educational use), and no modifications or adaptations are made. See: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="cmajo.20230006.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>M&#233;tis are a culturally unique and distinct population, yet little research has evaluated their health separate from the broader Indigenous population. We sought to explore current literature regarding the health of M&#233;tis Peoples in Canada and identify potential trends and gaps.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>Using the Arksey&#8211;O&#8217;Malley, 5-stage, scoping review method, we searched PubMed, MEDLINE, iPortal Indigenous Articles Portal Research Tool and pertinent reference lists using the terms &#8220;M&#233;tis,&#8221; &#8220;health&#8221; and &#8220;Canada.&#8221; Two reviewers conducted the initial searches independently, including English articles from 2012 to 2022, and focused on only M&#233;tis populations&#8217; health within Canada. We described characteristics of the articles and themes for discussion.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Of the 572 articles we identified, we included a total of 28 articles in this scoping review, of which 16 were quantitative, 9 were qualitative and 3 used mixed methods. Thirteen articles used consultation with M&#233;tis communities as part of their methods, and 8 extracted data from national surveys. One article focused on children, while all other articles focused on adults. Nine articles used data from across Canada, 6 were based in Ontario, 5 in Alberta and 4 each in British Columbia and Manitoba. Themes included health, well-being and spirituality; mental health and substance use; health conditions and risk factors; access to adequate health resources; and experiences in health care.</p></sec><sec><title>Interpretation:</title><p>M&#233;tis-specific health research is lacking in Canada, with a gap in volume, subject matter and diversity in the demographics studied. This review illustrates the need for more research with strong community engagement to further explore M&#233;tis health and health service needs.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>The M&#233;tis are 1 of 3 federally recognized Indigenous Peoples in Canada, with ancestral ties to First Nations of the Red River region and fur traders in the late 18th century.<xref rid="b1-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> M&#233;tis Peoples make up over one-third of the 1.7 million Indigenous Peoples in Canada and almost 2% of Canada&#8217;s entire population.<xref rid="b2-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> The M&#233;tis are a distinct Indigenous group &#8212; with their own culture, traditions, language, nationhood and way of life &#8212; who have faced ongoing impacts of colonialism in Canada, including forced removal of children to residential and mission schools, overrepresentation of M&#233;tis children in the child welfare system and land displacement strategies that have attempted to disconnect M&#233;tis from their lands.<xref rid="b1-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="b3-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="b5-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> M&#233;tis populations continually experience jurisdictional gaps in Canada, with many funded programs for Indigenous Peoples specifically including First Nations groups and excluding M&#233;tis.<xref rid="b4-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="b6-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> M&#233;tis also face federal exclusion from the Non-Insured Health Benefits program, a federal government program that entitles registered First Nations and Inuit Peoples to some health benefits regarding prescription drugs, counselling, medical equipment and dental care.<xref rid="b7-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="b8-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Literature suggests that M&#233;tis people, like other Indigenous groups, have poorer health outcomes than the general Canadian population, while also occupying a unique space of feeling caught between general and First Nations&#8211;specific services.<xref rid="b9-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></p><p>Most of the literature available on Indigenous health aggregates health outcomes among First Nations, Inuit and M&#233;tis Peoples into a homogenous group.<xref rid="b10-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> As each group is culturally distinct, there is a need to explore each community and Nation individually. For M&#233;tis Peoples in particular, previous work has suggested that they can feel excluded and discriminated against in mainstream and Indigenous-specific health services.<xref rid="b3-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> It is therefore imperative to scan the existing literature to better understand the needs of M&#233;tis communities and improve their experiences accessing health care services. <xref rid="b9-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="b11-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> M&#233;tis Peoples are often excluded from dedicated research, so this scoping review offers a unique opportunity to examine the health and breadth of health services and experiences among M&#233;tis Peoples living in Canada. Findings from this review may unmask potential health disparities faced by this specific population and support the ongoing effort to disaggregate heterogenous groups at an individual community level, from unique M&#233;tis communities as we discuss here, but also individual First Nations and Inuit communities.</p><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Study design</title><p>This study design is based on the guidelines outlined by Arksey and O&#8217;Malley<xref rid="b12-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> and further characterized by Levac and colleagues,<xref rid="b13-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> and the PRISMA Extension for Scoping Reviews.<xref rid="b14-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Accordingly, we identified the research question, identified relevant articles, selected the articles; charted data and collated and reported data. Our primary research question was, &#8220;What is currently known about M&#233;tis health and health services in Canada, and what gaps in knowledge exist?&#8221;</p></sec><sec><title>Eligibility criteria</title><p>We selected articles that were focused on only M&#233;tis populations&#8217; health in Canada. We excluded all articles with a broader focus that included other Indigenous communities (e.g., First Nations, Inuit). With a focus on contemporary literature and the ethical principles of the Tri-Council Policy Statement 2, we then selected only articles that were published between 2012 and 2022. We excluded systematic reviews, scoping reviews, editorials, commentaries, guidelines, policies, and other grey literature, in favour of focusing on peer-reviewed primary literature. Although systematic and scoping reviews were excluded,<xref rid="b15-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="b18-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> we scanned reference lists in these reviews for eligible articles. We also excluded any non-English language articles.<xref rid="b19-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></p></sec><sec><title>Search strategy</title><p>We conducted a comprehensive search, including published references, of articles published from January 2012 to December 2022. We used PubMed, MEDLINE, iPortal Indigenous Articles Portal Research Tool and relevant reference lists with the search terms &#8220;M&#233;tis&#8221;, &#8220;health&#8221; and &#8220;Canada.&#8221; One author and M&#233;tis scholar (G.L.) identified additional sources based on expertise. We conducted searches in May 2022 and again April 2023. We consulted a librarian with expertise in health research to guide strategy development. The full search strategy for PubMed is provided in the Appendix 1, available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.cmajopen.ca/content/11/5/E884/suppl/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">www.cmajopen.ca/content/11/5/E884/suppl/DC1</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Study selection and quality appraisal</title><p>Two reviewers (K.-L.G., K.G.H.) independently screened and selected titles and abstracts from peer-reviewed articles, and 1 additional reviewer with context expertise (G.L.) reviewed the list of articles and hand-picked any additional article that fit the study criteria (2 articles added). A spreadsheet was shared among reviewers, and 2 reviewers (K.-L.G., K.G.H.) independently extracted data. Two reviewers (K.-L.G., K.G.H.) then undertook a full-text review and revised the list of included articles until they reached full agreement. Reviewers resolved inconsistencies or disagreements in inclusion through discussion and with involvement of a third reviewer (S.B.).</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Data analysis</title><p>We coded articles in Microsoft Excel according to article metrics decided by the reviewers. We extracted information on methodology, study aims (as defined by the authors), location, participant ages, findings, implications, use of community consultation (i.e., consultations with the relevant communities in study design, in execution or in contextualizing extracted data, such as creating an advisory panel, partnering with a M&#233;tis organization or other forms of consultation with M&#233;tis communities) and use of national data (e.g., Census data, Aboriginal Peoples Survey), as described by Levac and colleagues.<xref rid="b12-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> If article methodology primarily involved interviews, focus groups or talking circles, and the main findings were presented as themes, then we defined the article&#8217;s methods as qualitative. If the methodology primarily focused on metrics such as extracted records or cross-sectional methods evaluating prevalence rates and quantifiable data, we defined the article as quantitative. If both elements were incorporated, we defined it as mixed methods.</p><p>After extracting these predetermined fields, each reviewer (K.-L.G., K.G.H.) assigned a main topic and message to each article, which were grouped into overarching themes that relate to aspects of M&#233;tis health and discussed by reviewers until consensus was achieved on a final set of themes. We resolved disagreements on identified themes by formal discussion until consensus was reached. We tallied themes by each article in Excel.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethics approval</title><p>The review did not involve human subjects research and therefore did not require ethics approval by our institutional review board.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>The search yielded 574 entries from PubMed, MEDLINE, and iPortal, and the content expert. After applying the inclusion and exclusion criteria, we identified 28 unique articles for the final analysis.<xref rid="b20-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="b45-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>
<xref rid="f1-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> illustrates the search results.</p><fig position="float" id="f1-cmajo.20230006" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1:</label><caption><p>Search results.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="cmajo.20230006f1.jpg"/></fig><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methodology of selected articles</title><p><xref rid="t1-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> illustrates the characteristics for each selected article. Collation and summary of included articles revealed interesting trends in M&#233;tis-related research. Of the 28 articles, 16 were quantitative, 9 were qualitative and 3 used mixed methods. Quantitative articles covered vast topics, but tended to lean toward health conditions and risk factors. The qualitative articles largely centred on mental health and substance use; health, well-being and spirituality; and M&#233;tis experience in health care services. The mixed-methods articles focused on access to health services and on health, well-being and spirituality.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="t1-cmajo.20230006" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1:</label><caption><p>Description of selected studies for scoping review on M&#233;tis health in Canada from 2012 to 2022<xref rid="tfn1-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></p></caption><table frame="box" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author and year</th><th valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type</th><th valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location</th><th valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study aims</th><th valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, yr</th><th valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Main findings</th><th valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Consultation with communities</th><th valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Used national survey data</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anderson et al. 2017<xref rid="b15-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine gender and sense of community belonging influences on sedentary behaviour</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adults, ages unspecified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community belonging among M&#233;tis men may reduce sedentary behaviour, but increased community belonging among M&#233;tis women may increase sedentary behaviour.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atzema et al. 2015<xref rid="b16-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ontario</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To determine rates of cardiovascular diseases in M&#233;tis population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unspecified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiovascular disease was higher among M&#233;tis people than the general population; the prevalence of 5 cardiovascular conditions was 25%&#8211;77% higher.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Auger 2019<xref rid="b3-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qualitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">British Columbia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To contribute to an increased understanding of M&#233;tis Peoples&#8217; experiences in mental health and wellness</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8211;84 (mean 46)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mental health is a priority for M&#233;tis people in British Columbia, and there is a need for increased access to culturally responsive health care.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Auger 2021<xref rid="b17-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qualitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">British Columbia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explores M&#233;tis Peoples&#8217; experiences and conceptualizations of mental health and cultural continuity</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805; 19</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Identified themes of M&#233;tis stories of culture, identity and mental health; the importance of community; and intergenerational knowledge transmission.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carri&#232;re et al. 2017<xref rid="b18-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To describe hospital admissions for ambulatory care&#8211;sensitive conditions among urban M&#233;tis adults relative to non-Aboriginal adults</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8211;74</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The age-standardized rates of hospital admission for ambulatory care&#8211;sensitive conditions among urban M&#233;tis adults were twice that of non-Aboriginal adults. These admissions were for diabetes or chronic obstructive pulmonary disease.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cooke et al. 2013<xref rid="b19-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine the socioeconomic, behavioural and M&#233;tis-specific factors that predict obesity among M&#233;tis children</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#8211;14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">An estimated 18.5% of M&#233;tis boys and 14.4% of M&#233;tis girls were obese. Risk factors included living in a lone-parent family, living in rural areas, and having a caregiver with a history with residential schooling. The effects were negative among older girls.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cooper et al. 2020<xref rid="b20-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qualitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manitoba</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To identify current supports, needs and expectations of unpaid M&#233;tis caregivers caring for M&#233;tis seniors</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adults, ages unspecified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Need to have tools in place to help people age and to care for aging family members in a culturally responsive manner.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Driedger et al. 2014<xref rid="b21-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed methods</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manitoba</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To evaluate the 2009/10 H1N1 influenza pandemic door-to-door risk communication campaign that focused on at-risk M&#233;tis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8211;65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This intervention ultimately did not meet its intended goals. Efforts can be made during interpandemic periods to build on established relationships, learn from past experiences and develop new solutions.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Driedger et al. 2015<xref rid="b22-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qualitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manitoba</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To connect vaccine behaviour with the attitudes and beliefs that influenced M&#233;tis study participants&#8217; H1N1 influenza vaccine decision-making</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adults, ages unspecified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The negatively influential factors were lack of knowledge about the vaccine and the pandemic, as well as concerns about vaccine safety. Risk of contracting H1N1 was the biggest positively influencing factor.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gershon et al. 2014<xref rid="b23-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ontario</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To measure and compare burden of asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease between M&#233;tis and non-M&#233;tis populations</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adults (asthma &#8805; 20 yr, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease &#8805; 35 yr)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence of asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease were 30% and 70% higher, respectively, among M&#233;tis people. Lower rates of physician visits suggested barriers in access to primary care services.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ginn et al. 2021<xref rid="b24-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qualitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alberta</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore links among health, spirituality and well-being for M&#233;tis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28&#8211;80</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Connection between ancestry, land, community and tradition contributed to well-being.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hayward et al. 2017<xref rid="b25-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ontario</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To compare the prevalence of chronic kidney disease and incidence of acute kidney injury and end-stage kidney disease among registered M&#233;tis citizens to general population</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805; 18</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence of chronic kidney disease was lightly higher among M&#233;tis citizens compared with the general population.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hutchinson et al. 2014<xref rid="b26-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed methods</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">British Columbia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To investigate health benefits of participating in cultural activities (e.g., harvesting) and demonstrate how applying mixed methods meets and informs these research standards and creates a unique, participatory Indigenous research method relevant for M&#233;tis People</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unspecified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Details of the physical benefits of participating in the traditional activity of hunting, while also describing the holistic health and well-being benefits related to harvesting among the M&#233;tis People.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jandoc et al. 2015<xref rid="b27-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ontario</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine osteoporosis management and common osteoporosis-related fractures among M&#233;tis citizens compared with the general population of older adults residing in Ontario</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Older adults (&gt; 50 yr and &gt; 65 yr)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Identified significantly lower sex-specific and age-standardized rates of bone mineral density testing among M&#233;tis people compared with the general population, but found little difference in fracture rates (both sexes) or pharmacotherapy (females only). They found age-standardized fracture rates for M&#233;tis people were similar to those of the general population.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kaspar 2014<xref rid="b28-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore link between suicidal ideation and major depressive episode among M&#233;tis who were fostered v. not fostered</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adults, ages unspecified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">More than one-third of emancipated respondents reported a past-year major depressive episode, a prevalence rate nearly 50% higher than the rate of major depressive episodes among M&#233;tis respondents without a history of placement in foster care. The 25% lifetime prevalence rate of suicidal ideation in the emancipated group was more than twice the rate observed in the non-fostered group.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">King et al. 2022<xref rid="b29-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed methods</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alberta</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To describe the unique approach in implementing Canada&#8217;s first M&#233;tis-led SARS-CoV-2 immunization clinic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unspecified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thirteen hundred people were vaccinated. Visitors shared appreciation for the culturally specific aspects of the clinic, which contributed to increased safety and comfort.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kumar et al. 2012<sup>30&#8217;</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To determine the prevalence of suicidal ideation among M&#233;tis people and identify its associated risk and protective factors</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#8211;59</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence of suicidal ideation was higher among M&#233;tis men than men who did not report Aboriginal identity. M&#233;tis women were more likely to report suicidal ideation than M&#233;tis men (14.9% v. 11.5%, respectively).</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Landy et al. 2022<xref rid="b31-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qualitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alberta</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore the experiences of M&#233;tis community members participating in dried blood spot testing for HIV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adults, unspecified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Four broad themes related to the participants&#8217; experiences included ease of process, overcoming logistical challenges associated with existing testing, reducing stigma through health role models and events, and M&#233;tis-specific services.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mazereeuw et al. 2018<xref rid="b32-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To estimate site-specific incidence rates and survival for the most common cancers among M&#233;tis people</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#8211;99</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incidence was significantly higher among M&#233;tis adults than among non-Aboriginal adults for lung, liver, larynx, gallbladder, cervix and female breast cancers. M&#233;tis people had poorer survival for prostate cancer. For all cancers and both sexes combined, cancer incidence was similar for M&#233;tis and non-Aboriginal adults.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monchalin et al. 2020<xref rid="b11-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qualitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ontario</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To learn from M&#233;tis women&#8217;s experiences to build an understanding on steps toward filling the health service gap</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adults, ages unspecified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M&#233;tis women experienced racial discrimination such as witnessing, absorbing and facing racism in mainstream service settings, as well as lateral violence and discrimination in Indigenous-specific services.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monchalin et al. 2019<xref rid="b33-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qualitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ontario</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To gather recommendations made by urban M&#233;tis women for improving access to health and social services in Toronto, Canada</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805; 15</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recommendations include M&#233;tis presence, holistic interior design, M&#233;tis-specific or informed service space, welcoming reception or front desk and culturally informed service providers.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nickel et al. 2022<xref rid="b34-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manitoba</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine patterns of prescription opioid dispensing among Red River M&#233;tis and compare them to other residents of Manitoba</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M&#233;tis were more likely to live in lower-income, rural areas and were more likely to have received a diagnosis of a mood, anxiety or substance use disorder in the previous 5 years. Rates of opioid prescription dispensing were consistently higher than the general Manitoba population.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ramage-Morin and Bougie 2017<xref rid="b35-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To better understand family networks and self-perceived general and mental health among M&#233;tis people</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805; 45</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strong family networks were associated with positive self-perceived general and mental health among M&#233;tis adults.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ryan et al. 2015<xref rid="b36-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine the correlates of current smoking among M&#233;tis with a particular focus on culturally specific factors</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805; 18</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The article found 39.9% of adult M&#233;tis respondents in the sample were current smokers. Adult M&#233;tis who reported a high level of spirituality were less likely to be current smokers. Those who spoke an Indigenous language, or who lived in a house where one was spoken, were more likely to be current smokers.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ryan et al. 2018<xref rid="b37-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To investigate correlates of leisure-time physical activity and active transportation (walking) among adult M&#233;tis, with a focus on culturally specific variables</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#8211;64</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Having attended a M&#233;tis cultural event in the previous year was positively associated with leisure-time physical activity, as was a high level of spirituality.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sanchez-Ramirez et al. 2016<xref rid="b38-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alberta</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore cancer incidence and mortality burden among M&#233;tis and to compare disease estimates with non-M&#233;tis populations</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages based on Alberta registry</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A higher incidence of bronchus or lung cancer was found among M&#233;tis men. No other statistically significant differences in cancer incidence or mortality were found between M&#233;tis and non-M&#233;tis groups.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sanchez-Ramirez et al. 2019<xref rid="b39-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alberta</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine injury-related health service use, defined as hospital admissions and emergency department visits, as well as mortality among M&#233;tis People in Alberta</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adults, ages unspecified</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Injury-related hospital admissions were 35% higher for M&#233;tis than non-M&#233;tis people; injuries were a concern among M&#233;tis people.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wesche 2013<xref rid="b40-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qualitative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">British Columbia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine links between M&#233;tis identity and health and well-being for M&#233;tis women at risk of sexual exploitation</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#8211;54</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M&#233;tis identity and well-being were strongly linked. Many M&#233;tis women reported negative experiences in accessing a range of both Aboriginal and mainstream services because of perceived prejudice. M&#233;tis-specific or M&#233;tis-inclusive services were desired but currently limited.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1-cmajo.20230006"><label>*</label><p>Please note that the term &#8220;Aboriginal&#8221; is only used as a consistency of how it was reported in studies. We note our preference for the language to be Indigenous.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Of the 28 articles, 13 described consultation with the community for study design or contextualization of data, which is critical in research involving Indigenous communities in Canada, as outlined by First Nations principles of Ownership, Control, Access, and Possession (OCAP) and guidance from the Canadian Institutes of Health Research.<xref rid="b46-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="b47-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> Qualitative and mixed-methods articles had strong engagement with M&#233;tis communities throughout their methodology, whereas only 1 quantitative article included engagement with community. Eight articles used data from national level surveys, such as the Aboriginal Peoples or the Canadian Census, and did not involve any community engagement in the extraction, analysis or interpretation of the data.</p></sec><sec><title>Location of selected articles</title><p>We mapped representative geographical regions for each article. Nine articles reflected Canada-wide data and did not break down results according to geographic region. Six articles represented Ontario-specific M&#233;tis populations, 2 of which focused on the Toronto area. Five articles focused on Alberta, 4 focused on British Columbia and 4 focused on Manitoba. There were no dedicated articles for any other province or territory.</p></sec><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Ages of participants</title><p>Although all selected articles focused on M&#233;tis populations in Canada, only 1 article specifically investigated children and youth, based on how caregivers responded in the 2006 Aboriginal Peoples Survey with respect to their child. Two articles focused on an age range that included adults and children; 20 of the selected articles involved only adults, 1 focused only on older adults and the remaining 4 did not specify ages of participants in their methods.</p></sec><sec><title>Identified themes</title><p>We analyzed the selected articles for themes based on the topic matter, with 5 themes generated, namely health, well-being and spirituality; mental health and substance use; health conditions and risk factors; access to adequate health resources; and experiences in health care. These are summarized and described in <xref rid="t2-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="t2-cmajo.20230006" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2:</label><caption><p>Themes emerged from data coding analysis stage, accompanied by theme definitions and summaries<xref rid="tfn2-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></p></caption><table frame="box" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Theme</th><th valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Summary</th><th valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health, well-being and spirituality</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Topics included belonging, community, connectedness to culture and M&#233;tis identity, and how these related to overall well-being and health.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="b3-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="b15-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="b17-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="b24-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="b26-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="b35-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="b37-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="b40-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mental health and substance use</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mental health issues included major depressive disorder, suicidal ideation, suicide attempts, suicide and posttraumatic stress disorder. Substance use issues included opioid prescription dispensing and smoking.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="b3-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="b17-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="b28-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="b30-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="b34-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="b36-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health conditions and risk factors</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Articles examined the prevalence, risk factors or inequities in physical health outcomes, including cardiovascular disease, obesity, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, cancer, osteoporosis and fractures, chronic kidney disease and smoking.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="b16-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="b19-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="b23-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="b25-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="b27-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="b32-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="b36-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="b38-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Access to adequate health resources</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Included reasons for health care access including hospital admissions and ambulatory care, and resource needs for aging population. Articles also included vaccine campaigns to promote awareness and accessibility around vaccines.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="b18-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="b20-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="b22-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="b29-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="b39-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experience in health care</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This theme focused on how M&#233;tis communities felt about accessing various health services and how those services could be improved to feel more welcoming to M&#233;tis Peoples.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref rid="b11-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="b31-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="b33-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn2-cmajo.20230006"><label>*</label><p>Codes and themes were created based on an inductive and iterative process. Topics were not mutually exclusive and articles often fell under more than 1 of the themes.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The main findings of the included articles are summarized in <xref rid="t1-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Several articles focused on health-related outcomes, such as prevalence of diseases (e.g., cancer) or incidence of smoking, and found that health outcomes for M&#233;tis populations in the regions identified tended to be worse than for non-Indigenous populations. In qualitative articles where M&#233;tis perspectives and experiences were sought, the key message included that M&#233;tis people felt they faced discrimination in both Indigenous and non-Indigenous service streams and a need for more M&#233;tis-specific and culturally sensitive services. Several articles linked strengths in the health and well-being of M&#233;tis people to their support network, cultural connectedness and spirituality.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Interpretation</title><p>This scoping review aimed to investigate the current literature on M&#233;tis-specific health and health services in Canada, and to identify potential gaps and trends in knowledge. Overall, we identified 28 peer-reviewed articles published in the last decade that focused specifically on M&#233;tis Peoples. We generated 5 prominent themes from these articles, namely health, well-being and spirituality; mental health and substance use; health conditions and risk factors; access to adequate health resources; and experiences in health care. More than half (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 16) of the articles used quantitative methods, many of which drew from large, national-level surveys; 9 articles were qualitative and 13 consulted with M&#233;tis communities during the process. Most articles focused on adult populations, and both pan-Canadian and provincial focuses were present, although some regions were missing, notably Saskatchewan.</p><p>Our findings build on the previous work of Kumar and colleagues,<xref rid="b48-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> which reviewed trends in M&#233;tis health literature in 1980&#8211;2009. Kumar and colleagues noted strengths in the literature, such as an increase in M&#233;tis-specific research from 1980 to 2009, a focus on a variety of health concerns (although these were largely physical health and risk factors), inclusion of both rural and urban M&#233;tis communities and an increase in the number of qualitative studies. They also noted many gaps in research including mental health and gender-specific literature, as well as work related to environment, genetics, policy and social determinants. Our review shows a continuation of many of these trends, including more research dedicated to M&#233;tis Peoples, more qualitative work and an increasing focus on mental health and substance use.</p><p>One of the primary gaps identified in our review included appropriate representation of M&#233;tis Peoples. According to 2016 Census data, M&#233;tis people reside in all provinces and territories, with most living in the provinces of Ontario, Alberta, Manitoba and BC.<xref rid="b2-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> The geographic breakdown of the identified articles reflects this, but notably lacks representation in other areas where M&#233;tis reside, such as Saskatchewan. In addition, there is a notable gap in the recent literature around diverse subpopulations of M&#233;tis Peoples. Only 1 identified article investigated children and adolescents, based on the 2006 Aboriginal Peoples Survey responses by their caregivers. <xref rid="b24-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> No articles sought the perspectives of M&#233;tis youth, although youth aged 15&#8211;24 years make up 16% of the M&#233;tis population in Canada.<xref rid="b49-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> Similarly, no literature explored the perspectives of M&#233;tis Elders, M&#233;tis identifying as part of 2SLGBTQIA+ communities or M&#233;tis people with disabilities. These subpopulations are likely to include unique perspectives and experiences with respect to their health and well-being.</p><p>A recurring issue among many articles in this review involved concerns around data quality, given reliance on potentially problematic sources. Nearly half of the selected articles used data from national surveys such as the 2006 Aboriginal Peoples Survey. Although this approach has some merit, namely in the volume and accessibility of data, these same articles did not participate in community consultations and lacked the perspective of the very communities they studied to help contextualize the findings or describe challenges that the Aboriginal Peoples Survey poses. There are also ethical considerations in using these types of data without community input regarding ownership and control of the data, as outlined in the First Nations principles of OCAP, as well guidance from the Canadian Institutes of Health Research and the M&#233;tis centre at the National Aboriginal History Organization.<xref rid="b46-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="b47-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="b50-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> There are challenges with using M&#233;tis data from these sources as they allow respondents to self-identify, which results in data stemming from both the culturally distinct M&#233;tis Peoples, as we have described thus far, and people who interpret M&#233;tis to broadly mean &#8220;of mixed Indigenous and European ancestry,&#8221; which skews the data collection and results.<xref rid="b51-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> However, the amount of research that meaningfully consults with M&#233;tis community members has increased, resulting in rich data that uncover the nuanced experiences of being M&#233;tis and actionable feedback that is relevant to improving health services for M&#233;tis Peoples.<xref rid="b52-cmajo.20230006" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></p><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>This review did not include a search of grey literature, which could have provided additional findings and trends worth noting. We excluded literature that evaluated multiple Indigenous communities and presented M&#233;tis data as potentially disaggregated; however, this was intentional to avoid overlapping messaging among several Indigenous communities, which may have biased results, was deemed out of scope and was against our purpose of focusing on completely disaggregated data, dedicated to only M&#233;tis outcomes. We did not include non-English language articles in the review (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1), given the high cost of professional translation services and time commitment required. We recognize that this may potentially bias our results, exclude key findings or limit the generalizability of our findings.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Findings suggest a lack of M&#233;tis-specific research in Canada, but that there is an overall increase in the number of studies on this topic. Nearly half of these articles were data extractions from large surveys and lacked elements of community engagement in their methodology, thus potentially excluding key perspectives and contextualization of findings. The themes of mental health and substance use and of health, well-being and spirituality were prominent over the last decade, suggesting a priority area of research and intervention. This review highlights the need to continue health research dedicated to and collaborating with diverse M&#233;tis communities and M&#233;tis subpopulations so that health services can be improved to be more accessible and welcoming to M&#233;tis Peoples, and so that dedicated health services can be tailored to the needs of M&#233;tis Peoples.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Appendix 1</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="open-2023-0006-1-at.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="PMC_2" content-type="local-data" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Reviewer comments</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="open-2023-0006-reviewer-comments.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="PMC_3" content-type="local-data" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Original submision</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="open-2023-0006-original-submission.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="PMC_4" content-type="local-data" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>PRISMA checklist</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="open-2023-0006-prisma-checklist.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="fn1-cmajo.20230006" fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> None declared.</p></fn><fn id="fn2-cmajo.20230006"><p>This article has been peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn id="fn3-cmajo.20230006"><p><bold>Contributors:</bold> Krysta-Leigh Gmitroski is a M&#233;tis medical student and citizen of both the Manitoba M&#233;tis Federation and M&#233;tis Nation British Columbia; she conceived and designed the study. All of the authors contributed to data acquisition, analysis and interpretation. Krysta-Leigh Gmitroski and Katherine Hastings drafted the manuscript. All of the authors revised it critically for important intellectual content, gave final approval of the version to be published and agreed to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p></fn><fn id="fn4-cmajo.20230006" fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This study was not funded.</p></fn><fn id="fn5-cmajo.20230006"><p><bold>Data sharing:</bold> This review used aggregate, published data that are publicly available. No additional data are available for sharing.</p></fn><fn id="fn6-cmajo.20230006"><p><bold>Supplemental information:</bold> For reviewer comments and the original submission of this manuscript, please see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.cmajopen.ca/content/11/5/E884/suppl/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">www.cmajopen.ca/content/11/5/E884/suppl/DC1</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-cmajo.20230006"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>About</source><publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc><publisher-name>M&#233;tis National Council</publisher-name><comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://archive.ph/2l5jk" ext-link-type="uri">https://archive.ph/2l5jk</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2022 May 17</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2-cmajo.20230006"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>Aboriginal Peoples highlight tables, 2016 Census</source><publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Statistics Canada</publisher-name><comment>modified 2020 Oct 2 Available<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2016/dp-pd/hlt-fst/abo-aut/Table.cfm?Lang=Eng&amp;T=101&amp;S=99&amp;O=A" ext-link-type="uri">https://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2016/dp-pd/hlt-fst/abo-aut/Table.cfm?Lang=Eng&amp;T=101&amp;S=99&amp;O=A</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2022 May 12</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3-cmajo.20230006"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Auger</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#8216;We need to not be footnotes anymore&#8217;: Understanding M&#233;tis people&#8217;s experiences with mental health and wellness in British Columbia, Canada</article-title><source>Public Health</source><year>2019</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30678887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.puhe.2018.12.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4-cmajo.20230006"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Settler colonialism in Canada and the M&#233;tis</article-title><source>J Genocide Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>52</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5-cmajo.20230006"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiola</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><source>Rekindling the sacred fire M&#233;tis ancestry and Anishinaabe spirituality</source><edition>1st ed</edition><publisher-loc>Winnipeg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Manitoba Press</publisher-name><year>2015</year><comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;scope=site&amp;db=nlebk&amp;AN=1234268" ext-link-type="uri">https://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;scope=site&amp;db=nlebk&amp;AN=1234268</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2022 May 17</date-in-citation><comment>Login required to access content</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6-cmajo.20230006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waldram</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herring</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><source>Aboriginal health in Canada: historical, cultural, and epidemiological perspectives</source><edition>2nd ed</edition><publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name><year>2006</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>367</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7-cmajo.20230006"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>First Nations and Inuit Health Branch</collab><source>Non-Insured Health Benefits program: annual report 2018/2019</source><publisher-name>Indigenous Services Canada</publisher-name><comment>modified 2020 May 20. Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.sac-isc.gc.ca/eng/1584392581890/1584393350542" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.sac-isc.gc.ca/eng/1584392581890/1584393350542</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2022 June 3</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8-cmajo.20230006"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smylie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>First Peoples, second class treatment: the role of racism in the health and well-being of Indigenous peoples in Canada</source><publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wellesley Institute</publisher-name><year>2015</year><comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.wellesleyinstitute.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Summary-First-Peoples-Second-Class-Treatment-Final.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.wellesleyinstitute.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Summary-First-Peoples-Second-Class-Treatment-Final.pdf</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2022 May 20</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9-cmajo.20230006"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smylie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan-Myrth</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Knowledge translation and indigenous knowledge</article-title><source>Int J Circumpolar Health</source><year>2004</year><volume>63</volume><issue>Suppl 2</issue><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15736639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3402/ijch.v63i0.17877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10-cmajo.20230006"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>M&#233;tis peoples and cancer: a scoping review of literature, programs, policies and educational material in Canada</article-title><source>Curr Oncol</source><year>2021</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>5101</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34940068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/curroncol28060429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8700482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11-cmajo.20230006"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monchalin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smylie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowgesic</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#8220;I guess i shouldn&#8217;t come back here&#8221;: racism and discrimination as a barrier to accessing health and social services for urban M&#233;tis women in Toronto, Canada</article-title><source>J Racial Ethn Health Disparities</source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31664676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40615-019-00653-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12-cmajo.20230006"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arksey</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Malley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scoping studies: towards a methodological framework</article-title><source>Int J Soc Res Methodol</source><year>2005</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13-cmajo.20230006"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levac</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colquhoun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Brien</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scoping studies: advancing the methodology</article-title><source>Implement Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>69</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20854677</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1748-5908-5-69</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2954944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14-cmajo.20230006"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tricco</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zarin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PRISMA extension for scoping reviews (PRISMA-ScR): checklist and explanation</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30178033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7326/M18-0850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15-cmajo.20230006"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mental health of Indigenous peoples in Canada: a critical review of research</article-title><source>Soc Sci Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28135694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.socscimed.2017.01.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16-cmajo.20230006"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wesche</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trends in M&#233;tis-related health research (1980&#8211;2009): identification of research gaps</article-title><source>Can J Public Health</source><year>2012</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22338324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF03404064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6974209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17-cmajo.20230006"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foulds</surname><given-names>HJA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shubair</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warburton</surname><given-names>DER</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review of the cardiometabolic risk experience among Canadian Metis populations</article-title><source>Can J Cardiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1006</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23465285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cjca.2012.11.029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18-cmajo.20230006"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>M&#233;tis peoples and cancer: a scoping review of literature, programs, policies and educational material in Canada</article-title><source>Curr Oncol</source><year>2021</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>5101</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34940068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/curroncol28060429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8700482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19-cmajo.20230006"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>La sant&#233; des Premi&#232;res nations, des Inuits et des M&#233;tis: les facteurs que doivent envisager les leaders en sant&#233; canadiens dans la foul&#233;e du rapport de la Commission de v&#233;rit&#233; et r&#233;conciliation du Canada</article-title><source>Healthc Manage Forum</source><year>2017</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28929884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0840470417695453</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20-cmajo.20230006"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Community belonging and sedentary behaviour among M&#233;tis Canadians: a gendered analysis</article-title><source>Int J Indig Health</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>14</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b21-cmajo.20230006"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atzema</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardiovascular disease rates, outcomes, and quality of care in Ontario M&#233;tis: a population-based cohort study</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0121779</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25793978</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0121779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4368556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b22-cmajo.20230006"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Auger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#8220;The strengths of our community and our culture&#8221;: cultural continuity as a determinant of mental health for M&#233;tis People in British Columbia</article-title><source>Turt Isl J Indig Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jps.library.utoronto.ca/index.php/tijih/article/view/36046" ext-link-type="uri">https://jps.library.utoronto.ca/index.php/tijih/article/view/36046</ext-link> (accessed 2022 May 6)</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b23-cmajo.20230006"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carri&#232;re</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanmartin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hospitalization for ambulatory care sensitive conditions among urban M&#233;tis adults</article-title><source>Health Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29261222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b24-cmajo.20230006"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predictors of obesity among M&#233;tis children: socio-economic, behavioural and cultural factors</article-title><source>Can J Public Health</source><year>2013</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>e298</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24044469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.17269/cjph.104.3765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6973954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b25-cmajo.20230006"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanguins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menec</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Culturally responsive supports for Metis Elders and Metis family caregivers</article-title><source>Can J Aging</source><year>2020</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>206</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31309912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/S0714980819000321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b26-cmajo.20230006"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Driedger</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanguins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pandemic H1N1 targeted messaging for Manitoba Metis: an evaluation of a risk communication intervention</article-title><source>Aborig Policy Stud</source><year>2014</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://journals.library.ualberta.ca/aps/index.php/aps/article/view/20022" ext-link-type="uri">https://journals.library.ualberta.ca/aps/index.php/aps/article/view/20022</ext-link> (accessed 2022 May 2)</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b27-cmajo.20230006"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Driedger</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Furgal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors influencing H1N1 vaccine behavior among Manitoba Metis in Canada: a qualitative study</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>128</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25884562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12889-015-1482-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4334920</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b28-cmajo.20230006"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gershon</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein-Geltink</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) prevalence and health services use in Ontario M&#233;tis: a population-based cohort study</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e95899</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24760036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0095899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3997509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b29-cmajo.20230006"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ginn</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ginn</surname><given-names>CWC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gervais</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exploring M&#233;tis health, spirituality and well-being: a patient-oriented community-based qualitative study with the M&#233;tis Nation of Alberta &#8212; Region 3</article-title><source>CMAJ Open</source><year>2021</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>E451</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.9778/cmajo.20200018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8101638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33888550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b30-cmajo.20230006"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McArthur</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Kidney disease among registered M&#233;tis citizens of Ontario: a population-based cohort study</article-title><source>Can J Kidney Health Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>2054358117703071</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2054358117703071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28491337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5406217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b31-cmajo.20230006"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dingwall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurtz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Maintaining the integrity of Indigenous knowledge; sharing Metis knowing through mixed methods</article-title><source>International Journal of Critical Indigenous Studies</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b32-cmajo.20230006"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jandoc</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jembere</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Osteoporosis management and fractures in the M&#233;tis of Ontario, Canada</article-title><source>Arch Osteoporos</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>12</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25910866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11657-015-0212-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4412654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b33-cmajo.20230006"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaspar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term depression and suicidal ideation outcomes subsequent to emancipation from foster care: pathways to psychiatric risk in the M&#233;tis population</article-title><source>Psychiatry Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>215</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24373554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.psychres.2013.09.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b34-cmajo.20230006"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Practice report: an Alberta M&#233;tis model for COVID-19 vaccine delivery</article-title><source>Can J Public Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34988925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.17269/s41997-021-00603-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8730752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b35-cmajo.20230006"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walls</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Suicidal ideation among M&#233;tis adult men and women &#8212; associated risk and protective factors: findings from a nationally representative survey</article-title><source>Int J Circumpolar Health</source><year>2012</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>18829</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22901287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3402/ijch.v71i0.18829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3417687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b36-cmajo.20230006"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogilvie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><collab>DRUM &amp; SASH team</collab><article-title>Assessing the acceptability of dried blood spot testing for HIV and STBBI among M&#233;tis people in a community driven pilot project in Alberta, Canada</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1496</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36482470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12913-022-08763-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9733141</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b37-cmajo.20230006"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazereeuw</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Withrow</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishri</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cancer incidence and survival among M&#233;tis adults in Canada: results from the Canadian census follow-up cohort (1992&#8211;2009)</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><year>2018</year><volume>190</volume><fpage>E320</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29555862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1503/cmaj.170272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5860893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b38-cmajo.20230006"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monchalin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smylie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourgeois</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>&#8220;I would prefer to have my health care provided over a cup of tea any day&#8221;: Recommendations by urban M&#233;tis women to improve access to health and social services in Toronto for the M&#233;tis community</article-title><source>Alternative</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b39-cmajo.20230006"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nickel</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Enns</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanguins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patterns of prescription opioid dispensing among Red River M&#233;tis in Manitoba, Canada: a retrospective longitudinal cross-sectional study</article-title><source>CMAJ Open</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>E288</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.9778/cmajo.20210025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9259467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35351781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b40-cmajo.20230006"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramage-Morin</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bougie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Family networks and health among M&#233;tis aged 45 or older</article-title><source>Health Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29261223</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b41-cmajo.20230006"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leatherdale</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The correlates of current smoking among adult M&#233;tis: evidence from the Aboriginal Peoples Survey and M&#233;tis Supplement</article-title><source>Can J Public Health</source><year>2015</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>e271</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26451987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.17269/cjph.106.5053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6972307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b42-cmajo.20230006"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The correlates of physical activity among adult M&#233;tis</article-title><source>Ethn Health</source><year>2018</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28277016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/13557858.2017.1294655</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b43-cmajo.20230006"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez-Ramirez</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colquhoun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cancer incidence and mortality among the M&#233;tis population of Alberta, Canada</article-title><source>Int J Circumpolar Health</source><year>2016</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>30059</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26837668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3402/ijch.v75.30059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4737713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b44-cmajo.20230006"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez-Ramirez</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Injury-related health services use and mortality among M&#233;tis people in Alberta</article-title><source>Can J Public Health</source><year>2019</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>422</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31218644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.17269/s41997-019-00224-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6964421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b45-cmajo.20230006"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wesche</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>M&#233;tis women at risk: Health and service provision in urban British Columbia</article-title><source>J Indig Wellbeing</source><year>2013</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>96</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b46-cmajo.20230006"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>CIHR guidelines for health research involving Indigenous people 2007&#8211;2010</source><publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Canadian Institutes of Health Research</publisher-name><comment>modified 2013 June 27. Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cihr-irsc.gc.ca/e/29134.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://cihr-irsc.gc.ca/e/29134.html</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2022 May 10</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="b47-cmajo.20230006"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>The First Nations Principles of OCAP</source><publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc><publisher-name>First Nations Information Governance Centre</publisher-name><comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://fnigc.ca/ocap-training/" ext-link-type="uri">https://fnigc.ca/ocap-training/</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2022 June 3</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="b48-cmajo.20230006"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wesche</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trends in M&#233;tis-related health research (1980&#8211;2009): identification of research gaps</article-title><source>Can J Public Health</source><year>2012</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22338324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF03404064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6974209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b49-cmajo.20230006"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chapter 4: Indigenous youth in Canada</article-title><source>Portrait of Youth in Canada: Data Report</source><publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Statistics Canada</publisher-name><comment>modified 2021 Dec</comment><volume>8</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/n1/pub/42-28-0001/2021001/article/00004-eng.htm" ext-link-type="uri">https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/n1/pub/42-28-0001/2021001/article/00004-eng.htm</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2022 May 12</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="b50-cmajo.20230006"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>NAHO publications and resources. First Nations, Inuit &amp; M&#233;tis Program</source><publisher-name>National Aboriginal Health Organization (NAHO)</publisher-name><comment>Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://fnim.sehc.com/se-learning/naho-publications-and-resources/metis-centre" ext-link-type="uri">https://fnim.sehc.com/se-learning/naho-publications-and-resources/metis-centre</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">accessed 2022 June 21</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="b51-cmajo.20230006"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><source>&#8220;M&#233;tis&#8221;: race, recognition, and the struggle for indigenous peoplehood</source><publisher-loc>Vancouver</publisher-loc><publisher-name>UBC Press</publisher-name><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="b52-cmajo.20230006"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Culhane-Pera</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pergament</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improving health through community-based participatory action research. Giving immigrants and refugees a voice</article-title><source>Minn Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20481170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5484585</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>