<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Clin Psychol Med Settings</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Clin Psychol Med Settings</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3814</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">phenaturepg</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Clinical Psychology in Medical Settings</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1068-9583</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1573-3572</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Springer Nature - PMC COVID-19 Collection</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10035972</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10035972.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10035972</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10035972</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36959430</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10880-023-09954-4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9954</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Hazardous Drinking Interventions Delivered During Medical-Surgical Care: Patient and Provider Views</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6271-7141</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Timko</surname><given-names initials="C">Christine</given-names></name><address><email>ctimko@stanford.edu</email><email>Christine.Timko@va.gov</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names initials="M">Mandy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lor</surname><given-names initials="MC">Mai Chee</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aldaco-Revilla</surname><given-names initials="L">Laura</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blonigen</surname><given-names initials="D">Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ilgen</surname><given-names initials="M">Mark</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.280747.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0419 2556</institution-id><institution>Department of Veterans Affairs, Center for Innovation to Implementation, </institution><institution>VA Palo Alto Health Care System, </institution></institution-wrap>795 Willow Rd. (152-MPD), Menlo Park, CA 94025 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.168010.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000419368956</institution-id><institution>Department of Psychiatry &amp; Behavioral Sciences, </institution><institution>Stanford University School of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>401 Quarry Rd, Stanford, CA 94305 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.497654.d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8603 8958</institution-id><institution>VA Center for Clinical Management Research (CCMR), </institution><institution>North Campus Research Complex, </institution></institution-wrap>2800 Plymouth Rd., Building 16, Ann Arbor, MI 48109 USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.214458.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000086837370</institution-id><institution>Department of Psychiatry, North Campus Research Complex, </institution><institution>University of Michigan, </institution></institution-wrap>2800 Plymouth Rd., Building 16, Ann Arbor, MI 48109 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">431877</issue-id><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>23</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>24</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-03-27 17:10:12.990"><day>27</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; This is a U.S. Government work and not under copyright protection in the US; foreign copyright protection may apply 2023</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for unrestricted research re-use and secondary analysis in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for the duration of the World Health Organization (WHO) declaration of COVID-19 as a global pandemic.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10880_2023_Article_9954.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Abstract</title><p id="Par1">Addressing hazardous drinking during medical-surgical care improves patients&#8217; health. This formative evaluation examined patients&#8217; consideration of options to change drinking and engage in treatment. It explored whether interventions such as &#8220;DO-MoST&#8221; overcome treatment barriers. We interviewed 20 medical-surgical patients with hazardous drinking in a trial of DO-MoST, and 16 providers. Analyses used a directed content approach. Patients were receptive to and comfortable discussing drinking during medical-surgical care. Interventions like DO-MoST (patient-centered, motivational approach to shared decision making) addressed some treatment barriers. Patients and providers viewed such interventions as helpful by building a relationship with a psychologist who facilitated self-awareness of drinking behaviors, and discussing connections between alcohol- and physical health-related problems and potential strategies to address drinking. However, both groups expressed concerns about individual and system-level barriers to long-term change. Interventions like DO-MoST bridge the gap between the patient&#8217;s medical treatment episode and transition to other health care settings.</p></sec><sec><title>Trial Registration</title><p id="Par88">The study is registered on ClinicalTrials.gov (ID: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT03258632">NCT03258632</ext-link>).</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Hazardous drinking</kwd><kwd>Clinical psychology</kwd><kwd>Medical-surgical care</kwd><kwd>Shared decision making</kwd><kwd>Treatment initiation and engagement</kwd><kwd>Health outcomes</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000738</institution-id><institution>U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>HSR&amp;D IIR 15-298</award-id><award-id>VA HSR&amp;D RCS 00-001</award-id><award-id>VA HSR&amp;D IIR 15-298</award-id><award-id>VA HSR&amp;D RCS 19-333</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Timko</surname><given-names>Christine</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ilgen</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par2">Hazardous drinking refers to drinking more than recommended limits, including meeting diagnostic criteria for an alcohol use disorder (AUD). Hazardous drinking is common among patients receiving inpatient or outpatient specialty medical-surgical care. About 25% of adults admitted to general hospitals in the US have AUDs or are being treated for drinking consequences (Brgdar et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2022</xref>); (Shah et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2022</xref>); (Wei et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2015</xref>). This likely underrepresents the prevalence of hazardous drinking among medical-surgical patients because alcohol-related problems often go undiagnosed during hospital stays and clinic visits (Danovitch et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2021</xref>). For example, a study at one hospital found that 29% of patients screened as having high-risk alcohol use had no alcohol-related codes associated with hospital admission (Wakeman et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2020</xref>).</p><p id="Par3">Hazardous drinking and medical-surgical conditions are interrelated via three primary pathways (Timko et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2016a</xref>); (Timko et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2016b</xref>). Hazardous drinking may be a causal factor in developing a medical condition (e.g. liver disease, traumatic injury), may exacerbate health conditions that developed apart from drinking (e.g. diabetes), and may complicate effective management of existing medical conditions through poor adherence to medications and to diet, no-smoking, and physical activity recommendations. Alcohol use prior to surgery is associated with during- and post-surgery complications, and patients with AUD have poorer post-surgery outcomes (Bernstein et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2022</xref>). In addition, hazardous drinking co-occurring with medical-surgical conditions increases costly health services use. Medical inpatients with AUD were 1.6 times more likely to be readmitted within 30&#160;days of discharge than those without AUD (Wei et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2015</xref>). Indeed, alcohol-related disorders are among the diagnostic categories with the highest rates of rapid hospital readmission (Gryczynski et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2021</xref>). In a study of inpatients and outpatients from 44 centers in the National COVID Cohort Collaborative, adults with COVID-19 and AUD (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;25,583) had higher odds of hospitalization and mortality compared to adults with COVID-19 but without AUD (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1,309,445), even when analyses adjusted for patients&#8217; demographic and clinical characteristics (Bailey et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2022</xref>).</p><p id="Par4">These findings on the co-occurrence and consequences of hazardous drinking and medical conditions underscore the importance of identifying and addressing hazardous drinking to improve medical-surgical patients&#8217; health. Medical care in the hospital or specialty outpatient clinic is an opportunity for psychologists to address hazardous drinking. It represents a teachable moment to conduct a behavioral intervention to initiate alcohol treatment (Bradley &amp; Kivlahan, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2014</xref>). An alcohol-related intervention during a medical care episode has the potential to facilitate treatment for alcohol use by increasing recognition of the need to reduce drinking, intent to do so, and awareness that engagement in alcohol treatment could be useful to reduce drinking.</p><p id="Par5">In light of the importance of better understanding how to encourage behavior change among medical-surgical patients with hazardous drinking, we developed a patient-centered intervention to improve alcohol treatment and/or mutual-help utilization (initiation and engagement) and outcomes (less or no drinking and better health). This approach is &#8220;Drinking Options&#8212;Motivate, Shared Decisions, Telemonitor&#8221; (DO-MoST) (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). DO-MoST, begun during the medical care episode, is intended to facilitate transitioning to help that is evidence based (i.e., behavioral and/or pharmacological treatment, mutual-help groups) and to improve outcomes (Bradley &amp; Kivlahan, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2014</xref>; Elwyn et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2014</xref>). Its development was informed by our previous implementation of treatment facilitation interventions with other patient populations (Ilgen et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2022</xref>; Timko et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2018</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2019</xref>). Delivered by a Decision Coach (master&#8217;s or doctorate level trained clinical provider), DO-MoST has three components: motivational interviewing approach to motivate patients to change drinking and initiate help seeking; use of a decision aid for patients to choose the type of evidence-based help they prefer and need; and telemonitoring to support and monitor patients&#8217; initiation of and engagement in their preferred modality of help (or, for patients not motivated to change, telemonitoring to continue motivational interviewing). Motivational interviewing respects and works with patients&#8217; ambivalence about changing drinking; the decision aid informs patients about the evidence behind different help sources so they can choose their preferred help source based on their needs; and telemonitoring continues to work with ambivalence as needed and provide support for patients&#8217; choices (DiClemente et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2017</xref>; Donovan et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2015</xref>). DO-MoST is designed to be intensive enough to produce change yet feasible to use in busy clinical settings with too much demand on too few staff with psychology training. It draws on approaches that are evidence based but have not been used together in an integrated way.<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Drinking Options&#8212;Motivate, Shared Decisions, Telemonitor (DO-MoST) by clinical psychologist providers</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10880_2023_9954_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par6">We are currently conducting a randomized trial of usual care plus DO-MoST compared to usual care alone. Patients in DO-MoST attend one 50-min individual session (in-person or by telephone) and six biweekly 15-min telephone sessions with the Decision Coach. At the initial session, the Decision Coach and patient engage in motivational interviewing to discuss the patient&#8217;s medical condition and need to make decisions about drinking goals (abstinence, moderation, or no change), and the goals&#8217; benefits and adverse effects. If the patient prefers to reduce or abstain from drinking and will consider obtaining help, the decision aid is employed to present evidence-based help options (medications, behavioral therapies, mutual help) and their benefits, adverse effects, and settings (e.g. primary care, specialty care). At the session&#8217;s end, patients complete a brief measure of their drinking and help preferences. If the patient is ready, a list with the location and contact number for each potential selected source of help is used to make the next step in obtaining help concrete.</p><p id="Par7">During each telephone session, patients complete the same progress assessment worksheet which includes drinking and help preferences, and answer questions about recent substance use, treatment, and mutual-help attendance. Patients indicating during the initial session that they do not want to change receive motivational interviewing during the telephone sessions. For patients indicating during the initial session willingness to initiate help, phone calls are used to make sure patients understand the help options available, the benefits and risks of each, and the specific next step needed to pursue the selected help option. Telemonitoring provides support when help is obtained, and problem solving on barriers to help initiation, and/or discussions of ways to improve patients&#8217; experience in accessing help. For example, coaches help patients work through the potential situation that a treatment provider suggests a different help option than the one the patient has selected. Telephone monitoring supports patients in moving from help initiation to help engagement.</p><p id="Par8">The present study was a formative evaluation to document critical factors at the patient, provider, and system levels that affect the likelihood that patients with hazardous drinking seen in medical-surgical settings will consider options to change their drinking and engage in treatment. In addition, the study explored whether a patient-centered intervention such as DO-MoST may overcome barriers to initiation of alcohol-related services and/or mutual help. The study draws from a conceptual model that describes patient characteristics and resources, provider experience within and across care sites, and system-level collaboration and feedback as facilitators and barriers to health care transitions (Cucciare et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2015</xref>; Timko et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2016a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2016b</xref>). We conducted qualitative interviews to examine patients&#8217; perspectives on alcohol use being brought up during treatment for a medical-surgical condition. Interviews were also intended to identify providers&#8217; views of barriers to patients receiving alcohol treatment in the context of current medical care, and patients&#8217; views of if and how interventions such as DO-MoST benefit patients, including which barriers they address. This study expands previous literature on intervening with patients having co-occurring alcohol and medical-surgical problems to engage in alcohol treatment by systematically and qualitatively examining factors that promote and hinder treatment initiation, from a provider perspective. It also examines patients&#8217; views of addressing alcohol use generally in the context of medical treatment, and of a specific intervention delivered by master&#8217;s or doctorate level clinical psychologists, DO-MoST, which has not been evaluated before.</p><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Participants</title><sec id="Sec44"><title>Patients</title><p id="Par9">Eligibility criteria for patients&#8217; participation in the trial are (1) in a current episode of inpatient or specialty outpatient medical-surgical care, (2) score of&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;4 (men) or&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;3 (women) on the AUDIT-C (i.e., positive screen for hazardous drinking), (3) no specialty addiction treatment or weekly mutual-help group attendance within 60&#160;days prior to the care episode, (4) no significant cognitive impairment (indicated with the Montreal Cognitive Assessment section on orientation; (Nasreddine et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2005</xref>), (5) ongoing access to a cellular or landline telephone, and (6) at least one contact who knows the patient&#8217;s contact information. Patients were located at two facilities (Midwestern and Western US) in the same health care system. All patients enrolled in the trial were alerted during the initial consent process that they may be contacted for participation in the formative evaluation (the qualitative) component of the study.</p><p id="Par10">We attempted to telephone 27 trial participants to ask them to participate in a qualitative interview. These 27 patients were selected consecutively based on their randomized condition assignment to DO-MoST during the second half of the recruitment period and their completion of the 12-month follow-up assessment. Of the 27 patients we attempted to call, 7 (26%) did not answer the phone and 20 (74%) agreed to participate, provided informed consent, and completed the interview. Patient characteristics are provided in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Interviews lasted for 30&#8211;45&#160;min and participants were remunerated for their participation.<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of patients (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;20) and providers (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;16)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patients</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Providers</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gender (n)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age: Mean (SD)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.3 (11.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not asked</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race (n)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not asked</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;White</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;American Indian or Alaska Native</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ethnicity (n)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not asked</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hispanic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Not Hispanic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Site (n)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Midwest</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;West coast</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medical treatment (n)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Inpatient</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Outpatient</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec45"><title>Providers</title><p id="Par11">To recruit providers, senior study staff identified clinical providers of care to medical-surgical patients with hazardous drinking (i.e., psychologists, social workers, unit or clinic physician-directors, nurses) and emailed them. The email briefly explained the purpose of the overall project and interview, and invited the individual to participate. We followed the email with a phone call to answer any questions the provider may have had about the project and to schedule the interview. Of 31 providers emailed, 15 (48%) did not respond to the email and 16 (52%) agreed to participate and were interviewed. Providers gave informed consent prior to the interview, and were prohibited by the health care system from receiving remuneration. Providers interviewed (6 nurses, with the other groups equally represented) were given a standardized summary of DO-MoST&#8217;s components and procedures before the interview began. Providers&#8217; characteristics are in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Interviews with providers lasted from 30 to 45&#160;min.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Procedure</title><p id="Par12">Draft interview guides were prepared by senior study staff and finalized with feedback from the full study team and pre-testing with two providers. Interviews were conducted by senior study staff (Drs. Timko, Blonigen, and Ilgen, experts in the content and methods of this study) and research assistants (Ms. Lewis, Ms. Lor, and Ms. Aldaco-Revilla) who were trained in carrying out such interviews. We used semi-structured interviews with specified prompts to understand how patients with hazardous drinking may be approached about their alcohol use, the process of changing alcohol use, and care utilization, and their experiences with the DO-MoST intervention. Researchers and participants did not have relationships prior to interacting for the study.</p><sec id="Sec5"><title>Patients</title><p id="Par13">In the semi-structured interviews, patients were asked what they thought about being approached to discuss their alcohol use while in treatment for a medical-surgical condition. These questions provided data about their impressions of the broader components of alcohol interventions. Specifically, they were asked about &#8220;providing patients with alcohol treatment resources available to them that they might not have known about, and seeing if patients might make changes to their drinking habits.&#8221; A prompt related to this topic was how well interviewees thought these discussions would meet the needs of patients in medical or surgical treatment who may need help in reducing their drinking.</p><p id="Par14">Patients were also asked specific questions to examine their perspectives on DO-MoST&#8217;s effectiveness. Effectiveness is a dimension contained in the RE-AIM framework, which was developed to translate scientific advances into practice (Glasgow et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2019</xref>). Patients were asked: &#8220;Tell me about your overall experience with DO-MoST. What did you like and dislike about DO-MoST? What did you find most and least helpful about DO-MoST?&#8221; Related prompts were &#8220;Did DO-MoST meet your expectations&#8212;why or why not? To what extent has DO-MoST impacted, positively or negatively, your health care, if at all? Your quality of life?&#8221;</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Providers</title><p id="Par15">The interviews examined providers&#8217; perspectives on barriers at the patient, program, and system levels that affect medical-surgical patients&#8217; initiation and engagement in alcohol treatment. The interview guide adapted the conceptual model developed by (Cucciare et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2014</xref>) on care transitions. Specific to identifying barriers, providers were asked: &#8220;What do you think the barriers are for your patients about discussing their alcohol use,&#8221; and, &#8220;What are some of the barriers you face with providing alcohol treatment options to patients during appointments or hospital stays?&#8221; Prompts related to these questions were &#8220;How comfortable are you when recommending alcohol treatment to patients, and what kind of help or support would you need to be more comfortable?&#8221; Additional prompts were, &#8220;What are common questions or concerns you hear about alcohol treatment from your patients,&#8221; and, &#8220;What are some of the benefits you could see from discussing alcohol treatment options with patients during appointments or inpatient stays?&#8221;</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Analysis Plan</title><p id="Par16">Interviews were audio recorded (with permission). The study&#8217;s data analysis approach consisted of directed content analysis using interview notes and verification with audio recordings (Nevedal et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2021</xref>). The interviewer took notes and captured quotations for each question during interviews. Immediately after the interviews, the interviewer coded the notes into an MS Excel file that contained the question matrix and noted when additional detail or a timestamp was needed. The primary analyst then reviewed the matrix, listened to the audio recordings when indicated, and edited and built upon the interviewer&#8217;s notes. The secondary analyst also reviewed the matrix, listened to the audio recordings when indicated, and edited and built upon the primary analyst&#8217;s notes. Analysts coded based on a codebook with deductive general alcohol discussion and effectiveness constructs (patient data), and patient, provider, and system-level constructs (provider data) as well as inductive codes that were relevant to the evaluation. Analysts used comments and highlighting in the matrix to flag sections of text for discussion and met to adjudicate differences and refine the codebook.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Patient Reports of Discussing Alcohol use During Medical-Surgical Care</title><p id="Par17">Patients&#8217; general reactions to their alcohol use being discussed in the course of medical-surgical treatment contained three themes (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). First, these discussions helped patients&#8217; think about their drinking in general; that is, they helped patients see the consequences of their alcohol use, and find out how to get help for drinking and change their use of alcohol (reduce or abstain from alcohol use). The second theme was that discussions about alcohol use helped patients improve their medical-surgical or mental health conditions, specifically. The third theme was that bringing up alcohol use during medical-surgical treatment would not help patients who do not see themselves as having problems regarding their drinking.<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Patient responses to approaches to discuss drinking during medical-surgical care</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Theme</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sample quotes:</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">a. Helped patients see their drinking is problematic; learned how to get help; and drank less</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[Discussions] help the Veterans who have a drinking problem and what effects it is having on them, and that they might come to the realization that drinking is not good for them and decide to quit. (PAME2)</p><p>A general medical doctor should know about a patient's drinking problem and should guide the patient in the right direction. [Other health care system&#8217;s] clinics do the same procedures to get veterans connected to services&#8230;. You just have to let them know that it [drinking] is very important and so they can be treated. (PALE1)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">b. Helped patients&#8217; medical-surgical and mental health problems</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>[Discussions helped to]</p><p>&#8230;gain an understanding of how people use alcohol to self-medicate for pain or other issues and see what other treatments would help vets have a healthier life. (AAHE4)</p><p>&#8230; feel better about overall health. As much as I am worried about the future health but the current health is also important and stopping alcohol is helping the current health. (PAME3)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">c. Would not help patients who do not see their drinking as problematic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>It won&#8217;t help if the person isn&#8217;t ready to help themselves. (AAME3)</p><p>It is up to the individual you are talking to. He has to be ready. (PAME3)</p></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Study participant ID numbers are contained in parentheses after each quote</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par18">Although not specifically asked in the interview questions, 7 patients advised on how to bring up alcohol use with patients during medical-surgical treatment (not tabled). The advice was to lead gradually to the topic of alcohol use, and to take a caring, non-confrontational, and non-judgmental approach, emphasizing confidentiality; for example: &#8220;With the conversation in the beginning, it is universal or global that helps people to get hooked on it and slowly go to the drinking problem&#8221; (study ID: PAHE1). One patient advised, &#8220;It is really good to feel that someone out there is interested in the care of the person in need. And to look into the situation&#8212;whether or not the person can be taken away from the alcohol or drug use in a manner that is not subjected to harm or demeaning or any of that&#8221; (PAME3).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Provider Reports of Barriers to Alcohol-Related Care Among Medical-Surgical Patients with Hazardous Drinking</title><p id="Par19">Provider reports of individual&#160;level barriers to alcohol care were represented in seven themes: patients&#8217; denial and lack of motivation; lack of desired available treatments; stigma associated with addiction and its treatment; life context factors; co-occurring health conditions; home environment; and lack of ability to initiate alcohol care (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Provider-reported barriers to medical-surgical patients&#8217; alcohol care</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Individual barriers</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sample quotes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">a. Lack of motivation for change; denial</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">One [barrier] is the patient is in denial about the severity of their illness and doesn't wish to acknowledge the severity of the problem. (PA5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">As far as general barriers, their level of interest in changing the behaviors. &#8230; I have heard vets say, I have drank this long&#8212;what difference does it make, the damage is already done. They are also concerned about withdrawal symptoms. Their desire to wanting to quit and change their behaviors. (AA6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">b. Lack of available desired treatments</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">We don't oftentimes have the resources to offer them that they are looking for. Most of the patients we see are hoping to get in the inpatient alcohol rehab which is very difficult to offer. &#8230; They often have to go outpatient IOP before getting a scheduled inpatient date and a lot of them are very concerned about relapsing in that interval. (PA6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vets don&#8217;t want to do groups and sit around and listen to others talk about using. (AA5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">c. Stigma of addiction and treatment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">As far as the barrier, I think it is the stigma that happens with any kind of addiction. (PA4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">They may also be afraid to be labeled an addict and the stigma of the label. (AA7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">d. Life context</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">There is a handful of the population that are homeless and their immediate is more short-sighted and not thinking longer-term. (PA3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">There can be transportation issues. (AA4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">e. Home environment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Having a partner or someone else in the home who is actively using alcohol or other substances&#8212;these are some other major barriers. (PA1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Some veterans see the hospital as a safe place and when they go home they have concerns about going back to where they were drinking. I have heard vets say, "I am doing fine here but when I get home I am concerned I will relapse." (AA6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">f. Co-occurring health conditions</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">I think barriers are.. mental health issues like depression, psychotic disorder, PTSD, anxiety, or concomitant chronic pain or insomnia, these are the major barriers. (PA1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any cognitive impairment is a barrier. (AA6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">g. Lack of means to make treatment appointment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The primary resource is providing [outpatient treatment] that really requires the veteran to call into for an appointment. We have quite a few veterans that can be a barrier. One, that the veterans don't have a phone or don't know how to use their phones, or are not reliable to keep a phone number for the [outpatient program]. (PA2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">We encounter a lot in terms of having veterans not taking the responsibility themselves because they don't even have a cell phone&#8212;that's a barrier. (PA3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Provider/Setting Barriers</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;a. Lack of provider&#8211;patient relationship</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A barrier is when the consult team doesn't have the time that is sometimes required to develop the trust and rapport that the veteran needs in order to feel safe to explore something that makes them self-vulnerable. &#8230; Our current hospital system doesn't allow a reasonable amount of time to really have a human connection and take the time that is necessary to give the information that is needed. (PA5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The time we have available to spend with the veterans to identify their triggers and needs is an issue. (AA6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;b. Lack of provider confidence in alcohol care</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">My biggest worry is that they won't have good outpatient follow-up. So a lot of times I am hesitant to start a new medication that needs monitoring. I can't track them&#8212;I worry about their follow-up. I am concerned about the side effects if they consume alcohol. I worry about polysubstance abuse that I don't know about, how much follow-up they are going to get even from counseling. (PA1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">I am not comfortable recommending specific programs because I don't know those specifics. &#8230; I don't think any of us in the inpatient knows the specifics of the types of programs that we have. (PA6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;c. Staff discomfort with substance use</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">There is a hesitancy to talk about alcohol use with people because of worries about damaging the therapeutic relationship, or anxiety about the veteran becoming angry. (PA1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Some medical learners or residents are thinking it&#8217;s not their lane to have these conversations and feel like it&#8217;s social workers and other providers are responsible. (AA6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">System barriers</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;a. Lack of treatment resources</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The need here surpasses the resources that are available. I very often have patients who are truly in a very vulnerable place that they are seeking help and we are not able to provide the help. That's when a lot of gap happens. (PA8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A barrier is the having better access. For example there can be a long wait for beds and transportation issues. Having more resources and access would be supportive, and having something for in between inpatient and treatment. (AA4)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Study participant ID numbers are contained in parentheses after each quote. <italic toggle="yes">IOP</italic> Intensive Outpatient Program</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par20"><italic toggle="yes">Low motivation and denial</italic> included patients&#8217; lack of readiness to change or discuss drinking due to their beliefs that harms of drinking were irreversible. Providers stated that patients feared experiencing withdrawal symptoms, and had low self-efficacy to change drinking due to previous &#8220;failed&#8221; treatments. Providers also noted the barrier of <italic toggle="yes">low availability of treatments that patients want</italic>. For example, some patients want residential treatment when only outpatient treatment is available, and when patients see outpatient treatment as acceptable, they would prefer individual treatment but are referred to group treatment. Providers saw another barrier to alcohol care as the <italic toggle="yes">stigmatization</italic> of addiction and patients&#8217; shame of drinking too heavily, and another as patients&#8217; <italic toggle="yes">life context</italic>; that is, patients&#8217; problems of living related to their finances, housing insecurity, and lack of transportation and social support take precedence to or interfere with treatment initiation. Similarly, patients&#8217; <italic toggle="yes">co-occurring health problems,</italic> such as poor mental health, chronic pain, insomnia, and cognitive impairment, make initiating alcohol care beyond the patient&#8217;s capability. This is likely exacerbated when patients <italic toggle="yes">lack the means</italic> (e.g. a phone) to make an appointment. Another patient-level barrier to alcohol care reported by providers is the <italic toggle="yes">home environment</italic> supporting substance use rather than abstinence.</p><p id="Par21">Provider reports of treatment and setting barriers to medical-surgical patients receiving alcohol care were fewer in number compared to patient-level barriers. The three themes represented were <italic toggle="yes">lack of an ongoing provider&#8211;patient relationship</italic>, such as one that allows trust to develop over time (especially in inpatient settings); <italic toggle="yes">lack of providers&#8217; confidence in alcohol care</italic> patients may receive, and <italic toggle="yes">lack of providers&#8217; comfort</italic> with discussing and treating substance use. Only one theme representing a system barrier was reported by providers. This was lack of inpatient or outpatient clinic access to treatment resources for immediate handoff, including detoxification services and outpatient and residential alcohol care.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Patient-Reported Effectiveness of DO-MoST</title><p id="Par22">The effectiveness of DO-MoST<bold>,</bold> reported by patients, was represented in seven themes (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The first was the patient&#8217;s relationship with the Decision Coach. Patients described the relationship as providing support, accountability, and information, and helping to fill the treatment gap. That the Decision Coach offered help on the phone over time was seen as a benefit of DO-MoST; calls were conveniently timed and completed from home over a sustained period. Patients&#8217; themes related to DO-MoST&#8217;s effectiveness were also represented by perceptions that DO-MoST helped with their self-evaluation and self-awareness, as well as creation of a change plan. DO-MoST was seen as facilitating reduced drinking, a better life due to positive consequences of less drinking (e.g. more involvement in activities, more responsible, better relationships), and better physical and mental health.<table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Patient-provided effectiveness of DO-MoST</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Benefit</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sample quotes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Relationship with Decision Coach</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The conversations were non-judgmental and the lady would expand in such a way to help me think about what I was doing. &#8230; The most helpful was people being concerned about me and learning about resources. (AAHE2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The accountability with someone I did not know had a positive impact. &#8230;It gave me someone who listened who cared. (AAHE4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The most helpful thing was just talking to somebody&#8230;. Knowing you are not alone and somebody is going to be there to talk to you and help you out. (AAHE6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Self-evaluation, self-awareness, self-insight</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">It made me more aware of my mental and physical health and aware of my drinking habits. &#8230;Being able to evaluate on my own if there was positive change and understanding if there was positive change it was because I made these changes. (AAHE4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Actually it made me aware that I was more in trouble using alcohol. If I know there is a problem going on, I can work on it. When I started with it, I was like, I am fine, don't worry about me attitude, and I know better now. (PAHE4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Telephone delivery</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">I loved everything about the phone. I loved not being seen by the person and them not seeing me and I did not have to travel. Not seeing them allowed me to focus on myself without trying to please the coach. (AAHE4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">I liked the phone platform. It was easy to talk and not be embarrassed over the phone. (PAME2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Helped with change plan</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The study helped me be vocal about my view about the world I was stuck in. The conversations helped me from foggy notions to something concrete in a productive way. (PAHE1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">I think anything that helps me keep my goals forefront in my mind&#8212;the conversations helped with that. &#8230; The main effect of DO-MoST was helping me feel focused. (AAHE5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Less alcohol consumption</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">It opened my eyes to what to drink and what not to drink, because I have diabetes and pancreatitis and so it was kind of like, okay, these phone calls were reminders. (PALE1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">My doctor also told me that my liver is not performing optimal so this along with DO-MoST helped me cut down on my drinking. (PAHE3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Better quality of life</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">One, when you don't buy the alcohol you can put that money to better use so you are saving money in the long run. Two, you are not getting the effects of the alcohol, which will keep your mind clear and keep the inside of your body better. (PALE1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">I no longer take days off from my responsibilities to go and drink. (PAHE4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">I am dealing with now and getting things done in my life. I could not deal with the issues when I was drinking. (AAME3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">It allowed me to have a better relationship with my husband as he did not have to monitor my drinking. (AAHE4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Better health</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">I woke up not groggy and over hung with alcohol&#8212;that has completely stopped. Hangover is completely gone and I am able to do a bunch of things before breakfast. (PAME3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">I think it has had a positive effect and not just alcohol. I am thinking more about other things like salt and sugar. Overall there has been a positive effect more than just alcohol. (AAHE6)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Study participant ID numbers are contained in parentheses after each quote</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par23">When coding patients&#8217; responses regarding the effectiveness of DO-MoST, we also documented patients&#8217; suggestions on how DO-MoST should be changed to provide more benefit (not tabled). The most common themes were to replace a small number of DO-MoST&#8217;s phone calls with in-person or video meetings (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8) and to offer more flexibility in terms of scheduling the phone calls (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;3).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par24">This study, using qualitative data from medical-surgical patients with untreated hazardous alcohol use and from health care providers, supports three broad conclusions. First, patients with untreated hazardous alcohol use are receptive to discussing their drinking during a medical-surgical care episode. Second, interventions delivered by clinical psychologists such as DO-MoST, that take a motivational approach to shared decision making over time using telephone sessions, address some but not all of the barriers providers identified to patients&#8217; obtaining help for hazardous drinking. Finally, patients viewed interventions such as DO-MoST as potentially helpful for reducing drinking by means of building a relationship with a coach who facilitated self-awareness of drinking behaviors and how to change drinking.</p><p id="Par25">Patients had positive views of being approached about their use of alcohol during a medical-surgical care episode. They thought that such discussions could help patients see that their drinking was problematic, learn about options for treatment, reduce or quit drinking, and have a better quality of life, although they cautioned that patients have to &#8220;be ready&#8221; to be helped. Patients also thought that such discussions could help improve both medical and mental health conditions. These views held by patients were consistent with provider-identified barriers to medical-surgical patients obtaining alcohol-related care, which included patients&#8217; denial of having drinking problems and lack of motivation to change drinking. Patients&#8217; views are also consistent with their evaluations of DO-MoST specifically, which was seen as overcoming these provider-identified barriers by facilitating patients&#8217; awareness of problematic drinking, creation of a change plan, drinking less, and having better health. Motivation to change drinking has been shown to be an important predictor of better alcohol use outcomes (Collins et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2012</xref>) and to be high among patients hospitalized for medical problems such as cardiovascular conditions (Siewert-Markus et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2022</xref>), and, thus, is a potentially important target for alcohol interventions in medical care settings. Motivation is seen as a dynamic and fluctuating state that can be modified by approaches to arouse and enhance it (CSAT, 2013; (Vederhus et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2014</xref>). Motivational approaches may have the additional advantage of helping patients with other patient-level barriers that providers identified in the present study, such as inflexibility regarding the desired type of treatment sought, the stigma of addiction and its treatment, and having other life context needs that supersede changing drinking.</p><p id="Par26">Interventions such as DO-MoST address an important provider-identified barrier to patients&#8217; obtaining alcohol care: the absence of a provider-patient relationship (Gressler et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2019</xref>). This barrier was explained as due to providers&#8217; lack of time to spend with patients to develop trust and a safe space in which patients could open up about their needs regarding alcohol use. Consistently, patients saw their relationship with a decision coach as a benefit of DO-MoST. A coach provided a caring and concerned listener who was non-judgmental but also offered accountability. In addition, a coach filled the gap between discharge from the medical-surgical care episode and initiation of available alcohol treatment. Patient&#8211;provider trust is also modifiable, in that specialized provider training that includes work on trust building for individuals with substance use disorders (SUDs) is feasible and potentially improves the quality of care and health outcomes for patients with these disorders (Bohnert et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2011</xref>). The present study&#8217;s patient interviews suggest that trust building and its positive consequences can be achieved with the use of interventions such as DO-MoST that are offered by telephone. Well known is that the COVID-19 pandemic led to an increase in the use of telehealth technologies (Deng et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2022</xref>); (Torous et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2021</xref>) and evidence suggests a positive association of patients&#8217; trust in the provider and their satisfaction with telehealth visits (Orrange et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2021</xref>). The benefits of telehealth may be particularly notable when the patient has had the ability to establish an initial connection with the provider (in this case, the Decision Coach) and the telephone contacts are used to build on this initial interaction and help enact and refine the plans that were developed during this initial session.</p><p id="Par27">While efforts such as DO-MoST address important provider-identified barriers to patients&#8217; alcohol care, they do not address the barrier of the systemic lack of treatment resources. Indeed, despite the high prevalence, mortality, and economic costs of hazardous drinking, only 8.3% of 15.8 million US adults who reported needing treatment for an alcohol problem received specialty alcohol treatment (Kranzler &amp; Soyka, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2018</xref>). More specifically, national US data indicate that persons with AUDs commonly utilize health care and are often screened about alcohol use, but few receive treatment, supporting the view that health care settings represent a prime opportunity to implement behavioral interventions to facilitate alcohol treatment to improve patient outcomes (Mintz et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2021</xref>). Consistent with our results for patients, another study using national US data from 2004 to 2017 found that a growing proportion of older adults sought first-time SUD treatment in residential facilities (Huhn et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2019</xref>). For patients who receive alcohol care in residential facilities, continuing care by telehealth technologies has been shown to be effective in that it reduced the number risky drinking days compared to a control condition (Gustafson et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2014</xref>).</p><p id="Par28">It is important to discuss approaches such as DO-MoST in the context of other efforts to increase access to and use of alcohol care in medical-surgical settings, such as inpatient consultation services. For example, (Englander et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2019</xref>) noted that while hospitalizations due to medical-surgical complications of SUDs are rising, most hospitals lack systems to treat SUD, and most people with SUDs do not engage in post-discharge treatment. They conducted a cohort study comparing Improving Addiction Care Team (IMPACT) patients with propensity-matched controls. IMPACT was more intensive and extensive than DO-MoST in that it included hospital-based consultation care from an interdisciplinary team of addiction medicine physicians, social workers, and peers with lived experience in recovery. It met with patients during hospitalization to offer pharmacotherapy, behavioral treatments, and harm reduction services, and supported linkages to SUD treatment after discharge. The main finding was that IMPACT patients engaged in post-discharge SUD treatment more often than controls did (39% vs 23%). A qualitative study of IMPACT found that peers in particular were able to help build trust with patients and also facilitated patient care by contextualizing patient experiences to providers (Collins et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">2019</xref>). However, the study also noted that integrating peer mentors into hospital care presents substantial challenges (Collins et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">2019</xref>).</p><p id="Par29">Wakeman et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2017</xref>) similarly conducted a prospective quasi-experimental evaluation comparing 30-day post-discharge outcomes between hospitalized patients (screened as having, or at high risk for, SUD) who did or did not receive addiction consultation. Addiction consultation consisted of a multidisciplinary specialty team offering pharmacotherapy, motivational counseling, treatment planning, and direct linkage to ongoing addiction treatment. Results were that the intervention group decreased more than the control group on alcohol and drug use severity, and increased more on number of abstinent days. Subsequently, (Wakeman et al.&#8217;s <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2021</xref>) randomized controlled trial tested the incremental benefit of telephone linkage to a post-discharge navigator among patients who had received addiction consultation during hospitalization. The intervention attempted four post-discharge phone calls from a navigator to review the recommended treatment plan and address barriers to engagement. At 1-month follow-up, both groups reduced alcohol and drug use compared to baseline, but there was no difference between groups at the 1- or 2-month follow-up. Follow-up rates were low at both 1&#160;month (46%) and 2&#160;months (41%).</p><p id="Par30">In related work, Gryczynski et al., (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2021</xref>) conducted a randomized controlled trial comparing Navigation Services to Avoid Rehospitalization (NavSTAR) to treatment as usual with hospitalized adults having co-occurring SUDs and medical conditions. NavSTAR used case management, advocacy, service linkage, and motivational support to resolve barriers to care and address SUD, medical, and basic needs for 3&#160;months post-discharge. Patients in NavSTAR compared to patients in treatment as usual were less likely to have an inpatient readmission within 30&#160;days of discharge (16% vs. 30%) and were more likely to enter community SUD care within 3&#160;months of discharge (50% vs. 35%).</p><p id="Par31">The intervention services offered in the studies led by Englander, Wakeman, and Gryczynski were more extensive and likely more costly than services offered by interventions such as DO-MoST. Although addiction consultation and navigation services were more successful than usual care at linking patients to substance use treatment, one-half or more of patients receiving these services did not initiate treatment (Englander et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2019</xref>; Gryczynski et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2021</xref>). Additional work is needed to both complete the current trial of DO-MoST and to determine in randomized trials the success of less intensive and costly approaches such as DO-MoST versus more extensive consultation and navigation services in connecting patients to care and improving their substance use outcomes.</p><sec id="Sec13"><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par32">Although this study had strengths (e.g. use of a care transition conceptual model to guide interviews), it also had limitations. Specifically, the sample consisted of patients and providers only in one health care system (US Veterans Health Administration [VHA] medical facilities), which may limit the generalizability of findings. However, VHA is the largest health care system in the US, and performance data show that health care provided in VHA is similar to or better than that in non-VHA health care systems (Anhang Price et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2018</xref>). In addition, findings may not generalize to patients who refused participation in the randomized trial of DO-MoST, to patients currently engaged in alcohol treatment, or to patients who are more diverse in terms of gender, race, and ethnicity. Further, we did not examine whether provider views differed across discipline, and this is an important direction for future research.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par33">Although hazardous alcohol use is common in medical-surgical patients, few evidence-based resources exist to leverage medical visits as a time for clinical psychologists to address hazardous alcohol use. Qualitative data from patients who participated in the DO-MoST intervention indicated that medical-surgical patients with hazardous alcohol use are comfortable discussing their drinking and derive benefit from discussing the relationship between their alcohol- and physical health-related problems, as well as potential strategies to address their alcohol use. Providers also see the potential benefits of such an approach, but both groups express concerns about potential individual and system-level barriers to long-term change. An intervention that utilizes a motivational approach to shared decisions &#8211; DO-MoST &#8211; was generally well-received and the combination of an initial session with multiple follow-up calls allowed the intervention to bridge the time period from the index medical treatment episode and when the patient transitioned to other settings. Once available, the randomized trial outcome data will indicate whether the relatively positive response to this intervention translates into sustained changes in alcohol use over time.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Andrea Nevedal, PhD, for consultation on the analytic approach.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>All authors contributed to the study conception and design, and performed material preparation. Data collection and analysis were performed by Timko, Lewis, Lor, and Aldaco-Revilla. The first draft of the manuscript was written by Timko and Ilgen and all authors commented on subsequent versions of the manuscript and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This research was supported by the Department of Veterans Affairs (VA), Health Services Research and Development Service (IIR 15&#8211;298 to Drs. Timko and Ilgen; RCS 00&#8211;001 to Dr. Timko; RCS 19&#8211;333 to Dr. Ilgen).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Code Availability</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par34">Authors Christine Timko, Mandy Lewis, Mai Chee Lor, Laura Aldaco-Revilla, Daniel Blonigen, Mark Ilgen have no relevant financial or non-financial interests to disclose.</p></notes><notes><title>Ethical Approval</title><p>Ethics approval was received from Stanford University (IRB-40127) and the VA Ann Arbor Health Care System (IRB-2017&#8211;1048). We certify that the study was performed in accordance with the ethical standards as laid down in the 1964 Declaration of Helsinki and its later amendments or comparable ethical standards.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Consent to Participate</title><p id="Par38">Informed consent to participate in the study was obtained from all participants.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for Publication</title><p id="Par37">Not applicable.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anhang Price</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sloss</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cefalu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussey</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparing quality of care in Veterans Affairs and non-Veterans Affairs settings</article-title><source>Journal of General Internal Medicine</source><year>2018</year><volume>33</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1631</fpage><lpage>1638</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-018-4433-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29696561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6153237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sayles</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalid</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anglim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ponce</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 patients with documented alcohol use disorder or alcohol-related complications are more likely to be hospitalized and have higher all-cause mortality</article-title><source>Alcoholis: Clinical and Experimental Research</source><year>2022</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>1023</fpage><lpage>1035</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/acer.14838</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9111368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35429004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bernstein, J., Rankin, K. A., &amp; Green, T. (2022). Movement if life-optimizing patient access to total arthroplasty: Alcohol and substance abuse disparities. <italic toggle="yes">Journal of the American Academy of Orthopaedic Surgeons.</italic> Online ahead of print 19 Apr 2022. 10.5435/JAAOS-D-21-00939<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5435/JAAOS-D-21-00939</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35442926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohnert</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zivin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kilbourne</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ratings of patient-provider communication among veterans: Serious mental illnesses, substance use disorders, and the moderating role of trust</article-title><source>Health Communication</source><year>2011</year><volume>26</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10410236.2010.549813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21390974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kivlahan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bringing patient-centered care to patients with alcohol use disorders</article-title><source>Journal of the American Medical Association</source><year>2014</year><volume>311</volume><fpage>1861</fpage><lpage>1862</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2014.3629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24825640</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4097878</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brgdar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gharbin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elawad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bishaw</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taha</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of substance use disorder on in-hospital outcomes of young patients presenting with a cardiovascular event</article-title><source>Cureus</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.22737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35386479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8969757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR100"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolaidis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gregg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gullickson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patten</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>&#8220;If it wasn't for him, I wouldn't have talked to them&#8221;: Qualitative study of addiction peer mentorship in the hospital</article-title><source>Journal of General Internal Medicine</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-019-05311-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31512181</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malone</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larimer</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Motivation to change and treatment attendance as predictors of alcohol-use outcomes among project-based Housing First residents</article-title><source>Addictive Behaviors</source><year>2012</year><volume>37</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>931</fpage><lpage>939</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.addbeh.2012.03.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22513197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3358454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cucciare</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saitz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Timko</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhancing transitions from addiction treatment to primary care</article-title><source>Journal of Addictive Diseases</source><year>2014</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.addbeh.2014.08.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25299380</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cucciare</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Timko</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A conceptual model to facilitate transitions from primary care to specialty substance use disorder care</article-title><source>Primary Health Care Research &amp; Development</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>492</fpage><lpage>505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1463423614000164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24818752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Danovitch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nuckols</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ober</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirocha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ros</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol use disorder among general hospital medical inpatients</article-title><source>Addiction Research</source><year>2021</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.33425/2639-8451.1024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Deng, H., Raheemullah, A., Fenno, L. E., &amp; Lembke, A. (2022). A telehealth inpatient addiction consult service is both feasible and effective in reducing readmission rates. <italic toggle="yes">Journal of Addictive Diseases.</italic> Online ahead of print. 12 Jul 2022.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/10550887.2022.2090822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35819268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DiClemente</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corno</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graydon</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiprovnick</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knoblach</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Motivational interviewing, enhancement, and brief interventions over the last decade</article-title><source>Psychology of Addictive Behaviors</source><year>2017</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>862</fpage><lpage>887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/adb0000318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29199843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatch-Maillette</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phares</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGarry</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peavy</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taborsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lessons learned for follow-up phone booster counseling calls with substance abusing emergency department patients</article-title><source>Journal of Substance Abuse Treatment</source><year>2015</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2014.10.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25534151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4305001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elwyn</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dehlendorf</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marrin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frosch</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shared decision making and motivational interviewing: Achieving patient-centered care across the spectrum of health care problems</article-title><source>Annals of Family Medicine</source><year>2014</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>270</fpage><lpage>275</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1370/afm.1615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24821899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4018376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Englander</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobbertin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lind</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolaidis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graven</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorfman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inpatient addiction medicine consultation and post-hospital substance use disorder treatment engagement: A propensity-matched analysis</article-title><source>Journal of General Internal Medicine</source><year>2019</year><volume>34</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2796</fpage><lpage>2803</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-019-05251-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31410816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6854181</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glasgow</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harden</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaglio</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RE-AIM planning and evaluation framework</article-title><source>Frontiers in Public Health</source><year>2019</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>64</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2019.00064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30984733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6450067</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gressler</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Natafgi</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeForge</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaneman-Robinson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaya</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What motivates people with substance use disorders to pursue treatment? A patient-centered approach to understanding patient experiences and patient-provider interactions</article-title><source>Journal of Substance Use</source><year>2019</year><volume>24</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14659891.2019.1620891</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31582894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6776437</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gryczynski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordeck</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Grady</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preventing hospital readmission for patients with comorbid substance use disorder</article-title><source>Annals of Internal Medicine</source><year>2021</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>899</fpage><lpage>909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M20-5475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33819055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gustafson</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McTavish</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chih</surname><given-names>M-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atwood</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A smartphone application to support recovery from alcoholism: A randomized clinical trial</article-title><source>JAMA Psychiatry</source><year>2014</year><volume>71</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>572</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2013.4642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24671165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4016167</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huhn</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hobelmann</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strain</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oyler</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trends in first-time treatment admissions for older adults with alcohol use disorder: Availability of medical and specialty clinical services in hospital, residential, and outpatient facilities</article-title><source>Drug and Alcohol Dependence</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2019.107694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31704379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ilgen</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coughlin</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Encouraging the use of the Veterans Crisis Line among high-risk Veterans: A randomized trial of a Crisis Line Facilitation intervention</article-title><source>Journal of Psychiatric Research.</source><year>2022</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2022.07.047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35940001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kranzler</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soyka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis and pharmacotherapy of alcohol use disorder: A review</article-title><source>Journal of the American Medical Association</source><year>2018</year><volume>320</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>815</fpage><lpage>824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2018.11406</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30167705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7391072</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mintz</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartz</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramsey</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grucza</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A cascade of care for alcohol use disorder: Using 2015&#8211;2019 National Survey on Drug Use and Health data to identify gaps in past 12-month care</article-title><source>Alcoholism: Clinical and Experimental Research</source><year>2021</year><volume>45</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>1286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/acer.14609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8254783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33993541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasreddine</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#233;dirian</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charbonneau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chertkow</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Montreal Cognitive Assessment, MoCA: A brief screening tool for mild cognitive impairment</article-title><source>Journal of the American Geratrics Society</source><year>2005</year><volume>53</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>695</fpage><lpage>699</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2005.53221.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15817019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nevedal</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reardon</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Widerquist</surname><given-names>MAO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cutrona</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rapid versus traditional qualitative analysis using the Consolidated Framework for Implementation Research (CFIR)</article-title><source>Implementation Science</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>67</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13012-021-01111-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34215286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8252308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orrange</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassetta</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patient satisfaction and trust in telemedicine during the COVID-19 pandemic: Retrospective observational study</article-title><source>JMIR Human Factors</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/28589</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33822736</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8103305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shah, I., Yakah, W., Ahmed, A., Kandasamy, C., Tintara, S., Sorrento, C., et al., (2022). Extrapancreatic complications in hospitalized patients with mild acute pancreatitis are associated with poorer outcomes. <italic toggle="yes">Pancreas, 51</italic>, 177&#8211;182<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MPA.0000000000001986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35404894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siewert-Markus</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulbricht</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaertner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zyriax</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#246;rr</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tobschall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Behavioral health risk factors and motivation to change among cardiovascular general hospital patients aged 50 to 79 years</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1963</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu14091963</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35565928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9105822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Center for Substance Abuse Treatment. (2013). <italic toggle="yes">Enhancing motivation for change in substance abuse treatment.</italic> Treatment Improvement Protocol (TIP) Series, No. 35. HHS Publication No. (SMA) 13&#8211;4212. Rockville, MD: Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22514841</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Timko</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Below</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vittorio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Festin</surname><given-names>FED</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brief</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Randomized controlled trial of enhanced telephone monitoring with detoxification patients: 3- and 6-month outcomes</article-title><source>Journal of Substance Abuse Treatment</source><year>2019</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2018.12.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30797391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6568005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Timko</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>AHS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jannausch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ilgen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Randomized controlled trial of telephone monitoring with psychiatry inpatients with co-occurring substance use and mental health disorders</article-title><source>Drug and Alcohol Dependence</source><year>2018</year><volume>194</volume><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2018.09.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30466040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6448768</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Timko</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vittorio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cucciare</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening and brief intervention for unhealthy substance use in patients with chronic medical conditions</article-title><source>Journal of Clinical Nursing</source><year>2016</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>3131</fpage><lpage>3143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jocn.13244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27140392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6430571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Timko</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Britt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cucciare</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transitioning from detoxification to substance use disorder treatment</article-title><source>Journal of Substance Abuse Treatment</source><year>2016</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2016.07.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27692190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6448765</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torous</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bucci</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kessing</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faurholt-Jepsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The growing field of digital psychiatry: Current evidence and the future of apps, social media, chatbots, and virtual reality</article-title><source>World Psychiatry</source><year>2021</year><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>318</fpage><lpage>335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wps.20883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34505369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8429349</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vederhus</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Timko</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hjemdahl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clausen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Motivational intervention to enhance post-detoxification 12-Step group affiliation: A randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>Addiction</source><year>2014</year><volume>109</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>766</fpage><lpage>773</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/add.12471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24400937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4282103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wakeman</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilens</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Regan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The prevalence of unhealthy alcohol and drug use among inpatients in a general hospital</article-title><source>Substance Abuse</source><year>2020</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08897077.2019.1635961</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31368860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wakeman</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metlay</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rigotti</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inpatient addiction consultation for hospitalized patients increases post-discharge abstinence and reduces addiction severity</article-title><source>Journal of General Internal Medicine</source><year>2017</year><volume>32</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>909</fpage><lpage>916</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-017-4077-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28526932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5515798</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wakeman</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rigotti</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Regan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effectiveness of post-discharge navigation added to an inpatient addiction consultation for patients with substance use disorder: A randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>Substance Abuse</source><year>2021</year><volume>42</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>646</fpage><lpage>653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08897077.2020.1809608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32881639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Defries</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lozada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tulsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An inpatient treatment and discharge planning protocol for alcohol dependence</article-title><source>Journal of General Internal Medicine</source><year>2015</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-014-2968-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25092008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4351284</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>