<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pneumonia (Nathan)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pneumonia (Nathan)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3233</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">pneumonia</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Pneumonia</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2200-6133</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11762896</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11762896.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11762896</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11762896</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39856755</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41479-024-00155-7</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">155</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Commonly prescribed medications and risk of pneumonia and all-cause mortality in people with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: a UK population-based cohort study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names initials="AD">Ann D.</given-names></name><address><email>a.morgan15@imperial.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Massen</surname><given-names initials="GM">Georgie M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names initials="HR">Hannah R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names initials="I">Iain</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names initials="G">Gisli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names initials="PM">Peter M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quint</surname><given-names initials="JK">Jennifer K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/041kmwe10</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7445.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2113 8111</institution-id><institution>School of Public Health, </institution><institution>Imperial College London, </institution></institution-wrap>London, UK </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/041kmwe10</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7445.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2113 8111</institution-id><institution>National Heart and Lung Institute, Imperial College London, </institution></institution-wrap>London, UK </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02218z997</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.421662.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9216 5443</institution-id><institution>Interstitial Lung Disease Unit, </institution><institution>Royal Brompton Hospital and Harefield NHS Foundation Trust, </institution></institution-wrap>London, UK </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478553</issue-id><elocation-id>2</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>25</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>26</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-01-27 02:25:49.967"><day>27</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="41479_2024_Article_155.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">A growing body of evidence suggests that prolonged use of inhaled corticosteroids (ICS) and proton pump inhibitors (PPIs) is associated with increased risks of pneumonia. A substantial proportion of people with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF) are prescribed PPIs or ICS to treat common comorbidities, giving rise to concerns that use of these medications may be associated with potential harms in this patient population.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">We used UK Clinical Practice Research Datalink (CPRD) Aurum primary care data linked to national mortality and hospital admissions data to create a cohort of people diagnosed with IPF on or after 1 January 2010. Patients were assigned to one of three exposure categories according to their prescribing history in the 12&#160;months prior to IPF diagnosis as follows: &#8220;regular&#8221; users (&#8805;&#8201;4 prescriptions), &#8220;irregular&#8221; users (1&#8211;3 prescriptions) and &#8220;non-users&#8221; (no prescriptions). We explored the association between PPI/ICS prescription and pneumonia hospitalisation and all-cause mortality using multinomial Cox regression models.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">A total of 17,105 people met our study inclusion criteria; 62.6% were male and 15.9% were current smokers. Median age at IPF diagnosis was 76.7&#160;years (IQR: 69.6&#8211;82.7). 19.9% were regularly prescribed PPIs, and 16.0% ICS, prior to IPF diagnosis. Regular prescribing of PPIs and ICS was positively associated with hospitalisation for pneumonia; the adjusted HR for pneumonia hospitalisation comparing regular PPI users with non-users was 1.14 (95%CI: 1.04&#8211;1.24); for regular ICS users the corresponding HR was 1.40 (95%CI: 1.25&#8211;1.55). We also observed a small increased risk for all-cause mortality in the &#8220;regular ICS user&#8221; group compared with the &#8220;non-user&#8221; control group (HR<sub>adj</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;1.19, 1.06&#8211;1.33). We found no evidence of an association between PPI prescribing and all-cause mortality.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Prolonged prescription of medications used to treat common comorbidities in IPF may be associated with increased risks for severe respiratory infections. These findings point to a need to adopt an adequate risk&#8211;benefit balance approach to the prescribing of ICS-containing inhalers and PPIs in people with IPF without evidence of comorbidities, especially older patients and/or those with more advanced disease in whom respiratory infections are more likely to result in poorer outcomes.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s41479-024-00155-7.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Pneumonia</kwd><kwd>Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</kwd><kwd>Inhaled corticosteroids</kwd><kwd>Antacids</kwd><kwd>Proton pump inhibitors</kwd><kwd>Electronic health records</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par17">Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF) is a chronic interstitial lung disease with a poor prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. It is characterised by progressive scarring of the lungs, and while rare in people under the age of 40&#160;years, prevalence increases steeply with age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. IPF is more common in men than women, and although labelled as idiopathic, several factors including smoking and occupational exposures are thought to play a role in pathogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p><p id="Par18">While the most common cause of death in people with IPF is respiratory failure due to IPF itself, around a third of patients die from comorbid conditions such as a cardiovascular disease or lung cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Interest in the role played by comorbidities in IPF has increased in recent years, not just because comorbidities are very common in this typically older patient population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] but also because of concerns surrounding the potential to cause harm by either underdiagnosing and undertreating comorbidities or by inappropriate prescribing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. In this context, medications used to treat chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) and gastro-oesophageal reflux disease (GORD) &#8211; namely inhaled corticosteroids (ICS) and proton pump inhibitors (PPIs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] &#8211; have garnered the most attention because of their associated pneumonia risks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The IPF-PPI debate is complicated by evidence that suggests that micro-aspiration caused by GORD is linked to IPF pathogenesis; this has led to the prescribing of antacids such as PPIs to IPF patients even in the absence of symptomatic GORD. However, studies exploring the associations between PPIs and mortality in IPF have shown inconsistent results, ranging from risk reductions of 50% to no association [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par19">The evidence linking use of PPIs and ICS with increased risks for pneumonia is also mixed. For example, longer-term prescription of PPIs has been linked to an increased risk of incident pneumonia in a population-based cohort of individuals aged 60&#160;years and over compared with age- and sex-matched controls not prescribed PPIs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Previous studies have also demonstrated a positive association between PPIs and pneumonia in subgroups of people with diseases such as liver cirrhosis, type-II diabetes and stroke [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Among the COPD population, however, results are inconsistent, with some studies reporting increased risks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] and others finding that PPI use did not contribute to a greater occurrence of pneumonia in people with COPD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Whether PPI use increases pneumonia risks in the IPF population is a question that has not yet been addressed, but given the high prevalence of GORD among people with IPF (up to 70% according to some studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]), it is one that merits an answer.</p><p id="Par20">Much of the evidence linking use of ICS-containing inhalers with an increased risk of pneumonia stems from the COPD literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. This evidence has recently been summarised by Miravitelles et al. in a comprehensive systematic review of both trial data and observational studies which concluded that exposure to ICS for&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;1&#160;year increases the risk of pneumonia in COPD by 41% (RR&#8201;=&#8201;1.41; 95%CI, 1.23&#8211;1.61) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Such evidence, taken together with that from mechanistic studies which shows that the same mediators that are believed to drive the increased risk of pneumonia in people with COPD are also present in people with IPF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], raises the prospect that prolonged use of ICS could also be harmful in IPF. This concern is heightened by the possibility that a proportion of people with IPF are being inappropriately treated with ICS, in the sense that they do not have comorbid COPD or asthma but have instead been misdiagnosed as having COPD and/or asthma in the period prior to their IPF diagnosis. Several studies have shown that misdiagnosis of IPF &#8211; which typically presents with non-specific symptoms such breathlessness and cough &#8211; is widespread [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p><p id="Par21">In sum, few large-scale studies have specifically addressed the question whether use of PPIs or ICS increases pneumonia risk in people with IPF. The aims of this study were two-fold, firstly to examine the patterns of PPI and ICS prescribing among a UK population-based cohort of people with a diagnosis of IPF (with and without comorbid COPD and GORD) using routinely-collected primary and secondary healthcare data, and secondly to test the hypothesis that people with IPF prescribed PPIs or ICS on a regular basis are at increased risk for severe pneumonia or all-cause mortality.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Data source</title><p id="Par22">Primary care data were provided by the Clinical Practice Research Datalink (CPRD). We used CPRD&#8217;s Aurum database (February 2022 build), which contains routinely-collected GP data for around 20% of the UK population. These data were linked to Hospital Episode Statistics (HES), specifically inpatient (admitted patient care or APC) data, mortality data curated by the Office for National Statistics (ONS), and socioeconomic data (Index of Multiple Deprivation (IMD)). These linkages were provided by CPRD for the purposes of this study but were only possible for English practices. CPRD Aurum data are representative of the population of England, with respect to age, sex, location and socioeconomic status [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study population</title><p id="Par23">To be included in the study, people had to have received their diagnosis of IPF between 1 January 2010 and 31 December 2019 and be aged 40&#160;years or over at the time of IPF diagnosis. The code set that was used to define our cohort of people with IPF was developed and validated by the authors of this study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Diagnosis date was the date of the first IPF record in primary care. Study participants also had to meet certain data quality standards, be male or female, and be registered at a GP practice eligible for linkage to HES and ONS data. Finally, participants had to have at least one year of continuous registration with the same GP prior to their IPF diagnosis; this one-year period of registration was used to categorise participants into one of three exposure categories based their medication history (see below) and was chosen to achieve a balance between adequate sample size and a sufficiently long period for defining longer-term use. People were followed up until the earliest of: the end of the study period (31/12/2019), date of death, date of transfer out of practice, last collection date of practice data, or date of last HES and ONS data collection (see Supplementary Fig. S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Exposure definition</title><p id="Par24">We defined two exposures of interest, prescription of PPIs or ICS. People were categorised into three exposure groups, depending on the number of prescriptions in the 12&#160;months prior to their IPF diagnosis (baseline period). Those who were prescribed either a PPI or an ICS-containing inhaler on four or more occasions (at least 1&#160;month apart) were classified as &#8220;regular&#8221; users; those who had 1&#8211;3 prescriptions were described as &#8220;irregular&#8221; users, and those with no evidence of a prescription in the baseline period were categorised as &#8220;non-users&#8221; (control group). These categorisations were based on clinical experience and knowledge of UK GP prescribing practices and are consistent with the approach adopted by other studies. For the purposes of this study, we defined ICS inhalers as any ICS-containing inhaler approved by NICE for the treatment of COPD or asthma, i.e. ICS monotherapy inhalers, combination inhalers (ICS with long-acting beta-agonists (ICS&#8201;+&#8201;LABA) or ICS with long-acting muscarinic antagonists (ICS&#8201;+&#8201;LAMA)) and triple therapy inhalers (ICS&#8201;+&#8201;LABA&#8201;+&#8201;LAMA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Outcomes</title><p id="Par25">Our main outcome of interest was hospitalisation for pneumonia during follow up (first and subsequent events). Hospitalisations for pneumonia were identified in APC HES data using ICD-10 codes (J12.xx&#8211;J18.xx). We only included events in which the ICD-10 pneumonia code was listed as the primary diagnosis in order to exclude occurrences of hospital-acquired pneumonia. Our secondary outcome was all-cause mortality, as recorded in ONS data.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Covariates</title><p id="Par26">Demographic patient characteristics (sex, age at IPF diagnosis) were obtained from primary care data; socioeconomic status (quintiles) was extracted from linked IMD records. People were categorised into four age bands, 40&#8211;59, 60&#8211;69, 70&#8211;79, 80&#8201;+&#8201;years. Lifestyle characteristics [body mass index (BMI (underweight, normal, overweight, obese), smoking status (current, ex, never)] were determined at the time of IPF diagnosis (using the closest recorded values to this date). The presence of the following comorbidities at any point prior to IPF diagnosis was described using a binary variable (yes, no): COPD, asthma, pulmonary arterial hypertension, lung cancer, GORD, ischaemic heart disease (IHD), hiatus hernia, heart failure and diabetes. Prescription of oral corticosteroids in the baseline period was also described using a binary variable (PPI analysis).</p><p id="Par27">All codelists used in this study can be accessed from: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/NHLI-Respiratory-Epi/IPF-PPI-ICS">https://github.com/NHLI-Respiratory-Epi/IPF-PPI-ICS</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Data analyses</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Descriptive analysis</title><p id="Par28">We explored patterns of ICS and PPI use in our study cohort, comparing the frequency of prescribing in the 12-months prior to IPF diagnosis with that in the 12-month period after. Baseline covariates (as specified above) were reported for the cohort as a whole and separately for our two exposed groups (regular and irregular users) and our control group (non-users), using frequencies for categorical variables and medians for continuous variables.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par29">Cox proportional hazard models were implemented to estimate hazard ratios (HRs) for the time to first pneumonia hospitalisation and all-cause mortality respectively, comparing non-users with irregular and regular users, separately for PPI and ICS. We used Schoenfeld residuals to check that proportional hazard assumptions were met. Rates of pneumonia hospitalisation were estimated using a negative binomial model.</p><p id="Par30">We utilised an intention-to-treat methodology such that people remained in the exposure groups they were assigned at baseline. However, as part of a series of sensitivity analyses, we repeated our primary analysis (hospitalisation for pneumonia) but excluded individuals who were prescribed ICS only after IPF diagnosis from our &#8220;non-users&#8221; control group. We also investigated, among those who were hospitalised due to pneumonia, how many were still prescribed PPIs in the 3&#160;months prior to their hospitalisation. In the context of assessing confounding by indication, in addition to adjusting for co-diagnoses of COPD and/or asthma in the case of the ICS analysis, and GORD and hiatus hernia in the case of the PPI analysis, we also tested for effect modification, and where this was significant reported stratified HRs for the association between medication use and our outcomes (pneumonia hospitalisation and all-cause mortality) for people with and without the corresponding comorbidities.</p><p id="Par31">All analyses were performed using Stata version 17. StataCorp LLC, TX, USA.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Cohort characteristics and prescribing patterns</title><p id="Par32">A total of 17,105 people met our study inclusion criteria (Supplementary Fig. S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>); 62.6% were male and 15.8% were current smokers. Median age at IPF diagnosis was 76.7&#160;years (IQR: 69.6&#8211;82.7). Nearly a quarter (23.1%) had a GP-recorded diagnosis of GORD prior to their IPF diagnosis, while 16% had a prior diagnosis of COPD. A similar proportion (17%) had been previously diagnosed with asthma. IHD, pulmonary hypertension, diabetes also ranked as highly prevalent comorbidities in our IPF study population (relative to the general adult population) (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of study cohort</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Whole cohort</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">PPI</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">ICS</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Regularly prescribed</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Irregularly prescribed</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Not prescribed</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Regularly prescribed</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Irregularly prescribed</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Not prescribed</bold></th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n (% of total)</bold><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n (% of total)</bold><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n (% of total)</bold><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n (% of total)</bold><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n (% of total)</bold><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n (% of total)</bold><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>n (% of total)</bold><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Total</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17,105 (100.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,396 (19.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,649 (9.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,060 (50.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,741 16.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,507 (8.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,857 (75.2%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Sex</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,706 (62.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,058 (60.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,000 (60.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7,648 (63.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,584 (57.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">894 (59.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8,228 (64.0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,399 (37.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,338 (39.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">649 (39.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,412 (36.58%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,157 (42.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">613 (40.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,629 (36.0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Age (years)</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Median (IQR)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76 (69&#8211;83)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77 (70&#8211; 83)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76 (69&#8212;83)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77 (70&#8211; 83)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76 (68 &#8211;81)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75 (67&#8211;81)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77 (70&#8211;83)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;40&#8211;59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,263 (7.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">188 (5.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">129 (7.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">859 (7.12%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">241 (8.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">148 (9.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">874 (6.8%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;60&#8211;69</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,214 (18.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">598 (17.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">322 (19.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,147 (17.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">570 (20.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">358 (23.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,286 (17.8%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;70&#8211;79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,516 (38.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,304 (38.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">585 (35.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,489 (37.22%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,104 (40.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">546 (36.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,866 (37.9%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;&gt;&#8201;&#8201;=&#8201;80</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,112 (35.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,306 (38.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">613 (37.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,565 (37.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">826 (30.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">455 (30.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,831 (37.6%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Index of Multiple Deprivation</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;1 (least deprived)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,530 (20.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">658 (19.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">301 (18.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,571 (21.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">458 (16.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">319 (21.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,753 (21.4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,676 (21.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">675 (19.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">345 (21.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,656 (22.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">509 (18.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">307 (20.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,860 (22.2%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,204 (18.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">611 (18.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">312 (19.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,281 (18.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">492 (18.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">304 (20.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,408 (18.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,211 (18.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">659 (19.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">313 (19.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,239 (18.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">561 (20.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">265 (17.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,385 (18.6%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;5 (most deprived)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,464 (20.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">785 (23.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">375 (22.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,304 (19.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">713 (26.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">311 (20.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,440 (19.0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Missing</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (0.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (0.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (0.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (0.29%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.07%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (0.09%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Body mass index (kg/m</italic></bold><sup><bold><italic toggle="yes">2</italic></bold></sup><bold><italic toggle="yes">)</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Underweight</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">466 (2.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72 (2.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41 (2.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">353 (2.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79 (2.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 (3.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">340 (2.6%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Normal (baseline)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,775 (22.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">710 (20.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">395 (24.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,671 (22.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">641 (23.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">313 (20.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,821 (21.9%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Overweight</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,502 (26.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">969 (28.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">438 (26.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,095 (25.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">771 (28.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">400 (26.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,331 (25.9%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Obese</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,399 (19.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">723 (21.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">294 (17.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,122 (17.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">705 (25.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">373 (24.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,321 (18.1%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Missing</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,963 (29.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">922 (27.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">481 (29.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,820 (31.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">545 (19.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">374 (24.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,044 (31.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Smoking status</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Never</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,950 (11.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">335 (9.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">185 (11.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,430 (11.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">218 (8.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">173 (11.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,559 (12.1%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Ex-smoker</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,431 (72.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,558 (75.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,221 (74.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8,667 (71.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,024 (73.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,091 (72.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9,316 (72.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Current smoker</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,712 (15.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">503 (14.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">243 (14.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,951 (16.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">499 (18.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">243 (16.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,970 (15.3%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Missing</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (0.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (0.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (0.1%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Comorbidities</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;GORD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,957 (23.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,330 (39.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">527 (68.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,100 (17.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">763 (27.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">372 (24.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,822 (22.0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;COPD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,777 (16.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">654 (19.26%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">276 (16.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,847 (15.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,396 (50.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">384 (25.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">997 (7.8%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Asthma</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,911 (17.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">695 (20.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">291 (17.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,925 (16.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,662 (60.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">481 (31.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">768 (6.0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;PAH</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">313 (1.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66 (1.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (1.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">218 (1.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56 (2.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (1.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">232 (1.8%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Lung cancer</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">137 (0.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (0.85%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (0.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94 (0.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32 (1.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (0.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94 (0.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;IHD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,657 (27.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,242 (36.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">493 (29.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,922 (24.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">735 (26.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">387 (25.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,535 (27.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Hiatus hernia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,445 (14.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">894 (26.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">293 (17.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,258 (10.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">456 (16.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">212 (14.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,777 (13.8%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Heart failure</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,844 (10.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">423 (12.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">182 (11.0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,239 (10.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">284 (10.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">117 (7.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,443 (11.2%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Diabetes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,052 (23.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">908 (26.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">416 (25.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,728 (22.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">633 (23.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">357 (23.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,062 (23.8%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">COPD</italic> Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, <italic toggle="yes">GORD</italic> Gastro-oesophageal reflux disease, <italic toggle="yes">ICS</italic> Inhaled corticosteroid, <italic toggle="yes">IHD</italic> Ischaemic heart disease, <italic toggle="yes">PAH</italic> Pulmonary arterial hypertension, <italic toggle="yes">PPI</italic> Proton pump inhibitor</p><p><sup>a</sup>Unless otherwise specified</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par33">Of the 17,105 people with IPF, 5,045 (29.5%) were prescribed a PPI at least once in the year prior to their IPF diagnosis, of whom 1,857 (36.8%) also had a diagnosis of GORD (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Of the people also diagnosed with hiatus hernia (<italic toggle="yes">n&#8201;=&#8201;</italic>2,445), 48.5% were prescribed a PPI in the baseline period. Among those not prescribed a PPI prior to their IPF diagnosis, 1,380 went on to receive a prescription for PPI in the year after their diagnosis, but were classed as &#8220;non-users&#8221;, and contributed data to the control population (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>PPI prescribing patterns pre- and post-IPF diagnosis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Prescription in year post IPF diagnosis</bold></th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No PPI</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Irregular PPI</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Regular PPI</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Total</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1"><bold>Prior prescription</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>No PPI</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,680</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">900</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">480</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,060</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Irregular PPI</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">639</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">528</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">482</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,649</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Regular PPI</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">228</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">609</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,559</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,396</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Total</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11,547</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,037</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,521</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17,105</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">IPF</italic> Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis, <italic toggle="yes">PPI</italic> Proton pump inhibitor</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par34">Regular and irregular ICS users comprised 16% (<italic toggle="yes">n&#8201;=&#8201;</italic>2,741) and 8.8% (<italic toggle="yes">n&#8201;=&#8201;</italic>1,507) of the study cohort, respectively (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Unsurprisingly, patients with a prior diagnosis of COPD or asthma were overrepresented in the ICS user groups, especially the regular users. Among the prior non-ICS users (<italic toggle="yes">n&#8201;=&#8201;</italic>12,857), 1,002 (or around 6% of the whole cohort) were prescribed an ICS-containing inhaler at least once after their IPF diagnosis (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Nearly a half of this subgroup (<italic toggle="yes">n&#8201;=&#8201;</italic>482; 48.1%) became regular ICS users post IPF diagnosis. Whereas patients who also had COPD and/or asthma dominated the pre-, post- and pre-and-post IPF ICS user groups (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a, b and c, respectively), among those who started on ICS only after an IPF diagnosis, only a third also had either a previous COPD or asthma diagnosis (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d). Among the subset of 1,002 new users, 719 (71.8%) were prescribed ICS at least once after their IPF diagnosis without having a concomitant diagnosis of either COPD or asthma, and 342 (34.1%) became regular ICS users (Supplementary Table S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Since only a very low proportion of the cohort (<italic toggle="yes">n&#8201;=&#8201;</italic>188; 1.1%) were regularly prescribed both ICS and PPIs in the baseline period, we did not mutually adjust for ICS and PPI use in our subsequent statistical analyses.<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig.&#160;1</label><caption><p>Patterns of ICS prescribing pre- and post-IPF diagnosis. ICS: Inhaled corticosteroids, COPD: chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41479_2024_155_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Pneumonia hospitalisation</title><p id="Par35">A total of 3,651 people with a diagnosis of IPF were admitted to hospital on at least one occasion for treatment for pneumonia, of whom 770 (21.1%) were regularly prescribed PPI and 391 (10.7%) were irregularly prescribed PPI in the year prior to IPF diagnosis. Similarly, 770 (21.1%) of the people hospitalised with pneumonia had a history of regular ICS prescription; 30.1% of those hospitalised had been prescribed ICS at least once.</p><p id="Par36">In adjusted Cox regression analyses, any prescription of PPIs and ICS in the 12-month period prior to IPF diagnosis was associated with a modest increased risk of hospitalisation for pneumonia. In the case of ICS, there was some evidence of a dose&#8211;response relationship (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>; Supplementary Table S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>). The adjusted rate of hospitalisations for pneumonia was also elevated in patients who were prescribed PPIs in the baseline period (relative to non-users) (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The association was more pronounced in ICS users; hospitalisations were increased by 51% in regular ICS users (95% CI: 33%&#8211;72%) and by 26% in irregular users (95% CI: 10%&#8211;44%), compared with non-users.<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig.&#160;2</label><caption><p>Hazard ratios for pneumonia hospitalisation and all-cause mortality relative to prescriptions of PPI and ICS in a cohort of people with IPF. PPI: proton pump inhibitor, ICS: inhaled corticosteroids</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41479_2024_155_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Association between medication use and rate of pneumonia hospitalisations in a cohort of people with IPF (complete-case analysis)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Unadjusted model</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Fully-adjusted model</bold><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>IRR</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>95% CI</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold><bold>-value</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>IRR</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>95% CI</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold><bold>-value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Proton pump inhibitors</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Non-users</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Irregular users</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.08&#8211;1.43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03&#8211;1.35</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.018</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Regular users</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.10&#8211;1.35</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03&#8211;1.26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Inhaled corticosteroids</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Non-users</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Irregular users</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12&#8211;1.47</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.10&#8211;1.44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Regular users</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.62&#8211;1.98</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.51</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.33&#8211;1.72</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">CI</italic> Confidence interval, <italic toggle="yes">IRR</italic> Incident rate ratio</p><p><sup>a</sup>Adjusted for age, sex, smoking history, index of multiple deprivation, COPD, asthma, lung cancer, gastro-oesophageal reflux disease, hiatus hernia, ischaemic heart disease, heart failure, pulmonary artery hypertension and type 2 diabetes. In the case of the PPI analysis, the fully-adjusted model was additionally adjusted for prescription of an oral corticosteroid (at least once in the 12&#160;months prior to IPF diagnosis)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>All-cause mortality</title><p id="Par37">Among our study cohort, all of whom were diagnosed with IPF after 1/1/2010, around a half (<italic toggle="yes">n&#8201;=&#8201;</italic>8,964; 52.4%) died before the end of the study period (31/12/2019). The median survival time for this group of patients was 1.7&#160;years (IQR: 0.68&#8211;3.25). Prescription of PPIs (regularly or irregularly) in the baseline period was not significantly associated with all-cause mortality (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). In a crude Cox regression analysis, we found that people who were prescribed ICS on a regular basis had a small increased risk of dying from any cause relative to non-ICS users (HR<sub>unadj</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;1.06; 95%CI, 1.03&#8211;1.25) (Table S2). Adjustment for both demographic/lifestyle factors and comorbidities had the effect of increasing the HR for this association (HR<sub>adj</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;1.25; 95%CI, 1.16&#8211;1.34), reflecting the tendency in this IPF cohort towards a higher prevalence of comorbidities such as COPD in the ICS-user group compared with the non-users (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Irregular use of ICS was not associated with a shorter survival time, relative to non-use, in either a crude analysis or adjusted analysis (Table S2).</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Sensitivity analyses</title><p id="Par38">Details of our sensitivity analyses are provided in Supplementary Material <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>. In summary, we found that in the case of our PPI analysis neither GORD nor hiatus hernia were effect modifiers of the association between PPI prescribing and our primary and secondary outcomes (hospitalisation for pneumonia and all-cause mortality). We found only weak evidence to suggest that concomitant diagnoses of COPD or asthma had a modifying effect on the relationship between ICS prescribing and risk of pneumonia hospitalisation (see Supplementary Tables S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>&#8211;S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par39">In a cohort of patients diagnosed with IPF between 2010 and 2019, we observed a positive association between prescription of ICS in the year prior to diagnosis and hospitalisation for pneumonia, which remained significant after adjustment for key confounders. We found a similar, slightly weaker relationship, for PPI. We also observed a small increased risk for all-cause mortality in the &#8220;regular ICS user&#8221; group (compared with the &#8220;non-user&#8221; control group); however, we found no evidence of an association between the prescription of PPIs and all-cause mortality.</p><p id="Par40">While other studies have reported increased pneumonia risks among longer-term users of ICS and PPIs, this is one of the largest studies to explicitly address this question in an IPF population. Our findings suggest that the same risks are present in people with IPF, which &#8211; given their age and high prevalence of conditions which are indications for ICS and PPIs &#8211; should be viewed as a potential cause for concern. At the very least the evidence for increased pneumonia risk should prompt clinicians to carefully consider the risk&#8211;benefit balance of continuing (or initiating) ICS/PPI use in people newly-diagnosed with IPF. This may be especially pertinent in people whose presenting respiratory symptoms may have been misdiagnosed as COPD or late-onset asthma prior to their IPF diagnosis, and in whom continuation of ICS is unlikely to confer any benefit. Several studies have established that misdiagnosis of non-specific respiratory symptoms is not only common in IPF but also leads to diagnostic delays, of up 5&#160;years in some cases, as well as poorer outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].</p><p id="Par41">In our study cohort, around three quarters of patients who were prescribed ICS prior to their IPF diagnosis continued to be prescribed ICS post-diagnosis. Both prior- and post-ICS prescription was highly correlated with a prior diagnosis of either COPD or asthma, but we were not able to ascertain what proportion of our study cohort had comorbid COPD or asthma and what proportion had been misdiagnosed and therefore potentially inappropriately treated. Nevertheless, given estimates of the proportion of IPF patients with comorbid COPD/emphysema tend to centre around 30% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], we suspect that a sizeable number of IPF patients may be continuing to be prescribed ICS-containing inhalers post diagnosis even though they do not have confirmed obstructive disease.</p><p id="Par42">In contrast, we found little evidence of over-prescribing of PPIs in our study cohort. The IPF management guidelines that were in place during the period of this study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] include a conditional recommendation to consider treating people with IPF with antacid therapies, irrespective of GORD symptoms. This was based on early retrospective data demonstrating improved survival [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] and a slowing of disease progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] in people with IPF on antacids. Subsequent studies, which found no longer-term benefit of antacids and in one case evidence of increased risk of respiratory infections in patients with advanced IPF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], have brought this recommendation into question [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] and the latest (2022) guidelines instead advise clinicians to only prescribe antacid medication to treat symptoms of GORD when present [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. We found that only 20.6% of our cohort were prescribed PPIs on at least four occasions in the year following their diagnosis, suggesting that even during the period that they were active, the older guidelines were not necessarily being followed.</p><p id="Par43">While in our study cohort both ICS and PPI prescribing was associated with an increased risk for pneumonia, only those prescribed ICS on a regular basis appeared to be at increased risk for all-cause mortality. We observed a statistically significant 25% increase in risk for all-cause mortality in regular ICS users, after adjustment for age, smoking status and comorbid conditions including COPD and lung cancer. The reasons behind this apparent association are likely complex, but without further investigation, we can only speculate as to the possible drivers. Part of the increased mortality risk might be attributed to higher likelihood of diagnostic delays in those prescribed inhaled therapies prior to their IPF diagnosis, denying patients the opportunity to initiate anti-fibrotic therapies at an earlier disease stage. Support for this hypothesis comes from a study conducted by Hoyer et al. involving 264 patients which found that longer diagnostic delays (over 1&#160;year) were associated with worse progression-free survival times than shorter delays (&lt;&#8201;1&#160;year) (HR&#8201;=&#8201;1.70, 95% CI: 1.18&#8211;2.46, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.004). Interestingly, diagnostic delay was not significantly associated with all-cause survival (HR&#8201;=&#8201;1.54, 95%&#8201;CI: 0.95&#8211;2.51, p&#8201;=&#8201;0.08) but the small sample size may mean that this study was underpowered with respect to mortality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].</p><sec id="Sec17"><title>Strengths and limitations</title><p id="Par44">The main strength of this study derives from the use of CPRD&#8217;s Aurum dataset to define a large population-based cohort of people with a diagnosis of IPF. Validation work has confirmed the high positive predictive value (PPV) of GP-recorded diagnoses of IPF in this database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]; this primary-care dataset has the added advantage of containing accurate prescribing information. Nevertheless, we have had to rely on prescribing history as a proxy for medication use as Aurum does not provide data on whether prescriptions were filled; this may result in overestimation of actual medication use. Conversely, over-the-counter antacid therapies have not been captured, and it is therefore possible that we have underestimated PPI use. However, for a high proportion of our study cohort, prescriptions are free of charge (i.e. in the over 60s) and thus use of over-the-counter antacids may be less significant.</p><p id="Par45">Our study has a number of other limitations. Identification of our primary outcome events, hospitalisation for pneumonia, relies on diagnosis and ICD-10 coding by hospital consultants and staff, and we cannot be certain that diagnoses have been confirmed by microbiological testing. It is also likely that there is some misclassification of pneumonia outcomes, with some events in truth being acute exacerbations of IPF. Between 10% and 20% of people with IPF experience an acute exacerbation each year and such events are associated with high mortality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. However, misclassification is most likely non-differential and as such would have minimal impact on our Cox-regression-based conclusions.</p><p id="Par46">This being an observational study, establishing cause-and-effect can be challenging and we acknowledge that we may not have fully adjusted for all potential sources of confounding. In the context of this study, confounding by indication is likely to be a significant issue. Adjustment for COPD and asthma did indeed noticeably reduce the magnitude of our HRs, but even after adjustment for these conditions, ICS use &#8211; even irregular use &#8211; was strongly associated with an increased risk of severe pneumonia, from which we inferred that while clearly present, confounding by indication alone cannot account for our findings. Furthermore, our sensitivity analyses, in which we explored the possibility of effect modification by COPD and/or asthma, found little evidence to suggest that the presence of COPD/asthma was driving the observed association: our stratified analyses indicate increased risks for both outcomes irrespective of the presence or absence of COPD and/or asthma (see Supplementary Material <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). The same is true of the PPI analyses: we found no evidence of effect modification of the association between PPI use and pneumonia by the presence of GORD or hiatus hernia. That said there may well be other risk factors for pneumonia which are also associated with the ICS and PPI use that we have not been able to account for (e.g. previous infections, more severe disease).</p><p id="Par47">While we acknowledge that use of a time-varying exposure may have been a more robust modelling strategy, we considered that in our cohort this approach was not warranted and unlikely to materially affect our conclusions. As part of our descriptive analyses, we ascertained that most people who were prescribed ICS before their IPF diagnosis continued to be prescribed ICS after. A sensitivity analysis in which we excluded those individuals who only initiated ICS therapy after IPF diagnosis from the control group generated broadly similar results. In addition, we determined that most people who were prescribed PPI in the baseline exposure period were also prescribed PPI in the 3&#160;months prior to their first pneumonia hospitalisation.</p><p id="Par48">Finally, we were unable to explore what may be driving the observed increased risk for all cause-mortality in regular ICS users. However, this question merits further study, especially as this finding appears to be peculiar to the IPF patient population. In people with COPD, ICS use is not generally associated with increased mortality and is likely to be protective in some subgroups, such as frequent exacerbators and those with concomitant asthma. Replication of our study in other IPF cohorts would confirm whether an increased mortality risk is unique to our study cohort, which with a survival time of 1.7&#160;years from IPF diagnosis, is likely to be dominated by individuals with more advanced IPF.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par49">We have shown that prolonged prescription of medications used to treat COPD and GORD, both common comorbidities in IPF, may be associated with increased risks for severe respiratory infections. While as yet unconfirmed in other IPF cohorts, these findings point to a need to adopt an adequate risk&#8211;benefit balance approach to the prescribing of ICS-containing inhalers and PPIs in people with IPF without evidence of these comorbidities, especially older patients and/or those with more advanced disease in whom respiratory infections are more likely to result in poorer outcomes, hospitalisation and even death. While our PPI findings add to the ongoing debate over the safety and efficacy of antacid therapy in IPF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], they do not provide resolution and further studies, including appropriately designed clinical trials, are needed. We await the results of the ongoing TIPAL trial of lansoprazole in IPF with interest (ISRCT Number: ISRCTN13526307).</p></sec><sec id="Sec19" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41479_2024_155_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>COPD</term><def><p id="Par5">Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CPRD</term><def><p id="Par6">Clinical Practice Research Datalink</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GORD</term><def><p id="Par7">Gastro-oesophageal reflux disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HES</term><def><p id="Par8">Hospital Episode Statistics</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICD-10</term><def><p id="Par9">International Classification of Disease (10th revision)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICS</term><def><p id="Par10">Inhaled corticosteroid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IPF</term><def><p id="Par11">Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LABA</term><def><p id="Par12">Long-acting beta-agonist</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LAMA</term><def><p id="Par13">Long-acting muscarinic antagonist</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NICE</term><def><p id="Par14">National Institute for Clinical Excellence</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ONS</term><def><p id="Par15">Office of National Statistics</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PPI</term><def><p id="Par16">Proton pump inhibitor</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Ann D. Morgan and Georgie M. Massen joint first authors.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Not applicable.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>Peter M. George (PMG) and Jennifer K. Quint (JKQ) developed the research question. Ann Morgan (AM) and JQ contributed to study conceptualisation and design.&#160; The data were curated and analysed by AM and Georgie Massen (GM); all authors interpreted the results. AM and GM drafted the first version of the manuscript. All authors and critically reviewed and revised the manuscript before providing final approval.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was part of an investigated initiated study funded by Boehringer Ingelheim, awarded to Professor Jennifer Quint. The funder did not have access to data, did not contribute or influence the study design nor the interpretation of results.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Code sets used in this study are available to download from the GITHub repository (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/NHLI-Respiratory-Epi/IPF-PPI-ICS">https://github.com/NHLI-Respiratory-Epi/IPF-PPI-ICS</ext-link>).</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par50">In the UK the protocol for this research was approved by the Independent Scientific Advisory Committee (ISAC) for MHRA Database Research (protocol number 22_002016 and the approved protocol was made available to the journal and reviewers during peer review. The interpretation and conclusions contained in this study are those of the authors alone.</p><p id="Par51">This study is based in part on data from the Clinical Practice Research Datalink obtained under license from the UK Medicines and Healthcare products Regulatory Agency. The data is provided by patients and collected by the NHS as part of their care and support. Linked pseudonymised data was provided for this study by CPRD. Data is linked by NHS Digital, the statutory trusted third party for linking data, using identifiable data held only by NHS Digital. Select general practices consent to this process at a practice level with individual patients having the right to opt-out. The Office for National Statistics (ONS) was the provider of the ONS Data contained within the CPRD Data and maintains a Copyright &#169; 2019, re-used with the permission of The Health &amp; Social Care Information Centre, all rights reserved.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par52">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par53">JKQ has been supported by institutional research grants from the Industrial Strategy Challenge Fund, the Medical Research Council, Health Data Research, GlaxoSmithKline, Boehringer Ingelheim, asthma+lung UK and Astra Zeneca and has received personal fees for advisory board participation, consultancy or speaking fees from GlaxoSmithKline, Evidera, Chiesi, AstraZeneca and Insmed. PMG has received grants from MRC, Boehringer Ingelheim and Roche Pharmaceuticals and personal fees from Boehringer Ingelheim, Roche Pharmaceuticals, Teva, Cippla, Astra Zeneca and Brainomix. GJ declares grants from Astra Zeneca, Biogen, Galecto, GlaxoSmithKline, Nordic Biosciences, RedX, UKRI and Pliant, and personal fees for advisory board participation, consultancy or speaking fees from Astra Zeneca, Brainomix, Bristol Myers Squibb, Chiesi, Cohbar, Daewoong, GlaxoSmithKline, Veracyte, Resolution Therapeutics, Pliant, Boehringer Ingelheim, Roche, PatientMPower, Galapagos and Vicore. GM, AM, HW and IS have no competing interests to disclose.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global incidence and prevalence of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>197</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-021-01791-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34233665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8261998</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Maher TM, et al. Global incidence and prevalence of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. Respir Res. 2021;22(1):197.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34233665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12931-021-01791-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8261998</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wijsenbeek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cottin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spectrum of Fibrotic Lung Diseases</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>383</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>958</fpage><lpage>968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra2005230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32877584</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Wijsenbeek M, Cottin V. Spectrum of Fibrotic Lung Diseases. N Engl J Med. 2020;383(10):958&#8211;68.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32877584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMra2005230</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caminati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comorbidities in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: An underestimated issue</article-title><source>Eur Respir Rev</source><year>2019</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>190044</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/16000617.0044-2019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31578211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9488913</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Caminati A, et al. Comorbidities in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: An underestimated issue. Eur Respir Rev. 2019;28: 190044.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31578211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/16000617.0044-2019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9488913</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis in the UK: analysis of the British Thoracic Society electronic registry between 2013 and 2019</article-title><source>ERJ Open Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>00187</fpage><lpage>2020</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/23120541.00187-2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33532476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7836645</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Spencer LG, et al. Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis in the UK: analysis of the British Thoracic Society electronic registry between 2013 and 2019. ERJ Open Res. 2021;7(1):00187&#8211;2020.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33532476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/23120541.00187-2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7836645</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Margaritopoulos</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kokosi</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnosing complications and co-morbidities of fibrotic interstitial lung disease</article-title><source>Expert Rev Respir Med</source><year>2019</year><volume>13</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>658</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17476348.2019.1632196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31215263</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Margaritopoulos GA, Kokosi MA, Wells AU. Diagnosing complications and co-morbidities of fibrotic interstitial lung disease. Expert Rev Respir Med. 2019;13(7):645&#8211;58.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31215263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/17476348.2019.1632196</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nathan</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: effects and optimal management of comorbidities</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(16)30222-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27599614</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">King CS, Nathan SD. Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: effects and optimal management of comorbidities. Lancet Respir Med. 2017;5(1):72&#8211;84.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27599614</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2213-2600(16)30222-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raghu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High prevalence of abnormal acid gastro-oesophageal reflux in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2006</year><volume>27</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.06.00037005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16387946</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Raghu G, et al. High prevalence of abnormal acid gastro-oesophageal reflux in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. Eur Respir J. 2006;27(1):136&#8211;42.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16387946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/09031936.06.00037005</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kew</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seniukovich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhaled steroids and risk of pneumonia for chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2014</year><volume>2014</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>Cd010115</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24615270</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD010115.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8966042</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Kew KM, Seniukovich A. Inhaled steroids and risk of pneumonia for chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2014;2014(3):Cd010115.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24615270</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD010115.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8966042</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fohl</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Regal</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proton pump inhibitor-associated pneumonia: Not a breath of fresh air after all?</article-title><source>World J Gastrointest Pharmacol Ther</source><year>2011</year><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4292/wjgpt.v2.i3.17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21731913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3124633</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Fohl AL, Regal RE. Proton pump inhibitor-associated pneumonia: Not a breath of fresh air after all? World J Gastrointest Pharmacol Ther. 2011;2(3):17&#8211;26.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21731913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4292/wjgpt.v2.i3.17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3124633</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suissa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparing New-User Cohort Designs: The Example of Proton Pump Inhibitor Effectiveness in Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis</article-title><source>Am J Epidemiol</source><year>2021</year><volume>190</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>928</fpage><lpage>938</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwaa242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33124647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8096489</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Tran T, Suissa S. Comparing New-User Cohort Designs: The Example of Proton Pump Inhibitor Effectiveness in Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis. Am J Epidemiol. 2021;190(5):928&#8211;38.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33124647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/aje/kwaa242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8096489</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zirk-Sadowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proton-Pump Inhibitors and Long-Term Risk of Community-Acquired Pneumonia in Older Adults</article-title><source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source><year>2018</year><volume>66</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1332</fpage><lpage>1338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgs.15385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29676433</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6099478</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Zirk-Sadowski J, et al. Proton-Pump Inhibitors and Long-Term Risk of Community-Acquired Pneumonia in Older Adults. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2018;66(7):1332&#8211;8.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29676433</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jgs.15385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6099478</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wongtrakul</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charoenngnam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ungprasert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of proton pump inhibitors is associated with a higher risk of pneumonia in cirrhotic patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Ann Gastroenterol</source><year>2020</year><volume>33</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32382231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.20524/aog.2020.0483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7196626</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Wongtrakul W, Charoenngnam N, Ungprasert P. Use of proton pump inhibitors is associated with a higher risk of pneumonia in cirrhotic patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Ann Gastroenterol. 2020;33(3):277&#8211;84.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32382231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.20524/aog.2020.0483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7196626</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of Increased Risk of Pneumonia and Using Proton Pump Inhibitors in Patients With Type II Diabetes Mellitus</article-title><source>Dose Response</source><year>2019</year><volume>17</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1559325819843383</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1559325819843383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31080379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6498779</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Lin WL, et al. Association of Increased Risk of Pneumonia and Using Proton Pump Inhibitors in Patients With Type II Diabetes Mellitus. Dose Response. 2019;17(2):1559325819843383.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31080379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1559325819843383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6498779</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk of post-stroke pneumonia with proton pump inhibitors, H2 receptor antagonists and mucoprotective agents: A retrospective nationwide cohort study</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e0216750</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0216750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31067267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6505944</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Song TJ, Kim J. Risk of post-stroke pneumonia with proton pump inhibitors, H2 receptor antagonists and mucoprotective agents: A retrospective nationwide cohort study. PLoS ONE. 2019;14(5): e0216750.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31067267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0216750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6505944</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The impact of acid-suppressing drugs to the patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: A nationwide, population-based, cohort study</article-title><source>J Res Med Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/1735-1995.156174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26109973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4468231</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Lee SW, et al. The impact of acid-suppressing drugs to the patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: A nationwide, population-based, cohort study. J Res Med Sci. 2015;20(3):263&#8211;7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26109973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4468231</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proton Pump Inhibitors Did Not Increase Risk of Pneumonia in Patients With Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</article-title><source>J Clin Med Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>880</fpage><lpage>883</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14740/jocmr2322w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26491501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4596270</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Lee SW, et al. Proton Pump Inhibitors Did Not Increase Risk of Pneumonia in Patients With Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease. J Clin Med Res. 2015;7(11):880&#8211;3.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26491501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14740/jocmr2322w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4596270</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raghu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comorbidities in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis patients: a systematic literature review</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2015</year><volume>46</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1113</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.02316-2014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26424523</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Raghu G, et al. Comorbidities in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis patients: a systematic literature review. Eur Respir J. 2015;46(4):1113.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26424523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/13993003.02316-2014</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Calverley</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Salmeterol and fluticasone propionate and survival in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>356</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>775</fpage><lpage>789</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa063070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17314337</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Calverley PM, et al. Salmeterol and fluticasone propionate and survival in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. N Engl J Med. 2007;356(8):775&#8211;89.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17314337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMoa063070</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chalmers</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keir</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>10&#8197;years since TORCH: shining a new light on the risks of inhaled corticosteroids in COPD</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2017</year><volume>50</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1701582</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.01582-2017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28931673</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Chalmers JD, Keir HR. 10&#8197;years since TORCH: shining a new light on the risks of inhaled corticosteroids in COPD. Eur Respir J. 2017;50(3):1701582.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28931673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/13993003.01582-2017</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekl&#246;f</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of inhaled corticosteroids and risk of acquiring Pseudomonas aeruginosa in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2022</year><volume>77</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>573</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2021-217160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34446524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9120392</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Ekl&#246;f J, et al. Use of inhaled corticosteroids and risk of acquiring Pseudomonas aeruginosa in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. Thorax. 2022;77(6):573&#8211;80.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34446524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2021-217160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9120392</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suissa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inhaled corticosteroids in COPD and the risk of serious pneumonia</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2013</year><volume>68</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1029</fpage><lpage>1036</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2012-202872</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24130228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3812880</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Suissa S, et al. Inhaled corticosteroids in COPD and the risk of serious pneumonia. Thorax. 2013;68(11):1029&#8211;36.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24130228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2012-202872</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3812880</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miravitlles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Systematic review on long-term adverse effects of inhaled corticosteroids in the treatment of COPD</article-title><source>Eur Respir Rev</source><year>2021</year><volume>30</volume><issue>160</issue><fpage>210075</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/16000617.0075-2021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34168063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9488732</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Miravitlles M, et al. Systematic review on long-term adverse effects of inhaled corticosteroids in the treatment of COPD. Eur Respir Rev. 2021;30(160): 210075.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34168063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/16000617.0075-2021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9488732</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Molyneaux</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of bacteria in the pathogenesis and progression of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>190</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>906</fpage><lpage>913</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201403-0541OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25184687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4299577</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Molyneaux PL, et al. The role of bacteria in the pathogenesis and progression of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2014;190(8):906&#8211;13.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25184687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1164/rccm.201403-0541OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4299577</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singanayagam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Corticosteroid suppression of antiviral immunity increases bacterial loads and mucus production in COPD exacerbations</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2229</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-04574-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29884817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5993715</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Singanayagam A, et al. Corticosteroid suppression of antiviral immunity increases bacterial loads and mucus production in COPD exacerbations. Nat Commun. 2018;9(1):2229.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29884817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41467-018-04574-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5993715</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singanayagam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inhaled corticosteroid suppression of cathelicidin drives dysbiosis and bacterial infection in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Sci Transl Med</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><issue>507</issue><fpage>eaav3879</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.aav3879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31462509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7237237</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Singanayagam A, et al. Inhaled corticosteroid suppression of cathelicidin drives dysbiosis and bacterial infection in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. Sci Transl Med. 2019;11(507):eaav3879.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31462509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/scitranslmed.aav3879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7237237</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Potential Delays in Diagnosis of Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis in Medicare Beneficiaries</article-title><source>Ann Am Thorac Soc</source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30620617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1513/AnnalsATS.201806-376RL</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6394124</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Mooney J, et al. Potential Delays in Diagnosis of Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis in Medicare Beneficiaries. Ann Am Thorac Soc. 2019;16(3):393&#8211;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30620617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1513/AnnalsATS.201806-376RL</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6394124</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Data resource profile: Clinical Practice Research Datalink (CPRD) Aurum</article-title><source>Int J Epidemiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>48</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1740</fpage><lpage>1740g</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyz034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30859197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6929522</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Wolf A, et al. Data resource profile: Clinical Practice Research Datalink (CPRD) Aurum. Int J Epidemiol. 2019;48(6):1740&#8211;1740g.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30859197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ije/dyz034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6929522</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Validation of the recording of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis in routinely collected electronic healthcare records in England</article-title><source>BMC Pulm Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>256</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12890-023-02550-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37434192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10337174</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Morgan A, et al. Validation of the recording of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis in routinely collected electronic healthcare records in England. BMC Pulm Med. 2023;23(1):256.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37434192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12890-023-02550-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10337174</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoyer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for diagnostic delay in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>103</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-019-1076-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31126287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6534848</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Hoyer N, et al. Risk factors for diagnostic delay in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. Respir Res. 2019;20(1):103.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31126287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12931-019-1076-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6534848</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoyer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diagnostic delay in IPF impacts progression-free survival, quality of life and hospitalisation rates</article-title><source>BMJ Open Respir Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e001276</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjresp-2022-001276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35798532</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9263910</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Hoyer N, et al. Diagnostic delay in IPF impacts progression-free survival, quality of life and hospitalisation rates. BMJ Open Respir Res. 2022;9(1): e001276.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35798532</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjresp-2022-001276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9263910</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raghu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An official ATS/ERS/JRS/ALAT statement: idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: evidence-based guidelines for diagnosis and management</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>183</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>788</fpage><lpage>824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.2009-040GL</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21471066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5450933</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Raghu G, et al. An official ATS/ERS/JRS/ALAT statement: idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: evidence-based guidelines for diagnosis and management. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2011;183(6):788&#8211;824.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21471066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1164/rccm.2009-040GL</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5450933</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raghu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An Official ATS/ERS/JRS/ALAT Clinical Practice Guideline: Treatment of Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis. An Update of the 2011 Clinical Practice Guideline</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>192</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e3</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201506-1063ST</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26177183</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Raghu G. An Official ATS/ERS/JRS/ALAT Clinical Practice Guideline: Treatment of Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis. An Update of the 2011 Clinical Practice Guideline. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2015;192(2):e3&#8211;19.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26177183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1164/rccm.201506-1063ST</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gastroesophageal reflux therapy is associated with longer survival in patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>184</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1390</fpage><lpage>1394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201101-0138OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21700909</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3262030</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Lee JS, et al. Gastroesophageal reflux therapy is associated with longer survival in patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2011;184(12):1390&#8211;4.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21700909</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1164/rccm.201101-0138OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3262030</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anti-acid treatment and disease progression in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: an analysis of data from three randomised controlled trials</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2013</year><volume>1</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(13)70105-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24429201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4059609</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Lee JS, et al. Anti-acid treatment and disease progression in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: an analysis of data from three randomised controlled trials. Lancet Respir Med. 2013;1(5):369&#8211;76.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24429201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2213-2600(13)70105-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4059609</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreuter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antacid therapy and disease outcomes in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: a pooled analysis</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>4</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(16)00067-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27050871</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Kreuter M, et al. Antacid therapy and disease outcomes in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: a pooled analysis. Lancet Respir Med. 2016;4(5):381&#8211;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27050871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2213-2600(16)00067-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of Proton Pump Inhibitors in Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis: A Population-Based Cohort Study</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>2021</year><volume>159</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>673</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chest.2020.08.2080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32882251</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Tran T, et al. Effectiveness of Proton Pump Inhibitors in Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis: A Population-Based Cohort Study. Chest. 2021;159(2):673&#8211;82.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32882251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.chest.2020.08.2080</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suissa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of anti-acid therapy on survival in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: a&#160;methodological review of observational studies</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2018</year><volume>51</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1800376</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.00376-2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29724921</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Tran T, Suissa S. The effect of anti-acid therapy on survival in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: a&#160;methodological review of observational studies. Eur Respir J. 2018;51(6):1800376.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29724921</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/13993003.00376-2018</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghebre</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raghu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proton pump inhibitors in IPF: beyond mere suppression of gastric acidity</article-title><source>QJM</source><year>2016</year><volume>109</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>579</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/qjmed/hcw115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27647940</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5943831</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Ghebre Y, Raghu G. Proton pump inhibitors in IPF: beyond mere suppression of gastric acidity. QJM. 2016;109(9):577&#8211;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27647940</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/qjmed/hcw115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5943831</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raghu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis (an Update) and Progressive Pulmonary Fibrosis in Adults: An Official ATS/ERS/JRS/ALAT Clinical Practice Guideline</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>205</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>e18</fpage><lpage>e47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.202202-0399ST</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35486072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9851481</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Raghu G, et al. Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis (an Update) and Progressive Pulmonary Fibrosis in Adults: An Official ATS/ERS/JRS/ALAT Clinical Practice Guideline. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2022;205(9):e18&#8211;47.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35486072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1164/rccm.202202-0399ST</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9851481</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Podolanczuk</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: state of the art for 2023</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2023</year><volume>61</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>2200957</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.00957-2022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36702498</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Podolanczuk AJ, et al. Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: state of the art for 2023. Eur Respir J. 2023;61(4):2200957.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36702498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/13993003.00957-2022</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raghu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-acid treatment in patients with IPF: interpret results from post-hoc, subgroup, and exploratory analyses with great caution</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>4</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>e46</fpage><lpage>e47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(16)30234-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27599250</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Raghu G. Anti-acid treatment in patients with IPF: interpret results from post-hoc, subgroup, and exploratory analyses with great caution. Lancet Respir Med. 2016;4(9):e46&#8211;7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27599250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2213-2600(16)30234-X</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>