<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2277</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">frontpubhealth</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Public Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2296-2565</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11840442</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11840442.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11840442</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11840442</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39980931</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2025.1455726</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Public Health</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The changing burden of gout in adults aged 70 and above based on the global burden of disease 2019</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yang</given-names></name><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2778147/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/visualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhong</given-names></name><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff><institution>Department of Orthopedics, Xiangtan Central Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Xiangtan</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn id="fn0001" fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Ourlad Alzeus G. Tantengco, University of the Philippines Manila, Philippines</p></fn><fn id="fn0002" fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Alvin Duke R. Sy, University of the Philippines Manila, Philippines</p><p>Jesse Hall, Nascent Biosciences, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Zhong Liu, <email>xtszxyylz@163.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">480651</issue-id><elocation-id>1455726</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>02</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>06</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>20</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-02-23 20:25:42.583"><day>23</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2025 Yang and Liu.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Yang and Liu</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fpubh-13-1455726.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Gout is a significant global health issue, particularly among adults aged 70 and above. Understanding its epidemiological evolution and associated factors is crucial for guiding interventions and improving management.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Methods</title><p>This study analyzed data from the Global Burden of Disease study to assess the prevalence and trends of gout among adults aged 70 and above from 1990 to 2019. We evaluated temporal trends and regional disparities by calculating the estimated annual percentage change (EAPCs).</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Results</title><p>Globally, the number of older adults individuals affected by gout increased from 5,316,210 cases in 1990 to 15,666,063 cases in 2019. It is noteworthy that the global burden of gout among the older adults continued to rise from 1990 to 2019, with an EAPC of 1.17 (95% CI: 1.02 to 1.32). In 2019, the prevalence rates among individuals aged 70&#8211;74, 75&#8211;79, 80&#8211;84, and 85 and above were 3,121.31 per 100,000, 3,437.17 per 100,000, 3,592.38 per 100,000, and 3,726.91 per 100,000, respectively. The regions with the highest prevalence rates of gout in 2019 were Australasia, High-income North America, and Southern Latin America, with rates of 8,500.73, 8,351.33, and 4,666.87 per 100,000, respectively. At the national level, some developed countries such as New Zealand, the United States of America, and Australia had the highest prevalence rates, reaching 8,893.74, 8,508.06, and 8,427.94 per 100,000, respectively. It is noteworthy that regions with higher levels of Socio-Demographic Index tended to have relatively higher burden of gout among the older adults, and the prevalence rates varied across different regions and age groups.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The study underscores the persistent burden of gout among the older adults, emphasizing the need for targeted interventions to address this issue and improve public health outcomes in this demographic.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>global burden of disease</kwd><kwd>gout</kwd><kwd>older adults people</kwd><kwd>prevalence</kwd><kwd>public health</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that no financial support was received for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="2"/><ref-count count="39"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="6440"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Aging and Public Health</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec5"><title>Introduction</title><p>Gout, formerly labeled the &#8220;disease of kings,&#8221; has transitioned from a malaise tied to wealth to one impacting a wider demographic, particularly the older adults (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). This longstanding condition, caused by the buildup of monosodium urate crystals in joints, has seen a global rise in prevalence, paralleling the increase in non-communicable diseases. In addition to its health impact, gout contributes to healthcare costs and is linked to renal and cardiovascular diseases. It also causes productivity losses due to frequent flare-ups (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Age emerges as a pivotal factor in gout risk, with incidence rates escalating notably after 40 and peaking among those aged 70 and above (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). This demographic shift is propelled by a intricate interplay of age-related physiological changes, encompassing reduced renal uric acid excretion and alterations in purine metabolism, compounded by the cumulative burden of prevalent comorbidities in older adults, such as hypertension, diabetes, and cardiovascular disease (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Age is an important factor, but other confounding variables like lifestyle, comorbidities (such as obesity or diet), could also significantly influence gout risk. These factors, however, were not the focus of this analysis and could be further explored in future studies.</p><p>Moreover, lifestyle elements like diet, alcohol intake, and sedentary habits, once synonymous with affluent lifestyles, have become widespread across diverse socio-economic strata, exacerbating the burden of gout among older populations worldwide (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Despite its pervasive impact, gout in older adults remains often overlooked and undertreated, resulting in substantial morbidity, diminished quality of life, and heightened healthcare utilization (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). The dearth of comprehensive epidemiological data on gout burden, particularly among those aged 70 and above, impedes efforts to devise targeted interventions and allocate resources effectively to tackle this burgeoning public health challenge (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p><p>Leveraging the comprehensive dataset of the Global Burden of Disease (GBD) project, renowned for reshaping our understanding of global health dynamics, our study aims to elucidate the trajectory of gout prevalence and its impact on this demographic (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). By analyzing GBD data from 1990 to 2019, spanning a wide range of countries and regions, we seek to uncover trends in gout incidence among older adults. Through this analysis, we aim to provide valuable insights to guide evidence-based interventions aimed at alleviating the global burden of gout and improving health outcomes for individuals aged 70 and above.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec6"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec7"><title>Data sources</title><p>The utilization of the Global Health Data Exchange Query Tool facilitated access to the GBD database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ghdx.healthdata.org/gbd-2019" ext-link-type="uri">https://ghdx.healthdata.org/gbd-2019</ext-link>) (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). In this investigation, a meticulous evaluation was conducted on 369 diseases and injuries, alongside an analysis of 87 risk factors (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Subsequent to this initial phase, the tool was then employed to retrieve data pertaining to gout incidence rates from a span of 204 countries and 21 regions, covering the period from 1990 to 2019 (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). The categorization of these 21 regional groupings of countries was based on considerations of geographic proximity and shared epidemiological characteristics (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p><p>Through the utilization of Socio-demographic Index (SDI) data, a segmentation of various regions and countries was performed, delineating them into categories of low, low-middle, middle, middle-high, and high-SDI (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). The primary aim was to explore the potential correlation between SDIs and the prevalence of gout among individuals aged 70&#8239;years and older (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Our comprehensive data collection efforts were inclusive of individuals from both genders and spanned across four distinct age groups: 70&#8211;74&#8239;years, 75&#8211;79&#8239;years, 80&#8211;84&#8239;years, and 85&#8239;years and older (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Notably, this research is grounded upon publicly available databases and does not necessitate ethical approval.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>This study was conducted to ascertain the burden of gout among individuals aged 70&#8239;years and older across diverse regions and countries within the GBD 2019, meticulously determining a 95% uncertainty interval (UI) for each parameter (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Utilizing the incidence rate per 100,000 population as a foundation for population-size-based rates, the investigation delved into the trends in incidence rates over a specified period, employing estimated annual percentage changes (EAPCs) for characterization (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). We selected the EAPC model for its simplicity and suitability in identifying broad, long-term trends in gout incidence, aligning with the study&#8217;s aim to provide a population-level overview. Given the chronic nature of gout, our analysis excludes non-linear trends and seasonality, focusing on overall trends across regions and time. However, alternative methods, such as multivariate regression models or subgroup analysis, may offer deeper insights into the impact of confounding variables, which could be considered in future research. Employing a joint regression model, regression analysis was undertaken to dissect the disease burden. To calculate the EAPC, a logarithmic linear regression model was adopted, with the natural logarithm of the incidence rate (y) as the dependent variable and the calendar year (x) as the independent variable, following the formula:</p><disp-formula id="E1"><mml:math id="M1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mi>&#945;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#949;</mml:mi></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="E2"><mml:math id="M2" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>EAPC</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#215;</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#8211;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Notably, trends indicating an increase in burden were depicted by lower limits of the EAPC and its 95% CI exceeding 0, while trends indicating a decrease were illustrated by upper limits of the EAPC and its 95% CI dipping below 0. Furthermore, Pearson correlation analysis was conducted to explore the association between the EAPC in 1990 and the incidence rate of gout among individuals aged 70&#8239;years and older (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Similarly, correlations between the EAPC in 2019 and the SDI were investigated. Additionally, the correlation between gout incidence rates and SDI for all countries was examined. The obtained correlation coefficient (<italic toggle="yes">&#961;</italic>) and corresponding <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values were used to evaluate the strength and significance of these associations.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec9"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec10"><title>Global estimates of gout prevalence among older adults aged 70 and above</title><p>Globally, the prevalence and trends of gout among individuals aged 70 and above from 1990 to 2019 are illustrated in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. As depicted in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>, the number of cases increased from 5,316,210 in 1990 to 15,666,063 in 2019, approximately tripling over the period. It is noteworthy that the number of cases in males was twice that of females, with 10,469,254 cases in males and 5,196,809 cases in females in 2019 (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Considering the changing global demographic structure, the prevalence of gout among individuals aged 70 and above (including males and females) has continuously increased by 1.17 (95% CI: 1.02 to 1.32) over the 30-year period (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref> and <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). This underscores the growing burden of gout among the older adults population globally, indicative of improvements in living standards. Additionally, hyperuricemia, a key factor in gout development, has significant implications for health, contributing to an increased risk of renal and cardiovascular diseases, as well as other metabolic disorders (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Trends in gout prevalence in adults aged 70 and above, 1990 to 2019. <bold>(A)</bold> Prevalence cases of gout by sex. <bold>(B)</bold> Prevalence rates of gout by sex. <bold>(C)</bold> Prevalence cases of gout by age group. <bold>(D)</bold> Prevalence rates of gout by age group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fpubh-13-1455726-g001.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The global prevalence rates and their change trends of gout aged 70+ from 1990 to 2019.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases_1990</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases_2019</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases_change</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rates_1990</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rates_2019</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EAPC_CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Global</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,316,210 (3,777,893 to 7,119,246)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,666,063 (11,472,118 to 20,377,053)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95 (1.86 to 2.07)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2637.70 (1874.45 to 3532.30)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3378.67 (2474.17 to 4394.68)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 (1.02 to 1.32)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,892,599 (1,326,232 to 2,522,938)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,196,809 (3,800,303 to 6,770,118)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75 (1.65 to 1.89)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1586.22 (1111.54 to 2114.52)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1996.76 (1460.18 to 2601.28)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.93 to 1.26)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,423,611 (2,438,770 to 4,579,369)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,469,254 (7,679,209 to 13,669,666)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06 (1.96 to 2.18)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4163.35 (2965.71 to 5568.84)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">514,677 (3775.16 to 6720.12)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.89 to 1.21)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Age</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70&#8211;74 aged</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,054,548 (1,357,009 to 2,910,296)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,839,571 (3,948,444 to 8,154,114)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.84 (1.76 to 1.94)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2431.03 (1605.67 to 3443.58)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3121.31 (2110.48 to 4358.45)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 (1.02 to 1.33)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 79 aged</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,641,447 (1,125,971 to 2,262,237)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,367,056 (3,076,023 to 5,862,878)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66 (1.59 to 1.76)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2677.32 (1836.54 to 3689.88)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3437.17 (2421.04 to 4614.48)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 (0.98 to 1.25)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80&#8211;84 aged</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,004,867 (646,362 to 1,492,787)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,032,776 (2,008,923 to 4,427,786)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02 (1.93 to 2.14)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2853.14 (1835.23 to 4238.50)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3592.38 (2379.61 to 5244.80)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.97 to 1.24)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85+ aged</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">615,348 (433,721 to 850,091)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,426,660 (1,759,024 to 3,272,478)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.94 (2.8 to 3.11)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3001.08 (2115.28 to 4145.94)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3726.91 (2701.54 to 5025.94)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.95 to 1.25)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">SDI regions</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High SDI</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,315,548 (1,662,110 to 3,092,105)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,533,153 (5,011,397 to 8,220,821)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82 (1.64 to 2.06)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3516.10 (2523.87 to 4695.28)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5090.64 (3904.88 to 6405.67)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83 (1.61 to 2.05)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High-middle SDI</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,272,263 (895,506 to 1,700,001)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,538,606 (2,525,011 to 4,745,667)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78 (1.71 to 1.86)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2293.45 (1614.29 to 3064.52)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2974.34 (2122.37 to 3988.92)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.97 to 1.24)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Middle SDI</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,022,560 (727,511 to 1,375,121)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,593,678 (2,530,865 to 4,836,968)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.51 (2.41 to 2.62)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2260.40 (1608.18 to 3039.75)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2867.30 (2019.31 to 3859.29)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.92 to 1.19)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low-middle SDI</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">496,819 (350,967 to 672,969)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,493,929 (1,057,420 to 2,007,544)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01 (1.93 to 2.09)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1970.01 (1391.67 to 2668.49)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2188.50 (1549.05 to 2940.92)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.36 to 0.44)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low SDI</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206,925 (146,631 to 278,525)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">501,469 (355,282 to 671,464)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42 (1.35 to 1.5)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2144.05 (1519.32 to 2885.94)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2225.08 (1576.43 to 2979.37)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09 (0.07 to 0.12)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Location</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Andean Latin America</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,782 (7,631 to 14,429)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41,579 (29,893 to 55,265)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.86 (2.68 to 3.08)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1056.18 (747.53 to 1413.46)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1323.19 (951.30 to 1758.73)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.81 to 0.87)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australasia</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85,059 (62,216 to 114,513)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">281,986 (210,200 to 370,429)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.32 (2.03 to 2.64)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5836.54 (4269.14 to 7857.64)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8500.73 (6336.67 to 11166.94)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46 (1.34 to 1.58)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caribbean</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,153 (9,984 to 19,180)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34,811 (24,958 to 46,871)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46 (1.35 to 1.58)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">949.73 (669.97 to 1287.06)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1129.44 (809.76 to 1520.74)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 (0.62 to 0.67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central Asia</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39,190 (27,595 to 52,749)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55,731 (39,274 to 74,742)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42 (0.36 to 0.48)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1761.36 (1240.26 to 2370.78)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1989.65 (1402.11 to 2668.36)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 (0.48 to 0.54)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central Europe</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112,698 (78,806 to 154,300)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221,356 (157,670 to 298,490)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.91 to 1.03)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1436.20 (1004.29 to 1966.36)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1583.46 (1127.89 to 2135.23)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44 (0.38 to 0.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central Latin America</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25,494 (17,850 to 34,864)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93,156 (66,360 to 125,447)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.65 (2.55 to 2.76)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">627.15 (439.10 to 857.65)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">715.15 (509.44 to 963.05)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (0.55 to 0.84)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central Sub-Saharan Africa</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,907 (14,638 to 28,496)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47,033 (32,747 to 63,614)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 (1.09 to 1.43)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2498.48 (1749.35 to 3405.48)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2410.26 (1678.18 to 3260.00)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.16 (&#8722;0.23 to &#8722;0.08)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Asia</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,061,024 (751,282 to 1,441,036)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,205,637 (2,952,393 to 5,679,490)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.96 (2.8 to 3.13)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2677.71 (1896.01 to 3636.75)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3754.38 (2635.61 to 5070.10)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (1.4 to 1.81)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eastern Europe</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">268,899 (188,474 to 365,174)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">427,184 (302,310 to 573,129)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59 (0.54 to 0.65)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1775.42 (1244.41 to 2411.09)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2087.77 (1477.47 to 2801.04)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68 (0.63 to 0.72)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eastern Sub-Saharan Africa</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79,423 (56,371 to 106,984)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">179,418 (126,923 to 239,819)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26 (1.19 to 1.33)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2521.75 (1789.83 to 3396.83)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2638.86 (1866.78 to 3527.24)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 (0.12 to 0.17)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High-income Asia Pacific</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">358,118 (249,805 to 479,677)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,198,965 (863,685 to 1,588,946)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35 (2.21 to 2.52)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3179.12 (2217.59 to 4258.25)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3606.10 (2597.68 to 4779.03)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.48 to 0.53)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High-income North America</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,072,781 (777,464 to 1,429,993)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,378,574 (2,716,986 to 4,116,484)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15 (1.8 to 2.63)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4593.51 (3329.00 to 6123.05)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8351.33 (6715.98 to 10175.34)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.29 (2.75 to 3.84)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North Africa and Middle East</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170,757 (120,603 to 229,661)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">507,252 (357,391 to 679,606)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97 (1.87 to 2.07)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2282.28 (1611.94 to 3069.58)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2598.91 (1831.09 to 3481.96)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39 (0.33 to 0.44)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oceania</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,526 (2,466 to 4,801)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,174 (6,454 to 12,513)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (1.46 to 1.79)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3243.18 (2268.12 to 4415.93)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3541.46 (2491.49 to 4830.22)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 (0.28 to 0.34)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Asia</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">413,727 (291,332 to 559,608)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,414,244 (1,003,246 to 1,904,109)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.42 (2.32 to 2.53)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1889.29 (1330.37 to 2555.45)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2045.94 (1451.36 to 2754.62)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 (0.18 to 0.25)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southeast Asia</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">272,663 (194,066 to 366,451)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">814,479 (574,546 to 1,095,299)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.99 (1.9 to 2.08)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2495.23 (1775.96 to 3353.51)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2932.30 (2068.49 to 3943.32)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 (0.61 to 0.66)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southern Latin America</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99,524 (70,464 to 134,368)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">244,138 (175,368 to 328,659)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45 (1.32 to 1.6)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3783.25 (2678.58 to 5107.78)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4666.87 (3352.28 to 6282.54)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 (0.68 to 0.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southern Sub-Saharan Africa</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38,159 (26,986 to 50,957)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79,753 (56,211 to 107,130)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (1.03 to 1.15)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2867.78 (2028.08 to 3829.58)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3008.05 (2120.13 to 4040.62)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 (0.09 to 0.21)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tropical Latin America</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41,150 (28,757 to 55,726)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157,002 (112,392 to 210,523)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.82 (2.67 to 2.98)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">946.78 (661.64 to 1282.13)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1173.53 (840.08 to 1573.58)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (0.76 to 0.84)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Western Europe</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,036,249 (742,703 to 1,393,819)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,088,578 (1,527,132 to 2,773,769)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.94 to 1.1)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2773.70 (1987.97 to 3730.80)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3282.87 (2400.38 to 4359.87)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.72 to 0.89)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Western Sub-Saharan Africa</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91,928 (64,870 to 123,285)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186,013 (131,443 to 250,463)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.98 to 1.07)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2308.31 (1628.87 to 3095.67)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2374.50 (1677.90 to 3197.21)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 (&#8722;0.13 to 0.14)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data in parentheses are 95% uncertainty intervals for cases and rates, and 95% confidence intervals for EAPC.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>We conducted a detailed analysis among older adults individuals in different age groups. From 1990 to 2019, the number of gout patients in the 70&#8211;74 age group was significantly higher than in other age groups, followed by the 75&#8211;79 age group, 80&#8211;84 age group, and 85+ age group (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref>). However, although the number of patients aged 70&#8211;74 was the highest, the prevalence rate was the opposite, possibly related to the population base of the corresponding age group. Specifically, the prevalence rates of gout among older adults individuals aged 70&#8211;74, 75&#8211;79, 80&#8211;84, and 85+ were 3121.31 per 100,000, 3437.17 per 100,000, 3592.38 per 100,000, and 3726.91 per 100,000, respectively (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1D</xref> and <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Regardless of the age group, the trend of gout among the older adults has been on the rise (EAPC between 1 and 1.18), indicating an increasing burden of gout among the older adults population (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). This highlights the need for attention to evidence-based interventions.</p></sec><sec id="sec11"><title>Regional differences of gout prevalence among older adults aged 70 and above</title><p>Within the global landscape, significant disparities exist in both the absolute number and prevalence of gout cases among individuals aged 70 and above, influenced by varying levels of socioeconomic development and geographical locations. Generally, in regions with high SDI, the burden of gout has markedly increased, with the number of cases rising from 2,315,548 in 1990 to 6,533,153 in 2019, representing a growth rate of 1.82 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref> and <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). However, it&#8217;s notable that in regions with higher SDI, the prevalence of gout among individuals aged 70 and above is also higher, while areas with lower SDI exhibit lower prevalence rates (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>). For instance, in High SDI regions, the prevalence reached 5,090.64 per 100,000 people in 2019, whereas in Low SDI regions, it was 2,225.08 per 100,000 people (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref> and <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Across High SDI, High-middle SDI, Middle SDI, Low-middle SDI, and Low SDI regions, the trends of gout burden, as indicated by EAPCs, were 1.83 (95% CI: 1.61 to 2.05), 1.1 (95% CI: 0.97 to 1.24), 1.06 (95% CI: 0.92 to 1.19), 0.4 (95% CI: 0.36 to 0.44), and 0.09 (95% CI: 0.07 to 0.12), respectively (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). This illustrates that the higher quality of life in High SDI regions has contributed to the increased burden of gout.</p><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Regional differences in gout prevalence in adults aged 70 and above. <bold>(A)</bold> Prevalence cases of gout by SDI regions. <bold>(B)</bold> Prevalence rates of gout by SDI regions. <bold>(C)</bold> Prevalence cases of gout in 2019 in low to high SDI and 21 GBD regions. <bold>(D)</bold> Prevalence rates of gout in 2019 in low to high SDI and 21 GBD regions.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fpubh-13-1455726-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>There are significant disparities in the prevalence of gout among individuals aged 70 and above across different regions. In 2019, the number of cases in 21 GBD regions is illustrated in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C</xref>. The regions with the highest prevalence rates were Australasia (8,500.73 per 100,000), High-income North America (8,351.33 per 100,000), and Southern Latin America (4,666.87 per 100,000). Specifically, the prevalence rates for males were 13,037.29 per 100,000, 12,456.31 per 100,000, and 7,427.33 per 100,000, respectively, while for females, the rates were 5,195.93 per 100,000, 4,684.13 per 100,000, and 2,767.55 per 100,000 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2D</xref>). It is noteworthy that from 1990 to 2019, the regions with the most rapid growth in gout burden among the older adults were High-income North America, East Asia, and Australasia, with EAPCs of 3.29 (95% CI: 2.75 to 3.84), 1.6 (95% CI: 1.4 to 1.81), and 1.46 (95% CI: 1.34 to 1.58), respectively (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>According to our analysis, we found that the prevalence of gout among the older adults is relatively low in Tropical Latin America, the Caribbean, and Central Latin America, with incidence rates of 1,173.53 per 100,000, 1,129.44 per 100,000, and 715.15 per 100,000, respectively (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Specifically, the prevalence rates for males were 1,712.33 per 100,000, 1,618.82 per 100,000, and 996.89 per 100,000, while for females, the rates were 777.53 per 100,000, 726.98 per 100,000, and 486.03 per 100,000 (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Interestingly, among these 21 geographical regions, only Central Sub-Saharan Africa exhibited a decreasing burden of gout, with an EAPC of &#8722;0.16 (95% CI: &#8722;0.23 to &#8722;0.08).</p></sec><sec id="sec12"><title>National differences of gout prevalence among older adults aged 70 and above</title><p>Due to regional disparities, there are significant variations in the prevalence of gout among individuals aged 70 and above across different countries, reflecting the influence of various factors. At the national level, among the 204 countries analyzed, China, the United States of America, and India had the highest absolute numbers of cases in 2019, with 4,041,719, 3,059,118, and 1,156,386 cases, respectively (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). This could be attributed to the large population sizes of these countries. When considering the prevalence per 100,000 individuals, we found that some developed countries such as New Zealand, the United States of America, and Australia had the highest prevalence rates, reaching 8,893.74 per 100,000, 8,508.06 per 100,000, and 8,427.94 per 100,000, respectively (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref> and <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). In contrast, countries with lower levels of economic development, such as Guatemala, Honduras, and Nicaragua, had very low rates of gout prevalence, with only 604.19 per 100,000, 618.75 per 100,000, and 618.93 per 100,000 individuals, respectively (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref> and <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The global prevalence rates of gout among individuals aged 70 and above, as well as their changing trends from 1990 to 2019, vary across different countries and regions. <bold>(A)</bold> Prevalence rates of gout in 204 countries in 2019. <bold>(B)</bold> The EAPC of gout prevalence rates in 204 countries from 1990 to 2019.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fpubh-13-1455726-g003.jpg"/></fig><p>It is noteworthy that over the past 30&#8239;years, Togo, the Democratic Republic of the Congo, and Zambia have effectively managed the burden of gout among the older adults, showing the most significant declines. Their EAPCs were&#8239;&#8722;&#8239;0.34 (95% CI: &#8722;0.38 to &#8722;0.3), &#8722;0.34 (95% CI: &#8722;0.43 to &#8722;0.24), and&#8239;&#8722;0.23 (95% CI: &#8722;0.27 to &#8722;0.19), respectively (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref> and <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). In contrast, China, Australia, and the United States of America have experienced a continuous increase in the burden of gout, with EAPCs of 1.66 (95% CI: 1.42 to 1.91), 1.68 (95% CI: 1.51 to 1.85), and 3.55 (95% CI: 2.93 to 4.18), respectively (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref> and <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). In fact, these countries have also undergone rapid economic development in recent decades, suggesting that multi-country cooperation in healthcare strategies and public health initiatives could help mitigate the growing burden of gout (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec13"><title>Correlations between EAPC, prevalence rates, and SDI in gout prevalence among older adults aged 70 and above</title><p>Expanding upon our initial epidemiological inquiry, we uncovered a noteworthy correlation between gout prevalence among the older adults and the SDI across diverse regions. This emphasizes the intricate relationship between socioeconomic factors and the incidence of this disease, shedding light on their complex interplay. Subsequent correlation analysis focused on the trends of gout prevalence among the older adults. <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref> illustrates that while there was no direct correlation between the trends represented by EAPC values and the prevalence in 1990 (<italic toggle="yes">&#961;</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.051, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.471), a robust positive correlation emerged with higher SDI levels (<italic toggle="yes">&#961;</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.463, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.001) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref>). Further examination of SDI levels across different regions revealed a compelling trend: regions with higher SDI levels tended to exhibit relatively higher prevalence rates (<italic toggle="yes">&#961;</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.407, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.001) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4C</xref>). Similarly, at the national level, this correlation appeared evident (<italic toggle="yes">&#961;</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.245, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.001) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4D</xref>), potentially attributed to the diverse socioeconomic conditions within each country. These findings underscore the presence of complex interactions among various factors influencing the prevalence of gout among the older adults, emphasizing the need for nuanced, context-specific approaches to address this health challenge.</p><fig position="float" id="fig4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Correlation of EAPC, prevalence, and SDI of gout prevalence in adults aged 70 and above. <bold>(A)</bold> The relationship between EAPC and prevalence rates in 1990. <bold>(B)</bold> The association between EAPC and SDI in 2019. <bold>(C)</bold> The correlation between prevalence and SDI at the regional level. <bold>(D)</bold> The relationship between prevalence and SDI at the national level.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fpubh-13-1455726-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec14"><title>Discussion</title><p>The pathogenesis of gout is a complex process involving disturbances in uric acid metabolism, genetic factors, lifestyle, and the interactions of various chronic diseases (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Recent research indicates that in addition to elevated uric acid levels, multiple factors such as inflammation, aberrant immune responses, and lifestyle-related conditions (e.g., obesity, dietary habits) play significant roles in the onset and progression of gout. However, these factors were not comprehensively included in the current analysis, and future studies should explore their impact in more detail (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). For example, emerging studies suggest that inflammatory mediators play crucial roles during gout flares and may serve as new therapeutic targets (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Additionally, genetic factors are considered important contributors to gout onset, particularly among the older adults population, where genetic susceptibility may exacerbate the development and worsening of gout (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). However, with socioeconomic development and lifestyle changes, gout has transitioned from being a disease primarily associated with affluent individuals to one affecting a broader population, especially the older adults (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). This transition reflects global trends of rising non-communicable disease prevalence and the impact of global population aging (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Despite the increasing prominence of gout among the older adults population, clinical practice often overlooks and inadequately treats gout in this demographic, leading to serious health issues and wastage of medical resources.</p><p>In this study, we utilized the comprehensive dataset from the GBD project to analyze the trends in gout prevalence among individuals aged 70 and above worldwide. Our analysis showed a consistent increase in gout prevalence among the older adults globally, particularly in developed countries and regions. This trend may be influenced by unaccounted confounding factors such as lifestyle changes, rising obesity rates, and associated comorbidities, which were not explicitly controlled for in this study. This increase is likely associated with improvements in living standards, changes in dietary patterns, rising obesity rates, and increasing prevalence of chronic diseases. However, the current analysis did not employ advanced statistical techniques, such as multivariate regression or stratified analysis, which could have better controlled for these confounding factors and provided more nuanced insights. Specifically, in some developed countries, there is a noticeable upward trend in gout prevalence, possibly due to factors such as high-sodium, high-fat diets, alcohol consumption, and lack of physical activity. It is noteworthy that in some low and middle-income countries and regions, the prevalence of gout is relatively low, which may be attributed to traditional dietary patterns, rural lifestyles, and insufficient healthcare resources (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Additionally, underexcretion of uric acid is a key factor in gout and contributes to its increasing prevalence. URAT-1 inhibitors offer promising treatments by improving uric acid excretion and reducing flare-ups. These advancements could help reduce the growing burden of gout, particularly in countries with rising prevalence (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>).</p><p>In recent years, significant progress has been made in gout research, deepening our understanding of its pathogenesis and providing new directions and strategies for its prevention and treatment (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Recent studies have shown that gout onset is not only associated with abnormalities in uric acid metabolism but also involves the activation of inflammatory mediators, genetic susceptibility, and lifestyle factors (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Among these, emerging research has identified inflammatory mediators as key players during gout flares, serving as novel therapeutic targets (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). By investigating the changes in inflammatory mediators such as IL-1&#946; and IL-6 during gout flares, scientists have found a significant association between their increase and joint pain and inflammatory responses in gout patients (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Therefore, interventions targeting inflammatory mediators, such as the use of IL-1&#946; inhibitors, have become one of the new strategies for gout treatment.</p><p>Furthermore, recent genetic studies have highlighted the significant role of genetic factors in the onset of gout (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Scientists have found that mutations in specific genes are closely associated with the risk of developing gout, particularly among the older adults population (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). The discovery of these genetic susceptibility genes provides new insights into personalized prevention and treatment strategies for gout, aiding in better identification and intervention for high-risk individuals (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). The proportion of the older adults population in each country influences the burden of gout. Countries with a higher percentage of older adults individuals tend to have a higher prevalence of gout due to the increased risk associated with aging. This demographic shift highlights the need for targeted healthcare strategies for aging populations. Additionally, recent epidemiological studies have revealed the importance of lifestyle factors in the onset of gout. Factors such as obesity, high-sodium diets, alcohol consumption, and lack of exercise are closely related to the risk of developing gout (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). Therefore, lifestyle interventions such as weight control, improving dietary patterns, limiting alcohol intake, and increasing physical activity are considered essential measures for preventing and managing gout, helping to reduce the incidence of gout and alleviate symptoms.</p><sec id="sec15"><title>Strengths and limitations</title><p>Although our study offers important insights into global gout trends among the older adults population aged 70 and above, it has several notable limitations. First, the use of a relatively simple statistical model, such as the EAPC, did not allow for the adjustment of key confounding factors, including comorbid conditions (e.g., diabetes, cardiovascular diseases) and lifestyle factors (e.g., diet, alcohol consumption, physical activity), which are known to influence gout prevalence. Second, data accuracy may be affected by variations in reporting practices and potential underreporting, particularly in regions with limited healthcare infrastructure. These factors could result in an incomplete understanding of the underlying drivers of the observed trends. Additionally, the use of a simple EAPC model without adjusting for potential confounding variables may have led to an incomplete understanding of the factors contributing to the increase in gout prevalence (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Nonetheless, our study serves as a foundation for future research and intervention efforts, emphasizing the need for improved data quality and the consideration of broader age ranges and geographical factors to enhance the effectiveness of interventions.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec16"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In summary, gout is on the rise worldwide, especially among the older adults, notably males, with prevalence peaking in those aged 70&#8211;74. Regional and national disparities are evident, with higher rates in more developed areas. While this study highlights important trends, future research should consider more complex models to account for confounding factors like comorbidities and lifestyle. These findings emphasize gout as a global health concern, guiding more targeted prevention and intervention strategies.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec17"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/<xref rid="sec22" ref-type="sec">Supplementary material</xref>, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author/s.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="sec18"><title>Author contributions</title><p>YY: Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Software, Validation, Visualization, Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. ZL: Conceptualization, Data curation, Project administration, Supervision, Validation, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec20"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec21"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec22"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpubh.2025.1455726/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpubh.2025.1455726/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomsen</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leishmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Optimising gout treatment: insights from a nurse-led cohort study</article-title>. <source>RMD Open</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e004179</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/rmdopen-2024-004179</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38663881</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11043733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molenberghs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verbeke</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahimi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McInnes</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Gout and incidence of 12 cardiovascular diseases: a case-control study including 152&#8200;663 individuals with gout and 709&#8200;981 matched controls</article-title>. <source>Lancet Rheumatol</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e156</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>67</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2665-9913(23)00338-7</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38383089</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yokose</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Challener</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanikella</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Serum urate and recurrent gout</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>331</volume>:<fpage>417</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2023.26640</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38319333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10848075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of comprehensive nursing intervention on quality of life and treatment outcomes in elderly patients with gout and hyperuricemia complicated with hypertension</article-title>. <source>Pak J Med Sci</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>358</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12669/pjms.40.3.7535</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38356818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10862416</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in blood pressure is associated with bone loss in US adults: a cross-sectional study from NHANES 2005-2018</article-title>. <source>Calcif Tissue Int</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>114</volume>:<fpage>276</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>85</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00223-023-01176-y</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38261009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuwabara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuta</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ouchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurajoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Exploring the multifaceted Nexus of uric acid and health: a review of recent studies on diverse diseases</article-title>. <source>Biomol Ther</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1519</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biom13101519</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37892201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10604821</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Georgel</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Georgel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Where epigenetics meets food intake: their interaction in the development/severity of gout and therapeutic perspectives</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>752359</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2021.752359</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34603340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8484966</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term exposure to ambient air pollution and incident gout: a prospective cohort study in the UK biobank</article-title>. <source>Environ Pollut</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>345</volume>:<fpage>123540</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2024.123540</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38341067</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global burden of hematologic malignancies and evolution patterns over the past 30 years</article-title>. <source>Blood Cancer J</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41408-023-00853-3</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37193689</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10188596</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll1">GBD 2019 Diseases and Injuries Collaborators</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Global burden of 369 diseases and injuries in 204 countries and territories, 1990-2019: a systematic analysis for the global burden of disease study 2019</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>396</volume>:<fpage>1204</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30925-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33069326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7567026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll2">GBD 2019 Risk Factors Collaborators</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Global burden of 87 risk factors in 204 countries and territories, 1990-2019: a systematic analysis for the global burden of disease study 2019</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>396</volume>:<fpage>1223</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>49</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30752-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33069327</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7566194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yon</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tizaoui</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koyanagi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global burden of gout in 1990-2019: a systematic analysis of the global burden of disease study 2019</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Investig</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>e13937</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/eci.13937</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36511834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global, regional and national burdens of gout in the young population from 1990 to 2019: a population-based study</article-title>. <source>RMD Open</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e003025</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003025</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37094981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10152042</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll3">GBD Spinal Cord Injuries Collaborators</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Global, regional, and national burden of spinal cord injury, 1990-2019: a systematic analysis for the global burden of disease study 2019</article-title>. <source>Lancet Neurol</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1026</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>47</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(23)00287-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37863591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10584692</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Global, regional, and national burden of inguinal, femoral, and abdominal hernias: a systematic analysis of prevalence, incidence, deaths, and DALYs with projections to 2030</article-title>. <source>Int J Surg</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>110</volume>:<fpage>1951</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>67</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JS9.0000000000001071</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38265437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11020045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Global epidemiological patterns in the burden of Main non-communicable diseases, 1990-2019: relationships with socio-demographic index</article-title>. <source>Int J Public Health</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>1605502</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/ijph.2023.1605502</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36726528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9884670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Gout and colorectal Cancer likelihood: insights from a nested case-control study of the Korean population utilizing the Korean National Health Insurance Service-National Sample Cohort</article-title>. <source>Cancers (Basel)</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>5602</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cancers15235602</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38067309</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10705350</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Trend dynamics of gout prevalence among the Chinese population, 1990-2019: a joinpoint and age-period-cohort analysis</article-title>. <source>Front Public Health</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1008598</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.1008598</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36311630</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9602928</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global, regional, and National Epidemiology of visual impairment in working-age individuals, 1990-2019</article-title>. <source>JAMA Ophthalmol</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>142</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaophthalmol.2023.5617</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38060235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10704345</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Minhas</surname><given-names>AMK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sedhom</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jean</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panza</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global burden of cardiovascular disease attributable to smoking, 1990-2019: an analysis of the 2019 global burden of disease study</article-title>. <source>Eur J Prev Cardiol</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>1123</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurjpc/zwae040</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38589018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Changing trends in the prevalence of heart failure impairment with Thalassemias over three decades</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Investigation</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>e14098</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/eci.14098</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37724975</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>FKL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Peptic ulcer disease</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>390</volume>:<fpage>613</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(16)32404-7</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28242110</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>S-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J-X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sam</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shuai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Global burden and risk factors of musculoskeletal disorders among adolescents and young adults in 204 countries and territories, 1990-2019</article-title>. <source>Autoimmun Rev</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>103361</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.autrev.2023.103361</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37230312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Projections of functional dependence among the late middle-aged and older population from 2018-2048 in China: a dynamic microsimulation</article-title>. <source>Glob Health Res Policy</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41256-024-00357-y</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38679749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11057077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pathogenesis of gout: exploring more therapeutic target</article-title>. <source>Int J Rheum Dis</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>e15147</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1756-185X.15147</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38644732</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pascart</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wasik</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Preda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chune</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torterat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prud&#8217;homme</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The gout epidemic in French Polynesia: a modelling study of data from the Ma&#8217;i u&#8217;u epidemiological survey. <italic toggle="yes">Lancet glob</italic></article-title>. <source>Health</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e685</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>96</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(24)00012-3</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38485432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yokose</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abhishek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalbeth</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pascart</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liot&#233;</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The clinical benefits of sodium-glucose cotransporter type 2 inhibitors in people with gout</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Rheumatol</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>216</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41584-024-01092-x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38472344</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The m6A reader IGF2BP3 promotes acute myeloid leukemia progression by enhancing RCC2 stability</article-title>. <source>Exp Mol Med</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>194</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>205</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s12276-022-00735-x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35217832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8894383</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between combined exposure to ambient air pollutants, genetic risk, and incident gout risk: a prospective cohort study in the UK biobank</article-title>. <source>Semin Arthritis Rheum</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>152445</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.semarthrit.2024.152445</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38579592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hennequin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Osta</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munoz-Sanchez</surname><given-names>M-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandenberghe Descamps</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andreeva</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feron</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Age related impairments in ingestion from a large population based-sample</article-title>. <source>Appetite</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>196</volume>:<fpage>107287</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.appet.2024.107287</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38452933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Inflammatory markers and physical frailty: towards clinical application</article-title>. <source>Immun Ageing</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12979-023-00410-3</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38184585</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10770917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dove</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Healthy lifestyle counteracts the risk effect of genetic factors on incident gout: a large population-based longitudinal study</article-title>. <source>BMC Med</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>138</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12916-022-02341-0</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35484537</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9052486</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roman</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Moving the needle in gout management: the role of culture, diet, genetics, and personalized patient care practices</article-title>. <source>Nutrients</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>3590</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu14173590</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36079846</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9460297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crittenden</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pillinger</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>New therapies for gout</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Med</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>325</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>37</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-med-080911-105830</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23327525</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ea</surname><given-names>H-K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kischkel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chirayath</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kl&#252;ck</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aparicio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loeung</surname><given-names>H-U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Systemic inflammatory cytokine profiles in patients with gout during flare, intercritical and treat-to-target phases: TNFSF14 as new biomarker</article-title>. <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>83</volume>:<fpage>945</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>56</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ard-2023-225305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38373842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Javed</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noreen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niazi</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiyani</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ul</surname><given-names>AQ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anti-gouty arthritis and anti-inflammatory effects of curcumin nanoparticles in monosodium urate crystals induced Balb/C mice</article-title>. <source>Inflammopharmacology</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1929</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10787-024-01450-x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38556563</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary factors and risk of gout: a two-sample Mendelian randomization study</article-title>. <source>Food Secur</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1269</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/foods13081269</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38672942</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11049247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Large-scale cross-ancestry genome-wide meta-analysis of serum urate</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>3441</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-024-47805-4</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38658550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11043400</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reinstatler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khaleel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pais</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Association of Pregnancy with stone formation among women in the United States: a NHANES analysis 2007 to 2012</article-title>. <source>J Urol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>198</volume>:<fpage>389</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.juro.2017.02.3233</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28238670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>