<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" id="pds70135" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">379</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">blackwellopen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PDS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1053-8569</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1099-1557</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Wiley Open Access Collection</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11930567</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11930567.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11930567</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11930567</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40122533</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pds.70135</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PDS70135</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">PDS-23-0501.R3</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mixed Impact of Direct Healthcare Professional Communications When Considering Proximal Outcomes and the Targeted Population: A Systematic Review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="pds70135-cr-0001" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names initials="E">Esther</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1258-9989</contrib-id><xref rid="pds70135-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="pds70135-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="pds70135-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Denig</surname><given-names initials="P">Petra</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7929-4739</contrib-id><xref rid="pds70135-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="pds70135-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monster</surname><given-names initials="TBM">Taco B. M.</given-names></name><xref rid="pds70135-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="pds70135-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="pds70135-cr-0004" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mol</surname><given-names initials="PGM">Peter G. M.</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4262-3180</contrib-id><xref rid="pds70135-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="pds70135-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><address><email>p.g.m.mol@umcg.nl</email></address></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="pds70135-aff-0001">
<label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department Clinical Pharmacy and Pharmacology</named-content>
<institution>University of Groningen, University Medical Center Groningen</institution>
<city>Groningen</city>
<country country="NL">the Netherlands</country>
</aff><aff id="pds70135-aff-0002">
<label>
<sup>2</sup>
</label>
<institution>Medicines Evaluation Board</institution>
<city>Utrecht</city>
<country country="NL">the Netherlands</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence:</bold><break/>
Peter G. M. Mol (<email>p.g.m.mol@umcg.nl</email>)<break/></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>34</volume><issue seq="220">3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">484970</issue-id><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pds.v34.3</issue-id><elocation-id>e70135</elocation-id><history><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>05</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>24</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>25</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-03-26 14:25:21.263"><day>26</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#169; 2025 The Author(s). <italic toggle="yes">Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</italic> published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use and distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non&#8208;commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="PDS-34-e70135.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:PDS-34-e70135.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><sec id="pds70135-sec-0001"><title>Background</title><p>Direct Healthcare Professional Communications (DHPCs) are an important risk minimisation measure. Their effect has been shown to be variable and has been measured using different outcomes and study populations. Depending on the content of the message, the optimal outcome to measure a direct effect of the DHPC can differ. This systematic review investigates whether the effects of DHPCs differ according to the use of proximal outcomes and the inclusion of the targeted population.</p></sec><sec id="pds70135-sec-0002"><title>Methods</title><p>EMBASE and MEDLINE were searched for European DHPC effectiveness studies performed up to April 6, 2022, evaluating the impact of DHPCs issued from 2008. Outcomes and their impact were extracted, together with a classification of the message. The outcomes were categorised as knowledge/awareness, self&#8208;reported behaviour (prescribing/monitoring), prescribing of medication (including dosage changes), monitoring, or adverse events/other health outcomes, including hospitalisation. The outcomes closest to the message of the DHPC were defined as proximal. Outcomes were coded 1 when effective and 0 if not. If multiple outcomes were reported in a study, a composite outcome was created ranging from 0 to 1. Chi&#8208;square or Fisher exact tests were performed.</p></sec><sec id="pds70135-sec-0003"><title>Results</title><p>From 7063 (scientific) publications identified in our literature search, 60 publications evaluating 31 different DHPCs were selected for our review. As publications could study multiple messages with an outcome, from the 60 scientific publications, 103 outcomes were generated for the messages, of which 30 had a high impact on the composite outcome, with the proportion of analyses with a significant association between 0.75 and 1. When taking the target population into account, some messages were studied in more than one population, resulting in 115 outcomes, of which 33 had a high impact, that is, a composite outcome between 0.75 and 1.</p></sec><sec id="pds70135-sec-0004"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Neither the use of proximal outcomes nor the restriction of the analysis to the targeted population significantly influenced the impact observed of the DHPC. These results stress the need for improving drug safety communication.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="pds70135-kwd-0001">DHPC</kwd><kwd id="pds70135-kwd-0002">drug safety</kwd><kwd id="pds70135-kwd-0003">effectiveness</kwd><kwd id="pds70135-kwd-0004">impact</kwd><kwd id="pds70135-kwd-0005">review</kwd><kwd id="pds70135-kwd-0006">risk communication</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="1"/><page-count count="21"/><word-count count="11100"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>March 2025</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.5.4 mode:remove_FC converted:23.03.2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><fn-group id="pds70135-ntgp-0001"><fn fn-type="funding" id="pds70135-note-0001"><p>
<bold>Funding:</bold> The authors received no specific funding for this work.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body id="pds70135-body-0001"><p>
<boxed-text position="anchor" content-type="box" id="pds70135-blkfxd-0001" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Summary</title></caption><p>
<list list-type="bullet" id="pds70135-list-0001"><list-item id="pds70135-li-0001"><p>DHPCs are an important tool for regulators to communicate about urgent drug safety issues. The impact of these DHPCs has reported to be variable and inadequate at times.</p></list-item><list-item id="pds70135-li-0002"><p>Our study confirms mixed effects of DHPCs, with a high impact (with a proportion of analyses with a significant association effect and studied outcome between 0.75 and 1) observed for less than a third of the outcomes evaluated.</p></list-item><list-item id="pds70135-li-0003"><p>The impact of DHPCs was not found not to be affected by the use of proximal outcomes for the type of DHPC message nor by the use of the targeted population of the DHPC.</p></list-item><list-item id="pds70135-li-0004"><p>The seriousness of the drug safety issue was not associated with the DHPC impact when measured using proximal outcomes in the targeted population.</p></list-item><list-item id="pds70135-li-0005"><p>Additional efforts to improve safety communication are required.</p></list-item></list>
</p></boxed-text>
</p><sec id="pds70135-sec-0007"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Direct Healthcare Professional Communications (DHPCs) inform healthcare professionals (HCPs) of new important drug safety information. It is one of the risk minimisation measures regulators can take during the life cycle of a drug (Figure&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The DHPC can be issued by, for example, the Pharmacovigilance Risk Assessment Committee (PRAC) of the European Medicines Agency (EMA) or by a national competent authority of an individual European country. When the DHPC is not effective, other measures should be taken to minimise the risk related to drug use.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="pds70135-fig-0001" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>The drug life cycle.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-1" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="PDS-34-e70135-g003.jpg"/></fig><p>Reviews that have reported on the impact of risk minimisation measures show that there is a large variability in findings [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. This has partly been attributed to the variation in risk minimisation measures studied and the content of the messages, and to methodological issues related to the study design, selected outcomes, and study population [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Studies looking at the effects of risk minimisation measures can use various outcomes, such as the knowledge of the receivers, their prescribing behaviour, or the occurrence of related adverse drug reactions [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The results may differ depending on the type of outcome or study design chosen. For example, to assess the effectiveness of risk minimisation measures concerning valproate, a survey study was performed and found good knowledge of the risks and required actions, particularly among physicians who acknowledged receiving the DHPC and related educational materials [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The same researchers assessed in a different study the changes in valproate prescribing and concluded that the effectiveness of the risk minimisation measures was limited on this outcome [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>What needs to be assessed to ascertain that a DPHC is effective depends on its content and intended outcomes [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The content may include information about new adverse reactions, indication limitations, new contraindications, changes in authorised dosage, additional monitoring, and new drug&#8211;drug interactions for a certain product [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. This information can be related to a specific target population of patients. To link such content to intended outcomes, Dusetzina et&#160;al. classified FDA safety communications into: recommendations for increased laboratory or clinical monitoring, avoiding co&#8208;prescribing due to drug&#8211;drug interactions, avoidance of use among a subpopulation, and general caution regarding a product [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Weatherburn et&#160;al. made a slightly different classification in a UK review based on the type of regulatory action: withdrawal from the market, recommendations to change practice based on a change or restriction of indication, recommendations for additional monitoring, and to be aware of new information without recommending specific action [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Based on such a classification of messages, outcomes for assessing proximal and distal effects can be defined. With those defined as proximal for outcomes closest to the message in the DHPC. Caution or be aware messages are primarily intended to increase the HCPs' knowledge or awareness of new information, with possible distal effects on behaviour. DHPCs with recommendations for additional monitoring or with new information about contraindications, drug&#8211;drug interactions or dosing changes are intended to change the HPCs' behaviour, with possible distal effects on health outcomes.</p><p>The content of a DHPC can refer to the specific patients at risk, implying that the primary outcome to assess the effectiveness of a DHPC should reflect this population. When this is not taken into account, incorrect conclusions may be drawn. For example, the DHPC informing HCPs on the new contraindication and restricted indication of cyproterone acetate 2&#8201;mg/ethinylestradiol 35 micrograms led to decreases in the overall prescribing of this drug but the proportion of prescribing in the targeted population did not improve [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. When looking at the content of a DHPC, there is also variation regarding the products and the seriousness of the safety issue itself. One review focusing on DHPCs issued in the Netherlands observed that the seriousness of the safety issue was associated with possible effects on prescribing [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>To gain a better understanding of the variable outcomes observed in the effectiveness of DHPCs, we performed a systematic review extending on previous work and explored whether this variation can be explained by the choice of the study outcomes, the study population, or the safety issue itself. Our primary question is whether the effects of DHPCs differ according to the use of proximal outcomes and the inclusion of the targeted study population. Our secondary question is whether the effect of the DHPC differs across the seriousness of the drug safety issue.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="pds70135-sec-0008"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><p>A systematic review was conducted including studies assessing the effects of DHPCs issued since 2008 by the European Medicines Agency (EMA) or national authorities in the European Union (EU). This year was chosen to limit variation caused by the introduction of a fixed DHPC template in 2008, since such a template may increase the impact of DHPCs [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Search strategies were developed for EMBASE and MEDLINE and performed on April 6, 2022 (Data&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref> and <xref rid="pds70135-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref>). Finalised studies in the EU PAS register of the European Network of Centres for Pharmacoepidemiology and Pharmacovigilance (ENCePP [now the HMA&#8208;EMA Catalogues of real&#8208;world data sources and studies]) up to April 21, 2022 were screened for studies assessing the effectiveness of a DHPC. Snowballing, a review of all identified studies' reference lists, was applied for all publications that met our inclusion criteria. The study protocol was registered in PROSPERO (CRD42022349593).</p><sec id="pds70135-sec-0009"><label>2.1</label><title>Study Selection</title><p>Original studies published in English or Dutch assessing the effects of DHPCs issued within the European Union on knowledge/awareness, self&#8208;reported behaviour, objectively measured behaviour, or health outcomes were included. Studies assessing DHPCs for suspensions, recalls, and withdrawals were excluded. Possible duplicates were marked by the screening tool Rayyan and checked by a researcher (EdV) before removal [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. First title and abstract screening and subsequent full publication screening were conducted independently by two researchers (EdV and RU) using Rayyan. Publications were excluded in the following order: do not concern DHPC, focus is not an effectiveness study, publication type being conference abstract/letter to the editor/commentary/review, country of DHPC being non&#8208;EU, language being other than English/Dutch, concerning DHPC issued before 2008, and/or duplicate outcomes (i.e., same outcomes presented in different studies).</p></sec><sec id="pds70135-sec-0010"><label>2.2</label><title>Data Extraction</title><p>Using a structured data extraction form in Research Electronic Data Capture (REDCap) [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], the following data were extracted: author, title, year, journal/ENCePP, issue number/ENCePP number, DHPC, date of DHPC, drug(s) mentioned in the DHPC (including co&#8208;drug in case of interaction), study period, type of study/study design (before&#8208;after/survey/other), statistical analyses used (descriptive/before&#8208;after/interrupted time series (ITS)), population studied, country where the study was performed, and key findings. For studies with clearly defined objectives, the corresponding outcomes were extracted. For studies without clear objectives or addressing also research questions not related to the effect of a DHPC, only the outcomes related to the DHPC were extracted. When effects of multiple DHPCs were reported in one publication, multiple data extraction forms were created. Data extraction were conducted by one researcher (EdV) and all data were checked and discussed with a senior researcher (PM).</p></sec><sec id="pds70135-sec-0011"><label>2.3</label><title>Additional Data Extraction and Classification</title><p>The original or Dutch DHPCs related to the included studies were retrieved and used to extract information on the drug safety issue. This was done using a previously developed archive [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and internet sources. If the DHPC could not be identified, we searched for a DHPC addressing the safety issue studied in another language or a report of the EMA discussing the safety issue and stating a DHPC was issued. The data extracted included information about the type of message, the target population, and the seriousness of the safety issue (see below). One DHPC could include multiple messages.</p><p>The type of message was classified as:
<list list-type="bullet" id="pds70135-list-0002"><list-item id="pds70135-li-0006"><p>Recommendation related to a change or restriction of indication or a new contraindication.</p></list-item><list-item id="pds70135-li-0007"><p>Recommendation related to a drug&#8211;drug interaction.</p></list-item><list-item id="pds70135-li-0008"><p>Recommendation related to a change in dosing or administration.</p></list-item><list-item id="pds70135-li-0009"><p>Recommendation for additional monitoring.</p></list-item><list-item id="pds70135-li-0010"><p>Be aware of an adverse event or risk without recommending specific actions</p></list-item><list-item id="pds70135-li-0011"><p>Reminder SmPC.</p></list-item><list-item id="pds70135-li-0012"><p>Other, such as new efficacy data and off&#8208;label use.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p>The target population refers to specific patients at risk.</p><p>The seriousness of the drug safety issue was classified as follows: death, life&#8208;threatening/(prolonged) hospital admission, (temporary/persistent) disability or incapacity/teratogenicity, or other [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. DHPCs mentioning fatal cases would be categorised as death. As the distinction between life&#8208;threatening and (prolonged) hospital admission can not often be made, these categories were combined.</p></sec><sec id="pds70135-sec-0012"><label>2.4</label><title>Data Synthesis</title><p>Outcomes were subdivided in assessing: knowledge/awareness, self&#8208;reported behaviour (prescribing/monitoring), prescribing of medication (including dosage changes), monitoring, or adverse events/other health outcomes (including hospitalisation).</p><p>First, the extracted outcomes were classified as showing supportive, unsupportive, or unknown impact of the DHPC. For pre&#8208;post designs, a significant effect on a given outcome in the desired direction was considered supportive. When no significant effect was found or was not in the desired direction, the outcome was considered unsupportive. When outcomes were presented only descriptively or only after the DHPC was issued, this was classified as having unknown impact. In studies measuring knowledge/awareness or self&#8208;reported behaviour, the outcome was considered supportive when at least 80% of the study population reached the required knowledge/awareness or recommended behaviour (Data&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3</xref>). Lower percentages were considered not supportive of the intended effect [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p><p>Next, a conceptual approach was used to determine whether the outcomes included in the studies were optimal for assessing proximal effects given the type of message (Figure&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Knowledge/awareness of the communicated safety issue was considered as proximal outcome when the type of message was to be aware of a safety issue without recommending specific actions. Prescribing behaviour was considered as proximal outcome for messages concerning (contra)indication, interactions, or dosing changes. Similarly, monitoring behaviour was considered as proximal outcome for messages concerning additional monitoring. Self&#8208;reported behaviour was not included as proximal outcome, given the expected self&#8208;report bias [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Finally, health outcomes were not considered as proximal outcome since they are not directly affected by the DHPC, but can of course be the ultimate intended outcome. Of note, each extracted outcome was linked to one type of the message. For example, when a DHPC would communicate a change in dosing and a monitoring advice, an outcome related to prescribed dosages would be linked to a &#8216;recommendation to change dosing&#8217; message.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="pds70135-fig-0002" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Proximal and distal outcomes according to the type of message. Continuous arrow: Proximal outcome. Interrupted arrow: Distal outcome.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-3" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="PDS-34-e70135-g004.jpg"/></fig><p>When a study reported multiple outcomes assessing, for example, the HCPs' knowledge of a safety issue, we combined these in a composite outcome to determine the impact of the message on knowledge. Also, when a specific outcome was measured in multiple countries within one study, a composite outcome was created (Data&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3</xref>). For this, each reported outcome supporting the effectiveness was coded 1, and all others 0. The composite outcome was expressed as the proportion of supportive outcomes on a scale from 0 to 1.</p><p>The DHPC was used to classify the study population as being the targeted population or the non&#8208;targeted population. This usually refers to the patient population at risk. For example, when it was communicated that diclofenac was contraindicated for people with congenital heart failure, changes in diclofenac prescribing assessed in the entire patient population were classified as &#8216;non&#8208;targeted population&#8217;, whereas assessing this in people with congenital heart failure was classified as &#8216;targeted population&#8217;. When assessing knowledge or self&#8208;reported behaviour, the target population may also refer to the HCPs. When this was assessed among all HCPs, including those that did not receive the DHPC, this was classified as &#8216;non&#8208;targeted population&#8217;.</p><p>To determine the effect of the seriousness of the safety issue on the impact of the DHPC, the unit of analysis was the safety issue addressed. Therefore, we created an overall outcome per drug safety issue, calculating the mean (composite) outcome of all data extraction forms for the same drug safety issue. For this analysis, only studies were included that used a proximal outcome and focused on the targeted population.</p></sec><sec id="pds70135-sec-0013"><label>2.5</label><title>Risk of Bias</title><p>The quality of all studies, except survey studies, was assessed with the Quality Assessment Tool of the NIH for Before&#8208;After (Pre&#8208;Post) Studies With No Control Group [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The Cochrane Effective Practice and Organisation of Care (EPOC) standard criteria for interrupted time series were used in addition for those studies having multiple measurements before and after the intervention [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The first question: &#8216;Was the intervention independent of other changes?&#8217; was not considered, since issuing a DHPC is by design not independent from other events. For the survey studies, the domain&#8208;based risk&#8208;of&#8208;bias tool for cross&#8208;sectional survey studies was used [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The quality of the studies was assessed independently by two researchers (E.d.V. and T.M.). Disagreements were resolved by mutual discussion and involvement of a third reviewer (P.D.) if not resolved.</p></sec><sec id="pds70135-sec-0014"><label>2.6</label><title>Analysis</title><p>The data were summarised showing the drug safety issue, seriousness, type of message, type of outcome, and (composite) outcomes in targeted and non&#8208;targeted populations. When similar outcomes were reported for targeted and non&#8208;targeted populations, they are presented as separate outcomes. The reported effects of the (composite) outcomes were classified as high (0.75&#8211;1), intermediate (0.74&#8211;0.25), or low (0.24&#8211;0). Chi&#8208;square tests were conducted to test whether the effect was influenced by (a) proximal outcomes or (b) the targeted populations. For these analyses, (composite) outcomes with an unknown effect were excluded. Chi&#8208;square tests were also used to test whether the effect was influenced by the seriousness of the drug safety issue. When numbers per cell were &lt;&#8201;5, Fisher exact tests were conducted.</p><p>One subgroup analysis was conducted to assess the impact of the targeted population, including only proximal outcomes. Another subgroup analysis was conducted assessing the impact of the targeted population, including only patient study populations, so excluding studies where HCPs were the study population. Also, subgroup analyses were conducted to assess the impact of the use of proximal outcomes or the targeted population, including only studies with limited or no bias. Two sensitivity analyses were performed to test the impact of using different cut&#8208;offs for the classification of the (composite) outcomes from high to low. First, using 0.80&#8211;1 (high), 0.20&#8211;0.79 (intermediate), and 0.19&#8211;0 (low) as cut&#8208;offs. Second, comparing; and 1 (full impact) to 0&#8211;0.99 (mixed/no impact). Finally, a subgroup analysis was conducted excluding studies for which it was unclear whether they studied a DHPC or other forms of national risk communication.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="pds70135-sec-0015"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><p>The screening of literature retrieved from Embase and Medline resulted in 58 relevant publications, and four were added due to snowballing (Figure&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="pds70135-fig-0003" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Flowchart of the inclusion of publications. DHPC: Direct Healthcare Professional Communication; ENCePP: The European Network of Centres for Pharmacoepidemiology and Pharmacovigilance.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-5" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="PDS-34-e70135-g005.jpg"/></fig><sec id="pds70135-sec-0016"><label>3.1</label><title>Data Summary&#8212;All Publications</title><p>The 81 identified publications (i.e., 60 scientific [Table&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>] and 21 ENCePP [Data&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4</xref>]) resulted in 86 data extraction forms linked to an individual DHPC.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pds70135-tbl-0001" content-type="TABLE" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Scientific publications overview showing the message, outcomes, and population.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Author</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Seriousness</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Year safety communication</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Type of message studied</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Outcomes measured</th><th align="center" colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Impact (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>/# outcomes measured)</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Countries</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Targeted population</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non&#8208;targeted population</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Antipsychotics: Risk of stroke and increased mortality</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gallini [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Be aware</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prescribing</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guthrie [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0004" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Be aware</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prescribing</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK (Scotland)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schulze (2013) [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Be aware</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prescribing</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stocks [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0004" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009, 2012</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Be aware</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prescribing</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United Kingdom</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sultana [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0004" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Be aware</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prescribing</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United Kingdom</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sultana [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0004" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Be aware</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Prescribing</p>
<p>Health outcomes</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>3/4</p>
<p>2/4</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United Kingdom and Italy<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thomas [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Be aware</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prescribing</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United Kingdom</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tifratene [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Be aware</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prescribing</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">McIlroy [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0004" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Be aware</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prescribing</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United Kingdom</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Valproate: Risk of severe developmental disabilities (30%&#8211;40%) and/or congenital malformations (10%) during pregnancy</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">De Vries [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0006" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>d</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Knowledge</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>1/12</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Croatia, Denmark, Ireland, Italy, the Netherlands, Norway, Spain, Sweden, and United Kingdom<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Puig&#8208;Molto [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014, 2018</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Prescribing</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>2/2</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Toussi [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Knowledge</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France, Germany, Spain, Sweden, and United Kingdom<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Toussi [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>Health outcomes</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>4/42</p>
<p>?/5</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France, Germany GP, Germany neurologist/psychiatrist, Spain GP, Spain neurologist/psychiatrist, Sweden, and United Kingdom<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hughes [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014, 2018</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ireland</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KarlssonLind [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweden</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Degremont [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Trimetazidine: Parkinson's disease</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pinto [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Portugal</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Von Bredow [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Indication/contraindication</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Knowledge</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>0/3</p>
<p>?/1</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bulgaria, Czech Republic, Estonia, France, Hungary, Latvia, Lithuania, Poland, Portugal, Romania, Slovakia, and Spain</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ehlken [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hungary, Romania, France, and Spain<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">(Es)citalopram: QT prolongation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Godman [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0004" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Be aware</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prescribing</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK (Scotland)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">De Bardeci [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Change in dosing</p>
<p>Drug&#8211;drug</p>
<p>SmPC reminder</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>4/4</p>
<p>0/2</p>
<p>1/1</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>1/2</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany, Switzerland, Austria, Belgium, and Hungary</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sch&#228;chtele [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Change in dosing</p>
<p>Drug&#8211;drug</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>2/2</p>
<p>0/4</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Clopidogrel: Decreased efficacy in combination with PPIs</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kruik&#8208;Koll&#246;ffel [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0005" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009, 2010</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug&#8211;drug</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>2/6</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>0/2</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Netherlands</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thomas [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug&#8211;drug</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United Kingdom</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kruik&#8208;Koll&#246;ffel [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0005" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009, 2010</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug&#8211;drug</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>0/2</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Netherlands</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Diclofenac: Arterial thrombosis</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">De Vries [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0006" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>d</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Knowledge</p>
<p>Knowledge</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>4/8</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Croatia, Denmark, Ireland, Italy, the Netherlands, Norway, Spain, Sweden, and United Kingdom<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morales [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0005" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK (Scotland), UK (England, Wales, and Northern&#8208;Ireland), Denmark, and the Netherlands<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morales [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0005" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>c</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Indication/contraindication</p>
<p>Be aware</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>Prescribing</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>13/16</p>
<p>10/12</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">the Netherlands, Denmark, UK (without Scotland), and UK (Scotland)<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Domperidone: Cardiac risks</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fife [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Indication/contraindication</p>
<p>Change in dosing</p>
<p>Drug&#8211;drug</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Knowledge</p>
<p>Knowledge</p>
<p>Knowledge</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>3/15</p>
<p>6/15</p>
<p>0/5</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belgium, France, Germany, Spain, and United Kingdom<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fife [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Indication/contraindication</p>
<p>Change in dosing</p>
<p>Drug&#8211;drug</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>11/24</p>
<p>5/5</p>
<p>4/10</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belgium, France, Germany, Spain, and United Kingdom<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Teeling [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Indication/contraindication</p>
<p>Drug&#8211;drug</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>0/3</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ireland</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Aliskeren combined with ACEI and ARB; risk of hyperkalaemia, kidney damage or hypotension</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rosich Mart&#237; [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug&#8211;drug</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>1/1</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>1/1</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Angelow [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012, 2014</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug&#8211;drug</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?/6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sindahl [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0004" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug&#8211;drug</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Denmark</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Combined hormonal contraceptives: Known risk of venous thromboembolism</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">De Vries [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0006" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>d</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Be aware</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Knowledge</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Knowledge</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>2/9</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Croatia, Denmark, Ireland, Italy, the Netherlands, Norway, Spain, Sweden, and United Kingdom<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Selke Krulichov&#225; [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Be aware</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prescribing</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Cyproterone acetate/ethinylestradiol (CPA/EE): Risk of venous and arterial thromboembolism</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Davis [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>SmPC reminder</p>
<p>Indication/contraindication</p>
<p>Be aware</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Knowledge</p>
<p>Knowledge</p>
<p>
<bold>Knowledge</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>9/20</p>
<p>0/6</p>
<p>9/10</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Czech Republic, the Netherlands, Spain, Austria, and France<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Penning&#8208;van Beest [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Indication/contraindication</p>
<p>Drug&#8211;drug</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>?/3</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?/6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Netherlands, United Kingdom, and Italy<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Flupirtine: Liver failure</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kaplan [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Change in dosing</p>
<p>Indication/contraindication</p>
<p>Drug&#8211;drug</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>1/1</p>
<p>0/1</p>
<p>0/1</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kaplan [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Indication/contraindication</p>
<p>Change in dosing</p>
<p>Additional monitoring</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Monitoring</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>0/4</p>
<p>1/1</p>
<p>0/1</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Ivabradine: Cardiovascular risk</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">De Vries [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0006" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>d</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SmPC reminder</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Knowledge</p>
<p>Knowledge</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/20</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>1/3</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Croatia, Denmark, Ireland, Italy, the Netherlands, Spain, Sweden, and United Kingdom<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salem [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SmPC reminder</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France, Germany, Italy, Spain, and United Kingdom</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Mirabegron: Severe hypertension, including hypertensive crisis and cerebrovascular and cardiac events</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heintjes [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>1/4</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">the Netherlands, Spain, United Kingdom, and Finland<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moriarty [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK (England)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Nimesulide: Hepatoxicity</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pinto [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>Health outcomes</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>1/1</p>
<p>0/1</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Portugal</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Franchi [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Indication/contraindication</p>
<p>Change in dosing</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Self&#8208;reported behaviour</p>
<p>Self&#8208;reported behaviour</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>9/9</p>
<p>18/18</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy, Portugal, Bulgaria, Poland, Czech Rep, Romania, Slovakia, Hungary, and Greece<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Pioglitazone: Bladder cancer</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cid Ruzafa [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Indication/contraindication</p>
<p>Be aware</p>
<p>Additional monitoring</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>Health outcomes</p>
<p>Prescribing</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>?/2</p>
<p>?/1</p>
<p>?/1</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Denmark</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hostenkamp [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Denmark and Germany<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Rosiglitazone: Cardiovascular risk</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leal [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0004" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>?/2</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United Kingdom</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Herdeiro [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0004" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Portugal</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Agomelatine: Hepatoxicity</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gonz&#225;lez&#8208;Bermejo [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012, 2013</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Additional monitoring</p>
<p>Indication/contraindication</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Prescribing</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>0/2</p>
<p>0/1</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>0/1</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Cabergoline/pergoline: Fibrotic heart valves</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italiano [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>Monitoring</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>?/2</p>
<p>?/1</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Cilostazol: Cardiovascular risk</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Castellsague [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0007" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>e</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Indication/contraindication</p>
<p>Additional monitoring</p>
<p>Drug&#8211;drug</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Monitoring</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>Health outcomes</p>
<p>
<bold>Monitoring</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Monitoring</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>?/4</p>
<p>?/5</p>
<p>?/5</p>
<p>?/5</p>
<p>1/5</p>
<p>?/13</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United Kingdom, EpiChron Aragon Spain, SIDIAP Catalonia Spain, Sweden, and GePaRD Germany<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Codeine: Respiratory depression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hedenmalm [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?/8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain, United Kingdom, France, and Germany<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Dabigatran: Risk of bleeding</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nyeland [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Additional monitoring</p>
<p>Be aware</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Prescribing</p>
<p>Health outcomes</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>0/1</p>
<p>?/1</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Denmark</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Fluoroquinolones (moxi&#8208;and levofloxacin): Liver failure and Steve Johnsons Syndrome</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Georgi [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008, 2009, 2012</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Be aware</p>
<p>Indication/contraindication</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Prescribing</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>3/3</p>
<p>3/3</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Hydrochloorthiazide: Skin cancer</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potteg&#229;rd [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Be aware</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prescribing</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?/3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Denmark</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Hydroxyzine: Known risk of QT prolongation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morales [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0007" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>e</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>3/8</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK (Scotland), UK (England), Denmark, and the Netherlands<xref rid="pds70135-note-0003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Intravenous iron&#8208;containing products Hypersensitivity reactions</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nathell [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0007" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>e</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health outcomes</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEA countries</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Midazolam injection: Overdose</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flood [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0004" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Change in dosing</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Health outcomes</p>
<p>Self&#8208;reported behaviour</p>
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>Knowledge</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>1/1</p>
<p>1/1</p>
<p>3/5</p>
<p>0/1</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK (England)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">NSAIDs: Narrowing artery resulting in foetal death, heart failure, kidney toxicity</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Araujo [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008, 2009</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SmPC reminder</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Osteoporosis drugs: Jaw osteonecrosis, atypical fractures, and oesophageal cancer</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hurtado Navarro [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0004" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Be aware</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prescribing</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">PPIs: Fractures with prolonged use</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sobel [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0004" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Be aware</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Prescribing</p>
<p>Health outcomes</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>?/1</p>
<p>2/2</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United Kingdom</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Quinine: Overdose</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acheampong [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0004" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Change in dosing</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</p>
<p>Health outcomes</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>1/2</p>
<p>?/1</p>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK (England)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Strontium ranelate: Risk of myocardial infarction</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Berencsi [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]<xref rid="pds70135-note-0007" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>e</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013/2014</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indication/contraindication</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prescribing</bold>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14/32</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Denmark, the Netherlands, Italy, Spain, and United Kingdom</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" valign="top" rowspan="1">Study summary (Outcomes&#8212;Analyses, Section&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-sec-0017" ref-type="sec">3.2</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total message&#8208;outcomes</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;103</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Message&#8208;outcomes with impact score (Figure&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;69</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total outcomes with impact score for populations (Figure&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;69</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total proximal outcomes with impact score for populations (Figure&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;38</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total overall outcomes with impact score in target population (Figure&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot id="pds70135-ntgp-0002"><fn id="pds70135-note-0002"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Note:</italic> Seriousness: f, death; h, (prolonged) hospital admission; d, (temporary/persistent) disability or incapacity/teratogenicity; o, other. Impact: ?, unknown. Bold: Proximal outcomes.</p></fn><fn id="pds70135-note-0003"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Studies measuring outcomes in different countries separately.</p></fn><fn id="pds70135-note-0004"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Studies excluded from the subgroup analysis involving studies mentioning the DHPC.</p></fn><fn id="pds70135-note-0005"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>Studies used same data sources.</p></fn><fn id="pds70135-note-0006"><label>
<sup>d</sup>
</label><p>Senior researcher PM involved in this study.</p></fn><fn id="pds70135-note-0007"><label>
<sup>e</sup>
</label><p>Scientific publication also included in the ENCePP database.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The 86 data extraction forms addressed 134 messages, several of which were included in multiple studies (Table&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>, Data&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4</xref>, and Figure&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Messages concerning changes or restrictions in indication or contraindication were studied most often (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;51), followed by be aware messages (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;28), drug&#8211;drug interaction (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;17), change in dosing (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;15), additional monitoring (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;13), SmPC reminder (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;9), and other (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="pds70135-fig-0004" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>Flowchart of data summary. ENCePP: The European Network of Centres for Pharmacoepidemiology and Pharmacovigilance.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-7" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="PDS-34-e70135-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>Prescribing was the most common outcome measured (68 extraction forms), followed by knowledge (18 extraction forms), health outcomes (11 extraction forms), monitoring (6 extraction forms), and self&#8208;reported behaviour (4 extraction forms). For the majority of the extraction forms, outcomes were measured in the targeted population, with 19 extraction forms investigating both targeted and non&#8208;targeted populations, whereas 12 extraction forms only included a non&#8208;targeted population (Table&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>, Data&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4</xref>). Usually, either the study population was too broad by including HCPs in a knowledge assessment who had not received the DHPC [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] or including patients without a certain contraindication or risk factor [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>] or including drugs that were not contraindicated or recommended [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].</p><p>The effects of 40 different DHPCs had been studied; 15 in both scientific and ENCePP publications, 16 in scientific only, and nine in ENCePP only. In 47 data extraction forms, the effects of 25 DHPCs were assessed in a single country, whereas in 39 data extraction forms the effects of 15 DHPCs were assessed in up to 12 countries. Often, more than one outcome was used to assess the effects of a DHPC (Table&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The publications were published one to 11&#8201;years after the last DHPC had been sent, with a median of 5&#8201;years. There was more time between the DHPC and the scientific publications than between the DHPC and the ENCePP publications; namely, a median of 6 versus 3&#8201;years.</p><p>The screening of ENCePP resulted in 21 relevant publications. However, for 13 of these, only a summary was publicly available. Therefore, the ENCePP publications were only used in the descriptive summary and not included in the main analysis.</p></sec><sec id="pds70135-sec-0017"><label>3.2</label><title>Outcomes&#8212;Analyses&#8212;Scientific Publications</title><sec id="pds70135-sec-0018"><label>3.2.1</label><title>Outcome&#8212;Proximal Outcomes</title><p>The 60 scientific publications resulted in 65 data extraction forms evaluating 31 different DHPCs. Often multiple outcomes were presented, leading to a large number of composite outcomes for our main analyses. In total, 103 outcomes were linked to a specific message. Of these outcomes, 58 were classified as proximal outcomes for assessing the effect of the message. Prescribing was used 72 times, of which 53 were classified as proximal outcomes. In the other cases, outcomes were used to assess the effects of a be aware message (16 times) or a monitoring message (three times). Knowledge was used 13 times for a variety of messages and seldom to assess a be aware message (two times).</p><p>Overall, 30 of the 103 outcomes had a high impact score, 28 had an intermediate impact score, and 24 had a low impact score when looking at the proportion of the analyses in which a significant association between respectively 0.75&#8211;1, 0.25&#8211;0.74, and 0&#8211;0.24 was found. The impact was unknown for the remaining 21 outcomes. In several studies, the DHPC impact was measured in multiple countries. Some of those studies found a similar impact in all studied countries [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], whereas others found different impacts among the countries studied [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Looking at the 82 outcomes with an impact score, there was no significant difference when comparing those with proximal versus other outcomes (Figure&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.69).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="pds70135-fig-0005" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p>Impact DHPC. DHPC: Direct Healthcare Professional Communication; DHPC impact high: 0.75&#8211;1 (blue); intermediate: 0.74&#8211;0.25 (orange); low: 0.24&#8211;0 (green). Statistical analysis: Chi&#8208;square test. To calculate the DHPC impact, each reported outcome supporting the effectiveness of a DHPC was coded 1, and all others 0. A composite outcome was then defined as the proportion of supportive outcomes divided by the total number of outcomes evaluating that DHPC message. Panels show Impact when analysing the effect of DHPCs on (a) proximal outcomes, in (b) target population, or when analyses are restricted to studies in (c) target population and using proximal outcomes.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-9" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="PDS-34-e70135-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="pds70135-sec-0019"><label>3.2.2</label><title>Outcome&#8212;Target Population</title><p>Some studies included multiple study populations. In 12 cases, the outcome measures were studied in both the targeted and non&#8208;targeted populations, which resulted in 115 outcomes that were linked to a specific message and study population; 94 had a measurable impact, and 21 had an unknown impact. A targeted population was used for 88 of these 115 outcomes (77%). Of the 94 outcomes with an impact score (i.e., 33 high, 29 intermediate, 32 low, as proportion of analyses with a significant association), 69 were measured in the targeted population. The use of the targeted population was not associated with the impact of the DHPCs, as shown in Figure&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5b</xref> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.48). When looking only at proximal outcomes, 56 of the 94 outcomes with an impact score remained. In the subgroup analysis including only proximal outcomes, there was also no influence of the use of the targeted population on the DHPC impact (Figure&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.79). Excluding studies where HCPs were the study population, 74 of the 94 outcomes with an impact score remained. Of those 74 outcomes, 53 outcomes were measured in the targeted population. In this subgroup analysis, the use of the targeted population also did not influence the impact of the DHPC (Data&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.61).</p></sec><sec id="pds70135-sec-0020"><label>3.2.3</label><title>Outcome&#8212;Seriousness</title><p>Seriousness of the drug safety issues assessed at DHPC level (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;22) was not associated with the overall impact, as measured by the proportion of analyses in which a significant association was found among studies using proximal outcomes in the targeted population (Figure&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.92).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="pds70135-fig-0006" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 6</label><caption><p>Impact DHPC, according to the seriousness of the message in studies using proximal outcomes measured in the target population (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;22, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.92). DHPC: Direct Healthcare Professional Communication; DHPC impact high: 0.75&#8211;1 (blue); intermediate: 0.74&#8211;0.25 (orange); low: 0.24&#8211;0 (green). Statistical analysis: Fisher exact tests. To calculate the DHPC impact, each reported outcome supporting the effectiveness of a DHPC was coded 1, and all others 0. An overall outcome was made for all drug safety issues, averaging the separate composite outcomes for the same drug safety issue.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-11" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="PDS-34-e70135-g006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="pds70135-sec-0021"><label>3.2.4</label><title>Outcome&#8212;Sensitivity Analyses</title><p>Sensitivity analyses using categories with different cut&#8208;off values showed somewhat higher Chi&#8208;square values but again no significant differences (see Data&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S6</xref> and <xref rid="pds70135-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S7</xref>). When including only the studies that specifically mentioned a DHPC, the results remained the same (Data&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S8</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="pds70135-sec-0022"><label>3.3</label><title>Quality Assessment</title><p>While (uncontrolled) before&#8208;after studies are an inherently weaker study design than interrupted time series [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>], the risk of bias was limited for many of the included before&#8208;after studies (Data&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S9</xref>). Not including a representative population, not performing statistical analysis providing <italic toggle="yes">p&#8208;</italic>values, and/or not measuring the outcome multiple times before and after the intervention were the main biases contributing to a higher risk of bias for these studies. The bias for most studies using interrupted time series was also limited (Data&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S10</xref>). Not specifying the shape/direction of the effect and/or not using appropriate interrupted time series techniques were the most commonly observed risks of bias. For survey studies, the risk of bias was introduced by not using a standard, validated, or piloted questionnaire (Data&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S11</xref>).</p><p>Subgroup analyses including before&#8208;after studies with a high risk of bias on no more than two criteria of the NIH assessment tool did not lead to other results (Data&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S12</xref>). Also, subgroup analyses including only studies with an interrupted time series design with a bias on no more than one of the EPOC criteria did not lead to other results (Data&#160;<xref rid="pds70135-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S13</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="pds70135-sec-0023"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>A total of 81 publications, consisting of 60 scientific publications and 21 publications from ENCePP, were identified that assessed the effects of European DHPCs issued after 2008. The distribution in low, intermediate, and high impact found for the DHPCs was similar for those studied with proximal outcomes and those who were not. The impact of DHPCs also did not differ between targeted and non&#8208;targeted populations. Finally, the seriousness of the drug safety issue was not associated with the impact of the DHPC. Overall, only 29% of the 103 outcomes evaluated in the literature showed high impact, a proportion of analyses with a significant association between 0.75 and 1, whereas 23% showed limited or no impact. Of note, for 20% the impact could not be assessed.</p><p>Although the majority of studies assessing DHPC effectiveness included proximal outcomes (56%) and measured those in targeted populations (70%), the impact found was mixed and not always sufficiently reported. This impact was not different for outcomes that were considered proximal to assess a certain type of message a DHPC can entail. For example, be aware messages were as likely or unlikely to lead to a change in prescribing as compared to messages regarding restricted indications or new contra&#8208;indications. In general, the lack of impact seen in many studies was not caused by the use of distal outcomes. Nonetheless, this review revealed that often a range of outcomes was included, making it difficult to draw a conclusion on whether there was an effect of the DHPC. The impact was often mixed, resulting in composite outcomes showing intermediate effects. Changing the cut&#8208;off to focus on studies showing full impact did not significantly change the findings. Furthermore, it has been mentioned that the evaluation period before and after the communication should not be too short for assessing changes in prescribing behaviour [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. A minimum number of data points, before and after interventions is not absolutely fixed, nor is the interval (e.g., monthly, quarterly or yearly) defined, but in order to include seasonality, an observation period of a year before and after is advised [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. This can lead to missing relevant changes. Some limitations of before&#8208;after studies can be addressed by an ITS design but only 33 out of the 56 (59%) before&#8208;after studies in this review used such a design. Previous reviews found a similar proportion of ITS designs: 45% and 67%, respectively, which suggests there is room for improvement still in these effectiveness studies [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>Previously, it has been noted that measuring the impact on prescribing can be difficult when drugs are not prescribed very often at baseline [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Sometimes the change is too small to be significant, or the change has started already before the DHPC was sent [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. In the latter case, one could argue that the communication was not effective, or it was redundant, but the goal of the communication was reached, namely safer prescribing. The process leading up to a DHPC already includes public information related to the agenda of the PRAC and other EMA communication, which may be picked up by other communication channels. Some drug safety issues are communicated through (social) media before they are communicated through a DHPC [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. This complicates the effect assessments and calls for ITS studies with prespecified shapes of intervention effects. This review showed that a lack of such a specification was a common bias in the ITS studies. Furthermore, other explanations for limited effect should be considered, which are related to the communication process. For a DHPC to have an impact, it should be received, understood, and accepted [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], all of which have been identified as suboptimal in previous research [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>].</p><p>Another important finding from our review was that the impact of DHPCs assessed in non&#8208;targeted populations was similar to that assessed in targeted populations. This indicates that a DHPC may have spillover effects in populations for whom it was not intended. It should be noted that this is not always a problem. For example, the use of valproate declined in a non&#8208;targeted population, being girls aged 0&#8211;14&#8201;years, which may be beneficial in preventing these girls from having to switch medication once they become of childbearing age [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Sometimes, however, effects are only seen in the non&#8208;targeted population [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. On the other hand, there were also examples where more effects were seen in the targeted patient population [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. When knowledge was the outcome of interest, more effects were consistently seen for the targeted populations of HCPs [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].</p><p>In contrast to a previous finding, we could not confirm that the impact of a DHPC was influenced by the seriousness of the drug safety issue [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In the previous study, multiple interrupted time series were conducted in one country using the same methodology, whereas in this review, multiple study designs were included, conducted in a variety of settings and countries. Outcomes measured in multiple countries showed a similar impact in a few cases, but often the impact differed between countries [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. This difference in impact could be due to differences in healthcare systems, reimbursement schemes, the availability of alternatives, but also due to different prescribing behaviour at baseline [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. In addition, we did not take the magnitude of the effect found into account, whereas the other review did. Due to this heterogeneity and also the relatively small sample, it may become more difficult to assess whether the content of a message influenced the impact. More studies are needed, including a large number of DHPCs assessing the impact of the content of the message, including the seriousness of the safety issue, on its effects using the same methodology and setting.</p><sec id="pds70135-sec-0024"><label>4.1</label><title>Implications</title><p>Recently, the European Guideline on good pharmacovigilance practices (GVP) Module XVI rev 3, including addendum II Methods for evaluating effectiveness of risk minimisation measures, has been published; it has been updated to provide more tools to assess effectiveness in terms of the delivery of a risk minimisation measure to the target audience, or with respect to measuring the intended knowledge and behavioural changes in the target audience and related health outcomes [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. Measurements are described for assessing the (1) dissemination coverage; (2) awareness, knowledge, and attitude; (3) behaviour changes; and (4) health outcomes. In the new GVP Module XVI, the DHPC is no longer considered a risk minimisation measure, although it can still guide how to evaluate the DHPC. We think that always assessing all outcomes is not meaningful. When a DHPC is intended to change behaviour, it is relevant to assess its impact at this level, preferably using one primary outcome. Qualitative research methods can provide additional insight, particularly when a DHPC appears ineffective and guidance is needed on additional risk minimisation measures. All studies identified in our review were of a quantitative nature. Our review illustrated that the impact of DHPCs issued since 2008 appears limited, even when this is assessed using proximal outcomes in the targeted population or in studies with low risk of bias. This implies that more effort should be put into improving the communication of new drug safety information. Currently, the DHPC is the only measure regulators can use to directly inform HCPs about new drug safety issues, and as such it cannot be dismissed. Improvements could be made to increase the applicability of the message for the target audience by providing clearer recommendations and information on clinical implications, but also by sending messages through various channels, including neutral senders and digital channels [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>, <xref rid="pds70135-bib-0091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. Some drug safety issues might be sent periodically, as was preferred by several hospital&#8208;based HCPs [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="pds70135-sec-0025"><label>4.2</label><title>Strengths and Limitations</title><p>Our systematic review provides an updated overview of European effectiveness studies of DHPCs sent from 2008 up to April 6, 2022. All steps of the literature review were performed by two researchers. Since the type of message a DHPC entails can be open for interpretation, two researchers were also involved in this classification. The included studies were assessed for bias and subgroup analyses showed that the results did not change when including only studies with limited or no bias. The impact of other bias thresholds was not assessed.</p><p>A limitation is that we did not look at the size of the impact per outcome. As pointed out by Morales et&#160;al. &#8216;it can be challenging to determine whether a regulatory action is considered successful when no established thresholds exist&#8217; [<xref rid="pds70135-bib-0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Given the large number of studies presenting multiple outcomes that were not likely to be independent (e.g., multiple outcomes assessing prescribing of related drugs), we calculated composite outcomes that average the reported effects per type of outcome. For these outcomes we applied arbitrary cut&#8208;offs to classify the impact as low, intermediate or high. The sensitivity analyses using other cut&#8208;offs did not significantly change our findings. Some DHPCs were studied multiple times by different studies. We have excluded two studies that presented data that were also included in other included studies. Regarding prescribing, the outcome of interest usually is prescribing behaviour but this was often assessed with dispensing data, which may not capture all changes in prescribing.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="pds70135-sec-0026"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>Only a minority of the DHPCs issued after 2008 in Europe showed an impact in all or most (&gt;&#8201;75%) of all assessments of DHPC effects on studied outcomes, even when proximal outcomes were used and the targeted population was included. Many studies assessed multiple outcomes instead of one primary outcome, often resulting in mixed findings. Furthermore, the impact of DHPCs was not significantly influenced by the seriousness of the drug safety issues. Efforts are needed to improve the communication of drug safety issues.</p><sec id="pds70135-sec-0027"><label>5.1</label><title>Plain Language Summary</title><p>Direct Healthcare Professional Communications (DHPCs) are a tool used by regulators to inform healthcare professionals about new important drug safety issues and aims to minimise the risks of the issue at hand. The effect of DHPCs has shown to be variable. However, how this is measured has been variable as well. This systematic review investigates the impact of DHPCs, when this is measured in the population at risk using outcomes most optimal to measure direct effects. DHPC effectiveness studies were identified from databases EMBASE and MEDLINE. From the retrieved studies we collected; for example, the study outcomes used and their impact, and the type of drug safety message. The drug safety message was used to classify the outcomes. Similar outcomes looking at the same drug safety message within a study were combined resulting in a score ranging from 0 to 1. A total of 60 studies were included with a total of 115 outcome scores. DHPCs had a limited impact, with only 29% showing a high or full impact (i.e., a score of 0.75 to 1). The use of optimal outcomes to measure impact of DHPCs and restriction to the population at risk did not result in an improved observed impact.</p></sec></sec><sec id="pds70135-sec-0029"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Study conception and design were performed by Esther de Vries, Petra Denig, and Peter G.M. Mol. Data collection and analysis were performed by Esther de Vries, Taco B.M. Monster, Petra Denig, and Peter G.M. Mol. The first draft of the manuscript was written by Esther de Vries, and all authors commented on previous versions of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="pds70135-sec-0032"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The authors state that no ethical approval was needed.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="pds70135-sec-0033"><title>Consent</title><p>The authors state that no patient consent was needed.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="pds70135-sec-0034"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>Petra Denig has no conflicts of interest that are directly relevant to the content of this study. Esther de Vries, Taco B.M. Monster, and Peter G.M. Mol are (part&#8208;time) employees of the Dutch Medicines Evaluation Board. Any opinions, conclusions, and proposals in the text are those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the views of the Dutch Medicines Evaluation Board.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting information</title><supplementary-material id="pds70135-supitem-0001" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>
<bold>Data S1.</bold> Supporting Information.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PDS-34-e70135-s001.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="pds70135-sec-0028"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>R. Ultee helped with the data collection and preparation before analysis. We would also like to thank the constructive reviewers input that helped to shape our manuscript and structure our main messages.</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="pds70135-sec-0031"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="pds70135-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="pds70135-bib-0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0001"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>C. J.</given-names><surname>Weatherburn</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B.</given-names><surname>Guthrie</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>T.</given-names><surname>Dreischulte</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>D. R.</given-names><surname>Morales</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Impact of Medicines Regulatory Risk Communications in the UK on Prescribing and Clinical Outcomes: Systematic Review, Time Series Analysis and Meta&#8208;Analysis</article-title>,&#8221; <source>British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</source><volume>86</volume> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>698</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>710</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31465123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/bcp.14104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7098864</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0002"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>U.</given-names><surname>Georgi</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Do Drug&#8208;Related Safety Warnings Have the Expected Impact on Drug Therapy? A Systematic Review</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><volume>29</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>229</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>251</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32045502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.4968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0003"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>T.</given-names><surname>Goedecke</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>D. R.</given-names><surname>Morales</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Pacurariu</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>X.</given-names><surname>Kurz</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Measuring the Impact of Medicines Regulatory Interventions &#8211; Systematic Review and Methodological Considerations</article-title>,&#8221; <source>British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</source><volume>84</volume> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>419</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>433</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29105853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/bcp.13469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5809349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0004"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Piening</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>F. M.</given-names><surname>Haaijer&#8208;Ruskamp</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J. T. N.</given-names><surname>de Vries</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>Impact of Safety&#8208;Related Regulatory Action on Clinical Practice: A Systematic Review</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Drug Safety</source><volume>35</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue> (<year>2012</year>): <fpage>373</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>385</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22480319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2165/11599100-000000000-00000</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0005"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Toussi</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Effectiveness of Risk Minimisation Measures for Valproate: A Cross&#8208;Sectional Survey Among Physicians in Europe</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Drug Safety</source><volume>30</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2021</year>): <fpage>283</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>291</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.5119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7894483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33216434</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0006"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Toussi</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Shlaen</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>F.</given-names><surname>Coste</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>H.</given-names><surname>de Voogd</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>V.</given-names><surname>Dimos</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Kaplan</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Effectiveness of Risk Minimisation Measures for Valproate: A Drug Utilisation Study in Europe</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><volume>30</volume> (<year>2021</year>): <fpage>292</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>303</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33108674</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.5166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7894134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="pds70135-cit-0007"><collab collab-type="authors">European Medicines Agency</collab>
, <article-title>&#8220;Guideline on Good Pharmacovigilance Practices (GVP) &#8211; Module XVI &#8211; Risk Minimisation Measures: Selection of Tools and Effectiveness Indicators (Rev 3),&#8221;</article-title> 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="pds70135-cit-0008"><collab collab-type="authors">European Medicines Agency</collab>
, <article-title>&#8220;Guideline on Good Pharmacovigilance Practices (GVP) Module XV &#8211; Safety communication (Rev 1),&#8221;</article-title> 2017.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0009"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S. B.</given-names><surname>Dusetzina</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Impact of FDA Drug Risk Communication on Health Care Ytilization and Health Behaviors: A Systematic Review</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Medical Care</source><volume>50</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>2012</year>): <fpage>466</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>478</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22266704</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MLR.0b013e318245a160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3342472</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0010"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>I. D.</given-names><surname>Bezemer</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>E.</given-names><surname>Smits</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>F. J. A.</given-names><surname>van Penning&#8208;Beest</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Asiimwe</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>R. M. C.</given-names><surname>Herings</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Thrombotic Risk Minimization for Diane&#8208;35 and Generics</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><volume>26</volume>, no. <issue>11</issue> (<year>2017</year>): <fpage>1411</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1417</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pds.4319</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28952198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0011"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>K. C.</given-names><surname>Reber</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Piening</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J. E.</given-names><surname>Wieringa</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>When Direct Health&#8208;Care Professional Communications Have an Impact on Inappropriate and Unsafe Use of Medicines</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Clinical Pharmacology and Therapeutics</source><volume>93</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue> (<year>2013</year>): <fpage>360</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>365</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23443752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/clpt.2012.262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0012"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Ouzzani</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Rayyan &#8211; A Web and Mobile App for Systematic Reviews</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Systematic Reviews</source><volume>5</volume>, no. <issue>210</issue> (<year>2016</year>): <fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13643-016-0384-4</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27919275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5139140</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0013"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>P. A.</given-names><surname>Harris</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>R.</given-names><surname>Taylor</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B. L.</given-names><surname>Minor</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>The REDCap Consortium: Building an International Community of Software Platform Partners</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Journal of Biomedical Informatics</source><volume>95</volume> (<year>2019</year>): <elocation-id>103208</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31078660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jbi.2019.103208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7254481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0014"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>E.</given-names><surname>de Vries</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>P.</given-names><surname>Denig</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S. T.</given-names><surname>de Vries</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>T. B. M.</given-names><surname>Monster</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J. G.</given-names><surname>Hugtenburg</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>P. G. M.</given-names><surname>Mol</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Drug Safety Issues Covered by Lay Media: A Cohort Study of Direct Healthcare Provider Communications Sent Between 2001 and 2015 in The Netherlands</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Drug Safety</source><volume>43</volume>, no. <issue>7</issue> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>677</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>690</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32212054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40264-020-00922-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7305079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="pds70135-cit-0015"><article-title>&#8220;ICH Topic E 2 A Clinical Safety Data Management: Definitions and Standards for Expedited Reporting, in CPMP/ICH/377/95 E.M. Agency, Editor.&#8221;</article-title> 1995.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0016"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>P.</given-names><surname>Vora</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>E.</given-names><surname>Artime</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Soriano&#8208;Gabarr&#243;</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>N.</given-names><surname>Qizilbash</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>V.</given-names><surname>Singh</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Asiimwe</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>A Review of Studies Evaluating the Effectiveness of Risk Minimisation Measures in Europe Using the European Union Electronic Register of Post&#8208;Authorization Studies</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><volume>27</volume>, no. <issue>7</issue> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>695</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>706</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29663572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.4434</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6055865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0017"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>F. A.</given-names><surname>Zeiler</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>F.</given-names><surname>AlSubaie</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>K.</given-names><surname>Zeiler</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>F.</given-names><surname>Bernard</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>Y.</given-names><surname>Skrobik</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Analgesia in Neurocritical Care: An International Survey and Practice Audit</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Critical Care Medicine</source><volume>44</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue> (<year>2016</year>): <fpage>973</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>980</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CCM.0000000000001602</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26983164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0018"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A. S.</given-names><surname>Adams</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S. B.</given-names><surname>Soumerai</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>Lomas</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>D.</given-names><surname>Ross&#8208;Degnan</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Evidence of Self&#8208;Report Bias in Assessing Adherence to Guidelines</article-title>,&#8221; <source>International Journal for Quality in Health Care</source><volume>11</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>1999</year>): <fpage>187</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>192</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/intqhc/11.3.187</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10435838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="pds70135-cit-0019"><collab collab-type="authors">The National Heart, L., and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</collab>
, <article-title>&#8220;Study Quality Assessment Tools,&#8221;</article-title> 2021, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health-topics/study-quality-assessment-tools" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health&#8208;topics/study&#8208;quality&#8208;assessment&#8208;tools</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0020"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>C.</given-names><surname>Hategeka</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>H.</given-names><surname>Ruton</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Karamouzian</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>L. D.</given-names><surname>Lynd</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M. R.</given-names><surname>Law</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Use of Interrupted Time Series Methods in the Evaluation of Health System Quality Improvement Interventions: A Methodological Systematic Review</article-title>,&#8221; <source>BMJ Global Health</source><volume>5</volume>, no. <issue>10</issue> (<year>2020</year>): <elocation-id>e003567</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33055094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjgh-2020-003567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7559052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0021"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M. P.</given-names><surname>Oktora</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>K. P.</given-names><surname>Kerr</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>E.</given-names><surname>Hak</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>P.</given-names><surname>Denig</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Rates, Determinants and Success of Implementing Deprescribing in People With Type 2 Diabetes: A Scoping Review</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Diabetic Medicine</source><volume>38</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2021</year>): <elocation-id>e14408</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32969063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/dme.14408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7891362</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0022"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Gallini</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Andrieu</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J. M.</given-names><surname>Donohue</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>N.</given-names><surname>Oumouhou</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Lapeyre&#8208;Mestre</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>V.</given-names><surname>Gardette</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Trends in Use of Antipsychotics in Elderly Patients With Dementia: Impact of National Safety Warnings</article-title>,&#8221; <source>European Neuropsychopharmacology</source><volume>24</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2014</year>): <fpage>95</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>104</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24126116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.euroneuro.2013.09.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4094113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0023"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B.</given-names><surname>Guthrie</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S. A.</given-names><surname>Clark</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>E. L.</given-names><surname>Reynish</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>C.</given-names><surname>McCowan</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>D. R.</given-names><surname>Morales</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Differential Impact of Two Risk Communications on Antipsychotic Prescribing to People With Dementia in Scotland: Segmented Regression Time Series Analysis 2001&#8211;2011</article-title>,&#8221; <source>PLoS One</source><volume>8</volume>, no. <issue>7</issue> (<year>2013</year>): <elocation-id>e68976</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23874832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0068976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3714253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0024"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>Schulze</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>H.</given-names><surname>van den Bussche</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>G.</given-names><surname>Glaeske</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>H.</given-names><surname>Kaduszkiewicz</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B.</given-names><surname>Wiese</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>F.</given-names><surname>Hoffmann</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Impact of Safety Warnings on Antipsychotic Prescriptions in Dementia: Nothing Has Changed but the Years and the Substances</article-title>,&#8221; <source>European Neuropsychopharmacology</source><volume>23</volume>, no. <issue>9</issue> (<year>2013</year>): <fpage>1034</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1042</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23498307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.euroneuro.2013.02.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0025"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S. J.</given-names><surname>Stocks</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>E.</given-names><surname>Kontopantelis</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>R. T.</given-names><surname>Webb</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A. J.</given-names><surname>Avery</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Burns</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>D. M.</given-names><surname>Ashcroft</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Antipsychotic Prescribing to Patients Diagnosed With Dementia Without a Diagnosis of Psychosis in the Context of National Guidance and Drug Safety Warnings: Longitudinal Study in UK General Practice</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Drug Safety</source><volume>40</volume>, no. <issue>8</issue> (<year>2017</year>): <fpage>679</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>692</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28439716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40264-017-0538-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5519656</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0026"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>Sultana</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Fontana</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>F.</given-names><surname>Giorgianni</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>The Effect of Safety Warnings on Antipsychotic Drug Prescribing in Elderly Persons With Dementia in the United Kingdom and Italy: A Population&#8208;Based Study</article-title>,&#8221; <source>CNS Drugs</source><volume>30</volume>, no. <issue>11</issue> (<year>2016</year>): <fpage>1097</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1109</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27423216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40263-016-0366-z</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0027"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>Sultana</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Fontana</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>F.</given-names><surname>Giorgianni</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>Measuring the Effectiveness of Safety Warnings on the Risk of Stroke in Older Antipsychotic Users: A Nationwide Cohort Study in Two Large Electronic Medical Records Databases in the United Kingdom and Italy</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Drug Safety</source><volume>42</volume>, no. <issue>12</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>1471</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1485</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31556019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40264-019-00860-z</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0028"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S. K.</given-names><surname>Thomas</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>Hodson</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>G.</given-names><surname>McIlroy</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Dhami</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J. J.</given-names><surname>Coleman</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>The Impact of Direct Healthcare Professional Communication on Prescribing Practice in the UK Hospital Setting: An Interrupted Time Series Analysis</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Drug Safety</source><volume>36</volume>, no. <issue>7</issue> (<year>2013</year>): <fpage>557</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>564</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23657825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40264-013-0057-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0029"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>K.</given-names><surname>Tifratene</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>V.</given-names><surname>Manera</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>R.</given-names><surname>Fabre</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>Antipsychotic Prescribing for Alzheimer's Disease and Related Disorders in Specialized Settings From 2010 to 2014 in France: A Repeated Cross&#8208;Sectional Study</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Alzheimer's Research &amp; Therapy</source><volume>9</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2017</year>): <fpage>34</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13195-017-0256-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5405526</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28446209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0030"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>G.</given-names><surname>McIlroy</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S. K.</given-names><surname>Thomas</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J. J.</given-names><surname>Coleman</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Second&#8208;Generation Antipsychotic Drug Use in Hospital Inpatients With Dementia: The Impact of a Safety Warning on Rates of Prescribing</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Journal of Public Health</source><volume>37</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2015</year>): <fpage>346</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>352</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24681910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/pubmed/fdu023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5942530</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0031"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S. T.</given-names><surname>de Vries</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Safety Communication Tools and Healthcare Professionals' Awareness of Specific Drug Safety Issues in Europe: A Survey Study</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Drug Safety</source><volume>41</volume>, no. <issue>7</issue> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>713</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>724</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29500798</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40264-018-0643-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5990574</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0032"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Puig&#8208;Molto</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>E.</given-names><surname>Pol&#8208;Yanguas</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>L.</given-names><surname>Segarra</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B.</given-names><surname>Lumbreras</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Impact of the EMA/FDA Alerts on the Use of Effective Contraceptive Method in Women of Childbearing Age Undergoing Valproic Acid Treatment in a Long&#8208;Stay Psychiatric Center</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Epilepsy &amp; Behavior</source><volume>107</volume> (<year>2020</year>): <elocation-id>107072</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32278266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.yebeh.2020.107072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0033"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J. E.</given-names><surname>Hughes</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>N.</given-names><surname>Buckley</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>Y.</given-names><surname>Looney</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Curran</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Mullooly</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>K.</given-names><surname>Bennett</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Valproate Utilisation Trends Among Women of Childbearing Potential in Ireland Between 2014 and 2019: A Drug Utilisation Study Using Interrupted Time Series</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><volume>31</volume> (<year>2022</year>): <fpage>661</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>669</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35285110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.5427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9315025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0034"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>L.</given-names><surname>Karlsson Lind</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>Komen</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B.</given-names><surname>Wettermark</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>von Euler</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>T.</given-names><surname>Tomson</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Valproic Acid Utilization Among Girls and Women in Stockholm: Impact of Regulatory Restrictions</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Epilepsia Open</source><volume>3</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>357</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>363</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30187006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/epi4.12228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6119758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0035"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Degremont</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>E.</given-names><surname>Polard</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Kerbrat</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>Impact of Recommendations on Sodium Valproate Prescription Among Women With Epilepsy: An Interrupted Time&#8208;Series Study</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Epilepsy &amp; Behavior</source><volume>125</volume> (<year>2021</year>): <elocation-id>108449</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34839242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.yebeh.2021.108449</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0036"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>D.</given-names><surname>Pinto</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Silva</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B.</given-names><surname>Heleno</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>D. S.</given-names><surname>Rodrigues</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>I.</given-names><surname>Santos</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>P. A.</given-names><surname>Caetano</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Effect of European Medicines Agency's Restrictions on Trimetazidine Utilization in Portugal</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><volume>27</volume>, no. <issue>9</issue> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>962</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>968</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29992780</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.4585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0037"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>D.</given-names><surname>von Bredow</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Toussi</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Samad</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>Evaluation of the Effectiveness of Risk Minimization Measures for Trimetazidine: A Cross Sectional Joint PASS Survey Among Physicians in Selected European Countries</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><volume>27</volume>, no. <issue>12</issue> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>1385</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1392</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30379361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.4675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0038"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B.</given-names><surname>Ehlken</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Toussi</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Samad</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>A Drug Utilization Study to Evaluate Effectiveness of Risk Minimization Measures for Trimetazidine in France, Hungary, Romania and Spain</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Journal of Clinical Pharmacy and Therapeutics</source><volume>44</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>400</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>408</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30659627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jcpt.12799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0039"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B.</given-names><surname>Godman</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Kurdi</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>H.</given-names><surname>McCabe</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>Ongoing Initiatives Within the Scottish National Health Service to Affect the Prescribing of Selective Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitors and Their Influence</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Journal of Comparative Effectiveness Research</source><volume>8</volume>, no. <issue>7</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>535</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>547</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31023070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2217/cer-2018-0132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0040"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>de Barci</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>W.</given-names><surname>Greil</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>H.</given-names><surname>Stassen</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>Dear Doctor Letters Regarding Citalopram and Escitalopram: Guidelines vs. Real&#8208;World Data</article-title>,&#8221; <source>European Archives of Psychiatry and Clinical Neuroscience</source><volume>273</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2022</year>): <fpage>65</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00406-022-01392-x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35217913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9957836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0041"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Sch&#228;chtele</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>T.</given-names><surname>T&#252;mena</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>K. G.</given-names><surname>Ga&#223;mann</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M. F.</given-names><surname>Fromm</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>R.</given-names><surname>Maas</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Implementation of Warnings From Dear Doctor Letters (Rote&#8208;Hand&#8208;Briefe): An Analysis of Medication Data From a Large Cohort of Elderly Patients</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Deutsches &#196;rzteblatt International</source><volume>111</volume>, no. <issue>15</issue> (<year>2014</year>): <fpage>255</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>263</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24776610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3238/arztebl.2014.0255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4004934</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0042"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>W. J.</given-names><surname>Kruik&#8208;Koll&#246;ffel</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>van der Palen</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>H. J.</given-names><surname>Kruik</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M. P. P.</given-names><surname>van Herk&#8208;Sukel</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>K. L. L.</given-names><surname>Movig</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Prescription Behavior for Gastroprotective Drugs in New Users as a Result of Communications Regarding Clopidogrel &#8211; Proton Pump Inhibitor Interaction</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacology Research &amp; Perspectives</source><volume>4</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue> (<year>2016</year>): <elocation-id>e00242</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28116095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/prp2.242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5242171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0043"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>W. J.</given-names><surname>Kruik&#8208;Koll&#246;ffel</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>van der Palen</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M. P. P.</given-names><surname>van Herk&#8208;Sukel</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>H. J.</given-names><surname>Kruik</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>K. L. L.</given-names><surname>Movig</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Decrease in Switches to Unsafe Proton Pump Inhibitors After Communications About Interactions With Clopidogrel</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Clinical Drug Investigation</source><volume>37</volume>, no. <issue>8</issue> (<year>2017</year>): <fpage>787</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>794</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28547741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40261-017-0536-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0044"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>D. R.</given-names><surname>Morales</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S. V.</given-names><surname>Morant</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>T. M.</given-names><surname>MacDonald</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>Impact of EMA Regulatory Label Changes on Systemic Diclofenac Initiation, Discontinuation, and Switching to Other Pain Medicines in Scotland, England, Denmark, and The Netherlands</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><volume>29</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>296</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>305</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31899936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.4955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7079064</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0045"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>D. R.</given-names><surname>Morales</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S. V.</given-names><surname>Morant</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>T. M.</given-names><surname>MacDonald</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>Impact of EU Regulatory Label Changes for Diclofenac in People With Cardiovascular Disease in Four Countries: Interrupted Time Series Regression Analysis</article-title>,&#8221; <source>British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</source><volume>87</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2021</year>): <fpage>1129</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1140</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32668021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/bcp.14478</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0046"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>D.</given-names><surname>Fife</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>Waller</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Kaplan</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>Awareness of, and Compliance With, Domperidone Revised Labeling After a Risk&#8208;Minimization Activity in Europe</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Clinical Drug Investigation</source><volume>39</volume>, no. <issue>11</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>1057</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1066</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31325111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40261-019-00831-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6800405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0047"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Teeling</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M. J.</given-names><surname>MacAvin</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>K.</given-names><surname>Bennett</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Impact of Safety Warnings on Domperidone Prescribing in Ireland</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Irish Journal of Medical Science</source><volume>187</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>281</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>285</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28730460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11845-017-1657-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0048"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>I.</given-names><surname>Rosich Mart&#237;</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Allepuz</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>G.</given-names><surname>Rodriguez Palomar</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>F.</given-names><surname>Ortin Font</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Soler Cera</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Impact of an Intervention on the Prescription of Aliskiren After New Evidence on Safety Reported</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><volume>26</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2017</year>): <fpage>91</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>96</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27859873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.4136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0049"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Angelow</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>T.</given-names><surname>Ploner</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>T.</given-names><surname>Grimmsmann</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>Walker</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J. F.</given-names><surname>Chenot</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Dual Renin&#8208;Angiotensin&#8208;Aldosterone Blockade: Implementation of Published Research and Dear Doctor Letters in Ambulatory Care: A Retrospective Observational Study Using Prescription Data</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><volume>29</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>530</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>537</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32162407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.4965</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0050"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>P.</given-names><surname>Sindahl</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>R.</given-names><surname>Ofori&#8208;Asenso</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>C. E.</given-names><surname>Hallgreen</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>K.</given-names><surname>Kemp</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>H.</given-names><surname>Gardarsdottir</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M. L.</given-names><surname>de Bruin</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Impact of Regulatory Interventions to Restrict the Combined Use of Renin&#8211;Angiotensin System Blockers: A Danish Nationwide Drug Utilisation Study</article-title>,&#8221; <source>British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</source><volume>88</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2022</year>): <fpage>1379</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1384</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34519065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/bcp.15080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9293443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0051"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>I.</given-names><surname>Selke Krulichov&#225;</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>G. W.</given-names><surname>Selke</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>U.</given-names><surname>Eichler</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>V.</given-names><surname>Lappe</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B.</given-names><surname>Godman</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>I.</given-names><surname>Schubert</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Impact of EU Risk Assessment Process and Administrative Regulations for Manufacturers of Combined Hormonal Contraceptive Prescribing. An Analysis of Developments in Germany and the Implications</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Current Medical Research and Opinion</source><volume>35</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>697</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>704</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30362365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/03007995.2018.1541317</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0052"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>K. H.</given-names><surname>Davis</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Evaluation of Risk&#8208;Minimization Activities for Cyproterone Acetate 2 Mg/Ethinylestradiol 35 &#956;g: A Cross&#8208;Sectional Physician Survey</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmaceutical Medicine</source><volume>31</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue> (<year>2017</year>): <fpage>339</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>351</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29056853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40290-017-0203-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5629244</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0053"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>F. J. A.</given-names><surname>Penning&#8208;van Beest</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>I. D.</given-names><surname>Bezemer</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>E.</given-names><surname>Smits</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>Reduction in Use of Cyproterone/Ethinylestradiol (Diane&#8208;35 and Generics) After Risk Minimization Measures in The Netherlands, UK and Italy</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Contraception</source><volume>102</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>243</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>245</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32470466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.contraception.2020.05.010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0054"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Kaplan</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B.</given-names><surname>Ehlken</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>X.</given-names><surname>Hamann</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Drug Utilization Patterns of Flupirtine Following Implementation of Risk Minimization Measures in Germany</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Current Medical Research and Opinion</source><volume>35</volume>, no. <issue>8</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>1397</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1403</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30865848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/03007995.2019.1594743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0055"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Kaplan</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B.</given-names><surname>Ehlken</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>X.</given-names><surname>Hamann</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>The Impact of Risk Minimization Measures on Compliance and Prescribing Practices of Flupirtine in Germany</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Current Medical Research and Opinion</source><volume>35</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>33</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29992843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/03007995.2018.1499507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0056"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>L.</given-names><surname>Salem</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Malouvier</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>Blatchford</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>E.</given-names><surname>Rivero&#8208;Ferrer</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>N.</given-names><surname>Deltour</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>E.</given-names><surname>Jacquot</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Ivabradine Drug Utilization Study in Five European Countries: A Multinational, Retrospective, Observational Study to Assess Effectiveness of Risk&#8208;Minimization Measures</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><volume>28</volume>, no. <issue>11</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>1470</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1479</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31486198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.4880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6899761</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0057"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>E. M.</given-names><surname>Heintjes</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Evaluating the Effectiveness of an Additional Risk Minimization Measure to Reduce the Risk of Prescribing Mirabegron to Patients With Severe Uncontrolled Hypertension in Four European Countries</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Clinical Epidemiology</source><volume>12</volume> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>423</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>433</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32431551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/CLEP.S242065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7200224</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0058"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>F.</given-names><surname>Moriarty</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Razzaque</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>R.</given-names><surname>McDowell</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>T.</given-names><surname>Fahey</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Prescribing Variation in General Practices in England Following a Direct Healthcare Professional Communication on Mirabegron</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Journal of Clinical Medicine</source><volume>7</volume>, no. <issue>10</issue> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC6210595/" ext-link-type="uri">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC6210595/</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/jcm7100320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6210595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30282903</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0059"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>D.</given-names><surname>Pinto</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Silva</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B.</given-names><surname>Heleno</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>D. S.</given-names><surname>Rodrigues</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>I.</given-names><surname>Santos</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>P. A.</given-names><surname>Caetano</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Effect of European Medicines Agency's Regulatory Measures on Nimesulide Utilization in Portugal</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><volume>27</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>630</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>637</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29602246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.4424</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0060"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Franchi</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>F.</given-names><surname>Heiman</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>E.</given-names><surname>Visentin</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>P.</given-names><surname>Sacerdote</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Survey on Appropriateness of Use of Nimesulide in Nine European Countries</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Drug, Healthcare and Patient Safety</source><volume>7</volume> (<year>2015</year>): <fpage>51</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25834467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/DHPS.S76320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4365741</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0061"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>Cid Ruzafa</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S. P.</given-names><surname>Ulrichsen</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>D.</given-names><surname>Bennett</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>V.</given-names><surname>Ehrenstein</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Post&#8208;Authorisation Safety Study of Pioglitazone Use and Safety Endpoints of Interest in Denmark After Direct Healthcare Professional Communication</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Drugs Real World Outcome</source><volume>6</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>133</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>140</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40801-019-0160-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6702533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31376066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0062"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>G.</given-names><surname>Hostenkamp</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>K. E.</given-names><surname>Fischer</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>K.</given-names><surname>Borch&#8208;Johnsen</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Drug Safety and the Impact of Drug Warnings: An Interrupted Time Series Analysis of Diabetes Drug Prescriptions in Germany and Denmark</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Health Policy</source><volume>120</volume>, no. <issue>12</issue> (<year>2016</year>): <fpage>1404</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1411</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27817873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.healthpol.2016.09.020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0063"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>I.</given-names><surname>Leal</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S. A.</given-names><surname>Romio</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Schuemie</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Oteri</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Sturkenboom</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>G.</given-names><surname>Trifir&#242;</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Prescribing Pattern of Glucose Lowering Drugs in the United Kingdom in the Last Decade: A Focus on the Effects of Safety Warnings About Rosiglitazone</article-title>,&#8221; <source>British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</source><volume>75</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2013</year>): <fpage>861</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>868</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22845019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2125.2012.04401.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3575953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0064"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M. T.</given-names><surname>Herdeiro</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Soares</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>T.</given-names><surname>Silva</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>F.</given-names><surname>Roque</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Figueiras</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Impact of Rosiglitazone Safety Alerts on Oral Antidiabetic Sales Trends: A Countrywide Study in Portugal</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Fundamental &amp; Clinical Pharmacology</source><volume>30</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue> (<year>2016</year>): <fpage>440</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>449</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27259384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/fcp.12207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0065"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>D.</given-names><surname>Gonz&#225;lez&#8208;Bermejo</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B.</given-names><surname>Castillo&#8208;Cano</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Rodr&#237;guez&#8208;Pascual</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>Effect of Regulatory Interventions on Agomelatine Use in Spain: A Multiple Intervention Time&#8208;Series Analysis in a Nationwide Electronic Healthcare Record Database</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><volume>31</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2022</year>): <fpage>294</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>301</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34676940</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.5374</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0066"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>D.</given-names><surname>Italiano</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>E.</given-names><surname>Bianchini</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Ilardi</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>Effectiveness of Risk Minimization Measures for Cabergoline&#8208;Induced Cardiac Valve Fibrosis in Clinical Practice in Italy</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Journal of Neural Transmission</source><volume>122</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>2015</year>): <fpage>799</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>808</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25230720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00702-014-1314-z</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0067"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>Castellsague</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B.</given-names><surname>Poblador&#8208;Plou</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Giner&#8208;Soriano</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>Effectiveness of Risk Minimization Measures for the Use of Cilostazol in United Kingdom, Spain, Sweden, and Germany</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><volume>27</volume>, no. <issue>9</issue> (<year>2018</year>): <fpage>953</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>961</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30043552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.4584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6175151</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0068"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>K.</given-names><surname>Hedenmalm</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>K.</given-names><surname>Blake</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>K.</given-names><surname>Donegan</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>A European Multicentre Drug Utilisation Study of the Impact of Regulatory Measures on Prescribing of Codeine for Pain in Children</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><volume>28</volume>, no. <issue>8</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>1086</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1096</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31219227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.4836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6771637</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0069"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M. E.</given-names><surname>Nyeland</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Vestergaard Laursen</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>T.</given-names><surname>Callr&#233;us</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Evaluating the Effectiveness of Risk Minimisation Measures: The Application of a Conceptual Framework to Danish Real&#8208;World Dabigatran Data</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><volume>26</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>2017</year>): <fpage>607</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>614</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28397317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.4203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0070"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>U.</given-names><surname>Georgi</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>F.</given-names><surname>Tesch</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>Schmitt</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>K.</given-names><surname>de With</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Impact of Safety Warnings for Fluoroquinolones on Prescribing Behaviour. Results of a Cohort Study With Outpatient Routine Data</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Infection</source><volume>49</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue> (<year>2021</year>): <fpage>447</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>455</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33258075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s15010-020-01549-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8159769</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0071"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Potteg&#229;rd</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B. H.</given-names><surname>Bech</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S. A.</given-names><surname>Pedersen</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B.</given-names><surname>Christensen</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Use of Hydrochlorothiazide in Denmark Following Publication of Skin Cancer Risk Findings</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><volume>30</volume>, no. <issue>11</issue> (<year>2021</year>): <fpage>1611</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1616</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34435407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.5350</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0072"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0072"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>D. R.</given-names><surname>Morales</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>T.</given-names><surname>Macfarlane</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>T. M.</given-names><surname>MacDonald</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>Impact of EMA Regulatory Label Changes on Hydroxyzine Initiation, Discontinuation and Switching to Other Medicines in Denmark, Scotland, England and The Netherlands: An Interrupted Time Series Regression Analysis</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety</source><volume>30</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue> (<year>2021</year>): <fpage>482</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>491</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33386650</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.5191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0073"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0073"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>L.</given-names><surname>Nathell</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Gohlke</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Wohlfeil</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Reported Severe Hypersensitivity Reactions After Intravenous Iron Administration in the European Economic Area (EEA) Before and After Implementation of Risk Minimization Measures</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Drug Safety</source><volume>43</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>35</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31583644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40264-019-00868-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6965341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0074"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0074"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>C.</given-names><surname>Flood</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>L.</given-names><surname>Matthew</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>R.</given-names><surname>Marsh</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B.</given-names><surname>Patel</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Mansaray</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>T.</given-names><surname>Lamont</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Reducing Risk of Overdose With Midazolam Injection in Adults: An Evaluation of Change in Clinical Practice to Improve Patient Safety in England</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Journal of Evaluation in Clinical Practice</source><volume>21</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2015</year>): <fpage>57</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25109525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jep.12228</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0075"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0075"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Araujo</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>C.</given-names><surname>Hurault&#8208;Delarue</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>C.</given-names><surname>Bouilhac</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>Non&#8208;steroidal Anti&#8208;Inflammatory Drug Prescriptions From the 6(th) Month of Pregnancy: Impact of Advice From Health Authorities</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Fundamental &amp; Clinical Pharmacology</source><volume>33</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>581</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>588</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30849185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/fcp.12460</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0076"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0076"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>I.</given-names><surname>Hurtado&#8208;Navarro</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Garc&#237;a&#8208;Sempere</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>C.</given-names><surname>Rodr&#237;guez&#8208;Bernal</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>J.</given-names><surname>Sanf&#233;lix&#8208;Genov&#233;s</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Peir&#243;</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>G.</given-names><surname>Sanf&#233;lix&#8208;Gimeno</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Impact of Drug Safety Warnings and Cost&#8208;Sharing Policies on Osteoporosis Drug Utilization in Spain: A Major Reduction but With the Persistence of Over and Underuse. Data from the ESOSVAL Cohort From 2009 to 2015</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Frontiers in Pharmacology</source><volume>10</volume> (<year>2019</year>): <elocation-id>768</elocation-id>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2019.00768</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31354484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6635591</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0077"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0077"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>R. E.</given-names><surname>Sobel</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>W.</given-names><surname>Blackwell</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>D. M.</given-names><surname>Fram</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Bate</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>A Novel Approach to Visualize Risk Minimization Effectiveness: Peeping at the 2012 UK Proton Pump Inhibitor Label Change Using a Rapid Cycle Analysis Tool</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Drug Safety</source><volume>42</volume>, no. <issue>11</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>1365</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1376</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31368080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40264-019-00853-y</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0078"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0078"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>P.</given-names><surname>Acheampong</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>G.</given-names><surname>Cooper</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>B.</given-names><surname>Khazaeli</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>Effects of MHRA Drug Safety Advice on Time Trends in Prescribing Volume and Indices of Clinical Toxicity for Quinine</article-title>,&#8221; <source>British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</source><volume>76</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>2013</year>): <fpage>973</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>979</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23594200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/bcp.12130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3845321</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0079"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0079"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>K.</given-names><surname>Berencsi</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Sami</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M. S.</given-names><surname>Ali</surname></string-name>, et&#160;al., &#8220;<article-title>Impact of Risk Minimisation Measures on the Use of Strontium Ranelate in Europe: A Multi&#8208;National Cohort Study in 5 EU Countries by the EU&#8208;ADR Alliance</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Osteoporosis International</source><volume>31</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue> (<year>2020</year>): <fpage>721</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>755</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31696274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00198-019-05181-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0080"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="pds70135-cit-0080"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Toussi</surname></string-name>, <article-title>&#8220;Drug Utilisation Study, in Five European Countries, Using Cross Sectional Analysis, to Assess the Extent of Prescriptions of Trimetazidine for Its Withdrawn Ophthalmological and ENT Indications Among General Practitioners, Ophthalmologists and ENT Specialists,&#8221;</article-title> 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0081"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0081"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>R.</given-names><surname>Jandoc</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A. M.</given-names><surname>Burden</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Mamdani</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>L. E.</given-names><surname>L&#233;vesque</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S. M.</given-names><surname>Cadarette</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Interrupted Time Series Analysis in Drug Utilization Research Is Increasing: Systematic Review and Recommendations</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Journal of Clinical Epidemiology</source><volume>68</volume>, no. <issue>8</issue> (<year>2015</year>): <fpage>950</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>956</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25890805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2014.12.018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0082"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="pds70135-cit-0082"><article-title>&#8220;Retrospective Drug Utilisation Study to Investigate the Routine Use of Hydroxyethyl Starch (HES)&#8208;Containing Infusion Solutions of B. Braun Melsungen AG in Hospitals,&#8221;</article-title> 2017.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0083"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="pds70135-cit-0083"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A.</given-names><surname>Ali</surname></string-name>, <article-title>&#8220;Healthcare Professional and Patient Surveys to Assess the Effectiveness of Risk Minimisation Measures for Concentrated Insulin Lispro (Humalog 200 units/mL KwikPen, Liprolog 200 units/mL KwikPen),&#8221;</article-title> 2017.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0084"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="pds70135-cit-0084"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>F.</given-names><surname>Stevenson</surname></string-name>, <article-title>&#8220;Study of Regulatory Communication and Risk Awareness Following the Article 31 Referral of Combined Hormonal Contraceptives in Relation to Thromboembolism,&#8221;</article-title> 2017.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0085"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0085"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>A. L.</given-names><surname>Bhasale</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Regulatory Authority and Clinical Acceptability: Physicians' Responses to Regulatory Drug Safety Warnings</article-title>,&#8221; <source>British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</source><volume>88</volume>, no. <issue>2</issue> (<year>2022</year>): <fpage>713</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>722</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bcp.15007</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34337777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0086"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0086"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>E.</given-names><surname>de Vries</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>E.</given-names><surname>Bakker</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>R. D. C.</given-names><surname>Francisca</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>S.</given-names><surname>Croonen</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>P.</given-names><surname>Denig</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>P. G. M.</given-names><surname>Mol</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Handling of New Drug Safety Information in the Dutch Hospital Setting: A Mixed Methods Approach</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Drug Safety</source><volume>45</volume> (<year>2022</year>): <fpage>369</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>378</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35349127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40264-022-01149-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9021088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0087"><label>87</label><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="pds70135-cit-0087"><collab collab-type="authors">E.M. Agency</collab>
, <article-title>&#8220;Guideline on Good Pharmacovigilance Practices (GVP) Module XVI Addendum II &#8211; Methods for Evaluating Effectiveness of Risk Minimisation Measures,&#8221;</article-title> 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0088"><label>88</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0088"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>G. M.</given-names><surname>Breakwell</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Risk Communication: Factors Affecting Impact</article-title>,&#8221; <source>British Medical Bulletin</source><volume>56</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue> (<year>2000</year>): <fpage>110</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>120</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10885109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1258/0007142001902824</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0089"><label>89</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0089"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>P.</given-names><surname>Slovic</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Perceived Risk, Trust, and Democracy</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Risk Analysis</source><volume>13</volume>, no. <issue>6</issue> (<year>1993</year>): <fpage>675</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>682</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0090"><label>90</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0090"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>E.</given-names><surname>de Vries</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>E.</given-names><surname>Bakker</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>T. B. M.</given-names><surname>Monster</surname></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>P.</given-names><surname>Denig</surname></string-name>, and <string-name name-style="western"><given-names>P. G. M.</given-names><surname>Mol</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>Factors Influencing Preferences and Responses Towards Drug Safety Communications: A Conjoint Experiment Among Hospital&#8208;Based Healthcare Professionals in The Netherlands</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Drug Safety</source><volume>45</volume>, no. <issue>11</issue> (<year>2022</year>): <fpage>1369</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1380</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36107383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40264-022-01230-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9560924</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pds70135-bib-0091"><label>91</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="pds70135-cit-0091"><string-name name-style="western"><given-names>M.</given-names><surname>Mollebaek</surname></string-name>, &#8220;<article-title>The Effectiveness of Direct to Healthcare Professional Communication &#8211; A Systematic Review of Communication Factor Studies</article-title>,&#8221; <source>Research in Social &amp; Administrative Pharmacy</source><volume>15</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue> (<year>2019</year>): <fpage>475</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>482</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31130181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.sapharm.2018.06.015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>