<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Arthrosc Sports Med Rehabil</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Arthrosc Sports Med Rehabil</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3834</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">asmr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Arthroscopy, Sports Medicine, and Rehabilitation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2666-061X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10461205</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10461205.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10461205</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10461205</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37645390</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.asmr.2023.05.004</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2666-061X(23)00090-1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100747</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Income and Insurance Status Impact Access to Health Care for Hip Osteoarthritis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Youn</surname><given-names initials="EJ">Erin J.</given-names></name><degrees>B.A.</degrees><email>erinjyoun@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#8727;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names initials="C">Caleb</given-names></name><degrees>B.S.</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haratian</surname><given-names initials="R">Ryan</given-names></name><degrees>B.A.</degrees><xref rid="PC_affbjRy5BWevk" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names initials="A">Alvarho</given-names></name><degrees>B.A.</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="JY">Joo Yeon</given-names></name><degrees>B.A.</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGahan</surname><given-names initials="P">Patrick</given-names></name><degrees>M.D.</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="JL">James L.</given-names></name><degrees>M.D., M.P.H.</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Advanced Orthopedics and Sports Medicine, San Francisco, California, U.S.A.</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Williams College, Williamstown, Massachusetts, U.S.A.</aff><aff id="PC_affbjRy5BWevk"><label>c</label>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Sports Medicine &amp; Rehabilitation, Wright State University Boonshoft School of Medicine, Dayton, Ohio, U.S.A.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#8727;</label>Address correspondence to Erin J. Youn, B.A., Advanced Orthopedics and Sports Medicine, 450 Sutter St, Ste 400, San Francisco, CA 94108, U.S.A. <email>erinjyoun@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>8</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">440549</issue-id><elocation-id>100747</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>27</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>29</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-08-30 11:25:20.073"><day>30</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2023 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>To explore differences in the affordability of and accessibility to health care among adults with hip osteoarthritis with respect to race/ethnicity, income, and insurance status.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>This cross-sectional retrospective study was conducted using 2016 National Health Interview Survey (NHIS) data. NHIS data collection occurred continuously from January to December 2016. Individuals belonging to households and noninstitutionalized groups were included in the study. Because NHIS randomized surveys are conducted face-to-face on an annual basis, follow-up data are not collected.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Answers from 38,158,634 weighted respondents with a mean age of 58.33 &#177; 0.33 years were assessed. Among adults with hip osteoarthritis, those with public insurance had increased odds of delaying care owing to lack of transportation and had decreased odds of delaying care and follow-up care owing to cost. Individuals who were uninsured or who belonged to lower income brackets were associated with increased odds of being unable to afford or utilize health care.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>In this study, we found that income bracket and insurance status affect the accessibility to health care among adults with hip osteoarthritis in the United States.</p></sec><sec><title>Level of Evidence</title><p>Level IV, prognostic case series.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0010">Osteoarthritis, the most common presentation of arthritis, affects 42% of the adult population by age 75 years.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Hip osteoarthritis is the second most common form of osteoarthritis, with a recorded incidence rate of 7.34% in 2019; this represents an increase from the 2008 recorded incidence rate of 4.03%, underscoring the increased prevalence of this condition.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Whereas conservative treatment options for hip osteoarthritis include physical therapy, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, and intra-articular corticosteroid injections, hip arthroplasty is the definitive form of surgical treatment for hip osteoarthritis.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></p><p id="p0015">Although numerous treatment modalities are available for hip osteoarthritis, understanding the influence of socioeconomic conditions on health outcomes can further elevate care for underprivileged patients experiencing hip osteoarthritis. Previous studies have explored the role of socioeconomic status and its impact on patient care.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Lurie and Dubowitz<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> showed a clear connection between socioeconomic status and health outcomes by finding an increased risk of morbidity among persons in racial and ethnic minority groups, as well as individuals who have obtained lower levels of education. Furthermore, Peek et&#160;al.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> found that among diabetic individuals, those in racial and ethnic minority groups have a higher incidence of surgical complications. These studies and many more underscore the role that variables such as race, sex, income, education, and access to health care have regarding health inequities.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p><p id="p0020">Numerous orthopaedic studies have also established the impact that various socioeconomic factors bear on elective orthopaedic procedures and outcomes.<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> For example, Testa et&#160;al.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> found that African American patients and patients with Medicaid or Workers&#8217; Compensation had decreased odds of undergoing anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction after an injury. Studies have also shown that among patients undergoing total knee arthroplasty operations, those in racial and ethnic minority groups such as Blacks/African Americans and Hispanics/Latinos have increased odds of readmissions and postsurgical complications.<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> Furthermore, Koressel et&#160;al.<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> found that outcomes of patients undergoing total hip arthroplasty were poorer for those eligible for both Medicare and Medicaid than for those with other insurance plans. Various studies have been conducted on the impact of socioeconomic factors on the utilization and outcomes of total hip arthroplasty.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></p><p id="p0025">The purpose of this study was to explore differences in the affordability of and accessibility to health care among adults with hip osteoarthritis with respect to race/ethnicity, income, and insurance status. We hypothesized that race, income status, and insurance status would pose barriers to the affordability of and accessibility to health care among individuals with hip osteoarthritis.</p><sec id="sec1"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec1.1"><title>Data Set and Data Collection</title><p id="p0030">This retrospective study was conducted using the 2016 National Health Interview Survey (NHIS), an annual cross-sectional survey administered to the non-institutionalized adult civilian population by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. The objective of the survey is to monitor the health of the US population through face-to-face and follow-up telephone interviews of approximately 30,000 adults in the 50 states and the District of Columbia.<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> The NHIS builds sampling weights to expand respondent representation to other individuals in the United States.<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> Demographic and socioeconomic factors are measured in addition to health metrics. Stratification, clustering, and oversampling of various ethnic populations are used to generate nationally representative data. Households are selected based on primary sampling unit (PSU) divisions. PSUs are defined as counties or metropolitan areas, and the United States is divided into 1,689 geographic PSUs. When appropriate, some state PSUs are divided into the strata of urban and rural, whereas other state PSUs are made up of a single stratum. From each stratum, 2,500 addresses are chosen, and a set number of addresses are then selected for the NHIS. Sample methodologies are redesigned every 10 years, and 2016 represents the first year for the most recent cycle.<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> For this study, the 2016 data set was chosen because it represents one of the most recent data sets to include the survey questions of interest. Notably, although the NHIS was restructured in 2019, the changes do not impact the survey findings of 2016. These changes include a reduction in the length of the survey and the introduction of rotating questions related to topics such as mental health and service utilization.<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> The supporting data for this study are openly available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhis/nhis_2016_data_release.htm" id="intref0010">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhis/nhis_2016_data_release.htm</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="sec1.2"><title>Ethics</title><p id="p0035">To protect study participants, the NHIS and the questions for this study were reviewed by the National Center for Health Statistics Research Ethics Review Board.<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> The National Institutes of Health (NIH) protocol was also approved by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention Institutional Review Board, and prior to participation, all survey respondents in the NHIS database provided verbal consent. According to the guidelines delineated by the NIH and the NIH decision tool, this research is not considered human subjects research because the database was not generated for this study, is publicly accessible, and lacks subject identifiers.</p></sec><sec id="sec1.3"><title>Hip Osteoarthritis Definition</title><p id="p0040">Among adults who had been informed by a doctor or health professional that they had osteoarthritis or a related condition, those with symptomatic hip osteoarthritis were identified by their responses to 2 consecutive questions: The first question, &#8220;During the past 30 days, have you had any symptoms of pain, aching or stiffness in or around the joint?,&#8221; was used to identify whether an individual was experiencing joint pain currently. An affirmative response to this question was followed by the second question, &#8220;Which joints are affected?,&#8221; which included the identification of pain in either hip. Previous studies using NHIS data have constructed definitions in a similar manner through survey questions.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref></p></sec><sec id="sec1.4"><title>Socioeconomic and Demographic Characteristics</title><p id="p0045">Socioeconomic and demographic variables were obtained and analyzed. Individuals were categorized into the following age groups: 18 to 29 years, 30 to 39 years, 40 to 49 years, 50 to 59 years, 60 to 69 years, and 70 years or greater. Sex was classified as male or female. Race/ethnicity was categorized into non-Hispanic white, Hispanic, non-Hispanic Black/African American, non-Hispanic Asian, and non-Hispanic other by combining the variables &#8220;Hispanic ethnicity, dichotomous&#8221; and &#8220;self-reported race.&#8221; Total combined family income was stratified as follows: less than $35,000, $35,000 to $74,999, $75,000 to $99,999, and $100,000 or greater. Education was classified as less than high school, high school or General Educational Development (GED), and greater than high school. Insurance status was categorized as private, public, uninsured, and other. Public insurance refers to Medicaid or Medicare, and individuals with &#8220;other insurance&#8221; comprise those who were unaware of their insurance type and those who had other types of insurance coverage. The covariates diabetes, hypertension, and smoking were incorporated to account for potential confounding medical comorbidities. Other studies using NHIS data have stratified socioeconomic and demographic variables similarly.<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></p><p id="p0050">Impediments to health care utilization were evaluated using the following variables present in the 2016 NHIS: whether patients did not have access to medical care or had to delay needed medical care owing to cost; whether patients delayed needed care owing to lack of transportation; and whether patients needed but did not receive follow-up care, specialist care, or prescription medications owing to cost (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#160;1</xref>). Response options were &#8220;yes,&#8221; &#8220;no,&#8221; &#8220;refused,&#8221; and &#8220;don&#8217;t know.&#8221;<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of Study Population by Hip Osteoarthritis Status According to 2016 National Health Interview Survey</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Hip Osteoarthritis, Weighted Respondents (%)<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> Value</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patients</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28,701,814</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9,456,820</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age group</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;18-29 yr</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,641,002 (9.20)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">603,147 (6.38)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;30-39 yr</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,102,889 (10.81)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">755,603 (7.99)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;40-49 yr</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,783,932 (13.18)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,092,278 (11.55)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;50-59 yr</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,012,890 (20.95)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,175,763 (23.00)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;60-69 yr</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,561,450 (22.86)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,519,591 (26.64)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#8805;70 yr</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,599,651 (22.99)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,310,438 (24.43)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Male</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,735,095 (44.37)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,382,723 (35.77)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Female</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,966,719 (55.63)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,074,097 (64.23)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;White</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20,540,304 (71.56)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7,322,555 (77.43)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hispanic</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,973,777 (10.36)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">664,376 (7.03)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;African American</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,462,724 (12.06)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,006,441 (10.64)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Asian</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,024,869 (3.57)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">145,380 (1.54)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">700,140 (2.44)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">318,068 (3.36)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Income</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$0-$34,999</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,646,164 (19.67)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,613,554 (17.06)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$35,000-$74,999</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,129,535 (10.90)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">923,441 (9.76)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$75,000-$99,000</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8,804,433 (30.68)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,697,779 (28.53)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#8805;$100,000</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11,121,682 (38.75)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,222,046 (44.65)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Education</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Less than HS</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,969,656 (13.88)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,185,275 (12.56)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.134</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;HS or GED</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7,274,885 (25.44)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,531,820 (26.82)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Greater than HS</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17,347,126 (60.09)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,723,045 (60.62)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Insurance plan type</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Private insurance</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16,402,994 (57.15)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,853,603 (51.32)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Public insurance</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,590,309 (15.99)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,871,226 (19.79)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Uninsured</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,064,447 (7.19)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">476,998 (5.04)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,644,064 (19.66)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,254,993 (23.85)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Comorbidities</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Diabetes</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,334,184 (15.72)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,000,756 (22.00)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hypertension</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,610,563 (47.51)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,038,766 (53.35)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Smoking</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,674,667 (47.77)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,031,258 (53.30)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Health care access</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Medical care inaccessible owing to cost</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,595,771 (9.00)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,184,515 (13.00)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Medical care delayed owing to cost</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,571,061 (12.45)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,563,633 (16.53)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Medical care delayed owing to lack of transportation</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">327 (3.56)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">179 (5.67)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Needed but could not afford follow-up care</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,263,333 (4.43)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">558,278 (6.25)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Needed but could not afford specialist care</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,708,363 (6.00)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">819,715 (8.72)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Needed but could not afford prescription medications</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,732,157 (9.59)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,242,679 (13.21)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>GED, General Educational Development; HS, high school.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec1.5"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p id="p0055">Statistical analysis was conducted using RStudio (version 1.4.1106; Boston, MA) with &#945;&#160;= .05. To generate a multistage probability sample, the NHIS data set uses stratification, clustering, and oversampling of various ethnic populations. Thus, prior to statistical analysis of the data, we applied proper sampling weights to generate nationally representative results. The &#967;<sup>2</sup> test was performed to analyze categorical outcomes. The role of socioeconomic factors in access to health care was assessed through multivariable logistic regressions. The assessed covariates were similar to those in previous studies also using NHIS data and included age, sex, income status, education, insurance plan type, and comorbidities such as diabetes, hypertension, and smoking.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Results</title><p id="p0060">A total of 38,158,634 weighted respondents with a mean age of 58.33 &#177; 0.33 years answered the question on joint pain on the 2016 NHIS. Of these respondents, 9,456,820 (24.78%) noted symptoms of hip pain, aching, and stiffness. Statistically significant differences were observed between participants presenting with hip osteoarthritis and individuals without this condition when categorized by the sociodemographic factors of age, sex, race, income bracket, and insurance plan type (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#160;1</xref>). Additionally, the comorbidities of diabetes, hypertension, and smoking were associated with increased odds of hip osteoarthritis. Furthermore, compared with individuals without hip osteoarthritis, those experiencing hip osteoarthritis reported facing barriers to health care more frequently, as assessed through &#967;<sup>2</sup> analyses (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#160;1</xref>).</p><sec id="sec2.1"><title>Multivariable Logistic Regression Analyses</title><p id="p0065">Multivariable logistic regression analyses were conducted to assess the impact of sociodemographic predictors on hip osteoarthritis (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#160;2</xref>). Older age groups were associated with higher odds of hip osteoarthritis compared with the 18- to 29-year-old reference age group, specifically the 50- to 59-year-old group (adjusted odds ratio [OR], 1.453; 95% confidence interval [CI], 1.177-1.793) and the 60- to 69-year-old group (adjusted OR, 1.411; 95% CI, 1.126-1.768). Female sex (adjusted OR, 1.453; 95% CI, 1.313-1.607) was associated with an increased risk of hip osteoarthritis. Racial/ethnic minority status was associated with a decreased risk of hip osteoarthritis, specifically Hispanic (adjusted OR, 0.625; 95% CI, 0.505-0.774), African American (adjusted OR, 0.723; 95% CI, 0.612-0.854), and Asian (adjusted OR, 0.416; 95% CI, 0.263-0.659). Individuals belonging to the lowest income bracket of less than $35,000 (adjusted OR, 1.206; 95% CI, 1.026-1.417) exhibited an increased risk of hip osteoarthritis compared with the reference income bracket group (i.e., &gt;$100,000). Individuals with public insurance coverage (adjusted OR, 1.296; 95% CI, 1.111-1.066) and other coverage (adjusted OR, 1.243; 95% CI, 1.081-1.442) were associated with increased odds of hip osteoarthritis. Moreover, the odds of hip osteoarthritis increased in individuals with the comorbidities of diabetes (adjusted OR, 1.405; 95% CI, 1.230-1.605) and smoking (adjusted OR, 1.235; 95% CI, 1.111-1.372).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;2</label><caption><p>Multivariable Logistic Regression Analysis of Sociodemographic Factors and Hip Osteoarthritis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adjusted OR (95% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age group</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;18-29 yr</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;30-39 yr</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.074 (0.830-1.391)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.587</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;40-49 yr</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.224 (0.956-1.567)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.110</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;50-59 yr</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.453 (1.177-1.793)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.001<xref rid="tbl2fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;60-69 yr</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.411 (1.126-1.768)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.003<xref rid="tbl2fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#8805;70 yr</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.211 (0.969-1.515)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.093</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Female</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.453 (1.313-1.607)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="tbl2fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;White</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hispanic</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.625 (0.505-0.774)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="tbl2fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;African American</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.723 (0.612-0.854)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.001<xref rid="tbl2fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Asian</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.416 (0.263-0.659)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="tbl2fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.253 (0.937-1.677)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.129</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Income</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#8805;$100,000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$75,000-$99,000</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.023 (0.846-1.236)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.817</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$35,000-$74,999</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.023 (0.873-1.198)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.780</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$0-$34,999</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.206 (1.026-1.417)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.024<xref rid="tbl2fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Education</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Less than HS</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;HS or GED</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.200 (1.021-1.412)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.028<xref rid="tbl2fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Greater than HS</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.226 (1.050-1.431)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.010<xref rid="tbl2fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Insurance plan type</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Private insurance</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Public insurance</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.296 (1.111-1.512)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.001<xref rid="tbl2fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Uninsured</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.834 (0.643-1.066)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.148</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.243 (1.081-1.442)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.003<xref rid="tbl2fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Comorbidities</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;No comorbidities</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Diabetes</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.405 (1.230-1.605)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="tbl2fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hypertension</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.055 (0.941-1.183)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.357</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Smoking</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.235 (1.111-1.372)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="tbl2fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>CI, confidence interval; OR, odds ratio.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fnlowast"><label>&#8727;</label><p id="ntpara0015">Statistically significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><sec id="sec2.1.1"><sec id="sec2.1.1.1"><title>Race</title><p id="p0070">Multivariable logistic regression analyses were conducted to assess the effect of race on the affordability of and accessibility to health care among individuals with hip osteoarthritis. When compared with white Americans, individuals in all other racial/ethnic groups with hip osteoarthritis did not experience increased odds of economic burden or inaccessibility to health care.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.1.1.2"><title>Income Status</title><p id="p0075">Multivariable logistic regression analyses were conducted to assess the effect of income status on the affordability of and accessibility to health care among individuals with hip osteoarthritis (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#160;3</xref>). Compared with individuals belonging to higher income brackets, those in the lowest income bracket presented increased risks of an inability to access care owing to cost (adjusted OR, 7.656; 95% CI, 3.663-16.002), delayed care owing to cost (adjusted OR, 5.195; 95% CI, 2.907-9.283), delayed care owing to lack of transportation (adjusted OR, 7.526; 95% CI, 2.190-25.866), and an inability to afford follow-up care (adjusted OR, 4.101; 95% CI, 1.742-9.653), specialist care (adjusted OR, 3.964; 95% CI, 2.018-7.788), and prescription medications (adjusted OR, 6.615; 95% CI, 3.321-13.177). Individuals in the other lower income brackets also exhibited significant health care inequities (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#160;3</xref>). A similar observation was made in the non-hip osteoarthritis population.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;3</label><caption><p>Multivariable Logistic Regression Analyses of Effect of Income Level on Accessibility to and Affordability of Care in Patients With Hip Osteoarthritis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Income Level</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adjusted OR (95% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient needed medical care but could not access it owing to cost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#8805;$100,000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$75,000-$99,000</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.320 (0.541-3.221)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.543</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$35,000-$74,999</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.730 (1.351-5.515)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.005<xref rid="tbl3fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$0-$34,999</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.656 (3.663-16.002)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="tbl3fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient needed medical care but it was delayed owing to cost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#8805;$100,000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$75,000-$99,000</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.099 (0.560-2.157)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.783</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$35,000-$74,999</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.382 (1.446-3.926)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="tbl3fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$0-$34,999</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.195 (2.907-9.283)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="tbl3fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient needed medical care but it was delayed owing to lack of transportation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#8805;$100,000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$75,000-$99,000</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.571 (0.800-15.934)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.096</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$35,000-$74,999</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.047 (0.823-11.290)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.096</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$0-$34,999</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.526 (2.190-25.866)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.001<xref rid="tbl3fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient needed follow-up medical care but could not access it owing to cost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#8805;$100,000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$75,000-$99,000</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.089 (0.388-3.054)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.871</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$35,000-$74,999</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.274 (0.996-5.191)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.052</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$0-$34,999</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.101 (1.742-9.653)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.001<xref rid="tbl3fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient needed care from specialist but could not access it owing to cost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#8805;$100,000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$75,000-$99,000</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.312 (0.556-3.099)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.535</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$35,000-$74,999</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.981 (1.042-3.766)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.038<xref rid="tbl3fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$0-$34,999</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.964 (2.018-7.788)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="tbl3fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient needed prescription medications but could not access them owing to cost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#8805;$100,000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$75,000-$99,000</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.340 (1.466-7.607)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.004<xref rid="tbl3fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$35,000-$74,999</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.551 (1.765-7.148)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="tbl3fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;$0-$34,999</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.615 (3.321-13.177)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="tbl3fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>CI, confidence interval; OR, odds ratio.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl3fnlowast"><label>&#8727;</label><p id="ntpara0020">Statistically significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec2.1.1.3"><title>Insurance Status</title><p id="p0080">Multivariable logistic regression analyses were conducted to assess the effect of insurance status on the affordability of and accessibility to health care among individuals with hip osteoarthritis (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table&#160;4</xref>). Compared with individuals with private insurance coverage, those with public insurance coverage had a decreased risk of a delay in medical care owing to cost (adjusted OR, 0.507; 95% CI, 0.332-0.775) and an inability to undergo follow-up owing to cost (adjusted OR, 0.523; 95% CI, 0.281-0.976) but had an increased risk of delayed care owing to lack of transportation (adjusted OR, 3.021; 95% CI, 1.787-5.108). Individuals who were uninsured exhibited increased risks of an inability to access care owing to cost (adjusted OR, 4.760; 95% CI, 2.952-7.675); delayed care owing to cost (adjusted OR, 5.016; 95% CI, 3.141-8.010); and an inability to afford follow-up care (adjusted OR, 3.747; 95% CI, 2.260-6.210), specialist care (adjusted OR, 4.777; 95% CI, 2.911-7.838), and prescription medications (adjusted OR, 4.338; 95% CI, 2.763-6.812). Furthermore, individuals with other insurance coverage had higher risks of delayed care owing to lack of transportation (adjusted OR, 2.367; 95% CI, 1.255-4.464) and an inability to access prescription medications owing to cost (adjusted OR, 2.000; 95% CI, 1.324-3.022). Similar effects were observed in the non-hip osteoarthritis population.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table&#160;4</label><caption><p>Multivariable Logistic Regression Analyses of Effect of Insurance Plan Type on Accessibility to and Affordability of Care in Patients With Hip Osteoarthritis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Insurance Plan Type</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adjusted OR (95% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient needed medical care but could not access it owing to cost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Private insurance</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Public insurance</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.736 (0.479-1.132)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.164</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Uninsured</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.760 (2.952-7.675)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="tbl4fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.147 (0.784 -1.677)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.481</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient needed medical care but it was delayed owing to cost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Private insurance</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Public insurance</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.507 (0.332-0.775)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.002<xref rid="tbl4fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Uninsured</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.016 (3.141-8.010)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="tbl4fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.033 (0.735-1.452)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.852</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient needed medical care but it was delayed owing to lack of transportation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Private insurance</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Public insurance</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.021 (1.787-5.108)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="tbl4fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Uninsured</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.953 (0.411-2.208)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.910</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.367 (1.255-4.464)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.008<xref rid="tbl4fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient needed follow-up medical care but could not access it owing to cost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Private insurance</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Public insurance</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.523 (0.281-0.976)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.042<xref rid="tbl4fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Uninsured</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.747 (2.260-6.210)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="tbl4fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.232 (0.761-1.995)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.396</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient needed care from specialist but could not access it owing to cost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Private insurance</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Public insurance</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.939 (0.579-1.522)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.798</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Uninsured</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.777 (2.911-7.838)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="tbl4fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.401 (0.899-2.183)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.137</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient needed prescription medications but could not access them owing to cost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Private insurance</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (reference)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Public insurance</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.919 (0.593-1.424)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.704</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Uninsured</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.338 (2.763-6.812)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001<xref rid="tbl4fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.000 (1.324-3.022)</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.001<xref rid="tbl4fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#8727;</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>CI, confidence interval; OR, odds ratio.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl4fnlowast"><label>&#8727;</label><p id="ntpara0025">Statistically significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0085">Our study reveals that income and insurance are associated with barriers to the affordability of and accessibility to health care among individuals affected by hip osteoarthritis. We found that individuals belonging to lower income brackets and those with public insurance or other insurance were more likely to cite lack of transportation as a barrier to health care. This finding is consistent with the results of numerous studies that have shown that transportation barriers may prevent individuals from accessing health care, which ultimately contributes to poorer health management outcomes.<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> Wallace et&#160;al.<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> found that individuals belonging to lower income brackets cite a lack of transportation as a cause of delayed medical care, a finding equally reflected in our study. Furthermore, in several large surveys, 24% to 51% of respondents cited unreliable transportation as a reason for rescheduling or missing an appointment, which underscores the important role that transportation plays in health care.<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> We also found that public insurance and other insurance were associated with delayed care owing to lack of transportation. A possible explanation for individuals with public insurance experiencing transportation barriers is that although government-sponsored public insurance programs, such as Medicaid, seek to expand insurance coverage, they do not provide individuals with tangible methods of reaching facilities for care.<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> This finding may also hold true for individuals with other insurance. A similar observation was made in the non-hip osteoarthritis population, further highlighting the role that transportation plays in health care inequities. Together, these findings emphasize that various socioeconomic variables may influence an individual&#8217;s access to care.</p><p id="p0090">According to our study, there was also an association between the affordability of and accessibility to health care and an individual&#8217;s income bracket. Many studies have established the adverse health effects that plague low-income individuals, such as overall poorer health outcomes and decreased life expectancy.<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> For example, Alvarez et&#160;al.<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> found that patients belonging to lower income brackets may have decreased access to total joint arthroplasty, as well as an increased readmission risk, compared with patients belonging to higher income brackets, underscoring the role of income status in the orthopaedic setting. For every variable we assessed in this study, the inability to afford and access care increased with decreasing income brackets, showing that patients with hip osteoarthritis are not immune to the income-related health care disparities cited in the literature.<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> With respect to specialist care, in 2006 Van Doorslaer et&#160;al.<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref> assessed specialist utilization among various countries and found that in all countries assessed, including the United States, individuals with higher incomes were more likely to see specialists and saw specialists with greater frequency. Furthermore, Heisler et&#160;al.<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref> assessed the different strategies that individuals used to cope with high prescription medication costs and found that these various strategies were particularly implemented among low-income individuals. Given that first-line treatment options for hip osteoarthritis include treatment with prescription medications, as well as intra-articular corticosteroid injections, which require specialist care, the findings of this study are concerning.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> Thus, there is a pressing need to address the health care disparities that exist for this population.</p><p id="p0095">Additionally, we found that uninsured individuals with hip osteoarthritis were associated with increased odds of an inability to access and afford care.<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref> In 2014, Sommers et&#160;al.<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr"><sup>45</sup></xref> established that uninsured individuals who obtained insurance in the past 12 months reported having fewer difficulties affording medical care, and 6 months after obtaining insurance, individuals reported having successfully established care with a doctor. This finding highlights the positive effects that insurance coverage can have on not only expanding the affordability of health care but also accessibility to health providers such as doctors and specialists. Furthermore, Matlock et&#160;al.<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref> showed that elective hip and knee arthroplasties increased at the age of 65 years as individuals who were uninsured obtained insurance coverage. This finding highlights the role of uninsured status in the field of orthopaedics and continues to support evidence regarding the negative effects of uninsured status on patients&#8217; health. Similarly, Miller and Wherry<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47</sup></xref> found that after the first 2 years of Medicaid expansion through the Affordable Care Act, follow-up care was more accessible to patients. Studies have also shown that prescription medications represent a significant cost for uninsured individuals, an effect that is reflected in our study as well (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table&#160;4</xref>).<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref> Thus, it is possible that uninsured individuals in this study may have had difficulty accessing prescription medications for hip osteoarthritis because of cost barriers. Furthermore, it is important to acknowledge that although our findings reveal that individuals with public or other insurance coverage were associated with increased odds of hip arthritis (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#160;2</xref>), this may also be a result of increased access to specialist care, which permitted an initial diagnosis. Collectively, these findings emphasize the important role that insurance has in increasing health care accessibility and affordability among patients with hip osteoarthritis.</p><p id="p0100">Surprisingly, race was not found to be a significant variable in the affordability of and accessibility to health care among individuals with hip osteoarthritis in our study. However, numerous other studies have continued to highlight the health inequities that exist with respect to race.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> These racial disparities not only are linked with health care outcomes but also extend toward utilization rates. For example, Zhang et&#160;al.<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref> found that compared with white patients, Black, Hispanic, Asian, Native American, and mixed-race patients face lower rates of total knee arthroplasty utilization, showcasing that these disparities also exist prior to surgical treatment. Thus, our finding may be explained by previous studies that have shown the role of other variables in contributing to health inequities. In 2010, Shi et&#160;al.<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref> found that Blacks and Hispanics were less likely to report barriers to medical care and prescription medications than their white counterparts. However, insurance status was found to be significantly correlated with health care disparities, with the uninsured population in particular facing barriers to health care.<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref> Jointly, these findings illustrate the complex relations that exist among various socioeconomic variables that must be further analyzed for a deeper understanding of health care disparities in the orthopaedic field.</p><p id="p0105">One strength of our study is that the NHIS contacts a broad portion of the population for data collection, including individuals who may not typically be found in a medical setting. Thus, we were able to conduct data analysis on a nationally representative sample. Furthermore, the large sample size allows for more accurate data analysis.</p><sec id="sec3.1"><title>Limitations</title><p id="p0110">One of the limitations of this study is the use of a data set from 2016, which may not accurately reflect the current socioeconomic disparities delineated in this article. The 2016 data set was one of the most recent data sets to include survey questions that are relevant to our study. Hip osteoarthritis was also defined in this study by 2 questions related to hip osteoarthritis in the 2016 NHIS survey. The inability to draw causal inferences owing to the cross-sectional nature of the study imposes further limitations to the study. Recall bias associated with survey responses to the questions presented and response bias linked to&#160;self-reported responses are additional factors to consider. For example, <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#160;1</xref> notes that about 18% of the 18- to 29-year-old population had hip osteoarthritis. However, this may be confounded by factors such as the increased prevalence of femoroacetabular impingement in individuals belonging to this age group rather than the prevalence of hip osteoarthritis itself.<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0115">In this study, we found that income bracket and insurance status affect the accessibility to health care among adults with hip osteoarthritis in the United States.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Urits</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orhurhu</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Minimally invasive therapies for osteoarthritic hip pain: A comprehensive review</article-title><source>Curr Pain Headache Rep</source><volume>24</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>37</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32506251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11916-020-00874-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arslan</surname><given-names>I.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Damen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Wilde</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Estimating incidence and prevalence of hip osteoarthritis using electronic health records: A population-based cohort study</article-title><source>Osteoarthritis Cartilage</source><volume>30</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>843</fpage><lpage>851</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35307534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.joca.2022.03.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the patient with hip pain</article-title><source>Am Fam Physician</source><volume>89</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24444505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsertsvadze</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grove</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Total hip replacement for the treatment of end stage arthritis of the hip: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>9</volume><year>2014</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e99804</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0099804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4086719</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25003202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Belk</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Houck</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Littlefield</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Platelet-rich plasma versus hyaluronic acid for hip osteoarthritis yields similarly beneficial short-term clinical outcomes: A systematic review and meta-analysis of Level I and II randomized controlled trials</article-title><source>Arthroscopy</source><volume>38</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>2035</fpage><lpage>2046</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34785294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arthro.2021.11.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lurie</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubowitz</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health disparities and access to health</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>297</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>1118</fpage><lpage>1121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17356034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.297.10.1118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peek</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cargill</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diabetes health disparities: A systematic review of health care interventions</article-title><source>Med Care Res Rev</source><volume>64</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>101S</fpage><lpage>156S</lpage><comment>(suppl)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17881626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1077558707305409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2367214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubay</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lebrun</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health, behavior, and health care disparities: Disentangling the effects of income and race in the United States</article-title><source>Int J Heal Serv</source><volume>42</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2190/HS.42.4.c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23367796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pickle</surname><given-names>L.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mungiole</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillum</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geographic variation in stroke mortality in blacks and whites in the United States</article-title><source>Stroke</source><volume>28</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>1639</fpage><lpage>1647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9259762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/01.str.28.8.1639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>N.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transportation barriers to health care in the United States: Findings from the National Health Interview Survey, 1997-2017</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source><volume>110</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>815</fpage><lpage>822</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32298170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2105/AJPH.2020.305579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7204444</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoenfield</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tipirneni</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwashyna</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of race and ethnicity on complications and mortality after orthopedic surgery: A systematic review of the literature on JSTOR</article-title><source>Med Care</source><volume>52</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>842</fpage><lpage>851</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25100230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MLR.0000000000000177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nwachukwu</surname><given-names>B.U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenny</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Losina</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chibnik</surname><given-names>L.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complications for racial and ethnic minority groups after total hip and knee replacement: A review of the literature</article-title><source>J&#160;Bone Joint Surg Am</source><volume>92</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>338</fpage><lpage>345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20124060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2106/JBJS.I.00510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2811969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sporer</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wennberg</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Racial, ethnic, and geographic disparities in rates of knee arthroplasty among Medicare patients</article-title><source>N&#160;Engl J Med</source><volume>349</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>1350</fpage><lpage>1359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14523144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMsa021569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zelle</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morton-Gonzaba</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adcock</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacci</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seifi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Healthcare disparities among orthopedic trauma patients in the USA: Socio-demographic factors influence the management of calcaneus fractures</article-title><source>J&#160;Orthop Surg Res</source><volume>14</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>359</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31718674</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13018-019-1402-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6852936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Testa</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brodeur</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Social and demographic factors impact shoulder stabilization surgery in anterior glenohumeral instability</article-title><source>Arthrosc Sport Med Rehabil</source><volume>4</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>e1497</fpage><lpage>e1504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.asmr.2022.06.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9402473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36033183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maloney</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Voloshin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thirukumaran</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Black race, Hispanic ethnicity, and Medicaid insurance are associated with lower rates of rotator cuff repair in New York State</article-title><source>Arthroscopy</source><volume>38</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>3001</fpage><lpage>3010.e2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35817374</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arthro.2022.06.028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Testa</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Modest</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brodeur</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemme</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>A.I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do patient demographic and socioeconomic factors influence surgical treatment rates after ACL injury?</article-title><source>J&#160;Racial Ethn Health Disparities</source><volume>10</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35006586</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40615-021-01222-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cusano</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Venugopal</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gronbeck</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halawi</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Where do we stand today on racial and ethnic health inequities? Analysis of primary total knee arthroplasty from a 2011&#8211;2017 national database</article-title><source>J&#160;Racial Ethn Health Disparities</source><volume>8</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>1178</fpage><lpage>1184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32940894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40615-020-00875-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>What factors lead to racial disparities in outcomes after total knee arthroplasty?</article-title><source>J&#160;Racial Ethn Health Disparities</source><volume>9</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>2317</fpage><lpage>2322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34642904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40615-021-01168-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9633442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koressel</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeAngelis</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerbel</surname><given-names>Y.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheth</surname><given-names>N.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Profound impact of insurance payor and socioeconomic status in total hip arthroplasty outcomes: Results from a high volume tertiary care center</article-title><source>J&#160;Arthroplasty</source><volume>37</volume><issue>suppl</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>S434</fpage><lpage>S438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35278670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2022.03.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>N.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muzammil</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howie</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biant</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Socioeconomic status affects the early outcome of total hip replacement</article-title><source>J&#160;Bone Joint Surg Br</source><volume>93</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>464</fpage><lpage>469</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21464483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1302/0301-620X.93B4.25717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartnett</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brodeur</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kosinski</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>A.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Socioeconomic disparities in the utilization of total hip arthroplasty</article-title><source>J&#160;Arthroplasty</source><volume>37</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>218.e1</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34748913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2021.10.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manheim</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Age and racial/ethnic disparities in arthritis-related hip and knee surgeries</article-title><source>Med Care</source><volume>46</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18219249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MLR.0b013e31815cecd8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab></person-group><article-title>About the National Health Interview Survey</article-title><comment>Published 2022</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhis/about_nhis.htm" id="intref0015">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhis/about_nhis.htm</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>IPUMS Health Surveys</collab></person-group><article-title>NHIS sample design</article-title><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nhis.ipums.org/nhis/userNotes_sampledesign.shtml" id="intref0020">https://nhis.ipums.org/nhis/userNotes_sampledesign.shtml</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab></person-group><article-title>Worker health information from the National Health Interview Survey</article-title><comment>Published 2022</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/niosh/topics/nhis/method.html" id="intref0025">https://www.cdc.gov/niosh/topics/nhis/method.html</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>E.X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between vestibular vertigo and motor vehicle accidents: Data from the 2016 National Health Interview Survey</article-title><source>Ear Hear</source><volume>39</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1232</fpage><lpage>1235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29782443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/AUD.0000000000000602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref28">Youn GM, Shah JP, Wei EX, Alyono JC. Perceptions of respect among patients with hearing loss in the United States [published online March 30, 2023]. Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/OHN.330" id="intref0030">10.1002/OHN.330</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ohn.330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36994933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szaflarski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tobias</surname><given-names>J.G.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szaflarski</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Poverty, insurance, and region as predictors of epilepsy treatment among US adults</article-title><source>Epilepsy Behav</source><volume>107</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">107050</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.yebeh.2020.107050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7242147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32294594</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Denney</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zamora-Kapoor</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Race/ethnicity, sleep duration, and mortality risk in the United States</article-title><source>SSM Popul Health</source><volume>21</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101350</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ssmph.2023.101350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9920264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36785549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref31">Shah JP, Youn GM, Wei EX, Patel ZM. Disparities in access to health care in adults with sinusitis in the United States [published online April 8, 2023]. Int Forum Allergy Rhinol. doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/ALR.23167" id="intref0035">10.1002/ALR.23167</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/alr.23167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37029607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Syed</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>L.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traveling towards disease: Transportation barriers to health care access</article-title><source>J&#160;Community Health</source><volume>38</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>976</fpage><lpage>993</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23543372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10900-013-9681-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4265215</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes-Cromwick</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mull</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Access to health care and nonemergency medical transportation: Two missing links</article-title><source>Transp Res Rec</source><volume>1924</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>84</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaiyachati</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeager</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of rideshare-based transportation services and missed primary care appointments: A clinical trial</article-title><source>JAMA Intern Med</source><volume>178</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29404572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamainternmed.2017.8336</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Altindag</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Truskinovsky</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berkman</surname><given-names>L.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of the Affordable Care Act Medicaid expansion on subjective well-being in the US adult population, 2010&#8211;2016</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source><volume>109</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1236</fpage><lpage>1242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31318591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2105/AJPH.2019.305164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6687253</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health disparities across the lifespan: Meaning, methods, and mechanisms</article-title><source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source><volume>1186</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20201865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2009.05337.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Braveman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Egerter</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The social determinants of health: Coming of age</article-title><source>Annu Rev Public Health</source><volume>32</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21091195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev-publhealth-031210-101218</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chetty</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stepner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The association between income and life expectancy in the United States, 2001-2014</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>315</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1750</fpage><lpage>1766</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27063997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2016.4226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4866586</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKeon</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spitzer</surname><given-names>A.I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Socioeconomic factors affecting outcomes in total knee and hip arthroplasty: A systematic review on healthcare disparities</article-title><source>Arthroplasty</source><volume>4</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>36</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36184658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s42836-022-00137-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9528115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okunrintemi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khera</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spatz</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of income disparities with patient-reported healthcare experience</article-title><source>J&#160;Gen Intern Med</source><volume>34</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>884</fpage><lpage>892</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30783877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-019-04848-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6544715</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Doorslaer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masseria</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koolman</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inequalities in access to medical care by income in developed countries</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><volume>174</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16415462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1503/cmaj.050584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1329455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heisler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piette</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patient strategies to cope with high prescription medication costs: Who is cutting back on necessities, increasing debt, or underusing medications?</article-title><source>J&#160;Behav Med</source><volume>28</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15887875</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10865-005-2562-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desroches</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uninsured and unstably insured: The importance of continuous insurance coverage</article-title><source>Health Serv Res</source><volume>35</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><comment>(pt 2)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10778809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1089095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ziller</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lenardson</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coburn</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Project MUSE&#8212;Health care access and use among the rural uninsured</article-title><source>J&#160;Health Care Poor Underserved</source><volume>23</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>1327</fpage><lpage>1345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24212177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1353/hpu.2012.0100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sommers</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Musco</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finegold</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunja</surname><given-names>M.Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDowell</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health reform and changes in health insurance coverage in 2014</article-title><source>N&#160;Engl J Med</source><volume>371</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>867</fpage><lpage>874</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25054609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMsr1406753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matlock</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Earnest</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Utilization of elective hip and knee arthroplasty by age and payer</article-title><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><volume>466</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>914</fpage><lpage>919</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18213506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11999-008-0122-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2504650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wherry</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health and access to care during the first 2 years of the ACA Medicaid expansions</article-title><source>N&#160;Engl J Med</source><volume>376</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>947</fpage><lpage>956</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28273021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMsa1612890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman Shepherd</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Locke</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maihafer</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health services use and prescription access among uninsured patients managing chronic diseases</article-title><source>J&#160;Community Health</source><volume>39</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>572</fpage><lpage>583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24338075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10900-013-9799-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boutin-Foster</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Racial and ethnic disparities in utilization rate, hospital volume, and perioperative outcomes after total knee arthroplasty</article-title><source>J&#160;Bone Joint Surg Am</source><volume>98</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1243</fpage><lpage>1252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27489314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2106/JBJS.15.01009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lebrun</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Access to medical care, dental care, and prescription drugs: The roles of race/ethnicity, health insurance, and income</article-title><source>South Med J</source><volume>103</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20710132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/SMJ.0b013e3181d9c2d8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jauregui</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salmons</surname><given-names>H.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oster</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gopinath</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adib</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of femoro-acetabular impingement in non-arthritic patients with hip pain: A meta-analysis</article-title><source>Int Orthop</source><volume>44</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>2559</fpage><lpage>2566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33094401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00264-020-04857-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Data</title><p id="p0125">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>ICMJE author disclosure forms</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgment</title><p id="p0120">The authors thank G. M. Youn and J. P. Shah for assistance with data analysis.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="d35e1262"><p id="ntpara0010">The authors report the following potential conflicts of interest or sources of funding: J.L.C. receives personal fees for lectures and educational material from Arthrex, outside the submitted work. Full ICMJE author disclosure forms are available for this article online, as <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">supplementary material</xref>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>