<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3211</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jamasd</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JAMA Network Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2574-3805</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>JAMA Network</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11843354</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11843354.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11843354</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11843354</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39976966</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.60794</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zoi241694</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Investigation</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="online-only"><subject>Online Only</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="subject-area"><subject>Anesthesiology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>New Persistent Opioid Use After Surgery</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="headline">New Persistent Opioid Use After Surgery</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">New Persistent Opioid Use After Surgery</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bologheanu</surname><given-names initials="R">Razvan</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi241694aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="zoi241694aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bilir</surname><given-names initials="A">Aylin</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi241694aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="zoi241694aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapral</surname><given-names initials="L">Lorenz</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref rid="zoi241694aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="zoi241694aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names initials="F">Felix</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref rid="zoi241694aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimberger</surname><given-names initials="O">Oliver</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref rid="zoi241694aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="zoi241694aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="zoi241694aff1"><label>1</label>Division of General Anesthesia and Intensive Care Medicine, Department of Anesthesia, Intensive Care Medicine, and Pain Medicine, Medical University of Vienna, Vienna, Austria</aff><aff id="zoi241694aff2"><label>2</label>Ludwig Boltzmann Institute for Digital Health and Patient Safety, Vienna, Austria</aff><aff id="zoi241694aff3"><label>3</label>The Umbrella Organization of Austrian Social Security Institutions, Vienna, Austria</aff><author-notes><title>Article Information</title><p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> December 16, 2024.</p><p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published:</bold> February 20, 2025. doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.60794</uri></p><p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-license-permissions" ext-link-type="uri">CC-BY License</ext-link>. &#169; 2025 Bologheanu R et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic>.</p><corresp id="zoi241694cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Oliver Kimberger, MD, MSc, Division of General Anesthesia and Intensive Care Medicine, Department of Anesthesiology, Intensive Care Medicine, and Pain Medicine, Medical University of Vienna, W&#228;hringer G&#252;rtel 18-20, 1090 Vienna, Austria (<email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oliver.kimberger@meduniwien.ac.at">oliver.kimberger@meduniwien.ac.at</email>).</corresp><p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Dr Bologheanu had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Concept and design:</italic> Bologheanu, Bilir, Kimberger.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> Bilir, Kapral, Gruber, Kimberger.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Bologheanu, Kimberger.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> Bilir, Kapral, Gruber, Kimberger.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Statistical analysis:</italic> Bologheanu, Kapral, Kimberger.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Bilir, Gruber, Kimberger.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Supervision:</italic> Kimberger.</p><p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr Bologheanu reported receiving grants from Fresenius Kabi GmbH and the Medical-Scientific Fund of the Mayor of the Federal Capital Vienna outside the submitted work. Dr Bilir reported receiving the Anton Proksch-Institut Research Prize Award from the Stiftung Anton Proksch-Institut Wien for student theses focusing on addiction outside the submitted work. No other disclosures were reported.</p><p content-type="data-sharing-statement"><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> See <xref rid="note-ZOI241694-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>.</p></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2025-02-20T10:00"><day>20</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">482673</issue-id><elocation-id>e2460794</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>20</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>22</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-02-25 03:25:32.523"><day>25</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright 2025 Bologheanu R et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic>.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2460794.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2460794.pdf">jamanetwopen-e2460794.pdf</self-uri><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.60794"/><abstract abstract-type="key-points"><title>Key Points</title><sec id="ab-zoi241694-1"><title>Question</title><p>What is the incidence of new persistent opioid use after surgery, and what risk factors are associated with it?</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi241694-2"><title>Findings</title><p>In this population-based study of 559&#8201;096 Austrian adults undergoing 642&#8201;857 surgical procedures, the incidence of new persistent postoperative opioid use was 1.7%. Spinal surgery, advanced age, prolonged hospital stay, a history of substance use disorder, and previous opioid use that was discontinued before surgery were associated with new persistent opioid use.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi241694-3"><title>Meaning</title><p>These findings are consistent with existing literature but suggest the need for additional studies comparing pain management strategies and systemic and organizational factors that contribute to the development of new persistent opioid use after surgery.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" specific-use="electronic"><p>This cohort study examines the incidence of and factors associated with the risk of new persistent opioid use after surgery among adults in Austria.</p></abstract><abstract><sec id="ab-zoi241694-4"><title>Importance</title><p>New persistent opioid use after surgery is contributing to the opioid crisis affecting the US, and interventions to limit postoperative opioid prescriptions have been proposed to mitigate the opioid-related health care burden. Limited information is available regarding the incidence of new persistent use after surgery in other countries.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi241694-5"><title>Objective</title><p>To determine the incidence of new persistent opioid use and to evaluate factors associated with its risk after surgery in Austria.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi241694-6"><title>Design, Setting, and Participants</title><p>This retrospective, population-based cohort study used administrative data from the national Austrian social insurance database for adult patients undergoing surgery between January 1, 2016, and December 31, 2021. Exclusion criteria were incomplete exposure or outcome data, early postoperative death, and ongoing opioid use at the time of surgery. Data were analyzed from September 2023 to August 2024.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi241694-7"><title>Exposures</title><p>General, gynecological, urological, orthopedic, and cardiac surgery.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi241694-8"><title>Main Outcomes and Measures</title><p>The primary study outcome was the incidence of new persistent opioid use up to 6 months after surgery in the Austrian population; the factors associated with use, including patient factors and surgical procedures, were analyzed. A logistic regression model was used to evaluate the association between the primary outcome and the independent variables after controlling for multicollinearity.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi241694-9"><title>Results</title><p>Among 559&#8201;096 patients undergoing 642&#8201;857 surgical procedures (median [IQR] age, 60 [48-71] years; 318&#8201;391 male patients [49.5%]), new persistent opioid use was documented in 10&#8201;810 cases (1.7%) overall, and the rates ranged from 0.3% for appendectomy (130 cases per 40&#8201;565 procedures) to 0.7% for abdominal surgery (2198 cases per 335&#8201;034 procedures) to 6.8% for spinal surgery (3495 cases per 51&#8201;348 procedures). The median (IQR) daily opioid dose in oral morphine equivalents was 7.4 (4.1-14.9) mg. Specific procedures, including spinal surgery (odds ratio [OR], 5.36; 95% CI, 5.04-5.69) and arthroplasty (OR, 1.57; 95% CI, 1.48-1.67), and patient characteristics, such as previous opioid use that was discontinued before surgery (OR, 3.06; 95% CI, 2.93-3.19) and the frequency of previously filled opioid prescriptions (OR, 16.49; 95% CI, 13.63-19.95), were associated with new persistent opioid use.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi241694-10"><title>Conclusions and Relevance</title><p>In Austria, the incidence of new persistent opioid use after surgery is lower than that in North America, but the factors associated with risk are similar. These findings suggest the need for studies comparing pain management strategies, as well as systemic and organizational factors, that contribute to the development of new persistent opioid use after surgery in North American and European health care systems, where less evidence about new persistent opioid use has been available.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="H1-1-ZOI241694"><title>Introduction</title><p>In the context of the current opioid crisis, new persistent opioid use (NPOU) after surgery has emerged as a major concern owing to its possible progression to long-term use and misuse in patients initially prescribed opioids for postoperative analgesia.<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241694r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Although various definitions have been proposed, NPOU usually involves continued use of opioids for at least 3 to 6 months postoperatively, in contrast with the expected postoperative course where acute postoperative pain subsides as the patients recover from surgery.<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> NPOU is considered both a postoperative complication and a clinical phenomenon that accompanies perioperative care, and its incidence and underlying factors have been particularly well documented in the setting of North American health care.<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241694r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241694r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Although certain procedures are more frequently complicated by NPOU (eg, orthopedic surgery), even low-risk but common surgical procedures, such as abdominal wall hernia repair, can greatly contribute to postoperative opioid prescriptions.<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241694r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241694r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></p><p>NPOU has been recognized as a major contributor to the opioid epidemic, which is a public health emergency in the US, and the associated increase in health care costs, thus prompting reevaluation of postoperative pain management practices.<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241694r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241694r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> Currently, there are few data available on opioid prescribing practices and postoperative opioid use outside North America and UK, where most of the existing research has been conducted.<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241694r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241694r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241694r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> However, there is a strong rationale for investigating opioid prescriptions and NPOU in health care systems outside North America and UK with different insurance coverage, access to care, prescribing practices, regulatory and cultural issues, and patient management strategies.<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241694r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> Upstream measures aimed at limiting the opioid supply, particularly postoperative opioid prescriptions, are considered key interventions to minimize the risk of long-term opioid use.<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> Therefore, understanding postoperative NPOU in health care systems where these limitations are already in effect is crucial for improving patient outcomes and preventing opioid-related complications following surgical procedures. Addressing this gap in the literature could help differentiate between systemic and clinical factors, potentially leading to more tailored interventions and policies for preventing postsurgical opioid misuse and may suggest improvements applicable both within and across health care systems. The aims of this nationwide cohort study were to determine the incidence of NPOU after surgery and to evaluate clinical factors associated with the risk of NPOU after surgery in the Austrian health care system.</p></sec><sec id="H1-2-ZOI241694"><title>Methods</title><sec id="H2-1-ZOI241694"><title>Study Design</title><p>This retrospective cohort study used administrative data collected by the Umbrella Organization of Austrian Social Security Institutions (Vienna, Austria), which is the public health insurance providing health care coverage for 98% of residents of Austria (8.6 to 8.8 million residents between 2016 and 2021). The health insurance database includes prescription fills from the outpatient sector for all drugs reimbursed by the insurance providers, including Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical Classification System and clinical data, such as demographics, hospital stay, discharge dates, along with <italic toggle="yes">International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems, Tenth Revision</italic> system&#8211;coded diagnoses. The Ethics Committee of the Medical University Vienna, Austria approved this study on April 18, 2023, and waived the requirement for informed consent because the data were deidentified, in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> The manuscript has been prepared in accordance with the Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/strobe/" ext-link-type="uri">STROBE</ext-link>) reporting guidelines.</p></sec><sec id="H2-2-ZOI241694"><title>Study Population and Data Collection</title><p>Patients undergoing surgery between January 1, 2016, and December 31, 2021, were identified on the basis of the billing codes for selected procedures. The procedures included in the study were abdominal wall hernia repair, appendectomy, cholecystectomy, colectomy, mastectomy and other breast surgery, prostatectomy, thyroidectomy, laryngeal surgery and other head and neck procedures, hysterectomy, spine surgery, coronary artery bypass graft, and knee and hip arthroplasty. Patients who filled an opioid prescription within 3 months before admission, as well as patient records with incomplete outcome or exposure data, were excluded from the study. Accordingly, patients who underwent surgery in the first 3 months in 2016 or the last 3 months of 2021, patients who underwent surgery between July and September 2021 and filled at least 1 opioid prescription in the first 3 months after surgery, and patients who died within 90 days after surgery were excluded.</p><p>Patient characteristics (eg, age, sex, residential area, primary diagnoses, surgical procedures, admission and discharge dates, and perioperative analgesic prescriptions, including the date when opioid prescriptions were filled and the dose) were pseudonymized and collected. Opioid prescriptions were identified according to the Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical codes. All opioid medications were included regardless of the approved indication (ie, tramadol, fentanyl, morphine, buprenorphine, methadone and levomethadone, oxycodone, and dihydrocodeine).</p></sec><sec id="H2-3-ZOI241694"><title>Primary Outcome and Independent Variables</title><p>NPOU after surgery was the primary outcome of this study. We used the definition proposed by Clarke et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> where NPOU is considered to occur whenever at least 1 opioid prescription is filled within the first 90 days after surgery followed by at least 1 prescription filled within the days 90 to 180 after surgery. Explanatory variables included remote opioid use, defined as previous opioid use that was discontinued before surgery, derived from preoperative opioid prescriptions, both as a binary variable and further categorized by recency, mean prescribed opioid dose (oral morphine equivalents), and frequency of opioid prescriptions. We further included patient demographics, residential area, the surgical procedures, including the type of access (open vs laparoscopic) and the anatomical site, and the following associated conditions: chronic pain, psychiatric comorbidities (grouped as schizophrenia, mood disorders, substance use disorder, and neurotic disorders), diabetes, congestive heart failure, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, and malignant neoplasms.</p></sec><sec id="H2-4-ZOI241694"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Data were analyzed from September 2023 to August 2024. All analyses were conducted using the open-source data science and statistical packages pandas and statmodels for Python statistical software version 3.10.9 (Python Software Foundation). Patients were grouped according to prior opioid use, and descriptive statistics were calculated for all explanatory variables. The incidence of NPOU was computed, and a logistic regression model was used to evaluate the association between the primary outcome and the independent variables after controlling for multicollinearity. Age, the prescribed opioid dose, the frequency of opioid prescriptions, and the hospital length of stay (LOS) were normalized between 0 and 1. The reciprocal value of the time between surgery and the most recent opioid prescriptions (1 divided by the time interval) was normalized&#8212;that is, values closer to 1 represented more recent opioid prescriptions. Model selection was performed using Akaike information criterion.</p><p>To account for the different preoperative windows of observation and to evaluate their association with the completeness of clinical data, particularly in respect to remote opioid use and previous surgical procedures, sensitivity analyses were performed, first, by adding the preoperative observation time and the time elapsed since the previous surgery to the regression model and second, by fitting the regression model on the dataset overall and stratified by year. Odds ratios (ORs) and 95% CIs were calculated, and statistical significance was defined as a 95% CI that did not contain the null value of 1.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-3-ZOI241694"><title>Results</title><p>We identified 600&#8201;316 patients who underwent 694&#8201;951 surgical procedures between 2016 and 2021. After excluding 25&#8201;572 procedures with incomplete outcome data and 6908 patients who died within 90 days after surgery, as well as 97&#8201;286 procedures for patients taking opioids at the time of surgery or missing data on preoperative opioid use, 642&#8201;857 surgical procedures (median [IQR] age, 60 [48-71] years; 318&#8201;391 male patients [49.5%]) among 559&#8201;096 patients were analyzed. Characteristics of the study participants and procedure type by previous opioid use category are shown in <xref rid="zoi241694t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. In 47&#8201;711 cases (7.4%), at least 1 opioid prescription was filled postoperatively. NPOU after surgery was recorded after 10&#8201;810 surgical procedures (1.7%) (<xref rid="zoi241694f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). NPOU incidence ranged from 0.3% for appendectomy (130 cases per 40&#8201;565 procedures) to 0.7% for abdominal surgery (2198 cases per 335&#8201;034 procedures) to 6.8% (3495 cases per 51&#8201;348 procedures) for spinal surgery (<xref rid="zoi241694t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The median (IQR) daily opioid dose in oral morphine equivalents was 7.4 (4.1-14.9) mg.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi241694t1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1. </label><caption><title>Surgical Procedures and Patient Characteristics</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="38.26%" span="1"/><col width="24.35%" span="1"/><col width="20%" span="1"/><col width="17.39%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th colspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Patients, No. (%)</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">No previous opioid use (n&#8201;=&#8201;576&#8201;941)<xref rid="zoi241694t1n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Remote opioid use (n&#8201;=&#8201;65&#8201;916)<xref rid="zoi241694t1n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (N&#8201;=&#8201;642&#8201;857)<xref rid="zoi241694t1n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, median (IQR), y</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (47-70)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (54-73)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (48-71)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">290&#8201;634 (50.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27&#8201;757 (42.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">318&#8201;391 (49.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286&#8201;307 (49.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38&#8201;159 (57.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">324&#8201;466 (50.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban area<xref rid="zoi241694t1n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176&#8201;835 (30.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#8201;614 (31.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197&#8201;449 (30.7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Substance use disorder</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13&#8201;051 (2.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3260 (4.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16&#8201;311 (2.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychiatric comorbidities</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mood disorders</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8201;943 (1.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4048 (6.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#8201;991 (2.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Schizophrenia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1316 (0.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190 (0.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1506 (0.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Neurotic, stress, and somatoform disorders</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5487 (0.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1658 (2.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7145 (1.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other comorbidities</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Chronic pain</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71&#8201;206 (12.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#8201;339 (38.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96&#8201;545 (15)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diabetes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26&#8201;405 (4.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7076 (10.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33&#8201;481 (5.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Congestive heart failure</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8006 (1.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2291 (3.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8201;297 (1.6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#8201;570 (2.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4532 (6.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19&#8201;102 (2.9)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Malignant neoplasm</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80&#8201;735 (14)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#8201;464 (17.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92&#8201;199 (14.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Procedure type</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Abdominal surgery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">313&#8201;099 (54.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#8201;935 (33.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">335&#8201;034 (52.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cardiac surgery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#8201;256 (2.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1279 (1.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8201;535 (2.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Head and neck surgery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55&#8201;025 (9.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4210 (6.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59&#8201;235 (9.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Spine surgery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#8201;680 (6.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#8201;668 (17.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51&#8201;348 (7.9)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Breast surgery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8201;906 (2.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1144 (1.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16&#8201;971 (2.6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Arthroplasty</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138&#8201;975 (24.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#8201;759 (39)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">164&#8201;734 (25.6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Open approach</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">452&#8201;461 (78.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57&#8201;046 (86.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">509&#8201;507 (79.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital length of stay, median (IQR), d</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (3-9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (4-11)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (3-9)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="zoi241694t1n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>During the study period, 49&#8201;706 patients underwent 2 surgical procedures, and 7776 patients underwent 3 or more surgical procedures.</p></fn><fn id="zoi241694t1n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>During the study period, 6728 patients underwent 2 surgical procedures, and 1255 patients underwent 3 or more surgical procedures.</p></fn><fn id="zoi241694t1n3"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>During the study period, 60&#8201;192 patients underwent 2 surgical procedures, and 10&#8201;389 patients underwent 3 or more surgical procedures.</p></fn><fn id="zoi241694t1n4"><label>
<sup>d</sup>
</label><p>There were 1570 patients with missing values.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="zoi241694f1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1. </label><caption><title>Patient Enrollment Flowchart</title><p>Adults undergoing abdominal wall hernia repair, appendectomy, cholecystectomy, colectomy, mastectomy and other breast surgery, prostatectomy, thyroidectomy, laryngeal surgery and other head and neck procedures, hysterectomy, spine surgery, coronary artery bypass graft, and knee and hip arthroplasty were screened to be included in this study.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2460794-g001.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi241694t2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2. </label><caption><title>Incidence of New Persistent Opioid Use After Surgery</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="41.74%" span="1"/><col width="13.91%" span="1"/><col width="17.39%" span="1"/><col width="26.96%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anatomical site and surgical procedure</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">New cases, No.</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total procedures, No.</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incidence, % (95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abdomen</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Abdominal wall hernia repair</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">579</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126&#8201;756</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 (0.42-0.50)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Appendectomy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#8201;565</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 (0.27-0.38)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cholecystectomy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">625</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84&#8201;452</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 (0.68-0.80)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Colectomy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">577</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26&#8201;570</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.17 (2.00-2.35)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hysterectomy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41&#8201;475</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 (0.48-0.62)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Prostatectomy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8201;216</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38 (0.29-0.49)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Breast surgery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">153</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16&#8201;971</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 (0.77-1.05)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Head and neck</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Laryngeal surgery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">742</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.71 (3.41-6.48)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Thyroidectomy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">146</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36&#8201;438</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 (0.34-0.47)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other procedures</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">502</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22&#8201;055</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.27 (2.08-2.48)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limb</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hip arthroplasty</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1499</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80&#8201;468</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86 (1.77-1.95)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Knee arthroplasty</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2503</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84&#8201;266</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97 (2.85-3.08)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spine</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Surgery of the spine</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3495</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51&#8201;348</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.80 (6.59-7.02)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Coronary artery bypass graft</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">279</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8201;535</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79 (1.59-2.01)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="H2-5-ZOI241694"><title>Factors Associated With Risk of NPOU</title><p>A total of 642&#8201;857 observations and 16 variables were included in the final regression model. NPOU after surgery was independently associated with several patient characteristics and surgical factors. The ORs for all explanatory variables included in the regression model are presented in <xref rid="zoi241694f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="zoi241694f2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2. </label><caption><title>Patient and Surgical Factors Associated With New Persistent Opioid Use</title><p>Figure shows results of multivariable regression analysis of new persistent opioid use after surgery. COPD indicates chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; and LOS, length of stay.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2460794-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>Remote opioid use was independently associated with the primary outcome (OR, 3.06; 95% CI, 2.93-3.19), as well as advanced patient age (OR, 2.78; 95% CI, 2.43-3.18) and a history of substance use disorder (OR, 1.46; 95% CI, 1.33-1.60). Surgical factors independently associated with the primary outcome included surgery of the spine (OR, 5.36; 95% CI, 5.04-5.69), the hospital LOS (OR, 12.87; 95% CI, 12.00-13.80), hip and knee arthroplasty (OR, 1.57; 95% CI, 1.48-1.67), and open approach surgery (OR, 1.64; 95% CI, 1.49-1.80). Of note, male patients (OR, 0.84; 95% CI, 0.81-0.88) and patients undergoing cardiac surgery (OR, 0.78; 95% CI 0.68-0.89) had lower odds of developing NPOU after surgery, although the effect sizes were small.</p></sec><sec id="H2-6-ZOI241694"><title>Remote Opioid Use Patterns and NPOU</title><p>Opioid use patterns were significantly associated with NPOU, the primary outcome of our study, whereas the prescribed opioid dose preoperatively did not have a significant association with the incidence of NPOU after surgery (eFigure 1 in <xref rid="note-ZOI241694-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). The frequency of preoperative opioid prescriptions was associated with much greater odds of NPOU (OR, 16.49; 95% CI, 13.63-19.95) compared with the time since the most recent preoperative opioid prescription (OR, 3.04; 95% CI 2.82-3.29).</p></sec><sec id="H2-7-ZOI241694"><title>Sensitivity Analysis</title><p>Sensitivity analyses confirmed the results of the initial regression model. Adding the length of the preoperative observation window as explanatory variable did not significantly alter the regression model. Stratified analyses by year yielded consistent results (eFigure 2 in <xref rid="note-ZOI241694-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). The incidence of NPOU ranged from 2.1% (1946 cases per 92&#8201;119 procedures) in 2016 to 1.1% (929 cases per 83&#8201;290 procedures) in 2021. Spinal surgery, arthroplasty, and breast surgery were consistently associated with NPOU across all strata, as well as increased patient age, longer hospital LOS, and history of opioid use and substance use disorders.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-4-ZOI241694"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this nationwide cohort study that included all patients covered by the Austrian public social insurance system undergoing various surgical procedures between 2016 and 2021, the incidence of NPOU after surgery was lower than that reported in North American studies.<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> The overall incidence was 1.7%, but interestingly, the incidence by procedure ranged from 0.3% for appendectomy to 6.8% for surgery of the spine. Unsurprisingly, the proportion of patients who filled an opioid prescription after surgery and the mean daily dose were also lower compared with the existing literature. These results are in line with available data on worldwide opioid prescriptions, which highlight striking differences between the number of prescriptions and the dose prescribed across different countries and regions, and a higher opioid consumption in North America compared with Europe.<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241694r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup></p><p>The dataset included procedures from both ends of the opioid use risk spectrum, but in all categories, the incidence of NPOU was lower than that reported in the US studies. For example, according to Brummett et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> the overall incidence of NPOU was estimated at 4.1% to 7.1%, depending on the payer types. Other studies<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241694r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> have found that after high-risk procedures, such as total hip or knee arthroplasty, as many as 1 in 5 patients develop NPOU. Although recent studies<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241694r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> suggest that prescribing patterns and patient factors might impact prolonged opioid use more than the type of surgery and postoperative pain, certain surgical procedures were found to be associated with increased risk of persistent opioid use in our study. Patients undergoing spine surgery, arthroplasty, and head and neck surgery were more likely to continue using opioids after discharge.</p><p>Certain comorbid conditions were also significantly associated with postoperative opioid use. In our cohort, chronic pain and psychiatric comorbidities, particularly mood disorders and substance use disorders, were consistently associated with NPOU after surgery. Our study adds to the body of literature documenting the complex interactions among cooccurring substance abuse, chronic pain, and mood disorders, whose underlying mechanisms cannot be determined from these data.<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241694r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> In patients with remote opioid use, the odds of NPOU after surgery were significantly higher, compared with opioid-naive patients. Agarwal et al<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> first described the effect of remote exposure in a secondary analysis of a prospective pain study with a relatively small sample size, but our investigation confirmed their results in a much larger cohort and found a larger effect size (OR, 3.06; 95% CI, 2.93-3.19). Furthermore, we were able to demonstrate that not only is remote opioid use associated with NPOU, but also the previous use patterns are significantly associated with opioid-related outcomes after surgery. The association of the prescriptions&#8217; frequency was greater than the association of their recency, whereas the prescribed dose was not associated with NPOU. These findings, which build on the report by Agarwal et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> could help stratify patients who have been previously exposed to opioids by the type of previous use to better estimate the risk of adverse opioid-related outcomes.</p><p>The main implication of our study is that NPOU is most likely determined by both systemic and clinical factors. Even in the context of a more restrictive opioid prescribing culture, NPOU is affecting opioid-naive patients, who are typically considered less challenging than opioid-tolerant patients with respect to postoperative analgesia. We were able to confirm that patients who are not taking opioids at the time of surgery but had a remote exposure to opioid analgesics have a higher risk of continued opioid use, and more frequent and more recent opioid use are the most significant aspects of remote previous opioid use as a factor associated with the risk of NPOU. Despite an overall low incidence of continued opioid use after surgery, previously described factors underlying NPOU had a similar association with postoperative opioid use in our cohort.<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> Our study suggests that a comparative evaluation of prescribing patterns and patient outcomes between different health care systems should be considered to further understand this clinical phenomenon affecting the postoperative course of many surgical patients. In turn, this will allow clinicians to better guide postoperative opioid prescribing and implement pain management strategies that do not increase the opioid-related health burden.</p><sec id="H2-8-ZOI241694"><title>Limitations</title><p>We acknowledge several limitations of our study. First, our study only includes administrative data. Including granular clinical data on postoperative pain management strategies, such as regional blocks and opioid-sparing strategies used, and pain scores would greatly improve the validity and interpretability of our results. Still, the size of the cohort and the broad spectrum of surgical procedures included support the generalizability of our findings regarding the factors associated with risk of NPOU. Second, we did not differentiate between inpatient and outpatient surgery and could not include data on in-hospital analgesia. The hospital LOS and in-hospital opioid use might play an important role. In-hospital opioid use is subject to tighter control by health care practitioners. Furthermore, organizational and cultural factors account for large differences in the hospital LOS for similar procedures in different countries.<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241694r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Although it was associated with the primary outcome in our cohort, the hospital LOS might be a surrogate for complicated postoperative course. However, given the magnitude of this association, the role of outpatient surgery and the hospital LOS should be addressed in further research. Third, we included data on filled opioid prescriptions, which likely informs the primary outcome. However, the number of prescriptions that were not filled and the actual opioid use are not known. In the US, where the incidence of NPOU is high, up to 75% of all surgical patients will fill an opioid prescription postoperatively, but excess opioid prescribing and unused analgesics supply are common.<sup><xref rid="zoi241694r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241694r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi241694r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> On a similar note, in the absence of patient-reported opioid use, we could only include filled opioid prescriptions that were reimbursed in the dataset and could not account for postoperative illicit opioid use. Fourth, the preoperative observation period and the duration of the follow-up varied by the year of the surgery. The patients who underwent surgery earlier had a shorter preoperative observation window, but a longer follow-up, and vice versa. Although we excluded all patients with uncertain outcome data (ie, follow-up insufficiently long to determine NPOU), this limitation is relevant for the remote opioid use, where in some cases, only relatively recent opioid use (ie, not more than 6 years before surgery for the longest observation period) could be determined.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-5-ZOI241694"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In this Austrian nationwide cohort study of 559&#8201;096 patients undergoing 642&#8201;857 surgical procedures, the incidence of postoperative NPOU and the average opioid doses prescribed were low. Patients who were exposed to opioids remotely had a higher risk of developing NPOU, as well as patients with mood disorders and substance use disorder. Further studies should investigate the quality of postoperative analgesia, as well as prescription patterns and actual opioid use in the Austrian health care system, along with other system-related factors, such as hospital discharge practices to guide opioid prescribing and analgesic management. This research will help streamline current efforts to reduce the opioid-related burden after surgery.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="REF-ZOI241694"><title>References</title><ref id="zoi241694r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mamdani</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Juurlink</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term analgesic use after low-risk surgery: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>172</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>425</fpage>-<lpage>430</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinternmed.2011.1827</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22412106</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brummett</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Waljee</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goesling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>New persistent opioid use after minor and major surgical procedures in US adults</article-title>. <source>JAMA Surg</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>152</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<elocation-id>e170504</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2017.0504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28403427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7050825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jivraj</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Raghavji</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bethell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Persistent postoperative opioid use: a systematic literature search of definitions and population-based cohort study</article-title>. <source>Anesthesiology</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>132</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1528</fpage>-<lpage>1539</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ALN.0000000000003265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32243330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8202398</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bicket</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Waljee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>New persistent opioid use after surgery: a risk factor for opioid use disorder?</article-title><source>Ann Surg</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>275</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e288</fpage>-<lpage>e289</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SLA.0000000000005297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35007229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10416118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karamchandani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tollinche</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TNY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harbell</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>New persistent opioid use after surgery</article-title>. <source>ASA Monitor.</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>8</fpage>-<lpage>10</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.ASM.0001079092.00524.9c</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gunaseelan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brummett</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Waljee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Englesbe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Telem</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>New persistent opioid use after inguinal hernia repair</article-title>. <source>Ann Surg</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>276</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e577</fpage>-<lpage>e583</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SLA.0000000000004560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33065653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8289484</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tay</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Narayan</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Penm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Patanwala</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Persistent postoperative opioid use after total hip or knee arthroplasty: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Am J Health Syst Pharm</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>79</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>147</fpage>-<lpage>164</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ajhp/zxab367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34537828</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8513405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Urman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Coppes</surname><given-names>OJM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Reducing new persistent opioid use after surgery: a review of interventions</article-title>. <source>Curr Pain Headache Rep</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>27</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11916-021-00943-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33760983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7990836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brummett</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Evans-Shields</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>England</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Increased health care costs associated with new persistent opioid use after major surgery in opioid-naive patients</article-title>. <source>J Manag Care Spec Pharm</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>760</fpage>-<lpage>771</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18553/jmcp.2021.20507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33624534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8177715</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hofer</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harnik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Trajectories of pain and opioid use up to one year after surgery: analysis of a European registry</article-title>. <source>Br J Anaesth</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>132</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>588</fpage>-<lpage>598</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bja.2023.12.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38212183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nolan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Angelov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Geoghegan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Postoperative opioid prescribing patterns in Ireland: a retrospective multicentre analysis</article-title>. <source>Br J Anaesth</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>132</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>982</fpage>-<lpage>983</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bja.2024.02.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38538513</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Keto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heiskanen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hamunen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kalliom&#228;ki</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Linna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Opioid trends in Finland: a register-based nationwide follow-up study</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>7261</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-10788-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35508479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9068911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>AHY</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Incidence and risk factors of new persistent opioid use after surgery and trauma: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>BMC Surg</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>210</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12893-024-02494-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39014357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11251237</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Velo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moretti</surname><given-names>U</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Direct-to-consumer information in Europe: the blurred margin between promotion and information</article-title>. <source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>626</fpage>-<lpage>628</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2125.2008.03283.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19032171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2661977</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Keates</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>B&#252;hringer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reimer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rehm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Non-medical use of prescription opioids and prescription opioid-related harms: why so markedly higher in North America compared to the rest of the world?</article-title><source>Addiction</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>109</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>177</fpage>-<lpage>181</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/add.12224</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23692335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dowell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ragan</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>CDC clinical practice guideline for prescribing opioids for pain&#8212;United States, 2022</article-title>. <source>MMWR Recomm Rep</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>95</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.rr7103a1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36327391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9639433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><collab>World Medical Association</collab></person-group>. <article-title>World Medical Association Declaration of Helsinki: ethical principles for medical research involving human subjects.</article-title><source>JAMA</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>310</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>2191</fpage>-<lpage>2194</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2013.281053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24141714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soneji</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wijeysundera</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Rates and risk factors for prolonged opioid use after major surgery: population based cohort study</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>348</volume>:<fpage>g1251</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.g1251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24519537</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3921439</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ladha</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Broms</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Opioid prescribing after surgery in the United States, Canada, and Sweden</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<elocation-id>e1910734</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.10734</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31483475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6727684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hereford</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>A</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stambough</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cherney</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mears</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of chronic opioid use in the elderly after hip fracture surgery</article-title>. <source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>7S</issue>):<fpage>S530</fpage>-<lpage>S535</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2022.01.071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35219575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brescia</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Waljee</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of prescribing on new persistent opioid use after cardiothoracic surgery</article-title>. <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>108</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1107</fpage>-<lpage>1113</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.athoracsur.2019.06.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31447051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6755048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Larach</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sahara</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>As-Sanie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Patient factors associated with opioid consumption in the month following major surgery</article-title>. <source>Ann Surg</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>273</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>507</fpage>-<lpage>515</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SLA.0000000000003509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31389832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7068729</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Larach</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Waljee</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bicket</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brummett</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bruehl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Perioperative opioid prescribing and iatrogenic opioid use disorder and overdose: a state-of-the-art narrative review</article-title>. <source>Reg Anesth Pain Med</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>602</fpage>-<lpage>608</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/rapm-2023-104944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37931982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11070448</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gunaseelan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>New persistent opioid use after surgery in patients with a history of remote opioid use</article-title>. <source>Surgery</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>171</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1635</fpage>-<lpage>1641</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.surg.2021.11.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34895768</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dijkink</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>van der Wilden</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Krijnen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Polytrauma patients in the Netherlands and the USA: a bi-institutional comparison of processes and outcomes of care</article-title>. <source>Injury</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>104</fpage>-<lpage>109</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.injury.2017.10.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29033079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Golinelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sanmarchi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Toscano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bucci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nante</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Analyzing the 20-year declining trend of hospital length-of-stay in European countries with different healthcare systems and reimbursement models</article-title>. <source>Int J Health Econ Manag</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>375</fpage>-<lpage>392</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10754-024-09369-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38512638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11457716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bicket</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pronovost</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Prescription opioid analgesics commonly unused after surgery: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>JAMA Surg</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>152</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1066</fpage>-<lpage>1071</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2017.0831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28768328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5701659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi241694r28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gunaseelan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of opioid prescribing with opioid consumption after surgery in Michigan</article-title>. <source>JAMA Surg</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>154</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<elocation-id>e184234</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2018.4234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30422239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6439853</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><notes notes-type="supplementary-material" id="note-ZOI241694-1"><supplementary-material id="note-ZOI241694-1-s" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplement 1.</label><caption><p><bold>eFigure 1.</bold> Multivariable regression analysis of new persistent opioid use after surgery with patterns of previous opioid use as explanatory variables</p><p><bold>eFigure 2.</bold> Multivariable regression analysis of new persistent opioid use after surgery: odds ratios by year</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2460794-s001.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplement 2.</label><caption><p>
Data Sharing Statement
</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2460794-s002.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></notes></back></article></pmc-articleset>