<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Behav Health Serv Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Behav Health Serv Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">365</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">springeropen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Behavioral Health Services &amp; Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1094-3412</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1556-3308</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Springer</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12174264</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12174264.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12174264</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12174264</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40128470</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11414-025-09942-6</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9942</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Primary Care Visit Frequency Is Associated With Diagnosis But Not Pharmacotherapy Prescribing for Patients With Alcohol Use Disorder</article-title><subtitle>AUD Pharmacotherapy Prescribing in Primary Care</subtitle></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1895-2715</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names initials="RA">Ruth A</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MBA</degrees><address><email>bishopru@musc.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names initials="R">Ralph</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schreiner</surname><given-names initials="A">Andrew</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MSCR</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCauley</surname><given-names initials="JL">Jenna L</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moran</surname><given-names initials="WP">William P</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname><given-names initials="S">Sarah</given-names></name><degrees>PharmD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/012jban78</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.259828.c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2189 3475</institution-id><institution>Department of Internal Medicine, </institution><institution>Medical University of South Carolina, </institution></institution-wrap>Charleston, SC USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/012jban78</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.259828.c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2189 3475</institution-id><institution>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, </institution><institution>Medical University of South Carolina, </institution></institution-wrap>Charleston, SC USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/012jban78</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.259828.c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2189 3475</institution-id><institution>Department of Public Health Sciences, </institution><institution>Medical University of South Carolina, </institution></institution-wrap>Charleston, SC USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>52</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">490973</issue-id><fpage>542</fpage><lpage>552</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>24</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>19</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-06-19 00:25:15.143"><day>19</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="11414_2025_Article_9942.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Primary care has been proposed as an ideal setting for the management of alcohol use disorder (AUD); however, there is limited research on the diagnosis and prescribing patterns of medications for alcohol use disorder (MAUD) within primary care. This retrospective study aims to determine whether primary care engagement is associated with the likelihood of an AUD diagnosis or prescription of MAUD. Analyzing administrative claims data from a statewide cohort of 10,138 Medicaid enrollees, only 5.9% of patients diagnosed with AUD were prescribed MAUD (including naltrexone, acamprosate, disulfiram, and topiramate). Patients with higher levels of primary care visit frequency were significantly more likely to carry an AUD diagnosis (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001); however, primary care visit frequency was not associated with prescription of MAUD. This study highlights the underutilization of MAUD within primary care, and the need for research identifying successful strategies to address barriers to prescribing MAUD in this setting.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords
</title><kwd>Alcohol use disorder</kwd><kwd>AUD</kwd><kwd>Medication for alcohol use disorder</kwd><kwd>MAUD</kwd><kwd>Medicaid</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Medical University of South Carolina</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open access funding provided by the Carolinas Consortium.</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; National Council for Mental Wellbeing 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Alcohol use disorder (AUD) is the most common substance use disorder in the United States, resulting in significant morbidity and mortality. In 2022, it was estimated that 11.2% of US adults over the age of 18 met criteria for AUD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>&#160;The economic costs of excessive alcohol use in the USA in 2019 were estimated to be $249 billion (about $770 per person in the USA) due to lost work productivity, motor vehicle crashes, criminal justice involvement, and healthcare expenses.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>&#160;It is estimated that over 140,000 people in the USA die annually from alcohol-related causes (annual average from 2014 to 2019), making it the fourth-leading preventable cause of death following tobacco use, unhealthy diet and insufficient exercise, and illicit substance use.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup></p><p id="Par3">FDA-approved pharmacotherapies for AUD include naltrexone, disulfiram, and acamprosate. Other non-FDA approved drugs including topiramate, gabapentin, and baclofen are also commonly used as medications for alcohol use disorder (MAUD).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup> These therapies have been shown to be effective in reducing heavy consumption and achieving sobriety<sup>7</sup> and are considered standards of care by many guidelines.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>&#160;Despite their availability and effectiveness, prescribing rates of pharmacotherapies for AUD remain low and present an area of both research and policy interest.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> Studies estimate that MAUD prescribing is quite low; only 2.1 to 9% of patients needing treatment for AUD received a prescription of one of the FDA-approved medications, which has also been found to be the case in primary care settings.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup></p><p id="Par4">Primary care has been proposed as an ideal setting for at-risk alcohol screening and prescription of MAUD given the longitudinal relationships developed between clinicians and patients and limited access to addiction specialists. Primary care may also be an ideal setting for perioperative screening of AUD given that excessive alcohol use is a risk factor for postoperative complications,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> and surgical patients are rarely offered alcohol screening or intervention referrals prior to surgery.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup></p><p id="Par5">Current literature suggests that physicians, including primary care physicians (PCPs), under-prescribe MAUD as it is estimated that only 1.9&#8211;5% of patients needing treatment for AUD received a prescription.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> This low prescribing rate is in spite of reimbursement for alcohol screening and treatment by Medicare and Medicaid, and several guidelines, such as the US Preventative Task Force, recommending evaluation and management of AUD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> Further research is needed to provide estimates of primary care prescribing rates of these medications and barriers limiting their prescription.</p><p id="Par6">This study examined the prevalence of AUD diagnoses in Medicaid claims among a South Carolina cohort. This study&#8217;s primary objectives were to identify whether patients with more frequent primary care visits were more likely to be diagnosed with AUD or receive pharmacotherapies for the treatment of AUD, while controlling for factors such as patient&#8217;s age, race/ethnicity, sex, and presence of opioid use disorder.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par7">This was a retrospective study involving a South Carolina Medicaid surgerical cohort originally formed as part of a parent study that examined post-surgical opioid trajectories.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> A surgical cohort was used to answer this question because of the robust nature of the dataset and the assumption that preoperative alcohol consumption is associated with postoperative complications, and thus, alcohol use in perioperative care would be more likely addressed in this sample than in the general population.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> Patients were included if they were insured by Medicaid and underwent a surgical procedure between January 1, 2014, and December 31, 2017. Each patient&#8217;s index time was set at 6&#160;months prior to the earliest surgery within this period, and each was followed through the remaining study timeframe. Surgeries were identified by International Classification of Diseases (ICD)&#8722;9/10-PCS procedure codes or Healthcare Common Procedure Coding System (HCPCS) codes and included procedures for appendectomy, cholecystectomy, colorectal surgery, lumbar spine surgery, total knee replacement, and tonsillectomy. Patients were excluded if (i) they were&#8201;&lt;&#8201;13&#160;years of age at the time of the surgical procedure, (ii) had an interruption in Medicaid eligibility during the period 6&#160;months prior until 9&#160;months after surgery, (iii) had no pharmacy claims during the same period, (iv) had any diagnosis code involving sickle cell disease or cancer, or (v) had a second surgery or hospitalization between 1 and 9&#160;months after their index surgery. Data were provided by the South Carolina Revenue and Fiscal Affairs Office and included Medicaid claims and associated Medicaid pharmacy and Medicare part-D claims. The Institutional Review Board at the author&#8217;s institution (IRB study #Pro00129391) approved this study.</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Outcomes</title><p id="Par8">Primary outcomes were receipt of an AUD diagnosis and prescription of MAUD during the study period. AUD diagnoses were identified from claims with a primary, secondary, or admitting diagnosis code contained in the ICD-9-CM or ICD-10-CM Elixhauser definitions for alcohol abuse as updated by Quan et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup> MAUD was identified based on one or more pharmacy claims for an FDA-approved medication for AUD treatment, which included formulations of acamprosate, disulfiram, and naltrexone.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> Topiramate use was considered an active AUD treatment when it occurred within 90&#160;days following an AUD diagnosis in patients without concurrent FDA-approved AUD treatment medications. Other pharmacotherapy options for AUD such as gabapentin and baclofen were not included given their frequent use for non-AUD conditions (e.g., migraine headache, neuropathic pain).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Exposure</title><p id="Par9">The primary exposure was primary care visit frequency, based on the number of visits with a primary care-designated clinician. Exposure level was a five-level categorical variable based on quartiles of annual primary care visits: none (no visits), low (0&#8211;25th percentiles;&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;3.9 visits/year), medium (26th&#8211;50th percentiles; 3.9&#8211;6.5 visits/year), high (51st&#8211;75th percentiles; 6.5&#8211;10.4 visits/year), and highest (76th&#8211;100th percentiles;&#8201;&gt;&#8201;10.4 visits/year). Primary care providers were identified when either the primary or secondary Medicaid provider specialty description was consistent with primary care, e.g., &#8220;family practice.&#8221; A full listing of primary care descriptions is included in the supplementary information section.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Covariates</title><p id="Par10">Demographic covariates included age (&lt;&#8201;18, 18&#8211;31, 32&#8211;48, 49&#8211;65, and&#8201;&gt;&#8201;65&#160;years), sex (female, male), and race/ethnicity (non-Hispanic Black, Hispanic, non-Hispanic White, Other/Unknown). Clinical variables included whether an AUD diagnosis or a MAUD claim could be linked to a primary care visit. Diagnosis linkage required the same visit claim to include a PCP and an AUD diagnosis code. MAUD linkage required a pharmacy claim within 90&#160;days following the visit claim. Given the original intent of the dataset, this study also included categorical variables for surgery type (appendectomy, cholecystectomy, colorectal surgery, lumbar spine surgery, total knee replacement, and tonsillectomy), diagnosis of opioid use disorder (Yes, No), and chronic use of opioid pharmacotherapies prior to and after surgery (Yes, No; defined as at least one opioid prescription filled during (1) the 180&#160;days prior and (2)&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;90 to 270&#160;days following the surgical procedure).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Statistical Analyses</title><p id="Par11">Summary statistics and univariate analyses were used to describe associations between AUD diagnosis and primary care visit frequency, receipt of MAUD, and other covariates using chi-square or Fisher&#8217;s exact tests, as appropriate. Multivariable logistic models were developed for (1) the AUD diagnosis outcome using the full cohort and (2) the prescription of MAUD outcome using a population limited to patients with an AUD diagnosis. The exposure in both models was primary care visit frequency; both models were adjusted for the covariates described above. Models were checked for multicollinearity using the variance inflation factor. SAS 9.4 was used for all statistical analyses (SAS Institute, Inc., Cary, NC).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Results</title><p id="Par12">The study cohort included 10,138 unique patients of whom 30% were age 18&#8211;31&#160;years, 78% were female, and 52% were non-Hispanic White (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Patients attended 197,801 primary care visits during the study period and were followed for a median of 2.8&#160;years (interquartile range (IQR): 1.5, 3.6). The median number of primary care visits per year for the study cohort was 6.2 (IQR: 3.5, 10.1). In total, 512 (5.1%) patients received a diagnosis for AUD, of which 227 (44.3%) received this diagnosis during a primary care visit. Of those with a diagnosis of AUD, 30 (5.9%) had a pharmacy claim for MAUD. Six (1.2%) of these patients were prescribed naltrexone, three (0.6%) acamprosate, three (0.6%) disulfiram, and 18 (3.5%) topiramate.
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the South Carolina Medicaid surgical cohort</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AUD</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No AUD</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Group size</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">512 (5.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9626 (95%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,138</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AUD medications prescribed?*</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Naltrexone</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (1.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (0.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (0.2%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Acamprosate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.03%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Disulfiram</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.03%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Topiramate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (3.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (0.2%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AUD diagnosis linked to PCP visit?</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">227 (44.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">227 (2.2%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AUD medications linked to AUD Dx visit?</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (4.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (0.2%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Primary care visit frequency**</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">None</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (1.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">494 (5.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">503 (5.0%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89 (17.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2388 (24.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2477 (24.4%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medium</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">131 (25.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2213 (23%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2344 (23.1%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">128 (25%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2303 (23.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2431 (24.0%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Highest</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">155 (30.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2228 (23.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2383 (23.5%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">310 (60.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7616 (79.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7926 (78.2%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">202 (39.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2010 (20.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2212 (21.8%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age group (in years)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (5.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1909 (19.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1938 (19.1%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18&#8211;31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">131 (25.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2908 (30.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3039 (30.0%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32&#8211;48</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">142 (27.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2402 (25%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2544 (25.1%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49&#8211;64</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">192 (37.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1748 (18.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1940 (19.1%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&gt;&#8201;&#8201;=&#8201;65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (3.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">659 (6.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">677 (6.7%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race/ethnicity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Black</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">144 (28.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3299 (34.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3443 (40.0%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hispanic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (1.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">315 (3.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">321 (3.2%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other/Unknown</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 (17.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1047 (10.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1135 (11.2%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">White</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">274 (53.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4965 (51.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5239 (51.7%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chronic opioid use pre- and post-surgery</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">228 (44.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2731 (28.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2959 (29.2%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OUD diagnosis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (6.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">163 (1.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">197 (1.9%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Surgery type</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Appendectomy</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64 (12.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1335 (13.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1399 (13.8%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cholecystectomy</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">254 (49.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4661 (48.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4915 (48.5%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Colon</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (4.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">154 (1.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">176 (1.7%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lumbar spine</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72 (14.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1060 (11%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1132 (11.2%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total knee replacement</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78 (15.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1208 (12.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1286 (12.7%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tonsillectomy</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (4.3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1208 (12.5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1230 (12.1%)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Naltrexone, acamprosate, or disulfiram at any point, or topiramate within 90&#160;days following AUD diagnosis<sup>**</sup>Primary care visit frequency: low&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;3.9 visits/year; medium&#8201;&gt;&#8201;3.9 and&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;6.5 visit/year; high&#8201;&gt;&#8201;6.5 and&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;10.4 visits/year; highest&#8201;&gt;&#8201;10.4 visits/year</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par13">Patients with higher levels of primary care visit frequency were significantly more likely to be diagnosed with AUD (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001). Men were more likely to receive an AUD diagnosis compared to women (9.3% vs. 3.9%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001). Those with an AUD diagnosis were more likely to be chronic opioid users before and after surgery (44.5% vs. 28.4% for non-AUD patients, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001) and were more likely to carry an opioid use disorder diagnosis (6.6% vs. 1.7%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001). Patient age, race and ethnicity, and surgery also differed by AUD diagnosis group.</p><p id="Par14">In the multivariable logistic regression model for receipt of an AUD diagnosis, patients in the medium (&gt;&#8201;3.9 and&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;6.5 visits/year), high (&gt;&#8201;6.5 and&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;10.4 visits/year), and highest (&gt;&#8201;10.4 visits/year) quartiles of primary care visit frequency all had more than twice the odds for having an AUD diagnosis compared to those with no primary care visits: (adjusted odds ratio (AOR): 2.55, 95% confidence interval (CI): 1.26, 5.17; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.009 for highest frequency level) (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Female patients had 65% lower odds for an AUD diagnosis compared to men (AOR 0.35; 95% CI 0.29&#8211;0.43; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001); however, they were significantly more likely to have pharmacy claims for MAUD if they carried an AUD diagnosis (AOR: 2.86; 95% CI 1.07, 7.67; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001). An OUD diagnosis was associated with substantially greater odds of an AUD diagnosis (AOR: 3.03; 95% CI 2.03, 4.51; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001). Primary care frequency was not associated with receipt of MAUD among patients with AUD.
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Logistic regression models for AUD diagnosis (Model 1) and fulfillment of a prescription for AUD pharmacotherapy among patients with an AUD diagnosis (Model 2)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 1</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 2</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">AUD diagnosis, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;10,138</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">MAUD prescription, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;512</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AOR (95% CI)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AOR (95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Primary care visit frequency***</p><p>ref&#8201;=&#8201;none</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.71 (0.84, 3.46)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.79</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.71 (0.06, 8.57)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medium</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.31 (1.14, 4.69)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.42</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.35 (0.03, 4.25)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.038</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.12 (1.04, 4.30)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.52</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.43 (0.03, 5.39)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Highest</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.009</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.55 (1.26, 5.17)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.45</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.38 (0.03, 4.66)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Race and ethnicity</p><p>ref&#8201;=&#8201;&#8220;White&#8221;</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-Hispanic White</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ref</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ref</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ref</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ref</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Black</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.38</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.91 (0.73, 1.13)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.52 (0.22, 1.20)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hispanic</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.52 (0.23, 1.18)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">*</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other/Unknown</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.054</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.29 (1.00, 1.68)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Age group</p><p>ref&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;18&#160;years</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 to 31&#160;years</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.87 (1.84, 4.47)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.65</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.64 (0.09, 4.51)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32 to 48&#160;years</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.18 (2.02, 4.98)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.52 (0.86, 23.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 to 64&#160;years</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.01 (3.15, 7.97)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.26 (0.21, 7.55)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65&#160;years or older</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.16</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.59 (0.83, 3.03)</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">**</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex (ref&#8201;=&#8201;male)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.35 (0.29, 0.43)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.037</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.86 (1.07, 7.67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Surgery type</p><p>ref&#8201;=&#8201;tonsillectomy</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Appendectomy</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.029</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.75 (1.06, 2.89)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.36</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.40 (0.05, 2.87)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cholecystectomy</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.051</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.60 (1.00, 2.55)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.46</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.52 (0.09, 2.93)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Colon</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.005</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.55 (1.32, 4.91)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.68</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.57 (0.04, 8.33)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lumbar spine</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.61</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.15 (0.68, 1.95)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.88</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.15 (0.17, 7.83)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total knee replacement</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.55</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.18 (0.69, 2.03)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.64</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.61 (0.08, 4.80)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chronic opioid use pre- and post-surgery</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes vs No</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.36 (1.11, 1.68)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.47</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.72 (0.29, 1.78)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Opioid use disorder</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes vs No</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.0001</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.03 (2.03, 4.51)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.68</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.72 (0.15, 3.42)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">CI</italic> confidence interval, <italic toggle="yes">AOR</italic> adjusted odds ratio*In model 2: Black, Hispanic, and Other groups combined to form minority groups due to smaller AUD population**In model 2: 65 and older group combined with 49 to 64 group***Primary care visit frequency: low&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;3.9 visits/year; medium&#8201;&gt;&#8201;3.9 and&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;6.5 visits/year; high&#8201;&gt;&#8201;6.5 and&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;10.4 visits/year; highest&#8201;&gt;&#8201;10.4 visits/year</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par15">In this study examining the relationship between primary care engagement and AUD diagnosis/MAUD prescribing, primary care engagement was associated with a higher probability of receiving an AUD diagnosis, but not pharmacotherapy, for AUD. The estimated prevalence of AUD in this cohort was 5.1%, slightly lower than the national prevalence of AUD estimated by SAMHSA&#8217;s National Survey on Drug Use and Health (NSDUH) during the study period 2014&#8211;2017, which ranged from 5.3 to 6.4%. Of those diagnosed with AUD, only 5.9% had an associated pharmacy claim for MAUD, suggesting that most patients with AUD do not receive guideline-based treatment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup></p><p id="Par16">Low rates of MAUD prescribing in this study are similar to other national and Veterans Health Administration studies both within and outside of primary care, suggesting broad underutilization of these medications in clinical practice at large.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup> This study replicates this finding within a Medicaid surgical cohort well-connected to primary care (median 6.2 primary care visits per year).</p><p id="Par17">While there is relatively limited literature describing the relationship between primary care visits and AUD diagnosis, several pre-existing studies suggest a similar relationship in that overall, AUD screening in primary care is low, but increased engagement with primary care is associated with an increased likelihood of AUD diagnosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> A cross-sectional analysis of the National Ambulatory Medical Care Survey data collected from 2014 to 2016 demonstrated that alcohol screening occurred during 2.6% of visits and counseling was documented in just 0.8% of visits. Despite these low rates of screening and treatment intervention, this study showed that screening was more likely if the patient was seen by their assigned primary care physician.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup></p><p id="Par18">Studies examining the relationship between primary care engagement and MAUD prescribing are also limited and demonstrate mixed results. One retrospective cohort study among primary care patients from a large, urban academic medical center demonstrated that patients engaged with primary care had a slightly higher probability of being prescribed MAUD compared to patients with limited primary care engagement (2.89% versus 2.56%).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> However, other studies have shown negative correlations between MAUD prescribing and primary care as well as large variations in individual primary care physician&#8217;s prescription rates, suggesting that a small number of providers are responsible for the majority of MAUD prescriptions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup></p><p id="Par19">Barriers to MAUD prescribing at the primary care provider level described in the literature include providers&#8217; lack of education on MAUD, provider&#8217;s negative beliefs about medication effectiveness or perceived poor patient adherence, and competing demands within primary care that make prescribing MAUD a lower priority.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup> This study highlights the need for evidence-based strategies to improve MAUD prescribing in primary care.</p><p id="Par20">This study has several limitations. This is a surgical, Medicaid cohort study; as Medicaid eligibility varies by state, study findings may not be generalizable to other states&#8217; Medicaid populations, to non-Medicaid populations, or to non-surgical populations. Additionally, it is possible that current AUD diagnosis and MAUD prescribing practices differ from 2014 to 2017, when this data was collected. Another limitation is this study examined prescriptions for MAUD but did not capture data on ambulatory screening or other types of treatment such as behavioral interventions. This study also did not capture treatment outcomes, adherence, or duration of treatment and excluded other medications that may have been prescribed for AUD including baclofen or gabapentin. Lastly, it is possible that not all patients with AUD or prescriptions for MAUD were captured within the cohort given that ICD-9/10 codes can have limited sensitivity for detecting clinical conditions in administrative data.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Implications for Behavioral Health</title><p id="Par21">The findings of this study indicate that a significant number of patients with AUD do not receive evidence-based pharmacotherapy treatments. Patients who saw their primary care provider more frequently were more likely to be diagnosed with AUD, suggesting that PCPs routinely identify AUD. However, the study revealed no positive correlation between the frequency of primary care visits and the prescription of medications for alcohol use disorder (MAUD), indicating that PCPs often fail to offer pharmacological treatment even when AUD is diagnosed.</p><p id="Par22">The underutilization of MAUD in primary care specialties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> underscores the need for future research to explore the barriers PCPs face when prescribing MAUD as well as implementation strategies to overcome these challenges. Future research should also aim to identify characteristics of patients that would make them the most appropriate candidates for MAUD. Given the increase in prevalence of AUD seen in the post-COVID era,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> these studies are needed now more than ever, offering a promising opportunity to improve outcomes for this common, costly, and devastating disease.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contribution</title><p>All contributors to this work appear in the author byline. All named authors contributed to the study design, data interpretation, manuscript editing, and submission decision. Dr. Bishop, Dr. Ward, Dr. Ball, Dr. McCauley, Dr. Moran, and Dr. Schreiner contributed to the writing and editing of the original draft. Dr. Ward developed the analysis plan and performed the analyses.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by the Carolinas Consortium. Data used in this project received funding through contracts (A201912450A and A202512450A) with the South Carolina Department of Health and Human Services (SCDHHS) for Drug Utilization Review services.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are not openly available due to reasons of sensitivity but are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request. Data are located in controlled access data storage at the Medical University of South Carolina.&#160;</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p id="Par23">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Disclaimer</title><p id="Par24">SCDHHS had no role in the preparation, approval, or decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References
</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><italic toggle="yes">Key Substance Use and Mental Health Indicators in the United States: Results from the 2022 National Survey on Drug Use and Health.</italic> Rockville, MD: Center for Behavioral Health Statistics and Quality, 2023. Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.samhsa.gov/data/release/2022-national-survey-drug-use-and-health-nsduh-releases">https://www.samhsa.gov/data/release/2022-national-survey-drug-use-and-health-nsduh-releases</ext-link>. Accessed 1 February, 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><italic toggle="yes">Excessive Drinking is Draining the U.S. Economy</italic>. Atlanta, GA: Centers for Disease Control, 2022. Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/alcohol/features/excessive-drinking.html">https://www.cdc.gov/alcohol/features/excessive-drinking.html</ext-link>. Accessed 20 August, 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sacks JJ, Gonzales KR, Bouchery EE, et al. 2010 national and state costs of excessive alcohol consumption. <italic toggle="yes">American Journal of Preventive Medicine</italic> 2015; 49(5):73&#8211;79. Available at 10.1016/j.amepre.2015.05.031. Accessed 20 August, 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amepre.2015.05.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26477807</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><italic toggle="yes">Alcohol Related Disease Impact (ARDI) Application</italic>. Atlanta, GA: Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 2024. Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nccd.cdc.gov/DPH_ARDI/default/default.aspx">https://nccd.cdc.gov/DPH_ARDI/default/default.aspx</ext-link>. Accessed 20 August, 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><italic toggle="yes">Alcohol-Related Emergencies and Deaths in the United States</italic>. Bethesda, MD: National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism, 2024. Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.niaaa.nih.gov/alcohols-effects-health/alcohol-topics/alcohol-facts-and-statistics/alcohol-related-emergencies-and-deaths-united-states">https://www.niaaa.nih.gov/alcohols-effects-health/alcohol-topics/alcohol-facts-and-statistics/alcohol-related-emergencies-and-deaths-united-states</ext-link>. Accessed 7 October, 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fairbanks J, Umbreit A, Kolla BP, et al. Evidence-based pharmacotherapies for alcohol use disorder. <italic toggle="yes">Mayo Clinic Proceedings</italic> 2020; 95(9):1964&#8211;1977. Available at 10.1016/j.mayocp.2020.01.030. Accessed 10 August, 2024.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.mayocp.2020.01.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32446635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">McPheeters M, O&#8217;Connor EA, Riley S, et al. Pharmacotherapy for alcohol use disorder: A systematic review and meta-analysis. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic> 2023; 330(17):1653&#8211;1665. Available at 10.1001/jama.2023.19761. Accessed 10 August, 2024.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2023.19761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10630900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37934220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Reus VI, Fochtmann LJ, Bukstein O, et al. The American Psychiatric Association practice guideline for the pharmacological treatment of patients with alcohol use disorder. <italic toggle="yes">American Journal of Psychiatry</italic> 2018; 175(1):86&#8211;90. Available at 10.1176/appi.ajp.2017.1750101. Accessed 10 August, 2024.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1176/appi.ajp.2017.1750101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29301420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of Alcohol Use Disorder</italic>. Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins University, 2020. Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK561234/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK561234/</ext-link>. Accessed 20 January, 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rittenberg A, Hines AL, Alvanzo AA, et al. Correlates of alcohol use disorder pharmacotherapy receipt in medically insured patients. <italic toggle="yes">Drug and Alcohol Dependence</italic> 2020; 214:108174. Available at 10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.108174. Accessed 20 January, 2024.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.108174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8011546</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32721788</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Harris AHS, Oliva E, Bowe T, et al. Pharmacotherapy of alcohol use disorders by the Veterans Health Administration: Patterns of receipt and persistence. <italic toggle="yes">Psychiatric Services</italic> 2012; 63(7):679&#8211;685. Available at 10.1176/appi.ps.201000553. Accessed 20 January, 2024.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1176/appi.ps.201000553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22549276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Carpenter JE, LaPrad D, Dayo Y, et al. An overview of pharmacotherapy options for alcohol use disorder. <italic toggle="yes">Federal Practitioner</italic> 2018; 35(10):48&#8211;58. Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6248154">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6248154</ext-link>. Accessed 20 January, 2024.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6248154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30766325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mark TL, Kassed CA, Vandivort-Warren R, et al. Alcohol and opioid dependence medications: Prescription trends, overall and by physician specialty. <italic toggle="yes">Drug and Alcohol Dependence</italic> 2009; 99(1):345&#8211;349. Available at 10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2008.07.018. Accessed 20 January, 2024.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2008.07.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3166770</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18819759</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Del Re AC, Gordon AJ, Lembke A, et al. Prescription of topiramate to treat alcohol use disorders in the Veterans Health Administration. <italic toggle="yes">Addiction Science and Clinical Practice</italic> 2013; 8(1):12. Available at 10.1186/1940-0640-8-12. Accessed 20 January, 2024.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1940-0640-8-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3716908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23835352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Joudrey PJ, Kladney M, Cunningham CO, et al. Primary care engagement is associated with increased pharmacotherapy prescribing for alcohol use disorder (AUD). <italic toggle="yes">Addiction Science and Clinical Practice</italic> 2019; 14(1):19. Available at 10.1186/s13722-019-0147-3. Accessed 20 January, 2024.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13722-019-0147-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6492411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31039820</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rubinsky AD, Bishop MJ, Maynard C, et al. Postoperative risks associated with alcohol screening depend on documented drinking at the time of surgery. <italic toggle="yes">Drug and Alcohol Dependence</italic> 2013; 132(3):521&#8211;527. Available at 10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2013.03.022. Accessed 20 January, 2024.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2013.03.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23683792</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bradley KA, Rubinsky AD, Sun H, et al. Prevalence of alcohol misuse among men and women undergoing major noncardiac surgery in the Veterans Affairs health care system. <italic toggle="yes">Surgery</italic> 2012; 152(1):69&#8211;81. Available at 10.1016/j.surg.2012.02.007. Accessed 20 January, 2024.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.surg.2012.02.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22503319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Aarvold A, Crofts T. Missed opportunities? Management of patients with alcohol problems in a surgical ward. <italic toggle="yes">Health Bulletin (Edinburgh)</italic> 2002; 60(1):55&#8211;61. Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/12664770">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/12664770</ext-link>. Accessed 20 January, 2024.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12664770</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">T&#248;nnesen H, Faurschou P, Ralov H, et al. Risk reduction before surgery: The role of the primary care provider in preoperative smoking and alcohol cessation. <italic toggle="yes">BMC Health Services Research</italic> 2010; 10(1):121. Available at 10.1186/1472-6963-10-121. Accessed 20 January, 2024.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1472-6963-10-121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2882918</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20462417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bernstein E, Guo N, Goto T, et al. Characterizing the variation of alcohol cessation pharmacotherapy in primary care. <italic toggle="yes">Journal of General Internal Medicine</italic> 2021; 36(7):1989&#8211;1996. Available at 10.1007/s11606-020-06454-1. Accessed 20 January, 2024.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-020-06454-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8298666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33515195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chockalingam L, Burnham EL, Jolley SE. Medication prescribing for alcohol use disorders during alcohol-related encounters in a Colorado regional healthcare system. <italic toggle="yes">Alcohol, Clinical and Experimental Research</italic> 2022; 46(6):1094&#8211;1102. Available at 10.1111/acer.14837. Accessed 20 January, 2024.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/acer.14837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9246874</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35723682</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bernstein EY, Pfoh ER, Le P, et al. Relationship between primary care providers&#8217; perceptions of alcohol use disorder and pharmacotherapy prescribing rates. <italic toggle="yes">Alcohol and Alcoholism</italic> 2023; 58(1):54&#8211;59. Available at 10.1093/alcalc/agac057. Accessed 20 August, 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/alcalc/agac057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36368012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><italic toggle="yes">Screening and Behavioral Counseling Interventions in Primary Care to Reduce Alcohol Misuse.</italic> Baltimore, MD: Center for Medicare and Medicaid Services, 2011. Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cms.gov/medicare-coverage-database/view/ncd.aspx?NCDId=347">https://www.cms.gov/medicare-coverage-database/view/ncd.aspx?NCDId=347</ext-link>. Accessed 20 August, 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rehm J, Anderson P, Manthey J, et al. Alcohol use disorders in primary health care: What do we know and where do we go? <italic toggle="yes">Alcohol and Alcoholism</italic> 2016; 51(4):422&#8211;427. Available at 10.1093/alcalc/agv127. Accessed 20 August, 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/alcalc/agv127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26574600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Curry SJ, Krist AH, Owens DK, et al. Screening and behavioral counseling interventions to reduce unhealthy alcohol use in adolescents and adults: US Preventive Services Task Force recommendation statement. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic> 2018; 320(18):1899. Available at 10.1001/jama.2018.16789. Accessed 20 August, 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2018.16789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30422199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bradley KA, Rubinsky AD, Sun H, et al. Alcohol screening and risk of postoperative complications in male VA patients undergoing major non-cardiac surgery. <italic toggle="yes">Journal of General Internal Medicine</italic> 2011; 26(2):162&#8211;169. Available at 10.1007/s11606-010-1475-x. Accessed 20 August, 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-010-1475-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3019325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20878363</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rubinsky AD, Sun H, Blough DK, et al. AUDIT-C alcohol screening results and postoperative inpatient health care use. <italic toggle="yes">Journal of the American College of Surgeons</italic> 2012; 214(3):296&#8211;305. Available at 10.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2011.11.007. Accessed 20 August, 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2011.11.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22244208</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">McCauley JL, Ward RC, Taber DJ, et al. Surgical prescription opioid trajectories among state Medicaid enrollees. <italic toggle="yes">Journal of Opioid Management</italic> 2023; 19(6):465&#8211;488. Available at 10.5055/jom.0832. Accessed 20 August, 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5055/jom.0832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38189189</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Quan H, Sundararajan V, Halfon P, et al. Coding algorithms for defining comorbidities in ICD-9-CM and ICD-10 administrative data. <italic toggle="yes">Medical Care</italic> 2005; 43(11):1130&#8211;1139. Available at 10.1097/01.mlr.0000182534.19832.83. Accessed 20 August, 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/01.mlr.0000182534.19832.83</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16224307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jonas DE, Amick HR, Feltner C, et al. Pharmacotherapy for adults with alcohol use disorders in outpatient settings: A systematic review and meta-analysis. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic> 2014; 311(18):1889&#8211;1900. Available at 10.1001/jama.2014.3628. Accessed 20 August, 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2014.3628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24825644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><italic toggle="yes">Key Substance Use and Mental Health Indicators in the United States: Results from the 2021 National Survey on Drug Use and Health.</italic> Rockville, MD: Center for Behavioral Health Statistics and Quality, 2023. Available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.samhsa.gov/data/release/2021-national-survey-drug-use-and-health-nsduh-releases">https://www.samhsa.gov/data/release/2021-national-survey-drug-use-and-health-nsduh-releases</ext-link>. Accessed 20 August, 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Glass JE, Bohnert KM, Brown RL. Alcohol screening and intervention among United States adults who attend ambulatory healthcare. <italic toggle="yes">Journal of General Internal Medicine</italic> 2016; 31(7):739&#8211;745. Available at 10.1007/s11606-016-3614-5. Accessed 25 August, 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-016-3614-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4907945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26862079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Iheanacho T, Issa M, Marienfeld C, et al. Use of naltrexone for alcohol use disorders in the Veterans&#8217; Health Administration: A national study. <italic toggle="yes">Drug and Alcohol Dependence</italic> 2013; 132(1):122&#8211;126. Available at 10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2013.01.016. Accessed 25 August, 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2013.01.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23434041</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chatterton B, Agnoli A, Schwarz EB, et al. Alcohol screening during US primary care visits, 2014&#8211;2016. <italic toggle="yes">Journal of General Internal Medicine</italic> 2022; 37(15):3848&#8211;3852. Available at 10.1007/s11606-021-07369-1. Accessed 25 August, 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-021-07369-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9640516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35048299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Harris AHS, Ellerbe L, Reeder RN, et al. Pharmacotherapy for alcohol dependence: perceived treatment barriers and action strategies among Veterans Health Administration service providers. <italic toggle="yes">Psychological Services</italic> 2013; 10(4):410&#8211;419. Available at 10.1037/a0030949. Accessed 25 August, 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1037/a0030949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23356858</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Oliva EM, Maisel NC, Gordon AJ, et al. Barriers to use of pharmacotherapy for addiction disorders and how to overcome them. <italic toggle="yes">Current Psychiatric Reports</italic> 2011; 13(5):374&#8211;381. Available at 10.1007/s11920-011-0222-2. Accessed 25 August, 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11920-011-0222-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4403628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21773951</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bhardwaj A, Sousa JL, Huskamp HA, et al. Prescribing medications for alcohol use disorder: A qualitative study of primary care physician decision making. <italic toggle="yes">Annals of Family Medicine</italic> 2023; 21(4):332&#8211;337. Available at 10.1370/afm.2997. Accessed 25 August, 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1370/afm.2997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10365869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37487716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Quan H, Li B, Saunders LD, et al. Assessing validity of ICD-9-CM and ICD-10 administrative data in recording clinical conditions in a unique dually coded database. <italic toggle="yes">Health Services Research</italic> 2008; 43(4):1424&#8211;1441. Available at 10.1111/j.1475-6773.2007.00822.x. Accessed 25 August, 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1475-6773.2007.00822.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2517283</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18756617</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Oslin DW, Lynch KG, Maisto SA, et al. A randomized clinical trial of alcohol care management delivered in Department of Veterans Affairs primary care clinics versus specialty addiction treatment. <italic toggle="yes">Journal of General Internal Medicine</italic> 2014; 29(1):162&#8211;168. Available at 10.1007/s11606-013-2625-8. Accessed 25 August, 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-013-2625-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3889933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24052453</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>