<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Lipids Health Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Lipids Health Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">116</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">liphdis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Lipids in Health and Disease</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1476-511X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11724460</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11724460.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11724460</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11724460</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39799346</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12944-024-02424-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2424</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Association between four anthropometric indices with age-related Macular Degeneration from NHANES 2005&#8211;2008</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="C">Chuyang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaorong</given-names></name><address><email>wxr98021@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/042v6xz23</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.260463.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2182 8825</institution-id><institution>Department of Ophthalmology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University, Jiangxi Medical College, </institution><institution>Nanchang University, </institution></institution-wrap>Nanchang, Jiangxi People&#8217;s Republic of China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478310</issue-id><elocation-id>11</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>11</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-01-13 12:25:23.037"><day>13</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12944_2024_Article_2424.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Age-related macular degeneration (AMD) decrease vision and presents considerable challenges for both public health and clinical management strategies. Obesity is usually implicated with increased AMD, and body mass index (BMI) does not reflect body fat distribution. An array of studies has indicated a robust relationship between body fat distribution and obesity. This research is to evaluate the relationship between anthropometric measurements and AMD in the United States citizens in a cohort of patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Our study included a cohort of 3,127 participants, all of whom were selected from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES) conducted between 2005 and 2008. Various anthropometric indices, including weight (WT), waist circumference (WC), Body Mass Index (BMI), waist-to-height ratio (WtHR), circularity index (CI), weight-adjusted waist circumference index (WWI), body roundness index (BRI), a body size index (ABSI), and visceral adiposity index (VAI), have been studied extensively within public health and nutrition to assess body fat distribution. Odds ratios (OR) for each anthropometric index, in relation to AMD and its different stages, were computed, adjusting for confounding variables. Smoothed curve fitting, coupled with weighted multivariable logistic regression analysis, was used to examine the impact of these anthropometric measures on the prevalence of AMD. Subgroup analyses were conducted according to gender, age, BMI, drinking, smoking, CVD, diabetes, hypertension, cataract operation, and glaucoma.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">After adjusting for all variables, significant positive correlations were observed between WtHR (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.237 (1.065&#8722;1.438)), BRI (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.221 (1.058&#8722;1.410)), CI (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.189 (1.039&#8722;1.362)), and WWI (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.250 (1.095&#8722;1.425)) with AMD, particularly for early AMD. However, no significant effects of these indicators were observed in late AMD. CI exhibited a positive linear relationship with AMD. Two-segment linear regression modeling revealed positive nonlinear associations between WtHR, BRI, and WWI with AMD. The positive association was more pronounced with excessive alcohol consumption for WtHR, BRI, CI, and WWI (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction&#8201;=&#8201;0.0033, 0.0021, 0.0194, and 0.0022, respectively). Additionally, WWI and CI exhibited stronger associations with AMD in females (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction&#8201;=&#8201;0.0146 and 0.0117, respectively). Furthermore, WtHR was associated with AMD in non-smokers (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction&#8201;=&#8201;0.0402).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">This study confirmed a increased risk between four anthropometric measures, including WtHR, BRI, CI, and WWI, with AMD, especially early AMD. The findings suggest that these four anthropometric indices should be more broadly utilized to improve early AMD prevention and treatment strategies. Additionally, we found that the positive association between these four body measurement indices and AMD was more pronounced in individuals with high alcohol consumption.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12944-024-02424-2.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Age-related macular degeneration</kwd><kwd>Anthropometric indicators</kwd><kwd>National health and nutrition examination survey</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">As a common neurodegenerative eye condition, AMD primarily affects older adults and has become the third most common contributor to vision loss globally [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. By 2020, the global population with AMD was estimated to be around 196&#160;million, with projections suggesting an increase to 288&#160;million by 2040 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. If the disease cannot be effectively prevented, affected individuals will continue to suffer, resulting in a substantial socio-economic burden. Although anti-vascular endothelial growth factor treatments provide some benefits for patients with wet AMD, effective medications for the majority of AMD cases remain unavailable. Therefore, identifying modifiable risk factors is crucial for preventing and managing this disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">The onset of AMD is influenced by an interplay of environmental and genetic factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The risk determinants associated with the deposition of drusen, a hallmark of AMD, are similar to atherosclerosis, suggesting that they can be linked [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Elevated body weight is associated with oxidative damage, inflammatory responses, and lipid irregularities, factors that contribute to AMD progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Research suggests that higher body fat may interfere with the transport of carotenoids to the macula, reducing macular pigment levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Twenty years ago, researchers suggested that lipid accumulation is a contributing factor to the progression of AMD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Some related studies reveals a connection between the formation of AMD and the lipid cholesterol metabolism, a relationship that was robustly substantiated through findings from the genome-wide association study (GWAS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Although obesity has been implicated with AMD in some Western populations, the exact mechanisms connecting obesity to AMD remain ambiguous [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Moreover, the impact of excess weight on the early versus late stages of AMD can differ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">Although BMI is a popular indicator of obesity, it is not a precise indicator of body fat distribution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Most research has explored the link between obesity and AMD primarily through the lens of BMI. Certain research has found an association between BMI and the development of AMD, while others have not observed such a correlation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Other studies have revealed a lack of apparent link between moderate-to-severe AMD and BMI. However, there were differences in the risk of moderate to severe macular edema between men and women and in WC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. WC is occasionally employed to estimate total body fat and provides a more focused evaluation of abdominal obesity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. A significant number of individuals with a normal BMI exhibit abnormal levels of body fat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Multiple anthropometric indices have been identified to evaluate body fat distribution, especially central obesity. Anthropometric indices include CI, BRI, VAI, WWI and WtHR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. These indices provide simple and effective ways to evaluate nutritional health and rapidly determine disease risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. And they offer more nuanced views of body composition and fat distribution. They specifically capture visceral and abdominal fat, which have been linked to higher metabolic risk and chronic diseases, offering a more precise assessment of an individual&#8217;s health risks compared to BMI alone. These indices have been increasingly recognized as valuable tools in epidemiological research, as they better reflect the underlying biological mechanisms driving obesity-related diseases.</p><p id="Par8">This article utilizes anthropometric measures to accurately assess whole-body lipid distribution and examine its impact on AMD in elderly Americans. We aimed to provide medical professionals and policymakers with tools to estimate AMD risk by exploring the relationship between various indices and AMD. This information could be used to inform targeted interventions for people at high risk, potentially contributing to a decrease in the incidence of AMD.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study Design and Sample sources</title><p id="Par9">The data of this article is original from the NHANES conducted between 2005 and 2008. The study was conducted as a cross-sectional analysis of American residents. Specific methods are publicly available and are accessible online. Eligibility criteria required participants to have complete data on weight, WC, BMI, triglycerides (TG), high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C), AMD, and relevant covariates. This study used data from 5,602 people aged 50 years or older, with a survey period of 2005&#8722;2008. Of these, 1,479 participants without retinal photographs or with ungradable images, 258 without WWI, VAI, or BMI data, and 738 with incomplete covariate data were excluded. Ultimately, 3127 individuals took part in this research. (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par10">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Diagram of participants included in the analyses</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e360" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12944_2024_2424_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Outcome variables</title><p id="Par11">Forty-five-degree non-mydriatic digital retinal images were obtained from survey participants using the Canon CR6-45NM Non-Mydriatic Retinal Camera. Fundus images were analyzed at the University of Wisconsin-Madison following the modified Wisconsin Age-Related Maculopathy Grading Scheme. Early AMD was characterized by the presence of drusen or pigmentary changes, while late AMD was identified by features such as subretinal fibrous scarring, choroidal neovascularization, or geographic atrophy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. When lesions exist in both eyes, the eye exhibiting the greater severity of AMD was selected for analysis. Each image was assessed by at least two trained graders, with an additional senior reviewer available to resolve any discrepancies.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Definition of Novel Anthropometric Indices</title><p id="Par12">Trained health technicians collected physical measurements, include WC, height, body weight, TG, and HDL-C. Subsequent calculations of BMI, ABSI, BRI, VAI, CI, WWI, and WtHR were performed using established formulas as detailed below:</p><p id="Par110">
<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\mathrm{BMI}=\mathrm{WT} / \text { height }^2$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12944_2024_2424_Article_Equa.gif"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p><p id="Par1101">
<disp-formula id="Equb"><alternatives><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\mathrm{ABSI}=\mathrm{WC} /\left(\mathrm{BMI}^{2 / 3} \times \text { height }^{0.5}\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12944_2024_2424_Article_Equb.gif"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p><p id="Par1201">
<disp-formula id="Equc"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\mathrm{BRI}=364.2-365.5 \times\left\{1-[(\mathrm{WC} / 2 \pi) /(0.5 \times \text { height })]^2\right\}^{0.5}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12944_2024_2424_Article_Equc.gif"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p><p id="Par12012">
<disp-formula id="Equd"><alternatives><tex-math id="M4">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\mathrm{VAI}=[\mathrm{WC}(39.68+(1.88 \times \mathrm{BMI}))] \times(\mathrm{TG} / 1.03) \times(1.31 / \mathrm{HDL}-\mathrm{C}) \mathrm{male}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12944_2024_2424_Article_Equd.gif"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p><p id="Par120102">
<disp-formula id="Eque"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\mathrm{VAI}=[\mathrm{WC} /(36.58+(1.89 \times \mathrm{BMI}))] \times(\mathrm{TG} / 0.81) \times(1.52 / \mathrm{HDL}-\mathrm{C}) \text { female }$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12944_2024_2424_Article_Eque.gif"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p><p id="Par12002">
<disp-formula id="Equf"><alternatives><tex-math id="M6">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\mathrm{WWI}=\mathrm{WC} / \text { weight }^2$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12944_2024_2424_Article_Equf.gif"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p><p id="Par120012">
<disp-formula id="Equg"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\mathrm{WtHR}=\mathrm{WC} \text { /height }$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12944_2024_2424_Article_Equg.gif"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p><p id="Par120121">
<disp-formula id="Equh"><alternatives><tex-math id="M8">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\mathrm{CI}=\mathrm{WC} / 0.109 /(\text { weight } / \text { height })^{0.5}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12944_2024_2424_Article_Equh.gif"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Covariates</title><p id="Par21">The records of in-person interviews provided a comprehensive dataset encompassing demographic, lifestyle, and medical history information. The demographic variables considered were age, race, gender, education level (including five levels), and marital status (classified as married or unmarried).</p><p id="Par22">Lifestyle variables included smoking and drinking. Classification of smoking based on blood cotinine was less than 0.015 ng/mL as low smoking, 0.015 to 3 ng/mL as moderate smoking and more than 3 ng/mL as high smoking. Individuals who do not consume alcohol, regardless of gender, were classified as non-drinkers. Individuals were classified as moderate drinkers if women reported consuming fewer than one alcoholic beverage per day and men indicated consumption of fewer than two beverages per day. Women who drink two to three drinks daily and men who consume three to four drinks were classified as heavy drinkers. Women who exceeded four alcoholic beverages per day and men who exceeded five beverages per day were categorized as excessive drinkers.</p><p id="Par23">Medical data were derived from both physical examinations and self-reported questionnaires. In the NHANES questionnaire data, a participant was classified as having cardiovascular disease (CVD) if they reported a heart-related health issue. Diabetes was diagnosed if a physician diagnosed the participant using insulin or oral hypoglycemic medication, a fasting blood glucose level of 7.0 mmol/L or higher, or a glycosylated hemoglobin level of 6.5% or greater. Participants who have systolic blood pressure&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;130 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;80 mmHg from three measurements, a history of hypertension, or use of antihypertensive drugs were diagnosed with hypertension. Cataract surgery history was based on self-report, following established diagnostic criteria from prior research. Due to the limited coverage and availability of cataract surgery in the United States, self-reported cataract surgery is a practical alternative indicator for clinically significant cataracts. Participants who have undergone cataract surgery were defined as having cataracts. The question assessed self-reported glaucoma prevalence, &#8220;Have you ever been informed by your ophthalmologist that you have glaucoma, sometimes referred to as ocular hypertension?&#8221; Participants who answered &#8220;yes&#8221; were classified as having glaucoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par24">Given the detailed multi-stage probability sampling approach used by NHANES, all analyses accounted for sample weights, stratification, and clustering to address the complexity of the survey design. The characteristics of the participants are expressed as means with 95% confidence intervals (CI) for continuous variables and as percentages with 95% CI for categorical variables. All anthropometric measures were standardized by employing z-scores., calculated as follows: z-score = (index - mean) / SD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Weighted multivariate regression analysis was utilized to investigate the complex interplay between anthropometric indices and AMD, including early and late stages. The results are presented as ORs along with their corresponding 95% CIs. Model 1 was without any adjustments; Model 2 was adjusted for gender, age, and race; and Model 3 included adjustments for gender, age, race, marital status, education, BMI, drinking, smoking, CVD, diabetes, hypertension, cataract surgery, and glaucoma.</p><p id="Par25">To explore the associations between anthropometric indices and AMD, smooth curve fitting models were implemented. Additionally, a thorough subgroup analysis was performed to investigate the relationships between different anthropometric indices and AMD. This analysis utilized stratified multivariable logistic regression models, which allowed us to account for potential confounding factors within specific subgroups. The covariates included in these models were stratified according to relevant characteristics, such as age, gender, BMI, diabetes status, hypertension status, alcohol consumption, smoking habits, CVD, history of cataract surgery, and glaucoma status. A <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value below 0.05 was considered statistically significant. Statistical analyses were performed using R Studio (version 4.3.3) and EmpowerStats (version 4.1).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>General characteristics in Population</title><p id="Par26">Details of AMD characteristics are shown in Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Of the 3,127 individuals, 2,825 (90.34%) were classified as having no AMD, while 302 (9.66%) showed any form of AMD. Specifically, 274 individuals (8.76%) had early AMD, while 28 (0.90%) were diagnosed with late AMD. The total prevalence of AMD in any form was 9.66%, with an average participant age of 71.248. Non-Hispanic White was the most common ethnicity (71.192%). Compared to the no AMD group, participants with AMD had higher indices of WT, CI, ABSI, and WWI (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). However, gender, race, and education were not significantly different between the any AMD and without AMD groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05). Unmarried individuals exhibited a markedly elevated prevalence of AMD, particularly in the late stage (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05).</p><p id="Par27">Regarding lifestyle factors, no substantial differences in drinking and smoking were identified across any of the stages of AMD (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05). Regarding health conditions, individuals with AMD were notably more likely to report a history of CVD and hypertension (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Additionally, more individuals with AMD had a history of cataract surgery or glaucoma (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). There were no substantial variations in the prevalence of diabetes among the various stages of AMD (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05).</p><p id="Par28">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The baseline characteristics of AMD status in the study population</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">without AMD</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">any AMD</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Early AMD</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Late AMD</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sample size</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2825(90.34%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">302(9.66%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">274(8.76%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28(0.90%%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WT, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83.119 (81.963 ,84.275)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80.269 (77.351 ,83.187)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80.976 (78.000 ,83.951)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73.685 (64.108 ,83.262)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0359</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WC, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101.401 (100.488 ,102.314)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102.217 (100.174 ,104.259)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102.785 (100.719 ,104.851)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96.918 (89.321 ,104.514)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4438</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BMI, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.012 (28.632 ,29.393)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.760 (27.792 ,29.728)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.003 (28.022 ,29.984)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.491 (24.034 ,28.949)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5763</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WtHR, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.601 (0.595 ,0.606)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.614 (0.601 ,0.626)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.617</p><p>(0.604 ,0.629)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.583 (0.547 ,0.620)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0553</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BRI, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.604 (5.476 ,5.732)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.880 (5.586 ,6.173)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5.959</p><p>(5.663 ,6.254)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.145 (4.324 ,5.967)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0850</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ABSI, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.083 (0.083 ,0.083)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.085 (0.084 ,0.085)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.085</p><p>(0.084 ,0.085)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.085 (0.084 ,0.086)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CI, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.331 (1.327 ,1.336)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.357 (1.348 ,1.367)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.359</p><p>(1.349 ,1.369)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.342 (1.306 ,1.379)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">VAI, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.807 (6.687 ,6.926)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.625 (6.255 ,6.994)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.617</p><p>(6.231 ,7.003)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.696 (5.830 ,7.562)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3101</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WWI, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.173 (11.130 ,11.217)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.470 (11.380 ,11.561)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.482 (11.388 ,11.575)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.365 (11.114 ,11.616)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AGE, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.288 (60.738 ,61.838)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69.430 (67.969 ,70.890)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.782 (67.303 ,70.260)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75.467 (72.749 ,78.185)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gender, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9153</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.831 (49.117 ,52.544)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.094 (46.360 ,55.810)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.420 (46.796 ,57.983)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.741 (12.934 ,72.915)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.169 (47.456 ,50.883)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.906 (44.190 ,53.640)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.580 (42.017 ,53.204)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.259 (27.085 ,87.066)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0563</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mexican American</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.231 (2.947 ,6.041)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.705 (2.285 ,5.953)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3.979</p><p>(2.424 ,6.464)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.153 (0.050 ,21.364)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other Hispanic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.644 (1.741 ,3.995)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.876 (0.824 ,4.212)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.077</p><p>(0.911 ,4.664)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000 (0.000 ,0.000)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-Hispanic white</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80.496 (76.043 ,84.292)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85.862 (80.178 ,90.117)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.812 (78.509 ,89.514)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95.647 (71.980 ,99.471)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-Hispanic black</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.590 (6.354 ,11.517)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.168 (2.500 ,6.869)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.272</p><p>(2.499 ,7.209)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.200 (0.228 ,32.384)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other Race</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.038 (3.081 ,5.278)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.389 (1.842 ,10.098)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.860 (2.038 ,11.149)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000 (0.000 ,0.000)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Education, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8899</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Less than 9th grade</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.861 (5.490 ,8.544)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.309 (3.956 ,13.117)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.970 (4.352 ,14.150)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.153 (0.050 ,21.364)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9&#8211;11th grade</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.404 (8.462 ,12.731)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.994 (8.205 ,17.205)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.448 (8.287 ,18.281)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.768 (0.770 ,47.746)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>High school</p><p>grad/GED or equivalent</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.629 (23.741 ,29.731)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.081 (22.275 ,34.723)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.426 (21.779 ,33.904)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.178 (13.822 ,62.702)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Some college or AA degree</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.015 (26.563 ,31.596)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.021 (21.566 ,35.534)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.398 (20.105 ,33.825)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.156 (14.156 ,77.755)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">College graduate or above</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.091 (23.284 ,31.267)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.594 (17.826 ,32.903)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.758 (18.432 ,34.756)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.745 (4.088 ,37.335)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Marital status, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0356</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">unmarried</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.804 (30.291 ,37.505)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.032 (33.493 ,49.018)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.282 (31.588 ,47.547)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.343 (31.175 ,79.958)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">married</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.196 (62.495 ,69.709)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58.968 (50.982 ,66.507)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.718 (52.453 ,68.412)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.657 (20.042 ,68.825)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Drink, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6958</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No drinking</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.329 (23.294 ,29.607)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.653 (22.680 ,33.248)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.683 (21.600 ,32.468)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.690 (15.291 ,65.044)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate drinking</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.291 (22.944 ,27.791)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.797 (18.456 ,27.812)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.386 (18.652 ,28.895)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.311 (3.636 ,53.735)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heavy drinking</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.449 (19.415 ,23.633)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.394 (15.922 ,25.739)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.302 (16.840 ,26.568)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.940 (2.202 ,44.946)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Over drinking</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.932 (24.316 ,29.718)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.155 (23.666 ,35.328)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.629 (22.715 ,35.378)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.058 (13.150 ,63.792)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoke, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5254</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.685 (16.395 ,23.450)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.259 (17.334 ,28.107)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.077 (16.620 ,28.709)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.954 (5.229 ,64.264)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medium</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.053 (53.562 ,60.475)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.139 (50.399 ,61.719)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.812 (49.582 ,61.865)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.180 (26.520 ,85.346)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.262 (20.548 ,26.216)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.603 (16.185 ,28.224)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.111 (16.742 ,28.610)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.866 (4.485 ,46.712)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CVD, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85.593 (83.601 ,87.380)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74.074 (65.983 ,80.800)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74.025 (65.063 ,81.347)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74.532 (47.488 ,90.449)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.407 (12.620 ,16.399)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.926 (19.200 ,34.017)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.975 (18.653 ,34.937)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.468 (9.551 ,52.512)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diabetes, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8600</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83.690 (81.218 ,85.893)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.199 (78.140 ,88.819)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83.875 (77.560 ,88.673)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87.213 (45.483 ,98.238)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.310 (14.107 ,18.782)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.801 (11.181 ,21.860)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.125 (11.327 ,22.440)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.787 (1.762 ,54.517)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hypertension, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0480</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.364 (25.018 ,29.844)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.587 (16.305 ,28.008)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.219 (15.371 ,26.125)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.334 (8.880 ,73.720)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.636 (70.156 ,74.982)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78.413 (71.992 ,83.695)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79.781 (73.875 ,84.629)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.666 (26.280 ,91.120)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cataract operation, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.801 (9.339 ,12.461)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.317 (19.837 ,31.713)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.006 (17.069 ,27.890)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.181 (22.430 ,85.041)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89.199 (87.539 ,90.661)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74.683 (68.287 ,80.163)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.994 (72.110 ,82.931)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.819 (14.959 ,77.570)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Glaucoma, (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0125</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.542 (4.477 ,6.843)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.205 (6.491 ,15.688)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.693 (6.249 ,14.737)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.979 (1.309 ,70.063)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94.458 (93.157 ,95.523)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89.795 (84.312 ,93.509)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90.307 (85.263 ,93.751)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85.021 (29.937 ,98.691)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par29">The characteristics of the participants are expressed as means with 95% CI for continuous variables and as percentages with 95% CI for categorical variables. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value presented is based on the comparison between participants without AMD and those with any AMD.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Association between the Anthropometric indices and AMD</title><p id="Par30">Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> provides a summary of the weighted logistic regression analysis results for any form of AMD. In unadjusted model 1, a higher ABSI Z-score (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.482 (1.306&#8722;1.681), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), CI Z-score (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.345 (1.182&#8722;1.531), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0001), and WWI Z-score (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.492(1.299&#8722;1.714), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001) were associated with higher odds of any AMD. After full adjustment, the WtHR Z-score was markedly correlation with any AMD (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.237 (1.065&#8722;1.438), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0215). Additionally, the BRI Z-score revealed a significant association with any AMD (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.221(1.058&#8722;1.410), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0232). The CI Z-score maintained its significance (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.189 (1.039&#8722;1.362), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0334), and the WWI Z-score retained its association with any AMD (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.250 (1.095&#8722;1.425), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0090).</p><p id="Par31">Subsequently, we investigated whether these anthropometric indices impacted the severity of AMD. The results of the association between anthropometric indices and early AMD are provided in STable <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>. After full adjustment, the WtHR, BRI, CI, and WWI exhibited significant associations with early AMD (OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.269 (1.089&#8722;1.479), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0138; OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.251 (1.081&#8722;1.449), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0151; OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.209 (1.045&#8722;1.399), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0310; and OR&#8201;=&#8201;1.281 (1.116&#8722;1.471), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0064). As for late AMD (STable <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>), all indices did not exhibit significant associations across models. These results suggest that these anthropometric indices (WtHR, BRI, CI, and WWI) can be important indicators for early AMD; however, their relevance is reduced for late AMD.</p><p id="Par32">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Weighted logistic regression analysis showing the correlation between anthropometric indices and any AMD</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Any AMD</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model 1</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model 2</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model 3</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WT Z-score</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.865</p><p>(0.753, 0.992)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0474</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.064</p><p>(0.892, 1.269)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4993</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.094</p><p>(0.917, 1.305)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3449</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WC Z-score</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.052</p><p>(0.926, 1.195)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4440</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.138</p><p>(0.971, 1.334)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1240</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.179</p><p>(1.009, 1.378)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0679</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BMI Z-score</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.960</p><p>(0.830, 1.110)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5846</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.129</p><p>(0.960, 1.328)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1542</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.178</p><p>(1.002, 1.386)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0788</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WtHR Z-score</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.152</p><p>(1.004, 1.321)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0526</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.182</p><p>(1.016, 1.375)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0404</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.237</p><p>(1.065, 1.438)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0215</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BRI Z-score</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.132</p><p>(0.993, 1.291)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0743</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.170</p><p>(1.014, 1.351)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0422</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.221</p><p>(1.058, 1.410)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0232</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ABSI Z-score</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.482</p><p>(1.306, 1.681)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.128</p><p>(0.976, 1.303)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1159</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.121</p><p>(0.968, 1.297)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1603</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CI Z-score</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.345</p><p>(1.182, 1.531)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.169</p><p>(1.015, 1.346)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0401</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.189</p><p>(1.039, 1.362)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0334</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">VAI Z-score</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.925</p><p>(0.788, 1.085)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3445</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0.998</p><p>(0.846, 1.178)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9832</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.007</p><p>(0.858, 1.182)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9337</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WWI Z-score</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.492</p><p>(1.299, 1.714)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.218</p><p>(1.065, 1.393)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0081</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1.250</p><p>(1.095, 1.425)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0090</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par33">Weighted logistic regression analysis showing the correlation between anthropometric indices and any AMD. Model 1: unadjusted model. Model 2: adjusted for gender, age and race. Model 3: adjusted for gender, age, race, marital status, education, drinking, smoking, hypertension, diabetes, CVD, cataract operation and glaucoma.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Subgroup analysis</title><p id="Par34">Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>-<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> shows the association between WtHR, CI, BRI, WWI, and AMD by stratified multivariate logistic regression analysis across various demographic and health-related subgroups, including gender, age, BMI, drinking, smoking, CVD, diabetes, hypertension, cataract operation, and glaucoma. There was a significant positive connection between WtHR and AMD in individuals who were overdrinking (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction&#8201;=&#8201;0.0033) and did not smoke (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction&#8201;=&#8201;0.0402). However, the correlation between WtHR and AMD did not vary significantly across age, gender, BMI, CVD, diabetes, hypertension, cataract surgery, and glaucoma subgroups (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Furthermore, CI, BRI, and WWI exhibited a significant positive correlation with AMD in participants with overdrinking (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction&#8201;=&#8201;0.0194, 0.0021, and 0.0022). The WWI and CI were significantly associated with AMD with females (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for the interaction&#8201;=&#8201;0.0146 and 0.0117, respectively). In contrast, the BRI demonstrated a consistent relationship with AMD across both genders (Figs.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">3</xref>&#8722;5). The relationships between CI, BRI, and WWI with AMD remained consistent across multiple subgroups, including divisions by age, BMI, smoking habits, drinking habits, presence of CVD, diabetes, hypertension, history of cataract surgery, and glaucoma.</p><p id="Par35">
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Subgroup analyses to determine the correlation of WtHR and AMD. Multivariable weight logistic analyses were conducted after adjusting for age, gender, BMI, drink, smoke, CVD, diabetes, hypertension, cataract operation, glaucoma</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1457" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12944_2024_2424_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par36">
<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Subgroup analyses to determine the correlation of CI and AMD. Multivariable weight logistic analyses were conducted after adjusting for age, gender, BMI, drink, smoke, CVD, diabetes, hypertension, cataract operation, glaucoma</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1467" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12944_2024_2424_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par37">
<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Subgroup analyses to determine the correlation of BRI and AMD. Multivariable weight logistic analyses were conducted after adjusting for age, gender, BMI, drink, smoke, CVD, diabetes, hypertension, cataract operation, glaucoma</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1477" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12944_2024_2424_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par4012">
<fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Subgroup analyses to determine the correlation of WWI and AMD. Multivariable weight logistic analyses were conducted after adjusting for age, gender, BMI, drink, smoke, CVD, diabetes, hypertension, cataract operation, glaucoma</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1487" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12944_2024_2424_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Relationship between four anthropometric indices with AMD</title><p id="Par39">To illuminate the correlation between WtHR, CI, BRI, and WWI with AMD, smooth curve fitting model was employed. A two-segment linear regression model analysis revealed nonlinear associations for WtHR, BRI, and WWI with AMD (inflection points at 0.535, 4.045, and 12.065, respectively). CI exhibited a linear and positive correlation with AMD (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).</p><p id="Par40">
<fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Smooth curve fitting models evaluated the correlation between four anthropometric indices with AMD. Adjusted smooth curve fitting models adjusted for gender, age, race, marital status, education, drinking, smoking, hypertension, diabetes, CVD, cataract operation, and glaucoma. The red line illustrates the smoothed curve that fits the data points, while the blue shaded areas indicate the 95% CI around the fit. (<bold>A</bold>) Smooth curve fitting model of WtHR. (<bold>B</bold>) Smooth curve fitting model of CI. (<bold>C</bold>) Smooth curve fitting model of BRI. (<bold>D</bold>) Smooth curve fitting model of WWI</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1517" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12944_2024_2424_Fig6_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par41">The NHANES cohort study from 2005 to 2008 investigated the associations between increased values of four anthropometric indices &#8212;WtHR, BRI, CI, and WWI&#8212; and the occurrence of AMD among U.S. citizens. The study findings revealed notable associations between elevated levels of these indices and increased AMD risk, enhancing our insight into the complex connections between anthropometric parameters and AMD. To date, this study provides strong positive evidence for WtHR, CI, BRI, and WWI with AMD. These indices were prominently associated with AMD in persons with heavy alcohol consumption. Additionally, WtHR was prominently associated with AMD in non-smokers. Additionally, WWI and CI exhibited stronger associations with AMD in females.</p><p id="Par42">This study indicated that increasing WtHR, CI, BRI, and WWI were linked to the onset of early AMD. However, these four indices do not appear to influence the risk of late AMD. Part of the reason could be the small sample size of late AMD cases, while another possible reason could be as follows. Early AMD typically refers to pigmentary changes in the macula (yellow deposits beneath the retina) and retinal cells. These early symptoms are often associated with chronic inflammation and oxidative stress. Obesity plays a role in these processes by releasing proinflammatory cytokines, which are inflammatory mediators linked to the early stages of AMD because they can damage retinal cells, induce drusen formation, and contribute to oxidative stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. In this study, late AMD is characterized by geographic atrophy, and the mechanisms leading to late AMD involve more complex and irreversible processes. Although inflammation remains a factor, the link between obesity and late AMD may not be as straightforward. Once macular degeneration reaches a certain threshold, the impact of obesity may be obscured by more severe pathological changes in the retina.</p><p id="Par43">Elevated total systemic cholesterol levels during middle age can contribute to the progression of AMD. Cholesterol accumulation within Bruch&#8217;s membrane plays a key role in AMD pathogenesis, leading to the formation of basal linear deposits and drusen, which are hallmark features of the disorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Furthermore, increased body fat levels can limit carotenoids&#8217; transit to the retina, lowering macular pigment levels and increasing AMD risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par44">Consequently, obesity is an important risk for AMD. Most studies use BMI and body weight as key measures of obesity. However, as muscle mass normally decreases with age, BMI cannot accurately represent obesity levels in the elderly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Moreover, BMI and weight do not comprehensively evaluate body fat distribution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. To overcome these limitations, recent advancements in anthropometric indices have been implemented to conduct a more comprehensive analysis of obesity trends. These novel methods are designed to better distinguish between central obesity and the associated risk of AMD.</p><p id="Par45">WtHR, and WC are widely considered biomarkers of central obesity. The advantages of WtHR include cost-effectiveness, safety of the model, ease of access, and substantial prediction in clinical settings. Several studies have demonstrated that WtHR outperforms other indicators in predicting cardiovascular diseases, diabetes, and hypertension [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Currently, no research connects WtHR to AMD despite its established utility. In this study, individuals with higher WtHR indices showed an increased risk of early AMD. Additionally, WtHR maintains a positive correlation with AMD below the inflection point of 0.535.</p><p id="Par46">BRI enables the assessment of both visceral and total body fat percentages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. BRI has demonstrated its reliability as a predictor of metabolic syndrome. Studies have indicated that increased BRI are independently linked with occurrences of diabetes. There is also no research establishing a connection between BRI and AMD, despite its proven utility. This study demonstrates a notable positive correlation between BRI with early AMD, with BRI exhibiting a positive relationship with AMD below the inflection point of 4.045.</p><p id="Par47">CI has been used in the diagnosis of T2DM and hypertension. A study has demonstrated that CI can affect lipid levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Up to date, there is no research linking CI to AMD, even though its usefulness is well recognized. This study demonstrates a notable positive correlation between CI with early AMD, indicating that a higher CI is significantly linked to the development of early AMD. Besides, CI demonstrated a positive linear relationship with AMD.</p><p id="Par48">WWI predominantly represents central obesity and can accurately diagnose excessive fat content combined with low muscle mass. Many studies suggest that WWI is linked with the development of hyperuricemia and other cardiovascular outcomes, including heart failure, left ventricular hypertrophy, and abdominal aortic calcification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Increased body weight leads to oxidative damage, inflammatory processes, and lipid imbalances, each of which contributes to AMD development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. This study demonstrates a notable positive correlation between BRI with early AMD. Furthermore, this study determined that below the inflection point of 12.065, WWI has a positive relationship with AMD.</p><p id="Par49">Our study found no significant outcomes for ABSI and VAI. The reasons for this discrepancy are not completely understood, but the limitations of ABSI and VAI in effectively detecting AMD may contribute. Unlike these four measurements, ABSI does not adequately reflect the distribution of fat and muscle throughout the body. Its predictability may be limited by high clustering around the mean and low variability. In contrast, VAI focuses more on TG and L-HDL indices related to visceral adiposity and also fails to differentiate between fat and muscle mass.</p><p id="Par50">This study identified a non-linear association between WtHR, BRI, and WWI with AMD, potentially influenced by various factors. First, the reduced sample size beyond certain thresholds may have affected the stability of the results, leading to a flattening or mild negative correlation between these indices and AMD. Additionally, fat accumulation may reach a saturation point, where its impact on AMD becomes negligible, with other biological mechanisms potentially driving the relationship [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. As fat distribution rises, metabolic abnormalities may reach a peak, and factors such as vascular health and oxidative stress may become more significant contributors to AMD progression. Furthermore, as individuals age, other comorbidities (such as age and diet) may exert a stronger impact on AMD risk, potentially diminishing the influence of fat distribution on AMD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p><p id="Par51">These four indicators are associated with centripetal obesity and suggest that BMI cannot effectively describe the risk of developing AMD. Whole-body fat distribution is more relevant to AMD.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Advantages and disadvantages</title><p id="Par52">The study has significant strengths and implications. First, the large sample size provides significant statistical power, increasing the reliability of the results. Second, smooth curve fitting allows for a comprehensive investigation of obesity prevalence rates and the associations between AMD and various measurement techniques. Third, our findings underscore the significant role of central adiposity in AMD, suggesting that WtHR, BRI, CI, and WWI could be early predictors of AMD.</p><p id="Par53">However, it should be acknowledged that the study possesses certain potential limitations and considerations. Firstly, due to its cross-sectional design, the study is inherently unable to establish causal relationships. Furthermore, several biases and potential correlations may have influenced our findings, which have not been fully addressed in this study. Additionally, selection bias could be a concern as the NHANES dataset, while diverse and representative of the US population, may not fully capture all segments, particularly those who are underserved or harder to reach. This could lead to an incomplete or biased picture of health outcomes and associated factors.</p><p id="Par54">One limitation of this study is its reliance on NHANES data from 2005 to 2008, during which the methods and diagnostic criteria for AMD were not as advanced as current standards, potentially affecting the accuracy of AMD classification. Additionally, the NHANES database excludes intermediate AMD, which may underestimate the true burden of the disease and hinder understanding of AMD progression and risk factors. Furthermore, the limited sample size of late AMD cases within the database may compromise the reliability of conclusions drawn from the data. These factors underscore the need for more comprehensive AMD classifications and larger, more up-to-date datasets to accurately assess the burden, progression, and risk factors associated with AMD.</p><p id="Par55">These indices offer superior insights into body fat distribution compared to traditional measures, but their complexity in measurement and calculation may hinder widespread clinical adoption. Future efforts should aim to simplify these indices while maintaining their clinical relevance. As such, future research and development should focus on simplifying these indices while preserving their accuracy and clinical relevance, to facilitate their practical use in everyday healthcare settings.</p><p id="Par56">To address this, future research should incorporate more recent data and updated diagnostic protocols to validate and expand upon our findings. Despite this limitation, our study provides valuable insights that could guide future investigations into the relationship between physical measurement indicators and AMD.</p><p id="Par57">In summary, although this study offers important insights, acknowledging these limitations and potential biases is essential. Future research should address these issues to enhance the applicability and robustness of the findings.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par58">Within the context of the study, an increase in the WtHR, BRI, and WWI indices was found to have a nonlinear positive association with AMD prevalence in U.S. adults aged 50 and older. Conversely, increases in the CI index showed a linear and positive association with AMD prevalence within this group. Physicians may recommend adopting a healthy lifestyle for patients with a normal BMI but elevated WtHR, BRI, CI, and WWI. This may include adopting a balanced diet and increasing physical activity, managing weight, and lowering blood lipid levels. While these interventions may help decrease AMD risk, the study has not conclusively shown that they definitely do so.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12944_2024_2424_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12944_2024_2424_MOESM2_ESM.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 2</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12944_2024_2424_MOESM3_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 3</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ABSI</term><def><p id="Par1275">A Body Shape Index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AMD</term><def><p id="Par63">Age-Related Macular Degeneration</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BMI</term><def><p id="Par64">Body Mass Index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BRI</term><def><p id="Par65">Body Roundness Index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p id="Par66">Confidence Interval</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CVD</term><def><p id="Par67">Cardiovascular Diseases</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GWAS</term><def><p id="Par68">Genome-Wide Association Study</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HDL</term><def><p id="Par69">High Density Lipoprotein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HbA1c</term><def><p id="Par70">Glycosylated Haemoglobin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HbA1c</term><def><p id="Par71">NHANES The National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OR</term><def><p id="Par72">Odds Ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SD</term><def><p id="Par73"> Standard Deviations</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TC</term><def><p id="Par74">Total Cholesterol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WC</term><def><p id="Par75">Waist Circumference</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WtHR</term><def><p id="Par76">Waist-to-Height Ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WWI</term><def><p id="Par7614">Weight-Adjusted Waist Index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VAI</term><def><p id="Par78">Visceral Fat Index</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#8217;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Home for Researchers editorial team (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.home-for-researchers.com">www.home-for-researchers.com</ext-link>) for language editing service.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>XCY: methodology, software, analysis, review, data integration and writing-original draft. WXR: article conception, writing review and editing, and methodology. All authors approved the final manuscript as submitted and agreed to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>No funding.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>No datasets were generated or analysed during the current study. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhanes">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhanes</ext-link>.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par59">This investigation was approved by the National Center for Health Statistics. Ethics Review Board. Informed consent was obtained from all subjects involved in the NHANES.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par60">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par61">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guymer</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age-related macular degeneration</article-title><source>Lancet (London England)</source><year>2023</year><volume>401</volume><issue>10386</issue><fpage>1459</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0140-6736(22)02609-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36996856</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Guymer RH, Campbell TG. Age-related macular degeneration. Lancet (London England). 2023;401(10386):1459&#8211;72. 10.1016/s0140-6736(22)02609-5. PubMed PMID: 36996856; eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36996856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(22)02609-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global prevalence of age-related macular degeneration and disease burden projection for 2020 and 2040: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Lancet Global Health</source><year>2014</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e106</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s2214-109x(13)70145-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25104651</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Wong WL, Su X, Li X, et al. Global prevalence of age-related macular degeneration and disease burden projection for 2020 and 2040: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet Global Health. 2014;2(2):e106&#8211;16. 10.1016/s2214-109x(13)70145-1. PubMed PMID: 25104651; eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25104651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2214-109X(13)70145-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhang Q-Y, Tie L-J, Wu S-S, et al. Overweight, obesity, and risk of age-related Macular Degeneration. Invest Opthalmology Visual Sci. 2016;57(3). 10.1167/iovs.15-18637.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1167/iovs.15-18637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26990164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Age-related macular degeneration: epidemiology, genetics, pathophysiology, diagnosis, and targeted therapy</article-title><source>Genes Dis</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gendis.2021.02.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35005108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8720701</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Deng Y, Qiao L, Du M, et al. Age-related macular degeneration: epidemiology, genetics, pathophysiology, diagnosis, and targeted therapy. Genes Dis. 2022;9(1):62&#8211;79. 10.1016/j.gendis.2021.02.009. PubMed PMID: 35005108; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC8720701. eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35005108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.gendis.2021.02.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8720701</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boddu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsiglia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors associated with reticular pseudodrusen versus large soft drusen</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>2014</year><volume>157</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>985</fpage><lpage>e9932</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajo.2014.01.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24491417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4115805</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Boddu S, Lee MD, Marsiglia M, et al. Risk factors associated with reticular pseudodrusen versus large soft drusen. Am J Ophthalmol. 2014;157(5):985&#8211;e9932. 10.1016/j.ajo.2014.01.023. PubMed PMID: 24491417; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC4115805. eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24491417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajo.2014.01.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4115805</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Curcio</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><collab>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States</collab></person-group><article-title>Complementing apolipoprotein secretion by cultured retinal pigment epithelium</article-title><source>Am</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><issue>46</issue><fpage>18569</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1115497108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3219100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22065764</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Curcio CA, Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States. Complementing apolipoprotein secretion by cultured retinal pigment epithelium. Am. 2011;108(46):18569&#8211;70. 10.1073/pnas.1115497108. PubMed PMID: 22065764; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC3219100. eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.1115497108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3219100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22065764</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kubista</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krugluger</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of visceral fat and pro-inflammatory factors on the pathogenesis of age-related macular degeneration</article-title><source>Acta Ophthalmol</source><year>2015</year><volume>93</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/aos.12670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25683020</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Haas P, Kubista KE, Krugluger W, et al. Impact of visceral fat and pro-inflammatory factors on the pathogenesis of age-related macular degeneration. Acta Ophthalmol. 2015;93(6):533&#8211;8. 10.1111/aos.12670. PubMed PMID: 25683020; eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25683020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/aos.12670</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tokarz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaarniranta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blasiak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of antioxidant enzymes and small molecular weight antioxidants in the pathogenesis of age-related macular degeneration (AMD)</article-title><source>Biogerontology</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10522-013-9463-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24057278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3824279</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Tokarz P, Kaarniranta K, Blasiak J. Role of antioxidant enzymes and small molecular weight antioxidants in the pathogenesis of age-related macular degeneration (AMD). Biogerontology. 2013;14(5):461&#8211;82. 10.1007/s10522-013-9463-2. PubMed PMID: 24057278; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC3824279. eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24057278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10522-013-9463-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3824279</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Johnson EJ. Obesity, lutein metabolism, and age-related macular degeneration: a web of connections. Nutrition reviews. 2005;63(1):9&#8211;15. 10.1111/j.1753-4887.2005.tb00105.x. PubMed PMID: 15730230; eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1753-4887.2005.tb00105.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15730230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bovier</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Jr. The relationship between lutein and zeaxanthin status and body fat</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>750</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu5030750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23529076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3705317</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Bovier ER, Lewis RD, Hammond BR. Jr. The relationship between lutein and zeaxanthin status and body fat. Nutrients. 2013;5(3):750&#8211;7. 10.3390/nu5030750. PubMed PMID: 23529076; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC3705317. eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23529076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/nu5030750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3705317</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of the atherosclerotic process in the pathogenesis of age-related macular degeneration</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><year>2000</year><volume>130</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>658</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0002-9394(00)00643-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11078846</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Friedman E. The role of the atherosclerotic process in the pathogenesis of age-related macular degeneration. Am J Ophthalmol. 2000;130(5):658&#8211;63. 10.1016/s0002-9394(00)00643-7. PubMed PMID: 11078846; eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11078846</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0002-9394(00)00643-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pennington KL, DeAngelis MM. Epidemiology of age-related macular degeneration (AMD): associations with cardiovascular disease phenotypes and lipid factors. Eye Vis (Lond). 2016;3:34. doi: 10.1186/s40662-016-0063-5. PubMed PMID: 28032115; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC5178091.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s40662-016-0063-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5178091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28032115</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinding</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>la Cour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Age-related maculopathy: a risk indicator for poorer survival in women: the Copenhagen City Eye Study</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2005</year><volume>112</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ophtha.2004.08.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15691568</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Buch H, Vinding T, la Cour M, et al. Age-related maculopathy: a risk indicator for poorer survival in women: the Copenhagen City Eye Study. Ophthalmology. 2005;112(2):305&#8211;12. 025. PubMed PMID: 15691568; eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15691568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ophtha.2004.08.025</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lavie CJ, De Schutter A, Patel D et al. Body composition and coronary heart disease mortality&#8211;an obesity or a lean paradox? Mayo Clinic proceedings. 2011;86(9):857&#8201;&#8211;&#8201;64. 10.4065/mcp.2011.0092. PubMed PMID: 21878597; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC3257992. eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4065/mcp.2011.0092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3257992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21878597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Munch</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linneberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Precursors of age-related macular degeneration: associations with physical activity, obesity, and serum lipids in the inter99 eye study</article-title><source>Investig Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>54</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>3932</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1167/iovs.12-10785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23652489</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Munch IC, Linneberg A, Larsen M. Precursors of age-related macular degeneration: associations with physical activity, obesity, and serum lipids in the inter99 eye study. Investig Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2013;54(6):3932&#8211;40. 10.1167/iovs.12-10785. PubMed PMID: 23652489; eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23652489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1167/iovs.12-10785</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maynard</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trends in mean waist circumference and abdominal obesity among US adults, 1999&#8211;2012</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2014</year><volume>312</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1151</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2014.8362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25226482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4608432</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Ford ES, Maynard LM, Li C. Trends in mean waist circumference and abdominal obesity among US adults, 1999&#8211;2012. JAMA. 2014;312(11):1151&#8211;3. 10.1001/jama.2014.8362. PubMed PMID: 25226482; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC4608432. eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25226482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2014.8362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4608432</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haslam</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>London</surname></name></person-group><source>England)</source><year>2005</year><volume>366</volume><issue>9492</issue><fpage>1197</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0140-6736(05)67483-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16198769</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Haslam DW, James WP, London. England). 2005;366(9492):1197&#8211;209. 10.1016/s0140-6736(05)67483-1. PubMed PMID: 16198769; eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(05)67483-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16198769</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bredlau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosy-Westphal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationships between body roundness with body fat and visceral adipose tissue emerging from a new geometrical model</article-title><source>Obes (Silver Spring Md)</source><year>2013</year><volume>21</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2264</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/oby.20408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3692604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23519954</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Thomas DM, Bredlau C, Bosy-Westphal A, et al. Relationships between body roundness with body fat and visceral adipose tissue emerging from a new geometrical model. Obes (Silver Spring Md). 2013;21(11):2264&#8211;71. 10.1002/oby.20408. PubMed PMID: 23519954; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC3692604. eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/oby.20408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3692604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23519954</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhang J, Liang D, Xu L, et al. Associations between novel anthropometric indices and the prevalence of gallstones among 6,848 adults: a cross-sectional study. Front Nutr. 2024;11. 10.3389/fnut.2024.1428488.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fnut.2024.1428488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11298442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39104753</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zwierzchowska A, Kantyka J, Roso&#322;ek B, et al. Sensitivity and specificity of Anthropometric indices in identifying obesity in women over 40 years of Age and their variability in subsequent decades of life. Biology. 2022;11(12). 10.3390/biology11121804. PubMed PMID: 36552313; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC9775391. eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biology11121804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9775391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36552313</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Age-related maculopathy in a multiracial United States population: the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey III</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>1999</year><volume>106</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1056</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0161-6420(99)90255-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10366071</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Klein R, Klein BE, Jensen SC, et al. Age-related maculopathy in a multiracial United States population: the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey III. Ophthalmology. 1999;106(6):1056&#8211;65. 10.1016/s0161-6420(99)90255-5. PubMed PMID: 10366071; eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10366071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0161-6420(99)90255-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fu Y, Chen X, Luo S, et al. Serum 25-Hydroxyvitamin D is differentially Associated with early and late age-related Macular Degeneration in the United States Population. Nutrients. 2023;15(5). 10.3390/nu15051216.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/nu15051216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10005371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36904215</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age-related macular degeneration</article-title><source>Pharmacotherapy</source><year>2013</year><volume>33</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>838</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/phar.1264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23580402</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Cheung LK, Eaton A. Age-related macular degeneration. Pharmacotherapy. 2013;33(8):838&#8211;55. 10.1002/phar.1264. PubMed PMID: 23580402; eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23580402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/phar.1264</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kananen F, Strandberg T, Loukovaara S, et al. Early middle age cholesterol levels and the association with age-related macular degeneration. Acta Ophthalmol. 2021;99(7). 10.1111/aos.14774.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/aos.14774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33533136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bosello F, Vanzo A, Zaffalon C, et al. Obesity, body fat distribution and eye diseases. Eating and Weight disorders - studies on Anorexia. Bulimia Obes. 2024;29(1). 10.1007/s40519-024-01662-8.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40519-024-01662-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11074037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38710948</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Batsis</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villareal</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sarcopenic obesity in older adults: aetiology, epidemiology and treatment strategies</article-title><source>Nat Reviews Endocrinol</source><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41574-018-0062-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6241236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30065268</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Batsis JA, Villareal DT. Sarcopenic obesity in older adults: aetiology, epidemiology and treatment strategies. Nat Reviews Endocrinol. 2018;14(9):513&#8211;37. 10.1038/s41574-018-0062-9. PubMed PMID: 30065268; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC6241236. eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41574-018-0062-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6241236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30065268</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flegal</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BMI and obesity trends in Chinese national survey data</article-title><source>Lancet (London England)</source><year>2021</year><volume>398</volume><issue>10294</issue><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)00892-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34217400</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Flegal KM. BMI and obesity trends in Chinese national survey data. Lancet (London England). 2021;398(10294):5&#8211;7. doi: 10.1016/s0140-6736(21)00892-8. PubMed PMID: 34217400; eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34217400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)00892-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashwell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Waist-to-height ratio is a better screening tool than waist circumference and BMI for adult cardiometabolic risk factors: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Obes Reviews: Official J Int Association Study Obes</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-789X.2011.00952.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22106927</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Ashwell M, Gunn P, Gibson S. Waist-to-height ratio is a better screening tool than waist circumference and BMI for adult cardiometabolic risk factors: systematic review and meta-analysis. Obes Reviews: Official J Int Association Study Obes. 2012;13(3):275&#8211;86. .x. PubMed PMID: 22106927; eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1467-789X.2011.00952.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22106927</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prospective associations of Waist-to-height ratio with Cardiovascular events in Postmenopausal women: results from the women&#8217;s Health Initiative</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2019</year><volume>42</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>e148</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc19-0612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31308018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6702600</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Lo K, Liu Q, Allison M, et al. Prospective associations of Waist-to-height ratio with Cardiovascular events in Postmenopausal women: results from the women&#8217;s Health Initiative. Diabetes Care. 2019;42(9):e148&#8211;9. 10.2337/dc19-0612. PubMed PMID: 31308018; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC6702600. eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31308018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/dc19-0612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6702600</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Positive association between weight-adjusted-waist index and hyperuricemia in patients with hypertension: the China H-type hypertension registry study</article-title><source>Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1007557</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2022.1007557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36277696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9582276</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Zhao P, Shi W, Shi Y, et al. Positive association between weight-adjusted-waist index and hyperuricemia in patients with hypertension: the China H-type hypertension registry study. Front Endocrinol (Lausanne). 2022;13:1007557. 10.3389/fendo.2022.1007557. PubMed PMID: 36277696; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC9582276. eng.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36277696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fendo.2022.1007557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9582276</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Deepak B, Sooyeun L, Hye Jin KJA. Antioxidants and Mechanistic Insights for Managing Dry Age-Related Macular Degeneration. 2024;13(5). 10.3390/antiox13050568. PubMed PMID: 38790673.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antiox13050568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11117704</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38790673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gang S, Yaqiong C, Jiahao C et al. The causal effects of lifestyle, circulating, pigment, and metabolic factors on early age-related macular degeneration: a comprehensive mendelian randomization study. 2024;22(1). 10.1186/s12967-024-05773-9. PubMed PMID: 39482668.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12967-024-05773-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11529295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39482668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>