<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Surg Open Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Surg Open Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3904</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">sopen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Surgery Open Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2589-8450</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10011477</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10011477.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10011477</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10011477</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36926590</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sopen.2023.02.003</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2589-8450(23)00005-2</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pain severity scale: A methodology for classifying postoperative pain severity by surgical procedure</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hitt</surname><given-names initials="J">James</given-names></name><email>James.Hitt@va.gov</email><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="cr0005" ref-type="corresp">&#8270;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names initials="R">Robert</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0015"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elkin</surname><given-names initials="P">Peter</given-names></name><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="af0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><aff id="af0005"><label>a</label>Veterans Healthcare Administration, Department of Anesthesiology, Western New York Healthcare System, Buffalo, NY, United States of America</aff><aff id="af0010"><label>b</label>Veterans Healthcare Administration, Department of Internal Medicine, Western New York Healthcare System, Buffalo, NY, United States of America</aff><aff id="af0015"><label>c</label>University at Buffalo, Jacobs School of Medicine, Department of Biomedical Informatics, Buffalo, NY, United States of America</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cr0005"><label>&#8270;</label>Corresponding author at: VA WNY Healthcare System, Department of Anesthesiology, 3595 Bailey Avenue, Buffalo, NY 14125, United States of America. <email>James.Hitt@va.gov</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">428193</issue-id><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>23</day><month>02</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-01-06 23:25:15.263"><day>06</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2023 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="ab0005"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Acute postoperative pain is common following many types of surgery, and a significant subset of patients experience severe pain, which can be difficult to manage and result in postoperative complications. Opioid agonists are commonly used to treat severe postoperative pain, but their use has been associated with adverse outcomes. This retrospective study uses data from the Veterans Administration Surgical Quality Improvement Project (VASQIP) database to develop a postoperative Pain Severity Scale (PSS) based on subjective pain reports and postoperative opioid requirements.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Postoperative pain scores and opioid prescription data were extracted from the VASQIP database for surgeries occurring between 2010 and 2020. Procedures were grouped by surgical Common Procedural Terminology (CPT) codes, and a total of 165,321 surgical procedures were examined, representing 1141 distinct CPT codes. <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>-means clustering analysis was used to group the surgeries based on 24-h maximum pain, 72-h average pain, and postoperative opioid prescriptions.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p><italic toggle="yes">K</italic>-means clustering analysis showed two optimal grouping strategies; one with 3 and the other with 5 groups. Both clustering strategies produced a PSS that categorized surgical procedures with generally increasing pain scores and opioid requirements. The 5-group PSS accurately captured typical postoperative pain experience across a range of procedures.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p><italic toggle="yes">K</italic>-means clustering produced a Pain Severity Scale that can distinguish typical postoperative pain for a large variety of surgical procedures based on subjective and objective clinical data. The PSS will facilitate research into the optimal postoperative pain management and could be used in the development of clinical decision support tools.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="ks0005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Data science</kwd><kwd>Postoperative outcomes</kwd><kwd>Postoperative pain</kwd><kwd>Opioid agonists</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0005"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0005">Acute postoperative pain is common following many types of surgery, with a significant subset of patients experiencing severe pain [<xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Clinicians treat postoperative pain based on their estimates of the pain severity associated with a given surgical procedure, as well as patient-reported subjective complaints and objective data like vital signs. Postoperative pain management guidelines and standards have been developed, including recommendations for the use of opioid-sparing analgesic adjuvant mediations and regional anesthesia techniques including epidural catheters and peripheral conduction nerve blocks [<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Despite these measures many patients require the use of opioid agonists, and the management of postoperative pain remains a challenge to clinicians [<xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], with some postulating that treating pain with opioid agonists may itself cause contribute to poor pain control by inducing opioid induced hyperalgesia in some patients [<xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Poorly controlled postsurgical pain starting on postoperative day one has been associated with postoperative complications, with high pain scores associated with a variety of postoperative complications [<xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and risk for the development of chronic pain [<xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. It has also been documented that many patients are dispensed excessive quantities of opioid medications after surgery, and a better understanding of typical postoperative patterns pain and opioid consumption can help inform efforts to evaluate appropriate postoperative prescription of opioids [<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p id="p0010">There are two main strategies for predicting and classifying the risk of postoperative pain: identifying patients at risk for severe postoperative pain based on patient-centered risk-factors or stratifying surgeries by their risk of postoperative pain using expert consensus or other methods. Patient centric risks include factors such as the presence of preoperative pain and opioid use, individual differences in the perception of painful stimuli [<xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], and psychological traits including anxiety and pain catastrophizing [<xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Surgery based risk stratification has been attempted by consensus methods and by prospective analysis. An example of a consensus method that has been previously used to classify surgical procedures in terms of their overall physiologic stress, is the operative stress score (OSS), but this categorization does not directly translate to anticipated postoperative pain. This scale, which classifies surgical procedures into 5 categories of physiologic stress, was developed using a modified Delphi method [<xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The OSS classification of physiologic stress associated with surgical aids in the prediction of adverse outcomes and mortality when combined with patient specific risk factors.</p><p id="p0015">The pain severity score (PSS) categorizes surgical procedures based on their expected level of postoperative pain, aiming to improve clinical intuition as well as provide a means to group and compare surgical procedures based on expected postoperative pain for research purposes. Previous analyses of postoperative pain have examined a small number of common surgeries that are known <italic toggle="yes">a priori</italic> to result in significant postoperative pain. Analysis of large surgical databases for the purposes of investigating how surgery relates to postoperative pain, opioid consumption, and chronic postsurgical pain are difficult to perform because of the large number of distinct surgical Current Procedural Terminology (CPT) codes, with significant variations in the extent of surgical tissue damage and resultant postoperative pain symptoms across the range of CPT codes. Understanding how a wide range of surgical procedures, as classified by CPT code, relate to postoperative pain will facilitate large scale retrospective reviews of postoperative pain and the efficacy of various treatments.</p><p id="p0020">The development of the PSS will facilitate future studies examining the prudent and effective use of postoperative opioid medications as well as the benefits of non-opioid pharmacologic compounds in treating acute postoperative pain. The effect of the anesthetic technique chosen for surgery and the effectiveness of regional anesthetic techniques could be examined using the PSS. In addition, by better understanding and classifying postoperative pain trajectories, we will be better able to understand the incidence of chronic postsurgical pain syndromes and the risk factors associated with development of this chronic pain state.</p><p id="p0025">The development of the PSS, which we describe in this paper, relied on a retrospective analysis of patient's experience of pain and its subsequent treatment over a large Veteran patient population. Patient experiences and outcomes were used to cluster surgical procedures by pain severity, without relying on expert consensus outside of the validation of the methodology. Previous studies have used longitudinal <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>-means clustering to identify and group patients in terms of their opioid use over time, using retrospective analysis of electronic health record (EHR) data [<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The approach used in the present study uses a similar methodology to identify groupings of surgical procedures by CPT codes based on pain outcomes using pain scores and opioid prescription data.</p><p id="p0030">This study presents an improvement over prior attempts to categorize postoperative pain for use in retrospective studies. These have largely been prospective analysis with small numbers of patients, numbering in the hundreds, due to the need for manual data collection [<xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. A large, prospective study compared pain on the first postoperative day for a variety of surgical procedures, analyzing data from over 50,000 patients and grouping surgeries into 179 groups. This study showed that counterintuitively some procedures thought of as less invasive generated unexpectedly high pain scores [<xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. While this study analyzed data from a large number of patients and surgical procedure types, data collection was limited to the first postoperative day and did not utilize prescription data to provide an objective measure of postoperative pain treatment.</p><p id="p0035">In the present study, <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-means clustering was used to analyze pain scores and opioid administration and prescription data group surgical procedures based on postoperative pain outcomes. Clustering was performed using three variables: the average maximum pain intensity in the first 24&#160;h, the time weighted average of pain scores for 72&#160;h, and the postoperative opioid requirements. The method presented here has not been previously described in the literature.</p></sec><sec id="s0010"><title>Methods</title><p id="p0040">Surgical cases were identified in the Veterans Administration Surgical Quality Improvement Project (VASQIP) database from between 2010 and 2020. Cases of American Society of Anesthesiology Physical Status Classification System (ASA Class) 5 or those with an emergency modifier were excluded along with patients who had repeat operation in the VASQIP database within 30&#160;days. The age range for the dataset was limited to patients between 20 and 75&#160;years of age. This yielded a total of 990,879 surgical cases for 3554 unique surgical Common Procedural Terminology (CPT) codes. Surgical CPT codes with less than 50 entries in the database were excluded (2212 CPT codes), resulting in a final analysis set of 1143 CPT codes. A final analysis dataset was created that included 200 randomly selected cases for CPT codes with greater than 200 occurrences and all entries for CPT codes less than 200 entries. The final dataset included 165,321 surgical procedures and 1141 unique surgical CPT codes. The study was approved by the VA Western New York Healthcare System IRB and a HIPPA consent waiver was granted.</p><p id="p0045">Pain scores were extracted from the Corporate Data Warehouse (CDW) vital signs table for 0 to 72&#160;h after surgery. The maximum pain score in the first 24&#160;h after surgery was determined. Average pain scores were calculated using the time weighted average pain score over a 72-h observation window [<xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. This technique takes the average value of adjacent pain observations and multiplies the value by the duration of time between the observations. The sum of the weighted pain scores is then divided by the total time of the observation window to determine the mean time-weighted pain score. The population mean for both maximum pain and time-weighted average pain was calculated for each CPT code patient group.</p><p id="p0050">Outpatient opioid prescriptions were extracted from the outpatient pharmacy table identifying any prescription with drug type equal to opioid analgesic from 1&#160;day before to 30&#160;days after surgery. Prescriptions from 1&#160;day before surgery were included because some patients received postoperative opioid prescriptions just before the date of surgery. Prescriptions for morphine, hydrocodone, oxycodone, tramadol, and codeine represented 99.0&#160;% of the perioperative prescriptions and were included in the analysis. Methadone and buprenorphine, medications typically used for the outpatient treatment of opioid use disorder, were prescribed in 0.7&#160;% and 0.3&#160;% of patients respectively, and those medications were excluded because their doses are not typically modified to treat acute postoperative pain and morphine equivalency conversions for those compounds are inaccurate.</p><p id="p0055">To facilitate comparison of opioid prescription dose across different pharmaceutical compounds, the medications listed in <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> were converted to milligrams of morphine equivalent dose (MED) using standard methodology [<xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The total MED of opioid medication dispensed in the 30&#160;days following surgery was calculated. A significant rightward skew of the data was found, and a log-transform of the dispensed opioid dose was calculated, and patients with a dose of zero were given a value of 1 to allow for the log-transform. Prescriptions that were more than 1.5 times the interquartile range over the 3rd quartile value (1650 MED) were truncated to be 1660 MED to lessen the impact of high doses opioid prescription used in a small subset of patients.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Outpatient postoperative opioid prescriptions.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0025">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Drug</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">n (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hydrocodone</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">90,042 (42.3&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Oxycodone</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">88,658 (41.7&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tramadol</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,270 (5.8&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Morphine</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9022 (4.2&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Codeine</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6314 (3.0&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hydromorphone</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4400 (2.1&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Methadone</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1487 (0.7&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Buprenorphine</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">574 (0.3&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Oxymorphone</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (0.0&#160;%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0060">Surgical CPT codes were assigned to groups of postoperative pain severity using k-means clustering. The mean maximum pain score occurring within the first 24&#160;h, the mean 72-h time weighted pain score, and the mean of the log-transformed 30-day opioid dose were used as the three postoperative pain indicators. The mean values for the population of patients grouped by surgical CPT codes were calculated for each of the three indicators, and the postoperative pain variable vectors were scaled to a mean of 0 and standard deviation of 1. <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>-means clustering was then used to divide the surgical CPT codes into groups using the scaled postoperative pain indicators. The <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>-means algorithm is an unsupervised learning algorithm that seeks to divide the group of surgical CPT codes into clusters that minimize the difference within a grouping and maximizes the difference between groups.</p><p id="p0065">In a given dataset, the <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-means algorithm groups observations in the data into a variable number cohesive clusters by calculating similarities between the different dimensions for each observation as measured by squared Euclidean distance [<xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The goal of the algorithm is to assign a grouping label for each observation that minimizes the difference within groups and maximizes the difference between groups. The optimal number of groupings (<italic toggle="yes">K</italic>) is not known <italic toggle="yes">a priori</italic> in this analysis technique.</p><p id="p0070">Many methods for determining the optimal number of clusters have been proposed. We first used the &#8220;elbow method&#8221; that examines the total within grouping sum of squares (WSS) across a range of <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> clusters. The WSS decreases monotonically as the number of clusters increases, and the optimal number of clusters is the point where the curve begins to flatten, indicating that further increases in the number of clusters results in small reductions in the WSS.</p><p id="p0075">Because the elbow method uses a subjective determination of the optimal number of clusters, other more objective methods have been proposed. We next used the gap statistic, which compares the change in within-cluster dispersion to a reference null distribution [<xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The value of the gap statistic indicates the degree to which clustering improves the dispersion measurement when compared to a random distribution, with larger values representing significant improvements over that expected with a random distribution. We examined the gap statistic across a range of clusters from 1 to 10 and noted the local maximum.</p></sec><sec id="s0015"><title>Results</title><p id="p0080">The patient demographics included a mean age of 57.1&#160;years (standard deviation of 12.7), and a median age of 61 with an interquartile range (IQR) of 17&#160;years. The age range was from 20 to 75. The distribution of the American Society of Anesthesiologists Physical Status Classification (ASA), a score assigned by the anesthesiologist reflecting the extent of comorbid disease, is shown in <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Other demographic characteristics are typical for a VA population.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Demographics of the sample population.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0030">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">ASA class</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">n (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4751 (2.9&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">44,897 (27.2&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100,950 (61.1&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,723 (8.9&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#8232;&#8232;</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ethnicity</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">n (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not Hispanic or Latino</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">147,248 (89.1&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hispanic or Latino</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9620 (5.8&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Missing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3437 (2.1&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Declined to Answer</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2563 (1.6&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unknown by Patient</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2453 (1.5&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#8232;&#8232;</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age: median (IQR)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age: Mean (sd)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">61 (17)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.1 (12.7)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#8232;&#8232;</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">n (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23,102 (14.0&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">142,219 (86.0&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#8232;&#8232;</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">n (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">White</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">115,343 (69.8&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Black or African American</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30,793 (18.6&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Missing</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7492 (4.5&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Declined to Answer</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5276 (3.2&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unknown by Patient</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2518 (1.5&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">American Indian or Alaska Native</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1658 (1.0&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1290 (0.8&#160;%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asian</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">940 (0.6&#160;%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0085">To determine the optimal number of clusters we first examined the effect of increasing number of clusters (<italic toggle="yes">k)</italic> using the within-cluster sum of square (WSS) dispersion metric (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). There was an inflection point in WSS at 3 clusters. The gap statistic was then calculated for the same range of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>, with two local maxima apparent at 3 clusters and 5 clusters (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).<fig id="f0005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Elbow plot showing the reduction in the total within-cluster sum of square dispersion metric for increasing number of clusters, with an apparent inflection point around 3 clusters. A second local optimum at 5 clusters was found using the gap statistic (see <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).</p></caption><alt-text id="al0005">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig><fig id="f0010" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>The gap statistic analysis shows a local maximum at a <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> of 3 clusters with a second peak at 5 clusters.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0010">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0090">The general consensus was that 3 clusters would be statistically optimal but the secondary peak at 5 clusters revealed by the gap stat analysis could add important information, so we proceeded with k-means clustering using a <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> of 3 and 5 clusters because of the potential for clinical utility in an expended number of PSS categories.</p><p id="p0095">The clustering of maximum pain scores, time-weighted average pain scores, and the mean postoperative opioid dose is plotted in <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>. The time weighted average pain (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>A) increased with each increase in the PSS grouping, but the maximum pain intensity (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>B) was low in the low PSS group and similar in the moderate and high PSS groups. Postoperative opioid prescriptions (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>C) were higher in the high PSS group and similar between the low and moderate PSS groups.<fig id="f0015" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Three level PSS. The mean and standard deviation of the clustering variables shows a general progression to higher pain scores and opioid doses with increasing PSS. Time-weighted mean pain (A) increases for each increase in PSS. The 24-h maximum pain (B) is lowest in the low PSS group and similar between the moderate and high PSS groups. Postoperative opioid prescription (C) is high in the high PSS group and similar in the low and moderate PSS groups.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0015">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0100">The 5-factor cluster analysis showed a similar gradual progression of time-weighted mean pain scores with increasing PSS (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>A). Maximum 24-h pain (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>B) was low in PSS groups 1 and 2 and high in groups 3 through 5, with a trend towards the highest maximum pain scores in PSS group 5. Postoperative opioid prescription values (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>C) generally followed the same trend, with the exception of PSS groups 2 and 3, where PSS group 3 had higher pain scores but lower levels of opioid prescription as compared to PSS group 2.<fig id="f0020" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Five level PSS. The mean and standard deviation of the clustering variables shows a general progression to higher pain scores and opioid doses with increasing PSS. Time-weighted mean pain (A) increases for each increase in PSS. The 24-h maximum pain (B) is lowest in PSS groups 1 and 2 and highest in groups 3 through 5. Postoperative opioid prescription (C) generally increases with increasing PSS, with the exception of group 3 that is associated with lower postoperative opioid prescriptions and higher pain scores.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0020">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0105">In general, there was clinician consensus that the PSS system accurately grouped postoperative pain severity for the various CPT surgery codes. The 5-factor <italic toggle="yes">k</italic>-means clustering provided additional discrimination of postoperative pain for similar procedures. For example, the 5-factor PSS separates shoulder surgeries based on extent of tissue damage, ranking arthroscopic shoulder surgeries in group 2 and open procedures involving arthroplasty in group 5. The 5-factor analysis associated the repair of a recurrent, incarcerated inguinal hernia (CPT 49521) with PSS group 3 as compared to laparoscopic repair of recurrent inguinal hernia (CPT 49651; PSS 2) and laparoscopic repair of initial inguinal hernia (CPT 49650; PSS 1).</p></sec><sec id="s0020"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0110"><italic toggle="yes">K</italic>-means cluster analysis identified 3 and 5 grouping strategies for 1141 surgical CPT codes based on postoperative pain reports and opioid prescription. Manual examination of common CPT code descriptions within each group by anesthesiologists experienced in the treatment of postoperative pain revealed consistent and reasonable groupings of procedures. The PSS appears to effectively represent typical postoperative pain and opioid requirements across a variety of surgical procedures, and the resulting table of surgical CPT codes listed by PSS can be applied to any large-scale review that uses warehoused electronic health record or claims data to identify surgical procedures. In addition, the PSS may be useful for surgeons and anesthesiologists to improve their clinical intuition about the painfulness of a given surgery.</p><p id="p0115">The 5-factor PSS results in additional groupings that distinguish varying levels of surgical trauma in procedures of the same general category, which could be useful when examining large databases of surgical outcomes or postoperative opioid prescriptions.</p><p id="p0120">There are several issues with data quality inherent in retrospective database reviews and overall availability of postoperative pain data in the VA CDW database. Patients undergoing outpatient surgery have a paucity of pain reports, often only 1 or 2 values, which required excluding them from analysis. Post-operative care unit (PACU) pain scores were not included because they are not captured in the data warehouse, likely due to the delayed deployment of digital record keeping in that area. Pain reports from patients admitted to the ICU after surgery were also limited in availability depending on the extent of electronic charting in the various ICU settings. In addition, CPT codes are highly granular, and this study looks at surgeries without grouping related surgeries by CPT code.</p><p id="p0125">Beyond the issues with data quality inherent to many informatics studies, this study has several additional limitations. This analysis used data from patients receiving care in the Veteran's Health Administration (VHA) system, and the demographics of this population may not generalize to other populations of patients. In addition, isolated pain scores are recorded without clinical context and do not capture all the nuanced complexity of subjective pain experiences. For example, pain reports captured at rest and during movement typically differ, with more severe pain being experienced during dynamic activity such as ambulation or deep breathing. The pain experience is multidimensional, with motivational and affective components influencing the subjective experience of pain. Various psychosocial factors can significantly modify suffering associate with pain, with pain catastrophizing and underlying anxiety being correlated to higher postoperative pain scores [<xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], and these aspects of pain were not captured in this analysis. Pain data stored in the VA CDW, like most EHR data repositories, includes only pain scores quantified using a numerical rating scale from 1 to 10 without the larger clinical context of the subjective report.</p><p id="p0130">Opioid doses were collected from outpatient prescription data and may not represent that dose required by the patient for the adequate treatment of pain. Both under and over prescribing may have occurred. There is evidence that a significant portion of patients do not use all the opioid analgesic medication prescribed for postoperative pain across a variety of surgical subspecialties [<xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Analysis of the outpatient pharmacy records did not distinguish between prescriptions of opioids for acute post-procedural pain and long-term prescriptions for chronic pain. Prescriptions for medications commonly used in the outpatient treatment of opioid use disorder, including methadone and buprenorphine formulations, were not included in the analysis, although the prescription rates for those medications was low for the patients included in the analysis.</p><p id="p0135">The Pain Severity Scale classifies postoperative pain for a wide range of CPT code defined surgical procedures. We plan to extend the analysis to other populations of patients in a variety of regional and national contexts to account for the many regional and societal differences in postoperative pain management practices and patient expectations. The Pain Severity Scale can be further refined through consensus review of the groupings by a diverse group of clinicians who are experts in postoperative pain treatment.</p></sec><sec id="s0025"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0140">We anticipate that the development of the PSS will facilitate research into the optimal management of opioid and adjuvant pain medications around the time of surgery. PSS was developed to facilitate retrospective research, but it could also be integrated into clinical decision support tools used in the perioperative period to stratify patients for postoperative pain risk at the point of care and guide treatment tailored towards expected pain severity outcomes. There have been attempts to create computerized clinical decision support to assist clinicians in treating post-operative pain based on specific surgical procedures. The development of PROSPECT, which publishes procedure specific guidelines in a web-based format, relies on expert review of qualitative and quantitative studies for individual procedures [<xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. As with this decision support tool, current postoperative pain management and decision making regarding opioid prescription relies on expert consensus [<xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The PSS was derived from the analysis of postoperative pain outcomes across a large patient population and diverse set of CPT surgical code with the goal of developing precise procedure-level recommendations. The validity of the PSS will be improved with extension of the analysis to more diverse patient populations and expert consensus review of the categorical groupings.</p><p id="p0145">We have demonstrated how <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>-means clustering can estimate postoperative pain severity, using maximum 24-h pain, time-weighted average pain calculated of 72&#160;h, and cumulative 30-day postoperative opioid prescription as variables. This analysis was performed using 3 and 5 groupings for postoperative pain severity, which can be helpful both for informing clinicians and for analyzing large clinical databases for retrospective analysis. The development of PSS is the first comprehensive retrospective analysis of postoperative pain across a large number of surgical procedures as defined by CPT codes.</p><p id="p0150">Interest in improving postoperative pain management has been recently renewed with the widespread adoption of enhanced recovery after surgery (ERAS) protocols for specific surgical procedures [<xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. These guidelines, which include recommendations for postoperative pain management, have been shown to improve time to recovery and decrease the rate of procedural complications. In order to develop patient centered recommendations for the management of opioid and non-opioid analgesics across the perioperative timespan, large scale informatics research will require a method to classify surgical procedures by pain severity. We have shown that the development of the pain severity score and classification of CPT codes into 3 or 5 clusters according to this score has internal consistency and predictive value. Future research will expand this analysis to more diverse populations and utilize this methodology to inform clinical practice with respect to the management of analgesics in the perioperative period.</p></sec><sec id="s0030"><title>Summary</title><p id="p0155">A postoperative Pain Severity Scale (PSS) was created by analyzing postoperative pain and opioid prescriptions for a variety of surgical procedures. Better understanding of relative postoperative pain for a large variety of surgical procedures will assist in establishing best practices for postoperative pain management and promoting opioid stewardship.</p></sec><sec id="s0035"><title>Funding/financial support statement</title><p id="p0160">This work has been supported in part by grants from <funding-source id="gts0005">NIH</funding-source> NLM T15LM012495, NIAAA R21AA026954, R33AA0226954 and <funding-source id="gts0010"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100006108</institution-id><institution>NCATS</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> UL1TR001412. This study was funded in part by the <funding-source id="gts0015"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000738</institution-id><institution>Department of Veterans Affairs</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>.</p></sec><sec id="s0040"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0165"><bold>James Hitt</bold>: Conceptualization, methodology, software, validation, formal analysis, data curation, writing &#8211; original draft/editing, visualization.</p><p id="p0170"><bold>Robert Lee</bold>: Conceptualization, writing &#8211; review/editing.</p><p id="p0175"><bold>Peter Elkin</bold>: Conceptualization, writing &#8211; review/editing, supervision, funding acquisition.</p></sec><sec id="s0045"><title>Ethics approval</title><p id="p0180">The study was approved by the VA Western New York Healthcare System IRB and a HIPPA consent waiver was granted. All research data was stored and analyzed on secure VA research servers.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p id="p0185">The authors have no direct or indirect financial or personal relationships, interests, or affiliations relevant to the subject matter of this publication.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bi0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bb0005"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Small</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laycock</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute postoperative pain management</article-title><source>Br J Surg</source><volume>107</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>e70</fpage><lpage>e80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31903595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/bjs.11477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0010"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenquist</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postoperative pain guidelines</article-title><source>Regional Anesthesia &amp; Pain Medicine</source><volume>28</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12945020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1098-7339(03)00035-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0015"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Leon-Casasola</surname><given-names>O.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bickler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Management of postoperative pain: a clinical practice guideline from the American Pain Society, the American Society of Regional Anesthesia and Pain Medicine, and the American Society of Anesthesiologists&#8217; Committee on Regional Anesthesia, Executive Committee, and Administrative Council</article-title><source>J Pain</source><volume>17</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26827847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jpain.2015.12.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0020"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raja</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of acute postoperative pain</article-title><source>Lancet.</source><volume>377</volume><issue>9784</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>2215</fpage><lpage>2225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21704871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60245-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0025"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinbroum</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postoperative hyperalgesia-a clinically applicable narrative review</article-title><source>Pharmacol Res</source><volume>120</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28365208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.phrs.2017.02.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0030"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Boekel</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warl&#233;</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielen</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vissers</surname><given-names>K.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Sande</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bronkhorst</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationship between postoperative pain and overall 30-day complications in a broad surgical population: an observational study</article-title><source>Ann Surg</source><volume>269</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>856</fpage><lpage>865</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29135493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/SLA.0000000000002583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0035"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glare</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aubrey</surname><given-names>K.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Myles</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transition from acute to chronic pain after surgery</article-title><source>Lancet.</source><volume>393</volume><issue>10180</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1537</fpage><lpage>1546</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30983589</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(19)30352-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0040"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sennett</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hemmons</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patient-reported opioid consumption and pain intensity after common orthopedic and urologic surgical procedures with use of an automated text messaging system</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e213243</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.3243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7994954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33764425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0045"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bicket</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pronovost</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>G.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prescription opioid analgesics commonly unused after surgery: a systematic review</article-title><source>JAMA Surg</source><volume>152</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1066</fpage><lpage>1071</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28768328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamasurg.2017.0831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5701659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0050"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>M.U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mjobo</surname><given-names>H.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>P.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prediction of postoperative pain: a systematic review of predictive experimental pain studies</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><volume>112</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>1494</fpage><lpage>1502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20460988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/ALN.0b013e3181dcd5a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0055"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Granot</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferber</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The roles of pain catastrophizing and anxiety in the prediction of postoperative pain intensity: a prospective study</article-title><source>Clin J Pain</source><volume>21</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>445</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16093750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/01.ajp.0000135236.12705.2d</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0060"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shinall</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arya</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Youk</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varley</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Massarweh</surname><given-names>N.N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of Preoperative Patient Frailty and Operative Stress with Postoperative Mortality</article-title><source>JAMA Surg</source><volume>155</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e194620</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamasurg.2019.4620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6865246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31721994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0065"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mullin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zola</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacKenzie</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brickman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Longitudinal K-means approaches to clustering and analyzing EHR opioid use trajectories for clinical subtypes</article-title><source>J Biomed Inform</source><volume>122</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">103889</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jbi.2021.103889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9035269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34411708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0070"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gkotsi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petsas</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakalis</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fotas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Triantafyllidis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vouros</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pain point system scale (PPSS): a method for postoperative pain estimation in retrospective studies</article-title><source>J Pain Res</source><volume>5</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23152699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/JPR.S37154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3496529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0075"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerbershagen</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aduckathil</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Wijck</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peelen</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalkman</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meissner</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pain intensity on the first day after surgery: a prospective cohort study comparing 179 surgical procedures</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><volume>118</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>934</fpage><lpage>944</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23392233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/ALN.0b013e31828866b3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0080"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peperzak</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinges</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bollag</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postoperative pain and opioid dose requirements in patients on sublingual buprenorphine: a retrospective cohort study for comparison between postoperative continuation and discontinuation of buprenorphine</article-title><source>Clin J Pain</source><volume>38</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/AJP.0000000000000996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34723862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0085"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prevention NCfI</surname></name></person-group><part-title>Control. CDC compilation of benzodiazepines, muscle relaxants, stimulants, zolpidem, and opioid analgesics with oral morphine milligram equivalent conversion factors, 2018 version</part-title><year>2018</year><publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Atlanta, GA</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0090"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Obeidat</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Losardo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Twelve frequently asked questions about growth curve modeling</article-title><source>J Cogn Dev</source><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21743795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/15248371003699969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3131138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0095"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walther</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastie</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating the number of clusters in a data set via the gap statistic</article-title><source>J R Stat Soc Series B Stat Methodology</source><volume>63</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2001</year><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>423</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0100"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kehlet</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>H.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Camu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prospect</surname><given-names>Working G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PROSPECT: evidence-based, procedure-specific postoperative pain management</article-title><source>Best Pract Res Clin Anaesthesiol</source><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17489225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bpa.2006.12.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0105"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Rourke</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keshock</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boxhorn</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Correll</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Glasser</surname><given-names>A.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gazelka</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Preoperative management of opioid and nonopioid analgesics: Society for Perioperative Assessment and Quality Improvement (SPAQI) consensus statement</article-title><source>Mayo Clin Proc</source><volume>96</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>1325</fpage><lpage>1341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33618850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.mayocp.2020.06.045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0110"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Overton</surname><given-names>H.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanna</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruhn</surname><given-names>W.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutfless</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bicket</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Makary</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Opioid-prescribing guidelines for common surgical procedures: an expert panel consensus</article-title><source>J Am Coll Surg</source><volume>227</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30118896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2018.07.659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6353661</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0115"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>G.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kehlet</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postoperative pain management in the era of ERAS: an overview</article-title><source>Best Pract Res Clin Anaesthesiol</source><volume>33</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31785712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bpa.2019.07.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>