<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Exp Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Exp Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">365</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">springeropen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Clinical and Experimental Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1591-8890</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1591-9528</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Springer</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10618386</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10618386.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10618386</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10618386</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37219793</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10238-023-01094-1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1094</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Clinical significance of serum antinuclear antibodies in patients with autoimmune hepatitis and comorbidity</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="H">Hui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuqi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="P">Peng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="X">Xin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yunyun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="X">Xin</given-names></name><address><email>leaxin@ccmu.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.24696.3f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0369 153X</institution-id><institution>Department of Center of Integrated Traditional Chinese and Western Medicine, Beijing Ditan Hospital, </institution><institution>Capital Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02v51f717</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.11135.37</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2256 9319</institution-id><institution>Department of Center of Integrated Traditional Chinese and Western Medicine, </institution><institution>Peking University Ditan Teaching Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>23</volume><issue>7</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">448283</issue-id><fpage>3453</fpage><lpage>3463</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>23</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>02</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-01-26 19:25:11.183"><day>26</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10238_2023_Article_1094.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Autoimmune hepatitis (AIH) is often complicated with immune diseases, which greatly affected the course and clinical outcome of AIH. We aimed to systematically assess clinical characteristics, prognosis in autoimmune hepatitis accompanied by immune diseases. Clinical records of 358 patients with AIH from Beijing Ditan Hospital in China were retrospectively reviewed. The clinical features of AIH with immune diseases were compared retrospectively, including clinical characteristics, prognosis and outcome. Prevalence of immune diseases in patients with AIH was 26.5%. Connective tissue disease (CTD) was the commonest immune diseases associated with AIH (33/358, 9.2%), and the incidence of primary biliary cholangitis (PBC) and thyroid dysfunction (TD) was low (4.7% and 8.5%, respectively). At diagnosis, AIH-PBC patients had higher IgM and ALP, lower weight, Hgb, ALT and AFP (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Meanwhile, AIH-CTD patients had lower mean platelet volume, serum K and triglyceride (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). AIH-TD patients had a lower proportion of ANA positive (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The overall survival time of AIH-TD was significantly shorter than AIH patients (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0011), but there were no differences in AIH-PBC and AIH-CTD. Furthermore, ANA negative (<italic toggle="yes">HR</italic>: 0.21, 95%<italic toggle="yes">CI</italic> 0.13&#8211;0.35, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001) can be a factor to predict the poor prognosis of AIH, and also in AIH-TD patients. About 26.5% of AIH patients had at least one immune disease, and TD coexisted with AIH impaired patients&#8217; survival. ANA negative can be used as an independent indicator to predict the poor prognosis of AIH and AIH-TD.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Autoimmune hepatitis</kwd><kwd>Immune disease</kwd><kwd>ANA</kwd><kwd>Prognosis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Innovation Team and Talents Cultivation Program of National Administration of Traditional Chinese Medicine</institution></funding-source><award-id>ZYYCXTD-C-202006</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the Beijing Hospitals Authority&#8217;s Ascent Plan</institution></funding-source><award-id>DFL20221601</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Xin</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the Natural Science Foundation of Beijing</institution></funding-source><award-id>7212053</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Xin</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2023</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par40">Autoimmune hepatitis (AIH) is an immune-mediated inflammatory diseases of hepatic parenchymal cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Its pathogenesis is complex, which is different from viral infection, alcohol injury and fat deposition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. AIH is mainly manifested as interface hepatitis infiltrated by lymphocytes and plasma cells, resulting in damage of liver parenchyma cells, subsequent fibrosis, cirrhosis and eventually liver failure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par41">Most patients with AIH are of young women initially, but since the late 1990s, more and more studies reported that AIH could occur in different age, even in over 60&#160;years old [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Some studies have also found that AIH can be found in different geographical regions, including Europe, the North America, China, India and New Zealand [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. In recent years, the rising incidence of AIH has aroused widespread concern. It was reported that the contemporary incidence rate in European countries increases from 0.4/100,000 to 2.39/100,000 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. A prospective study from New Zealand showed that the incidence of AIH increased by 1.93/100,000 from 2008 to 2016 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Similarly, a recent study from the US reported an AIH prevalence as high as 31.2/100,000 based on a commercial database from 2014 to 2019 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. All above studies indicated that AIH was distributed in people of any age and race. Although AIH is relatively rare, the clinical burden is disproportionately high compared with the morbidity and prevalence of the population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], which brings a serious burden to the patients.</p><p id="Par42">The most common manifestations of AIH are elevated serum aminotransferase level, hyper IgG and positive serum autoantibodies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. In view of the fact that AIH is mainly caused by immune-mediated liver diseases, it can involve multiple organs throughout the body. It is shown that about 30&#8211;35% of AIH patients have extrahepatic immune diseases, such as primary sclerosing cholangitis (PSC), thyroiditis, Sjogren's syndrome and other immune diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. A study from Italy showed that about 42% of AIH patients were complicated with extrahepatic immune diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Notably, it is presented that about 50% of children and young patients had overlapping phenotype in the west [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. The coexistence of immune diseases makes the diagnosis and treatment of AIH more difficult, and affects the prognosis and the life quality of patients. The coexistence of such diseases often increases the difficulty of AIH diagnosis and treatment.</p><p id="Par43">In view of the above situation and the lack of prognostic factors related to AIH and AIH complication, we collected the clinical characteristics of AIH and comorbidity in China from a clinical and research center for liver disease. In this research, a formed database was established, which records AIH patients admitted in Beijing Ditan Hospital since 2008, and these are the main data resources of the research. The clinical features of AIH complicated immune diseases including baseline characteristics, overall survival and vital status were analyzed, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study population</title><p id="Par44">A total of 358 consecutive patients, who had been diagnosed with AIH from October 2008 to May 2020 at Beijing Ditan Hospital, were included in this study. All patients were negative for hepatitis B or C infections. Patients who were heavy alcohol drinkers (&gt;&#8201;25&#160;g/day of alcohol), with Wilson&#8217;s disease or nonalcoholic fatty liver disease, with extrahepatic biliary disease, chronic liver disease other than AIH, taking drugs with known hepatotoxicity and a history of malignancy within 5&#160;years were excluded. Patients with incomplete data were also excluded. This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of Beijing Ditan Hospital.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Diagnosis of AIH</title><p id="Par45">For the diagnosis of AIH, both the revised IAIHG criteria and the simplified IAIHG criteria were used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. If a patient met any of the criteria, then the patient was determined as a probable or definite AIH patient; at least 10 points for the revised criteria and 6 points for the simplified criteria.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Definition of immune diseases</title><p id="Par46">All patients were evaluated for the presence of immune diseases and assessed systemic involvement. PBC was diagnosed based on the American Association for the Study of Liver Diseases (AASLD) 2009 Practice Guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The diagnostic criteria of Sj&#168;ogren&#8217;s syndrome (SS) was based on the LeRoy classification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]; The diagnosis of rheumatoid arthritis (RA) was made on the basis of revised classification criteria of the American College of Rheumatology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]; Systemic Lupus Erythematosus (SLE) was diagnosed according to the revised ACR SLE classification criteria of the Systemic Lupus Collaborating Clinics (SLICC; 2009) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. The SS, SLE and RA were classified as connective tissue disease (CTD). Thyroid dysfunction (TD) was based on the combination of clinical features, the presence of serum antibodies against thyroid antigens (mainly TSH, TPOAb and TGAb) and thyroid sonography [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Data collection and follow-up</title><p id="Par47">Clinical data and quality indicators related to laboratory testing were obtained through inpatient medical record system. Survival time was determined by follow-up. All patients were followed up by telephone or in-hospital follow-up review until death appears or until December 31, 2021, whichever comes first.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par48">Data was analyzed by using the SPSS statistical software (Version 19.0. IBM Corp, Armonk, NY, USA) and R Studio software (Version 3.5.1).</p><p id="Par49">Continuous variables were expressed as mean&#8201;&#177;&#8201;standard deviation (SD) or median (range) and categorical variables were presented as frequencies or ratios. Nonparametric variables were presented as median with interquartile range. Comparison of outcomes between groups was performed by using Student&#8217;s t-test or Mann&#8211;Whitney U test for continuous data; statistical significance for categorical data was determined by using the Chi-square test or Wilcoxon rank-sum test. Univariate and multivariate cox regression analysis was used to determine the independent influencing factors related to AIH prognosis, and the hazard ratio (HR) and 95% confidence interval (CI) of the prognostic factors were shown in the forest map. Kaplan&#8211;Meier method was used to analyze the survival of AIH and comorbidity. All statistical tests were two-sided, and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Clinical characteristics</title><p id="Par50">A total of 358 consecutive patients with AIH were enrolled from Beijing Ditan Hospital between October 2008 and May 2020. At diagnosis, the average age of AIH patients was about 55&#160;years old. Among the 358 consecutive AIH patients, 81 patients complicated with one immune disease and 14 patients complicated with over two immune diseases. According to the types of immune diseases, it is mainly divided into four groups: AIH group (n&#8201;=&#8201;277), AIH-PBC group (n&#8201;=&#8201;17), AIH-CTD group (n&#8201;=&#8201;33) and AIH-TD group (n&#8201;=&#8201;31). Basic demographic information is presented in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Actually, the AIH-CHD group (9%) has the highest proportion in AIH complicated with immune diseases, followed by AIH-TD group (8.6%), and it is interesting that hypothyroidism (4.7%) accounts for the largest proportion in AIH-TD group. Therefore, AIH patients complicated with immune diseases are common, especially CTD and TD.<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>AIH patients complicated with immune diseases</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Comorbidities</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of AIH patients, n (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Primary biliary cholangitis (PBC)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (4.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Connective tissue disease (CTD)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (9.0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Sjogren&#8217;s syndrome</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (3.6%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Systemic lupus erythematosus</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (1.3%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Rheumatoid arthritis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (2.2%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Overlapping ctd</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (1.9%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Thyroid dysfunction (TD)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (8.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Graves&#8217;s thyroiditis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.8%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Hashimoto&#8217;s thyroiditis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.8%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Hypothyroidism</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (4.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;Thyroid nodule</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (2.2%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par51">The baseline characteristics of the patients with AIH, AIH-PBC, AIH-CTD and AIH-TD is presented in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Interestingly, it is shown that the weight, ALT and AFP levels in AIH group are higher than AIH-PBC group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.01, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.028 and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.034, respectively), while IgM and ALP levels are significantly lower (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.044 and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.003, respectively). In addition, it is also found that AIH-CTD patients showed a lower level of serum K, MPV and TG (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.029, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.038 and<italic toggle="yes"> P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.035, respectively). The proportion of ANA-positive in AIH-TD patients is significantly less than that of AIH patients (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.02). None of the patients have a positive test for LKM-1.<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of the patients with AIH, AIH-PBC, AIH-CTD and AIH-TD</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AIH (n&#8201;=&#8201;277)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AIH-PBC (n&#8201;=&#8201;17)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AIH-CTD (n&#8201;=&#8201;33)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AIH-TD (n&#8201;=&#8201;31)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P-</italic>value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">243/277(87.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14/17(82.4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28/33(84.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30/31(96.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (years)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56(48&#8211;64)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58(41.5&#8211;66)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55(48&#8211;62.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57(43&#8211;63)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Weight (kg)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60(55&#8211;68)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55(48.38&#8211;58.25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60(52.63&#8211;65.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.5(55&#8211;67)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.010*/NS&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IgG (g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.4(18.3&#8211;25.78)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.6(16.4&#8211;34.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.6(19.5&#8211;26.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.4(18.75&#8211;29.25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IgA (g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.435(2.38&#8211;4.77)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.45(2.92&#8211;6.25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.97(2.95&#8211;5.14)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.45(2.28&#8211;4.30)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IgM (g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.53(0.98&#8211;2.28)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.71(1.46&#8211;3.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.26(0.9&#8211;2.13)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.28(0.97&#8211;2.09)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.044*/NS&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WBC (10<sup>9</sup>/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.52(3.37&#8211;5.88)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.04(3.45&#8211;6.13)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.17(3.38&#8211;5.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.02(3.52&#8211;6.54)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NE% (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54.32&#8201;&#177;&#8201;12.26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.96&#8201;&#177;&#8201;18.71</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.95&#8201;&#177;&#8201;16.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.63&#8201;&#177;&#8201;11.08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MO% (%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.8(7.58&#8211;12.38)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.35(6.05&#8211;10.13)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.93(7.45&#8211;12.06)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.9(7.67&#8211;11.37)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hb(g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">118.6(103.28&#8211;131)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">105(95&#8211;119.15)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">112.9(101.25&#8211;125.85)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">117.25(103.8&#8211;136.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.028*/NS&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PLT (10<sup>9</sup>/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">146(93.4&#8211;200.53)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95.8(60.25&#8211;206.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">121.3(83.4&#8211;198.85)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">165.7(120.03&#8211;217.25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MPV (fl)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.1(9&#8211;11.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.7(9.05&#8211;11.25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.3(8.8&#8211;10.61)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.5(8.95&#8211;12)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8225;/0.038&#8224;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">K (mmol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.61(3.35&#8211;3.89)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.515(3.05&#8211;3.80)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.37(3.09&#8211;3.84)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.575(3.19&#8211;3.81)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8225;/0.029&#8224;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Na (mmol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">139.4(137.3&#8211;141.38)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">138.45(135.78&#8211;141.15)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">139.5(136.6&#8211;141.25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">139.9(138.68&#8211;140.65)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phos (mmol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.11(0.97&#8211;1.21)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.205(0.95&#8211;1.29)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.06(0.94&#8211;1.16)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.15(1.04&#8211;1.27)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">UREA (mmol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.96(3.24&#8211;5.28)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.28(3.46&#8211;5.17)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.24(3.295&#8211;5.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.065(3.19&#8211;4.60)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CREA (umol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57(50.05&#8211;65.65)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.55(55.55&#8211;69.25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58.2(52&#8211;69.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.5(47.75&#8211;78.08)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">URCA (umol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">235(189&#8211;291)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">195(150&#8211;284.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">220(178.25&#8211;254.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">224.5(159&#8211;293.75)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GLU (mmol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.32(4.675&#8211;6.17)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.22(4.425&#8211;6.84)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.4(4.63&#8211;6.95)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.09(4.75&#8211;6.23)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ALT (U/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">124.6(41.75&#8211;370.35)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.4(25.7&#8211;109.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80.6(31.85&#8211;353.45)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">162.8(58&#8211;354.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.034*/NS&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AST (U/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">134.2(56.75&#8211;327.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">110(60.7&#8211;172.45)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98(41.35&#8211;373.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">193.4(100.9&#8211;337.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TBIL (umol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.25(16.73&#8211;109.68)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.6(22.75&#8211;73.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.9(15.45&#8211;92.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.8(27.3&#8211;134.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DBIL (umol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.8(8.2&#8211;85.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.1(13.1&#8211;49.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.9(6.75&#8211;62.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.5(12.55&#8211;110.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ALB (g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.61&#8201;&#177;&#8201;5.45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.96&#8201;&#177;&#8201;7.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.28&#8201;&#177;&#8201;4.94</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.03&#8201;&#177;&#8201;5.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GLO (g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.1(35.95&#8211;44)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.9(34.8&#8211;53.65)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.9(35.9&#8211;48.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.3(34.7&#8211;44.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GGT (U/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">147.7(61.2&#8211;274.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">154.95(84.78&#8211;530.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">139.75(63&#8211;233.28)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103.2(74.9&#8211;246.15)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ALP (U/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">130.2(90.9&#8211;195.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">246.95(129.55&#8211;789.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">113.5(87.83&#8211;257.08)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">119.9(86.15&#8211;177.75)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003*/NS&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TBA (umol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54.9(19&#8211;146.45)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88.3(24.28&#8211;130.98)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.95(9.33&#8211;127.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80.6(18.5&#8211;183.55)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TC (mmol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.76(3.07&#8211;4.35)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.635(2.22&#8211;4.94)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.32(2.91&#8211;4.045)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.5(2.63&#8211;4.61)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TG (mmol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.29(0.84&#8211;1.81)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.13(0.69&#8211;1.96)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.96(0.75&#8211;1.32)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.17(0.85&#8211;2.46)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8225;/0.035&#8224;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HDLC (mmol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.71(0.32&#8211;1.03)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.84(0.55&#8211;1.10)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.91(0.48&#8211;1.11)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.56(0.31&#8211;0.96)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LDLC (mmol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2(1.52&#8211;2.53)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.225(1.41&#8211;3.74)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8(1.31&#8211;2.28)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.09(1.32&#8211;2.43)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PT (s)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.1(11.9&#8211;15)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.9(11.55&#8211;14.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.95(11.2&#8211;15.55)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.4(11.35&#8211;14.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">APTT (s)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.4(32.6&#8211;39.75)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.7(34.3&#8211;41.55)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.7(31.55&#8211;42.15)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.25(31.7&#8211;36.83)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">INR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.13(1&#8211;1.29)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.09(1&#8211;1.27)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14(0.98&#8211;1.34)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12(0.99&#8211;1.26)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TT (s)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.55(16.55&#8211;19.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.7(16.4&#8211;19)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.5(16.45&#8211;20.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.4(16.8&#8211;20.28)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AFP (ng/mL)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.8(3.8&#8211;23.85)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.4(2.6&#8211;5.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.5(3.65&#8211;38.65)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.9(3.93&#8211;22.36)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003*/NS&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ANA&#8201;+&#8201;</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">232/271(85.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16/17(94.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32/33(97%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20/29(69%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;/0.020&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SMA&#8201;+&#8201;</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14/271(5.2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1/17(5.9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cirrhosis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">147/277(53.1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10/17(58.8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19/33(57.6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21/31(67.7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*&#8224;&#8225;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data was shown as mean&#8201;&#177;&#8201;SD and/or median (range) and/or number/total (percent)</p><p><italic toggle="yes">AIH</italic> Autoimmune hepatitis; <italic toggle="yes">PBC</italic> Primary biliary cholangitis; <italic toggle="yes">CTD</italic> Connective tissue disease; <italic toggle="yes">TD</italic> Thyroid dysfunction; <italic toggle="yes">IgG/A/M</italic> Immunoglobulin G/A/M; <italic toggle="yes">WBC</italic> White blood cell; <italic toggle="yes">NE%</italic> Neutrophil percentage; <italic toggle="yes">MO%</italic> Monocytes percentage; <italic toggle="yes">Hb</italic> Hemoglobin; <italic toggle="yes">PLT</italic> Platelet count; <italic toggle="yes">MPV</italic> Mean platelet volume; <italic toggle="yes">Phos</italic> Serum phosphorus; <italic toggle="yes">CREA</italic> Creatinine; <italic toggle="yes">URCA</italic> Uric acid; <italic toggle="yes">GLU</italic> Glucose; <italic toggle="yes">ALT</italic> Alanine aminotransferase; <italic toggle="yes">AST</italic> Aspartate aminotransferase; <italic toggle="yes">TBIL</italic> Total bilirubin; <italic toggle="yes">DBIL</italic> Direct bilirubin; <italic toggle="yes">ALB</italic> Albumin; <italic toggle="yes">GLO</italic> Globulin; <italic toggle="yes">GGT</italic> Gamma-glutamyl transferase; <italic toggle="yes">ALP</italic> Alkaline phosphatase; <italic toggle="yes">TBA</italic> Total bile acid; <italic toggle="yes">TC</italic> Total cholesterol; <italic toggle="yes">TG</italic> Triglycerides; <italic toggle="yes">HDLC</italic> High-density lipoprotein cholesterol; <italic toggle="yes">LDLC</italic> Low-density lipoprotein cholesterol; <italic toggle="yes">PT</italic> Prothrombin time; <italic toggle="yes">APTT</italic> Activated partial thromboplastin time; <italic toggle="yes">INR</italic> International normalized ratio; <italic toggle="yes">TT</italic> Thrombin time; <italic toggle="yes">AFP</italic> Alpha-1-fetoprotein; <italic toggle="yes">ANA</italic>+&#8201;Antinuclear antibody-positive; <italic toggle="yes">SMA</italic>+&#8201;Anti-smooth muscle antibody positive</p><p>NS, not significant (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05); Values in bold are significant (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05)</p><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value for AIH vs AIH-PBC</p><p>&#8224;<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value for AIH vs AIH-CTD</p><p>&#8225;<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value for AIH vs AIH-TD</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Survival analysis of AIH complicated with immune diseases</title><p id="Par52">As of December 31, 2021, the survival data of all patients were collected. In AIH group, 261 patients survived and 16 patients died from liver related diseases. The 3-year, 6-year and 9-year survival rates of AIH group were 90.9%, 74.7% and 44% respectively, and the median survival time was 8.4&#160;years. In AIH-PBC group, 16 patients survived and 1 died. The 3-, 6- and 9-year survival rates were 94.1%, 76.5% and 58.8% respectively, and the median survival time was 10.2&#160;years. In AIH-CTD group, 27 cases survived and 6 cases died. The 3-, 6- and 9-year survival rates were 87.9%, 84.8% and 39.4% respectively, and the median survival time was 8.4&#160;years. In the AIH-TD group, 31 cases survived and none died. The 3-,6- and 9-year survival rates were 80.6%, 54.8% and 19.4% respectively, and the median survival time was 6.2&#160;years. Therefore, Kaplan&#8211;Meier survival analysis showed that the overall survival time of AIH combined with TD was significantly shorter than that of AIH group (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0011), while the overall survival time of AIH-PBC or AIH-CTD was similar to that of AIH, with no statistical significance (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.64 and Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.8, respectively).<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Survival curve of the patients with AIH, AIH-PBC, AIH-CTD and AIH-TD Abbreviations are same as in the text</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10238_2023_1094_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Univariate/multivariate cox regression analysis of prognostic factors of AIH patients</title><p id="Par53">Univariate analysis of prognostic factors of AIH patients by cox proportional risk model showed that ANA (<italic toggle="yes">HR</italic>: 0.36, 95% CI: 0.26&#8211;0.49, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001), liver cirrhosis (<italic toggle="yes">HR</italic>: 1.2, 95%CI: 1&#8211;1.5, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.049), TD (<italic toggle="yes">HR</italic>: 1.9, 95%CI: 1.3&#8211;2.7, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001), WBC (<italic toggle="yes">HR</italic>: 1, 95%CI: 1&#8211;1.1, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.032), MPV (<italic toggle="yes">HR</italic>: 1.3, 95%CI: 1.2&#8211;1.4, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001), serum K (<italic toggle="yes">HR</italic>: 1,95%) 95%CI: 1&#8211;1, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.017), AST (<italic toggle="yes">HR</italic>: 1, 95%CI: 1&#8211;1, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.024), TBA (<italic toggle="yes">HR</italic>: 1, 95%CI: 1&#8211;1, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0026), and HDL-C (<italic toggle="yes">HR</italic>: 0.69, 95%CI: 0.53&#8211;0.89, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.004), INR (<italic toggle="yes">HR</italic>: 1.2, 95% CI: 1.1&#8211;1.4, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001) and TT (<italic toggle="yes">HR</italic>: 1.1, 95%CI: 1&#8211;1.1, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0063) were found to predict the survival time of AIH patients (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Univariate cox regression analysis of factors associated with reduced survival in AIH patients. Abbreviations are same as in the text. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05; **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01; ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10238_2023_1094_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par54">Based on the result of univariate cox regression, multivariate cox regression analysis showed that ANA negative (<italic toggle="yes">HR</italic>: 0.21, 95%CI: 0.13&#8211;0.35, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001), MPV <italic toggle="yes">(HR</italic>: 1.25,95% CI: 1.11&#8211;1.4, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001), serum K (<italic toggle="yes">HR</italic>: 0.93, 95%CI: 0.87&#8211;0.99, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.019) and INR (<italic toggle="yes">HR</italic>: 2.22, 95% CI: 1.63&#8211;3.03, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001) can be used as independent predictors of poor prognosis in AIH patients (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Multivariate cox regression analysis of factors associated with overall survival in AIH patients. Abbreviations are same as in the text. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05; **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01; ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10238_2023_1094_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Kaplan&#8211;Meier survival curves to estimate the prognostic factors of AIH and comorbidity</title><p id="Par55">As shown in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A, it is worth mentioning that the survival time of ANA negative group was significantly shorter than the ANA positive group in AIH patients (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001). There are no survival differences in groups sorted by MPV, serum K<sup>+</sup> and INR (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B&#8211;D). Considering the differences of ANA between AIH and AIH-TD patients, further Kaplan&#8211;Meier survival curves show that ANA negative can be used as an indicator to predict the poor prognosis of AIH and AIH-TD (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Kaplan&#8211;Meier analysis of factors associated with overall survival in AIH patients</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO4" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10238_2023_1094_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig><fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Kaplan&#8211;Meier analysis of ANA associated with overall survival in AIH-TD patients</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO5" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10238_2023_1094_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par56">This retrospective study specifically focuses on AIH complicated with immune diseases and compares incidence rate, clinical characteristics and prognosis. Three main findings arose from our study: (a) AIH is closely related to other immune diseases. (b) Patients with AIH-TD had significantly poor prognosis, and mean survival of patients in AIH-TD groups was found to be shorter than that of those with AIH. (c) It is worth noting that ANA negative can be used as independent indicators to predict the poor prognosis of AIH patients. To the best of our knowledge, this is a valuable study to provide basis for further mining the mechanism of AIH.</p><p id="Par57">AIH is not only limited to intrahepatic immune injury, but also often associated with some extrahepatic immune diseases. Similar to the study of Italy and Germany, a study from the UK observed that 42% of AIH patients coexisted with extrahepatic immune diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Some researchers presented that AIH often occurs in genetically susceptible individuals, causing intrahepatic or extrahepatic autoimmunity in individuals and families [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Another interesting finding was that 43% of AIH patients have extrahepatic immune diseases in their first-degree relatives, usually accompanied by thyroid diseases, diabetes and other disease types [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. However, our data showed that only 26.5% of AIH patients were complicated with extrahepatic immune diseases, which was slightly lower than other studies.</p><p id="Par58">Considering that immune diseases are related to low cognition in Asia, it further shows that immune diseases may be related to geographical location [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Interestingly, our research showed that in AIH complicated diseases, hypothyroidism (4.7%) is significantly higher than hyperthyroidism (0.8%). This is accordance with the previous research that AIH may affect thyroid function, and hypothyroidism is easier to be diagnosed than hyperthyroidism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. In view of few related studies on AIH complicated with immune diseases, it is necessary to carrying a large-scale cohort study. Considering that Beijing Ditan hospital is one of the largest clinical and research centers for liver diseases and infectious diseases in China, this cohort is highly representative. Therefore, the findings of this study were more closely resemble the real-world situation so as to further understand AIH complicated with intrahepatic/extrahepatic immune diseases.</p><p id="Par59">Similar to the previous study, this study found that the weight of AIH patients is heavier than AIH-PBC group in this study, possibly due to malabsorption caused by the decrease of bile acid secretion in bile of PBC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. In addition, it was observed for the first time that ALT and AFP levels in AIH group were higher than AIH-PBC group, and IgM and ALP levels were significantly lower in this study (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). It can be inferred from two assumptions. Firstly, AIH is insidious, and about 7% of patients have progressed to cirrhosis at the time of diagnosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Considering that AIH and PBC had different injury position, AIH is mainly localized in liver parenchyma injury, while bile duct injury caused by immune disorder in PBC, which bring the diversity of liver function. Secondly, the immune response of AIH-PBC patients is stronger, resulting in higher IgM than AIH patients, which was consistent with Ma's research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. In addition, we also found that AIH-CTD patients showed a lower level of serum K and MPV (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), which may be due to the involvement of kidney and hematopoietic function in CTD patients, resulting in renal tubular acidosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. In all, the clinical features of AIH complicated with different immune diseases are various.</p><p id="Par60">As AIH may occur on the rise, it is clear that the prognosis of AIH is noteworthy. The other interesting finding in our study is that ANA, MPV, serum K<sup>+</sup> and INR can be used as independent prognostic factors of AIH (Figs.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), which is consistent with Yamamoto's research conclusion that INR is related to the occurrence of death outcomes in AIH patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. A study from Japan showed that age and stage IV of liver fibrosis are independent risk factors affecting the overall survival of AIH [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Another national study from Denmark found that male and cirrhosis were unfavorable factors for the prognosis of AIH [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. In contrast, Joshita's research showed that ANA has no significant difference in clinical manifestation, histopathology or disease outcome of AIH, but ALP&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;500 or GGT&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;200 may be an independent risk factor for AIH recurrence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Therefore, it is indispensable for AIH patients to evaluate prognosis by paying attention to clinical indicators.</p><p id="Par61">Moreover, in this study, the proportion of ANA-positive in AIH-TD patients was significantly less than that of AIH patients (69% vs. 85.6%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.02). Interestingly, the survival time of AIH-TD patients was significantly shorter than that of AIH patients (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.001), while the overall survival of AIH-PBC and AIH-CTD patients was not significantly different from AIH patients. Another interesting finding was the survival time of ANA negative group was significantly shorter than that of the ANA positive group in AIH and AIH-TD (Figs.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>), which is rarely reported. Furthermore, some studies also reported that ANA was related to the prognosis of immune diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], such as systemic lupus erythematosus, dermatomyositis. However, whether or not ANA could predict the prognosis outcome of AIH remains to be further studied.</p><p id="Par62">There are some limitations in this study: Firstly, this study only included AIH patients who were hospitalized in a tertiary hospital specializing in the treatment of liver diseases, which may lead to bias in the inclusion of patients. Secondly, because this study is a single center and the sample size is relatively small, there is no statistical significance in some clinical features. Finally, because this study is a retrospective design, it is inevitable that some indicators cannot be included in the data collection, and there are some uncontrolled biases. Therefore, further multicenter studies are needed, which need a large enough sample size and a long follow-up period to detect the significant correlation between the results.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par63">Our data showed that AIH was closely related to other immune diseases and about 26.5% of AIH patients had at least one immune disease in a cohort from China. It was also found that TD coexisted with AIH could impaired patients&#8217; survival significantly. Moreover, we found that ANA negative can be used as an independent indicator to predict the poor prognosis of AIH and comorbidity patients. Therefore, identifying unique clinical features and biochemical manifestations to locate specific involved organs may be helpful for early diagnosis, treatment and better prognosis of AIH.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AIH</term><def><p id="Par2">Autoimmune hepatitis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PBC</term><def><p id="Par3">Primary biliary cholangitis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CTD</term><def><p id="Par4">Connective tissue disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TD</term><def><p id="Par5">Thyroid dysfunction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IgG/A/M</term><def><p id="Par6">Immunoglobulin G/A/M</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WBC</term><def><p id="Par7">White blood cell</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NE%</term><def><p id="Par8">Neutrophil percentage</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MO%</term><def><p id="Par9">Monocytes percentage</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Hb</term><def><p id="Par10">Hemoglobin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PLT</term><def><p id="Par11">Platelet count</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MPV</term><def><p id="Par12">Mean platelet volume</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Phos</term><def><p id="Par13">Serum phosphorus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CREA</term><def><p id="Par14">Creatinine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>URCA</term><def><p id="Par15">Uric acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GLU</term><def><p id="Par16">Glucose</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ALT</term><def><p id="Par17">Alanine aminotransferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AST</term><def><p id="Par18">Aspartate aminotransferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TBIL</term><def><p id="Par19">Total bilirubin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DBIL</term><def><p id="Par20">Direct bilirubin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ALB</term><def><p id="Par21">Albumin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GLO</term><def><p id="Par22">Globulin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GGT</term><def><p id="Par23">Gamma-glutamyl transferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ALP</term><def><p id="Par24">Alkaline phosphatase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TBA</term><def><p id="Par25">Total bile acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TC</term><def><p id="Par26">Total cholesterol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TG</term><def><p id="Par27">Triglycerides</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HDLC</term><def><p id="Par28">High-density lipoprotein cholesterol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LDLC</term><def><p id="Par29">Low-density lipoprotein cholesterol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PT</term><def><p id="Par30">Prothrombin time</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>APTT</term><def><p id="Par31">Activated partial thromboplastin time</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>INR</term><def><p id="Par32">International normalized ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TT</term><def><p id="Par33">Thrombin time</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AFP</term><def><p id="Par34">Alpha-1-fetoprotein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ANA+&#8201;</term><def><p id="Par35">Antinuclear antibody-positive</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SMA+&#8201;</term><def><p id="Par36">Anti-smooth muscle antibody positive</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HR</term><def><p id="Par37">Hazard ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SD</term><def><p id="Par38">Standard deviation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p id="Par39">Confidence interval</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Conception and design (LH, LX, WY, WP), data collecting (LH, WY, WP, WX, YY), data analysis (LH, WX), data interpretation (LH, WY, WP, WX, YY), manuscript drafting and revising (LH, LX, WY, WP, WX, YY).</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the Beijing Hospitals Authority&#8217;s Ascent Plan (Grant No. DFL20221601), Natural Science Foundation of Beijing (Grant No.7212053); Innovation Team and Talents Cultivation Program of National Administration of Traditional Chinese Medicine (Grant No. ZYYCXTD-C-202006).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Data available on request from the authors.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par64">The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Terziroli</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mieli</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vergani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Autoimmune hepatitis</article-title><source>Cell Mol Immunol</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>158</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41423-021-00768-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34580437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8475398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Komori</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent updates on the management of autoimmune hepatitis</article-title><source>Clin Mol Hepatol</source><year>2021</year><volume>27</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3350/cmh.2020.0189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33291862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7820207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sebode</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vergani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>International Autoimmune Hepatitis Group (IAIHG) Autoimmune hepatitis: from current knowledge and clinical practice to future research agenda</article-title><source>Liver Int</source><year>2018</year><volume>38</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/liv.13458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28432836</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sucher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sucher</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gradistanac</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Autoimmune hepatitis-immunologically triggered liver pathogenesis-diagnostic and therapeutic strategies</article-title><source>J Immunol Res</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2019/9437043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31886312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6899271</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mashiba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeniya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Present status of autoimmune hepatitis in Japan: a nationwide survey</article-title><source>J Gastroenterol</source><year>2011</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>1136</fpage><lpage>1141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00535-011-0421-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21597932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katsumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology and surveillance of autoimmune hepatitis in Asia</article-title><source>Liver Int</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/liv.15155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34990076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Systematic review and meta-analysis on the incidence and prevalence of autoimmune hepatitis in Asian, European, and American population</article-title><source>J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><year>2019</year><volume>34</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1676</fpage><lpage>1684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgh.14746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31146297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trivedi</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirschfield</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent advances in clinical practice: epidemiology of autoimmune liver diseases</article-title><source>Gut</source><year>2021</year><volume>70</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1989</fpage><lpage>2003</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2020-322362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34266966</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ngu</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stedman</surname><given-names>CAM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trends in incidence of autoimmune liver diseases and increasing incidence of autoimmune hepatitis</article-title><source>Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><year>2021</year><volume>19</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>573</fpage><lpage>579</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cgh.2020.05.061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32526342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tunio</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mansoor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheriff</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of autoimmune hepatitis (AIH) in the United States between 2014 and 2019: a population-based national study</article-title><source>J Clin Gastroenterol.</source><year>2021</year><volume>55</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>903</fpage><lpage>910</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MCG.0000000000001449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33074948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8050120</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jim&#233;nez-Rivera</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Incidence and characteristics of autoimmune hepatitis</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><year>2015</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>e1237</fpage><lpage>1248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2015-0578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26482664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mieli-Vergani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vergani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Czaja</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montano-Loza</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Autoimmune hepatitis</article-title><source>Nat Rev Dis Primers</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>18017</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrdp.2018.17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29644994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeong</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Concurrent extrahepatic autoimmunity in autoimmune hepatitis: implications for diagnosis, clinical course and long-term outcomes</article-title><source>Liver Int</source><year>2017</year><volume>37</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/liv.13236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27541063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muratori</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fabbri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lalanne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Autoimmune liver disease and concomitant extrahepatic autoimmune disease</article-title><source>Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><year>2015</year><volume>27</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1175</fpage><lpage>1179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MEG.0000000000000424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26148248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teufel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahaly</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Concurrent autoimmune diseases in patients with autoimmune hepatitis</article-title><source>J Clin Gastroenterol</source><year>2010</year><volume>44</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MCG.0b013e3181c74e0d</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20087196</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>International autoimmune hepatitis group report: review of criteria for diagnosis of autoimmune hepatitis</article-title><source>j hepatol</source><year>1999</year><volume>31</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>929</fpage><lpage>938</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0168-8278(99)80297-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10580593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hennes</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeniya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Czaja</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>International autoimmune hepatitis group. Simplified criteria for the diagnosis of autoimmune hepatitis</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><year>2008</year><volume>48</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.22322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18537184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poupon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary biliary cirrhosis: a 2010 update</article-title><source>J Hepatol</source><year>2010</year><volume>52</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>745</fpage><lpage>758</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2009.11.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20347176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mavragani</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nezos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moutsopoulos</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New advances in the classification, pathogenesis and treatment of Sjogren's syndrome</article-title><source>Curr Opin Rheumatol</source><year>2013</year><volume>25</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>623</fpage><lpage>629</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/BOR.0b013e328363eaa5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23846338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cush</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rheumatoid arthritis: early diagnosis and treatment</article-title><source>Med Clin North Am</source><year>2021</year><volume>105</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>365</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcna.2020.10.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33589108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aringer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costenbader</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daikh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>European league against rheumatism/american college of rheumatology classification criteria for systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title><source>Ann Rheum Dis</source><year>2019</year><volume>78</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1151</fpage><lpage>1159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/annrheumdis-2018-214819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31383717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Menconi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marcocci</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marin&#242;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis and classification of Graves' disease</article-title><source>Autoimmun Rev</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><issue>4&#8211;5</issue><fpage>398</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.autrev.2014.01.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24424182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Gerven</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verwer</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Witte</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dutch Autoimmune hepatitis STUDY group. Epidemiology and clinical characteristics of autoimmune hepatitis in the Netherlands</article-title><source>Scand J Gastroenterol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>49</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1245</fpage><lpage>1254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/00365521.2014.946083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25123213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Chalabi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Underhill</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Portmann</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of gender on the long-term outcome and survival of patients with autoimmune hepatitis</article-title><source>J Hepatol</source><year>2008</year><volume>48</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2007.08.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18023911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Milo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahana</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple sclerosis: geoepidemiology, genetics and the environment</article-title><source>Autoimmun Rev</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>A387</fpage><lpage>A394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.autrev.2009.11.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19932200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationship between autoimmune liver disease and autoimmune thyroid disease: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Scand J Gastroenterol</source><year>2020</year><volume>55</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00365521.2019.1710766</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32083943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characteristics and inpatient outcomes of primary biliary cholangitis and autoimmune hepatitis overlap syndrome</article-title><source>J Clin Transl Hepatol</source><year>2021</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>392</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14218/JCTH.2021.00008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34221925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8237146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thuluvath</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanish</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Savva</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Liver transplantation in cryptogenic cirrhosis: outcome comparisons between NASH, Alcoholic, and AIH cirrhosis</article-title><source>Transplantation</source><year>2018</year><volume>102</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>656</fpage><lpage>663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/TP.0000000000002030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29215462</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The natural history and prognosis of primary biliary cirrhosis with clinical features of autoimmune hepatitis</article-title><source>Clin Rev Allergy Immunol</source><year>2016</year><volume>50</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12016-015-8516-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26411425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishioka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zoshima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Urinary abnormality in mixed connective tissue disease predicts development of other connective tissue diseases and decrease in renal function</article-title><source>Mod Rheumatol</source><year>2021</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1899602</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14397595.2021.1899602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33706652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyake</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohira</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Intractable liver and biliary diseases study group of Japan. Prognosis of autoimmune hepatitis showing acute presentation</article-title><source>Hepatol Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>43</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>630</fpage><lpage>638</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1872-034X.2012.01109.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23088515</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohira</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical features of hepatocellular carcinoma in patients with autoimmune hepatitis in Japan</article-title><source>J Gastroenterol</source><year>2013</year><volume>48</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00535-012-0616-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22688407</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gr&#248;nb&#230;k</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilstrup</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jepsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Autoimmune hepatitis in Denmark: incidence, prevalence, prognosis, and causes of death. A nationwide registry-based cohort study</article-title><source>J Hepatol</source><year>2014</year><volume>60</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>612</fpage><lpage>617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2013.10.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24326217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joshita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshizawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Umemura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Japan Autoimmune Hepatitis Study Group (JAIHSG) Clinical features of autoimmune hepatitis with acute presentation: a Japanese nationwide survey</article-title><source>J Gastroenterol</source><year>2015</year><volume>53</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1079</fpage><lpage>1088</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00535-018-1444-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29476251</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ricard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laurent</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Papo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical and prognostic significance of antinuclear antibodies in primary antiphospholipid syndrome: a multicenter retrospective study</article-title><source>Joint Bone Spine.</source><year>2022</year><volume>89</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>105297</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbspin.2021.105297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34656751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nomogram to predict dermatomyositis prognosis: a population-based study of 457 cases</article-title><source>Clin Exp Rheumatol</source><year>2022</year><volume>40</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.55563/clinexprheumatol/0ddt88</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34528507</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>