<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2992</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">heliyon</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10412833</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10412833.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10412833</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10412833</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37576311</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e18758</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2405-8440(23)05966-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e18758</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A dynamic machine learning model for prediction of NAFLD in a health checkup population: A longitudinal study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuhan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names initials="J">Jingzhu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaona</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">g</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names initials="C">Canqing</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">h</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names initials="J">Jun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">h</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name name-style="western"><surname>Man</surname><given-names initials="S">Sailimai</given-names></name><email>sailimai.man@meinianresearch.com</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref><xref rid="PC_corJqBxcQvGK8" ref-type="corresp">&#8727;&#8727;&#8727;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="B">Bo</given-names></name><email>paul@meinianresearch.com</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">h</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#8727;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au9"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="L">Liming</given-names></name><email>lmlee@bjmu.edu.cn</email><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">h</xref><xref rid="PC_corNh0xFTyKRz" ref-type="corresp">&#8727;&#8727;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Chongqing Research Institute of Big Data, Peking University, Chongqing, China</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Meinian Institute of Health, Beijing, China</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>School of Population Medicine and Public Health, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences &amp; Peking Union Medical College, Beijing, China</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, School of Public Health, Peking University, Beijing, China</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Peking University Health Science Center Meinian Public Health Institute, Beijing, China</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>Key Laboratory of Epidemiology of Major Diseases (Peking University), Ministry of Education, Beijing, China</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>g</label>MJ Health Screening Center, Beijing, China</aff><aff id="aff8"><label>h</label>Peking University Center for Public Health and Epidemic Preparedness &amp; Response, Beijing, China</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#8727;</label>Corresponding author. Meinian Institute of Health, Beijing, China. <email>paul@meinianresearch.com</email></corresp><corresp id="PC_corNh0xFTyKRz"><label>&#8727;&#8727;</label>Corresponding author. Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, School of Public Health, Peking University, Beijing, China <email>lmlee@bjmu.edu.cn</email></corresp><corresp id="PC_corJqBxcQvGK8"><label>&#8727;&#8727;&#8727;</label>Corresponding author. Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, School of Public Health, Peking University, Beijing, China <email>sailimai.man@meinianresearch.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>8</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>8</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">441736</issue-id><elocation-id>e18758</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>25</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>27</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-08-14 11:25:22.843"><day>14</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2023 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) is one of the most common liver diseases worldwide. Currently, most NAFLD prediction models are diagnostic models based on cross-sectional data, which failed to provide early identification or clarify causal relationships. We aimed to use time-series deep learning models with longitudinal health checkup records to predict the onset of NAFLD in the future, and update the model stepwise by incorporating new checkup records to achieve dynamic prediction.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>10,493 participants with over 6 health checkup records from Beijing MJ Health Screening Center were included to conduct a retrospective cohort study, in which the constantly updated initial 5 checkup data were incorporated stepwise to predict the risk of NAFLD at and after their sixth health checkups. A total of 33 variables were considered, consisting of demographic characteristics, medical history, lifestyle, physical examinations, and laboratory tests. L1-penalized logistic regression (LR) was used for feature selection. The long short-term memory (LSTM) algorithm was introduced for model development, and five-fold cross-validation was conducted to tune and choose optimal hyperparameters. Both internal validation and external validation were conducted, using the 20% randomly divided holdout test dataset and previously unseen data from Shanghai MJ Health Screening Center, respectively, to evaluate model performance. The evaluation metrics included area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUROC), sensitivity, specificity, Brier score, and decision curve. Bootstrap sampling was implemented to generate 95% confidence intervals of all the metrics. Finally, the Shapley additive explanations (SHAP) algorithm was applied in the holdout test dataset for model interpretability to obtain time-specific and sample-specific contributions of each feature.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Among the 10,493 participants, 1662 (15.84%) were diagnosed with NAFLD at and after their sixth health checkups. The predictive performance of the deep learning model in the internal validation dataset improved over the incorporation of the checkups, with AUROC increasing from 0.729 (95% CI: 0.698,0.760) at baseline to 0.818 (95% CI: 0.798,0.844) when consecutive 5 checkups were included. The external validation dataset, containing 1728 participants, was used to verify the results, in which AUROC increased from 0.700 (95% CI: 0.657,0.740) with only the first checkups to 0.792 (95% CI: 0.758,0.825) with all five. The results of feature significance showed that body fat percentage, alanine transaminase (ALT), and uric acid owned the greatest impact on the outcome, time-specific, individual-specific and dynamic feature contributions were also produced for model interpretability.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>A dynamic prediction model was successfully established in our study, and the prediction capability kept improving with the renewal of the latest checkup records. In addition, we identified key features associated with the onset of NAFLD, making it possible to optimize the prevention and control strategies of the disease in the general population.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Machine learning</kwd><kwd>Dynamic prediction</kwd><kwd>Time-series data</kwd><kwd>Checkup records</kwd><kwd>NAFLD</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">As one of the most common chronic hepatic diseases worldwide, non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) has affected 29.6% of the Asian population and the prevalence rate is increasing significantly over time [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. NAFLD can transit to hepatic inflammation and fibrosis, and is highly associated with other non-liver-specific diseases, especially cardiovascular and metabolic disorders [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], presenting severe healthcare burdens globally [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. However, given the multifactorial and intricate etiology of the disease, it's still difficult to determine a specific prevention strategy and achieve early identification of high-risk groups to reduce the prevalence of the disease. Therefore, improved prediction of the risk of NAFLD may be of great value in the prevention and control of the disease in the general population.</p><p id="p0015">Artificial intelligence methods, together with massive data collected in the medical field, make it possible to precisely predict the risk of NAFLD. As expected, more and more research has been conducted to solve such issues. However, previous related studies were mostly cross-sectional and mainly focused on the development of diagnostic prediction models, which failed to determine causal relationships or provide early risk probabilities sometime before the confirmed diagnosis of NAFLD [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>]. Besides, most existing studies were based on conventional machine learning models with a single measurement of variables [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], ignoring the variation tendency contained in multiple measurements of data.</p><p id="p0020">To date, the valuable information contained in health checkup data, characterized by annually repeat-measured items, is underutilized, while the commonly used machine learning models, such as random forest and XGBoost, may be unable to handle these kinds of time-series data well [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Presently, deep learning-based models [<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], including the recurrent neural network (RNN) and its derived models, can make full use of the constantly updated records and have been proven to show good performance, but almost in ICU settings [<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. However, despite the promising prediction performance, the complex structures and large amounts of parameters in deep learning models restrict their acceptance and practical application [<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], while the introduction of model interpretability algorithms largely solved this problem and facilitate the understanding of the black boxes. Among all the algorithms, Shapley additive explanations (SHAP) algorithm [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], a widely used model interpretability method for any machine learning models, seems both effective and prospective in quantifying the impact of each variable on the outcomes [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p><p id="p0025">To the best of our knowledge, no studies have ever used constantly updated time-series health checkup data to develop a dynamic prediction model based on deep learning algorithms to predict NAFLD. In this study, we use the long short-term memory (LSTM) model with SHAP interpretability algorithms to predict the risk of NAFLD one year after health checkups and update the prediction model over checkups, and further verify the results on an external validation dataset.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Method</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Data source and study participants</title><p id="p0030">A retrospective cohort study was conducted based on data from Beijing MJ Health Screening Center. Beijing MJ Health Checkup Database contains routinely annual checkup data from 2003 to 2021, with more than 50,000 checkup records collected every year. During each checkup, a series of standardized protocols including physical examinations, laboratory tests, imaging diagnoses and a questionnaire survey about demographic characteristics, dietary habits, physical activity and other comprehensive lifestyle and health conditions were applied and inquired to all the participants. The external validation dataset was obtained from Shanghai MJ Health Screening Center, a health checkup center independent of that in Beijing, containing checkup records from 2003 to 2021.</p><p id="p0035">In our study, participants who attended more than 6 checkups were included. The exclusion criteria were as follows: (1) age under 18 years at the first checkup; (2) having been diagnosed with fatty liver on liver ultrasound at any of the initial five checkups; (3) having ethanol intake of more than 30&#160;g per day for men and 20&#160;g for women or with missing data on drinking at any of the initial five checkups; (4) having a self-reported history of hepatic diseases at any of the initial five checkups. After excluding those who meet the exclusion criteria, a total number of 10,493 participants were included for model development and 1728 for model validation in our study (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). The median time intervals between two consecutive checkups of the participants were presented in Supplemental F. 1.<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Inclusion flow chart of study participants.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Predictors and outcomes</title><p id="p0040">The following variables at each of the initial 5 visits were extracted: (i) demographic characteristics: sex, age, education, income; (ii) physical examinations: body mass index (BMI), waist circumference (WC), body fat percentage (BFP), systolic blood pressure (SBP), diastolic blood pressure (DBP); (iii) laboratory tests: fasting blood glucose (FBG), total cholesterol (TC), triglyceride (TG), high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDLC), low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDLC), alanine transaminase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), direct bilirubin (DB), total bilirubin (TB), total protein (TP), albumin (ALB), globulin (GLB), glutamyl transferase (GGT), alkaline phosphatase (ALP), lactate dehydrogenase (LD), uric acid (UA); (iv) smoking status; (v) dietary habits: dietary regularity, fruit intake, dairy intake, fried food intake; (vi) medical history: hypertension, diabetes and hyperlipidemia.</p><p id="p0045">The consumption of food was classified into three tiers of low, moderate, and high, delineated by the following specifics: the low fruit intake is defined as either no consumption or less than 150&#160;g per day, moderate intake is defined as consuming 150&#160;g&#8211;300&#160;g fruit per day, and high intake is defined as consuming more than 300&#160;g fruit per day; the low intake of dairy products is defined as no consumption or less than one cup of milk (240&#160;ml) or one serving of dairy products (30&#160;g of cheese or 1 slice of cheese) per week, moderate intake is defined as consuming 1&#8211;3 cups of milk or 1&#8211;3 servings of dairy products per week, and high intake is defined as consuming more than four cups of milk or more than four servings of dairy products per week; a low level of intake of fried food indicates either no consumption or consumption of less than one serving per week, a moderate level of intake indicates consumption of 1&#8211;3 servings per week, and a high level of intake indicates consumption of four or more servings per week, with one serving defined as half a bowl.</p><p id="p0050">The outcome was defined as whether the participant was diagnosed with NAFLD on ultrasonography from their sixth health checkups until the end of their follow-ups.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Data preprocessing and statistical analysis</title><p id="p0055">Participants in the development dataset from Beijing MJ database were randomly divided into a training set (80%) and an internal validation dataset (20%), and imputations of missing values were conducted in the two datasets, together with the external validation dataset, respectively. Except for certain variables (sex for example) that were constant at each checkup, most of the variables were time-series forms, which means that they were measured repetitively at each checkup and not independent of each other, so the last observation carried forward (LOCF) method was conducted to impute missing values for repeated measurements. After the first imputation, variables with missing rates over 30% were excluded from our analysis, including TP and ALB. For continuous variables, their means were used to impute the rest missingness. Outliers were identified as values distributed more or less than three standard deviations from the mean and were handled the same way as missing values. All continuous variables were maintained as their original forms in case of information loss, and categorical variables with multiple levels were re-classified, then the unordered were one-hot encoded, while the ordered were kept as their reclassification forms. Continuous variables were presented as means with standard deviations (SDs) and utilized Student's t-test or Wilcoxon rank-sum test for statistical analysis. Categorical variables were presented as counts and percentages, and the Chi-square test was employed for comparison.</p><p id="p0060">After the preprocessing step, L1-penalized logistic regression (LR) was conducted based on the newest records in the training set to select a subset of the total features generated from the preprocessing procedure, then the LSTM algorithm was introduced to develop the prediction model, and the model was updated as the number of visit times increased and new measurements of predictors entered. The hyperparameters were selected through a five-fold cross-validation process, in which all combinations of hyperparameters were tested and the optimal combination was chosen based on the mean area under the receiver operating curve (AUROC) across five validation sets derived from the training dataset. Besides, considering the imbalanced issue of the dataset [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], in which participants with NAFLD were less than those without, we kept all the samples in the minority class in each epoch and randomly selected the same number of samples from the majority class to train the model, and both balanced datasets and imbalanced datasets were tested through five-fold cross-validation. In addition, to establish a benchmark for the prediction of NAFLD, LR was conducted using data based on each health checkup.</p><p id="p0065">In the internal validation dataset and external validation dataset, discrimination and calibration of the prediction models were assessed, in which AUROC, sensitivity, and specificity were used as metrics of discrimination ability, while Brier score was used to evaluate calibration capability. Besides, Platt scaling method [<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] was used to transform outputs into risk probabilities by fitting LR to improve calibration, and the Brier score was calculated after recalibration. Bootstrap sampling was performed to generate 95% confidence intervals (CIs) of the metrics above. Specifically, the same size of samples as the validation dataset was randomly selected with replacement 1000 times, and the distribution of the results was used to obtain 95% CIs. Meanwhile, decision-curve characteristic on the internal validation dataset was evaluated. The Delong test was utilized to compare the consecutive AUCs resulting from model updates. Furthermore, as predictive performance with model updates was not independent, we employed repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) to compare the overall performance between models based on LSTM algorithms and LR across all five time points. After the comparison of the updated models, the best-performed model was selected to show feature significance. The SHAP algorithm was applied in the internal validation dataset to enhance models&#8217; interpretability by obtaining patient-specific contributions of each feature at a specific time point.</p><p id="p0070">All the data preprocessing was conducted using SAS 9.4 and statistical analyses using Python 3.7.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>LSTM for model development</title><p id="p0075">LSTM [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] is introduced on the basis of the RNN, which can tackle time-series problems and selectively retain important information through its gating systems: input gate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), forget gate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and output gate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). Specifically, the input gate determines how much information to input at the present step, the forget gate controls how much information to throw away from the previous steps, and the output gate decided how much current information to output. After the disposal conducted by the gate systems, redundant information is filtered out, largely releasing the memory of the hidden layer. The equations and diagram of an LSTM neuron (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>) are as below:<disp-formula id="ufd1"><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#963;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#8722;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="ufd2"><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#963;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#8722;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="ufd3"><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#963;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#8722;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="ufd4"><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#732;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>tanh</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#8289;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#8722;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="ufd5"><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&#8857;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#8722;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&#8857;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#732;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="ufd6"><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#8857;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">tanh</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Diagram of an LSTM neuron.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0080">In our study, the NAFLD risk prediction was updated timely by incorporating new checkup records to construct dynamic models, and all these longitudinal data integrated into the models were used for the prediction of NAFLD in future checkups.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>SHAP for model interpretability</title><p id="p0085">In the SHAP algorithm [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], feature importance is presented according to Shapley values. For a single sample, a probability is a certain output from a prediction model, indicating the outcome risk of this sample, and in the same way, we can get a mean probability of all samples. Through the SHAP algorithm, each of the current features of this sample corresponds to a Shapley value, which indicates the contribution of this feature (considering its interactions with other features) to the outcome. The sum of all Shapley values is the difference between the actual probability of a single sample and the mean probability of whole samples, which can be represented as:<disp-formula id="ufd7"><mml:math id="M10" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#8230;</mml:mo><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>In our study, the global contribution, together with the time-specific and sample-specific contributions of each feature can be generated by this algorithm.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><p id="p0090">After excluding individuals who did not meet the inclusion criteria, a total of 10,493 participants were included for model development in our study. Among them, 1662 (15.84%) were diagnosed with NAFLD at and after their sixth checkup. Characteristics of study participants at baseline stratified by the outcome are presented in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. People with the onset of NAFLD were older (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001), comprised more males (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001), with lower educational degrees (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001) and lower income (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001). Moreover, they had higher values of anthropometric measures, including BMI (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001), WC (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001), BFP (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001), SBP (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001), and DBP (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001). The differences in most of the laboratory tests between the two groups were also statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.05). Besides, the NAFLD group comprised more current smokers (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001), and had lower dairy intake (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;=&#160;0.003), and the prevalence of hypertension (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001) and hyperlipidemia (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001) was also significantly higher in the NAFLD group. To comprehensively demonstrate the longitudinal characteristics of the study participants, we also presented the characteristics of their fifth health checkup and the checkup prior to their last follow-up in Supplemental Tab. 1 and Supplemental Tab. 2, respectively. Following the random partitioning of the dataset, we investigated differences in the baseline characteristics of the study participants between the training and internal validation sets. Supplemental Tab. 3 displays the results of this assessment, which demonstrated no statistically significant differences in any of the analyzed features.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of study participants at baseline stratified by outcome.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0060">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Characteristic, n (%)<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Total (N&#160;=&#160;10,493)<hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">NAFLD<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes (N&#160;=&#160;1662)<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">No (N&#160;=&#160;8831)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Demographic characteristics</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Sex</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3162 (30.13)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">714 (42.96)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2448 (27.72)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7331 (69.87)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">948 (57.04)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6383 (72.28)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age</bold>/year</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.40&#160;&#177;&#160;8.73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.13&#160;&#177;&#160;9.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.08&#160;&#177;&#160;8.63</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Education</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">University degree or below</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1781 (16.97)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">390 (23.47)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1391 (15.75)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Undergraduate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6018 (57.35)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">961 (57.82)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5057 (57.26)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">University degree and above</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2694 (25.67)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">311 (18.71)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2383 (26.98)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Income</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7867 (74.97)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1326 (79.78)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6541 (74.07)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1456 (13.88)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">191 (11.49)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1265 (14.32)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1170 (11.15)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">145 (8.72)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1025 (11.61)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Body measurement</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>BMI</bold>/(kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.30&#160;&#177;&#160;2.27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.45&#160;&#177;&#160;2.15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.08&#160;&#177;&#160;2.23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Waist circumference</bold>/cm</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.35&#160;&#177;&#160;7.25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75.93&#160;&#177;&#160;7.11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71.68&#160;&#177;&#160;7.08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Body fat percentage</bold>/%</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.66&#160;&#177;&#160;5.54</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.33&#160;&#177;&#160;5.80</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.35&#160;&#177;&#160;5.44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>SBP</bold>/mmHg</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">105.86&#160;&#177;&#160;11.65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108.00&#160;&#177;&#160;12.34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">105.46&#160;&#177;&#160;11.47</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>DBP/</bold>mmHg</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.88&#160;&#177;&#160;8.72</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.91&#160;&#177;&#160;9.32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.69&#160;&#177;&#160;8.59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Laboratory tests</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>FBG/</bold>(mmol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.25&#160;&#177;&#160;0.36</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.33&#160;&#177;&#160;0.35</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.24&#160;&#177;&#160;0.36</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>TC/</bold>(mmol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.37&#160;&#177;&#160;0.70</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.47&#160;&#177;&#160;0.73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.35&#160;&#177;&#160;0.70</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>TG/</bold>(mmol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.84&#160;&#177;&#160;0.34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95&#160;&#177;&#160;0.37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.82&#160;&#177;&#160;0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>HDLC/</bold>(mmol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.57&#160;&#177;&#160;0.29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.50&#160;&#177;&#160;0.28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.59&#160;&#177;&#160;0.29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>LDLC/</bold>(mmol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.58&#160;&#177;&#160;0.59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.67&#160;&#177;&#160;0.59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.56&#160;&#177;&#160;0.59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>ALT</bold>/(U/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.93&#160;&#177;&#160;7.36</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.70&#160;&#177;&#160;7.84</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.59&#160;&#177;&#160;7.22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>AST</bold>/(U/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.94&#160;&#177;&#160;4.51</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.44&#160;&#177;&#160;4.61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.84&#160;&#177;&#160;4.48</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Direct bilirubin/</bold>(&#956;mol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.00&#160;&#177;&#160;2.15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.42&#160;&#177;&#160;2.15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.11&#160;&#177;&#160;2.13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Total bilirubin/</bold>(&#956;mol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.63&#160;&#177;&#160;6.25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.29&#160;&#177;&#160;6.41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.88&#160;&#177;&#160;6.18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Total protein/</bold>(g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.80&#160;&#177;&#160;2.44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.81&#160;&#177;&#160;2.08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.80&#160;&#177;&#160;2.50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.838</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Albumin/</bold>(g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.43&#160;&#177;&#160;1.53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.48&#160;&#177;&#160;1.34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.42&#160;&#177;&#160;1.56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.087</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Globulin</bold>/(g/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.38&#160;&#177;&#160;2.15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.34&#160;&#177;&#160;1.83</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.38&#160;&#177;&#160;2.21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.351</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>GGT/</bold>(U/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.24&#160;&#177;&#160;5.95</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.36&#160;&#177;&#160;5.84</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.03&#160;&#177;&#160;5.95</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>ALP/</bold>(U/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.65&#160;&#177;&#160;10.59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.28&#160;&#177;&#160;9.59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.34&#160;&#177;&#160;10.74</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>LD/</bold>(U/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">148.94&#160;&#177;&#160;15.65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150.34&#160;&#177;&#160;14.61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">148.68&#160;&#177;&#160;15.83</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Uric acid/</bold>(&#956;mol/L)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">277.90&#160;&#177;&#160;58.55</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">292.31&#160;&#177;&#160;58.32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">275.19&#160;&#177;&#160;58.19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Living habits</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Smoking status</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">971 (9.25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">237 (14.26)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">734 (8.31)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Former</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200 (1.91)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (1.50)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">175 (1.98)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Never</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9322 (88.84)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1400 (84.24)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7922 (89.71)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Dietary regularity</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.161</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Regular</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8563 (81.61)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1336 (80.39)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7227 (81.84)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Irregular</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1930 (18.39)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">326 (19.61)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1604 (18.16)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Fruit intake</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.061</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2117 (20.18)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">357 (21.48)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1760 (19.93)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7468 (71.17)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1183 (71.18)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6285 (71.17)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">908 (8.65)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">122 (7.34)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">786 (8.90)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Dairy intake</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4905 (46.75)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">840 (50.54)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4065 (46.03)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2707 (25.80)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">401 (24.13)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2306 (26.11)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2881 (27.46)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">421 (25.33)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2460 (27.86)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Fried food intake</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.132</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6177 (58.87)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">951 (57.22)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5226 (59.18)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3734 (35.59)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">604 (36.34)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3130 (35.44)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">582 (5.55)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">107 (6.44)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">475 (5.38)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Personal history</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Hypertension</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">404 (3.85)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">106 (6.38)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">298 (3.37)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,089 (96.15)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1556 (93.62)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8533 (96.63)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Diabetes</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.483</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">133 (1.27)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (1.44)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">109 (1.23)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,360 (98.73)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1638 (98.56)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8722 (98.77)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Hyperlipidemic</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2625 (25.02)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">516 (31.05)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2109 (23.88)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7868 (74.98)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1146 (68.95)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6722 (76.12)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>BMI&#160;=&#160;body mass index. SBP&#160;=&#160;systolic blood pressure. DBP&#160;=&#160;diastolic blood pressure. FBG&#160;=&#160;fasting blood glucose. TC&#160;=&#160;total cholesterol. TG&#160;=&#160;triglyceride. HDL-C&#160;=&#160;high-density lipoprotein cholesterol. LDL-C&#160;=&#160;low-density lipoprotein cholesterol. ALT&#160;=&#160;alanine transaminase. AST&#160;=&#160;aspartate aminotransferase. GGT&#160;=&#160;glutamyl transferase. ALP&#160;=&#160;alkaline phosphatase. LD&#160;=&#160;lactate dehydrogenase.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0095">The characteristics of participants at baseline and at fifth checkup in the external validation dataset after feature selection were presented in Supplemental Tab. 4 and Supplemental Tab. 5.</p><p id="p0100">After feature selection, a total of 16 features, including sex, education, income, BMI, WC, BFP, ALT, UA, DB, LD, TG, AST, HDLC, ALP, GGT and GLB were included in our model. Model performance in predicting NAFLD improved as checkup records were renewed. In the internal validation dataset, the AUC increased significantly from 0.729 (95% CI: 0.698,0.760) at baseline to 0.818 (95% CI: 0.798,0.844) when consecutive 5 checkups were included (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>A&#8211;B). The recalibrated Brier scores decreased when more checkup records were included, indicating improved calibration. The decision curve analysis also showed that the net benefits of the model incorporated all five checkups significantly outperformed those of the other throughout all threshold probabilities (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). The same growth trend in AUC can be seen in the external validation set, from 0.700 (95% CI: 0.657,0.740) at baseline to 0.792 (95% CI: 0.758,0.825) with all 5 checkups (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>C&#8211;D), although less accurate compared with those in the internal validation dataset. Brier scores also showed an improved calibration with the update of the checkups. The results of Delong test indicated that the improvement of AUC was statistically significant both in internal and external validation datasets (Supplemental Tab. 6). All metrics are presented in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of AUCs as the number of checkups increased. ROC curves of internal validation (A) and external validation (C); AUC as a function of checkup times in the internal validation dataset (B) and external validation dataset (D).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Decision curve analysis with the update of checkups in the internal validation dataset. The gray solid line and the gray dashed line represent the net benefit generated by intervention, and non-intervention to all participants, respectively. Other colored lines present intervention to all potential patients identified by each model throughout threshold probabilities.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Model performance with the update of health checkups based on LSTM.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0065">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">AUC<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sensitivity<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Specificity<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Brier score<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="5" rowspan="1">Internal validation dataset</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 Checkup</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.729 (0.698,0.760)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.700 (0.548,0.870)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.641 (0.459,0.780)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.131 (0.119,0.142)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 Checkups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.744 (0.715,0.775)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.774 (0.649,0.884)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.605 (0.481,0.721)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.112 (0.101,0.123)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 Checkups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.775 (0.748,0.802)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.735 (0.653,0.808)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.715 (0.652,0.784)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.087 (0.076,0.094)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 Checkups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.786 (0.758,0.813)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.748 (0.660,0.872)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.700 (0.558,0.775)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.067 (0.058,0.077)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 Checkups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.818 (0.798,0.844)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.804 (0.713,0.873)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.690 (0.627,0.772)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.052 (0.041,0.066)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>External validation dataset</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 Checkup</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.700 (0.657,0.740)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.741 (0.532,0.897)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.590 (0.422,0.788)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.076 (0.066,0.087)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 Checkups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.730 (0.690,0.769)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.765 (0.646,0.925)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.579 (0.446,0.745)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.077 (0.066,0.088)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 Checkups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.749 (0.710,0.784)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.786 (0.702,0.877)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.642 (0.524,0.686)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.076 (0.066,0.088)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 Checkups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.765 (0.730,0.801)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.792 (0.702,0.904)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.646 (0.516,0.710)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.067 (0.057,0.078)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 Checkups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.792 (0.758,0.825)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.791 (0.611,0.911)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.695 (0.503,0.790)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.066 (0.055,0.077)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>LSTM&#160;=&#160;long short-term memory. AUC&#160;=&#160;area under the curve.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0105">For comparison, LR was also used to develop prediction models at each health checkup, the model performance was presented in Supplemental Tab. 7. Although AUC increased with updated health checkup records, from 0.724 (95% CI: 0.695,0.753) to 0.784 (95% CI: 0.758,0.810) in internal validation dataset, and from 0.713 (0.673,0.753) to 0.787 (0.750,0.823) in external validation dataset, the overall performance of the model was inferior to that of LSTM models (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.0001) based on the result of repeated measures ANOVA, and the improvement trend was not as strong as the latter (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.0001), as evidenced by the results presented in Supplemental Tab. 8 and Supplemental Tab. 9. Specifically, significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&lt;&#160;0.001) were observed in the prediction performance of the models in the internal validation set as the number of health checkups varied. Additionally, the LSTM models outperformed the LR models in terms of overall performance over five time points, with mean AUC values of 0.770 and 0.752, respectively. Moreover, the trend in AUC improvement with the update of checkup records differed significantly between the two models, with the LSTM model showing a stronger improvement trend than the LR model (difference in AUC between final and initial visits: 0.089 vs. 0.060, respectively). These results were further supported by external validation. Besides, to more clearly compare the predictive performance differences between LR and LSTM models, we also used Wilcoxon signed rank tests to compare the AUC differences between the two models at or before each time point. The results are presented in Supplemental Tab. 10.</p><p id="p0110">To address the concern of potential improvement in model performance due to the decreasing time interval between the measurement time of the variables and the occurrence of the outcome with the incorporation of new health checkup records, we further developed models relative to the time of the fifth checkup, incorporating the fourth, the third, and until the first gradually, and evaluating its performance. The results are presented in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>A and B and <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, which also showed an increased trend in model performance.<fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>AUC as a function of checkup times incorporated from the fifth checkup till the first in the internal validation dataset (A) and external validation dataset (B).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr5.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Model performance incorporated checkup data from the fifth till the first.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0070">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">AUC</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sensitivity</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Specificity</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Brier score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" rowspan="1">Internal validation dataset</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5th Checkup</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.765 (0.739,0.790)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.770 (0.679,0.858)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.655 (0.564,0.729)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.118 (0.110,0.127)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4th-5th Checkups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.772 (0.745,0.796)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.774 (0.677,0.855)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.666 (0.566,0.750)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.115 (0.106,0.123)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3rd-5th Checkups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.797 (0.771,0.821)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.789 (0.699,0.865)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.684 (0.608,0.763)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.092 (0.083,0.101)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2nd-5th Checkups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.800 (0.775,0.824)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.773 (0.686,0.844)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.712 (0.649,0.807)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.071 (0.060,0.084)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1st-5th Checkups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.818 (0.798,0.844)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.804 (0.713,0.873)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.690 (0.627,0.772)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.052 (0.041,0.066)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left" rowspan="1">External validation dataset</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5th Checkup</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.740 (0.697,0.785)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.629 (0.494,0.748)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.770 (0.684,0.879)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.088 (0.082,0.095)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4th-5th Checkups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.762 (0.723,0.797)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.717 (0.494,0.888)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.682 (0.449,0.888)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.091 (0.084,0.098)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3rd-5th Checkups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.768 (0.741,0.806)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.784 (0.696,0.892)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.647 (0.533,0.723)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.081 (0.073,0.088)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2nd-5th Checkups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.789 (0.756,0.821)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.804 (0.607,0.950)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.640 (0.476,0.832)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.079 (0.073,0.086)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1st-5th Checkups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.792 (0.758,0.825)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.791 (0.611,0.911)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.695 (0.503,0.790)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.066 (0.055,0.077)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>AUC&#160;=&#160;area under the curve.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0115">The contributions of each feature in the model related to the risk of NAFLD are shown in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>A and B. Among all these features, body fat percentage, ALT, and uric acid own the biggest impact on the outcome, with higher values above indicating greater risks of the development of NAFLD. Besides, some demographic characteristics, like income and education, are also at the priority level.<fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Summary plot of the impact of features on the risk of NAFLD. (A) The blue bars represent the sum of the absolute SHAP value on features. The higher SHAP values indicate more contributions to prediction. (B) Feature significance decreased from top to bottom. Each point represents the impact of a feature on NAFLD prediction for one participant at a given checkup time. Red points with positive SHAP values, which are the same as blue points with negative SHAP values, represent positive associations with the outcome, while red points with negative SHAP values, similarly to blue points with positive SHAP values, mean negative relationships. BFP&#160;=&#160;body fat percentage. ALT&#160;=&#160;alanine transaminase. UA&#160;=&#160;uric acid. WC&#160;=&#160;waist circumference. DB&#160;=&#160;direct bilirubin. LD&#160;=&#160;lactate dehydrogenase. TG&#160;=&#160;triglyceride. AST&#160;=&#160;aspartate aminotransferase. HDLC&#160;=&#160;high-density lipoprotein cholesterol. ALP&#160;=&#160;alkaline phosphatase. GGT&#160;=&#160;glutamyl transferase. GLB&#160;=&#160;globulin. BMI&#160;=&#160;body mass index.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Fig. 6</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr6.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0120">The dynamic prediction model can also be interpreted at a specific checkup time, the summary plots of which can be seen in Supplemental F. 2&#8211;6. The results of the mean importance rank of the features over time are presented in <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>, which illustrates the changing contributions of a certain feature. We note that body fat percentage and ATL occupied the top ranks in almost all checkup times, HDLC gained importance with the extension of time steps, while the ranks of DB decreased, meaning losing importance over time.<fig id="fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>The dynamic impact of features on the risk of NAFLD. BFP&#160;=&#160;body fat percentage. ALT&#160;=&#160;alanine transaminase. UA&#160;=&#160;uric acid. WC&#160;=&#160;waist circumference. DB&#160;=&#160;direct bilirubin. LD&#160;=&#160;lactate dehydrogenase. TG&#160;=&#160;triglyceride. AST&#160;=&#160;aspartate aminotransferase. HDLC&#160;=&#160;high-density lipoprotein cholesterol. ALP&#160;=&#160;alkaline phosphatase. GGT&#160;=&#160;glutamyl transferase. GLB&#160;=&#160;globulin. BMI&#160;=&#160;body mass index.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Fig. 7</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr7.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0125">We presented the fourth and fifth checkups of a representative case from the internal validation dataset in <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>A and B, respectively. The participant was a 45-year-old male, with an undergraduate degree and a moderate level of income. At his fourth checkup, his BMI was 26.93&#160;kg/m<sup>2</sup>, waist circumference 82&#160;cm, and body fat percentage 39.0%, with none of the three chronic diseases. Laboratory tests showed his direct bilirubin 2.67&#160;&#956;mol/L, ALT 16.0U/L, TG 1.95&#160;mmol/L, and HDLC 1.01&#160;mmol/L, which were all risk factors identified by the model. One year later, he tested a 10U/L increase in GGT, which was out of the normal range and pulled the prediction towards the onset of NAFLD. The values of waist circumstance, TG and direct bilirubin decreased but were still identified as risk factors. Meanwhile, the measurements of BMI, body fat percentage, HDLC, ALT and LD, increased a little compared with the fourth checkup, although most of which, especially the laboratory test results, were still within their normal limits, identified as strong risk factors to the prediction. This participant was diagnosed with NAFLD at his sixth checkup. More information about this individual can be seen in Supplemental Tab. 11.<fig id="fig8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Time-specific impact of features for a single participant (A) the 4th checkup (B) the 5th checkup. The features in red color drive the outcome towards the side of the development of the NAFLD, while the features in blue color pull down the risk probability.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Fig. 8</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr8.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0130">BFP&#160;=&#160;body fat percentage. GGT&#160;=&#160;glutamyl transferase. DB&#160;=&#160;direct bilirubin. ALT&#160;=&#160;alanine transaminase. TG&#160;=&#160;triglyceride. HDLC&#160;=&#160;high-density lipoprotein cholesterol. UA&#160;=&#160;uric acid. WC&#160;=&#160;waist circumference. LD&#160;=&#160;lactate dehydrogenase. BMI&#160;=&#160;body mass index. GLB&#160;=&#160;globulin.</p><p id="p0135">We further explored the relationships between features and the outcome, and detailed how some features interact (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>). A non-linear relationship exists between UA measured at the third checkup, ALP measured at the fourth checkup and the outcome (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>A and B). The normal ranges of UA and ALP are 180&#8211;420&#160;mmol/L and 40&#8211;150U/L, respectively, meaning that the results of these two laboratory tests in most participants are within the normal ranges. Besides, the relationship between the measurement value and the risk of NAFLD was found to be non-linear, contrary to the expected linear relationship. Specifically, the risk of NAFLD increased initially with the measurement values, followed by a decrease, indicating a complex relationship between the predictors and the outcome. Furthermore, it is obvious that a higher value of HDLC is associated with a lower risk of NAFLD, but when considering BMI, we can see that most of the dots in red color, indicating high BMI, are distributed far away from the position of 0 SHAP value, which means that the interaction of high BMI and HDLC has a stronger impact on the prediction (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>C). Similarly, a lower educational degree forebodes a higher risk of NAFLD, and a higher BMI also strengthens the impact (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>D).<fig id="fig9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Impact of feature interactions on NAFLD prediction. (A) the relationship between UA and the outcome; (B) the relationship between ALP and the outcome; (C) the interaction of HDLC and BMI; (D) the interaction of education and BMI. The SHAP value corresponding to each dot represents the impact of a feature and its interaction with other features for one participant. The positive SHAP value pushes the prediction towards the onset of NAFLD, while the negative SHAP value reduces the risk of the disease. UA&#160;=&#160;uric acid. ALP&#160;=&#160;alkaline phosphatase. HDLC&#160;=&#160;high-density lipoprotein cholesterol. BMI&#160;=&#160;body mass index.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0055">Fig. 9</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr9.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0140">In this study, a time-series deep learning model was developed to predict the risk of NAFLD within the health checkup population, and the model was updated when new checkup records were incorporated to achieve dynamic prediction. SHAP algorithm was used to enhance model interpretability and identify features that had a great impact on outcomes.</p><p id="p0145">As expected, with the extension of the time step, the latest records were incorporated and more information about temporal trends was contained, so the model performance improved significantly. However, when incorporating records from the first checkups to the fifth checkups stepwise, the time of predictors measurement will approach the time of prediction, so the model performance may improve on this account. To deal with this problem, we further developed a model relative to the time of the fifth checkup, incorporating the fourth, the third, and until the first gradually, and evaluating its performance. The results also showed an increased trend in model performance, although not as significant as the forward incorporation. This finding indicates that the features measured years before the development of NAFLD are still of great value and need to be taken into account to better predict the outcome.</p><p id="p0150">While cross-sectional data-based diagnostic prediction models have shown promising results, they fall short in predicting the future incidence of NAFLD and identifying high-risk populations before the onset of the disease [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Prognosis prediction models, on the other hand, excel in early risk estimation for diseases. Compared to existing studies on prognosis prediction models, the predictive performance of the model developed in our study demonstrates certain advantages. In a study by Zhu et al., multivariate LR model was constructed to predict the risk of NAFLD among lean pre-diabetics with normal blood lipid levels, achieving an AUC of 0.796 in the longitudinal internal validation with a 5-year follow-up period [<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Abeysekera et al. utilized variables measured at the participants' adolescence to predict the incidence risk of NAFLD at the age of 24 using LR, yielding the highest AUROC of 0.79 [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Wang et al. conducted a four-year cohort study to predict the incidence risk of NAFLD among 13,240 baseline NAFLD-free individuals using cox proportional hazards regression analyses. In the internal validation cohort, the AUC for 1-year, 2-year, 3-year, and 4-year risk predictions were 0.817, 0.820, 0.814, and 0.813, respectively [<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. In contrast, our study focused on developing a dynamic prediction model with constantly updated health checkup records using advanced deep learning algorithms that estimated the incidence risk of NAFLD from the sixth health checkup onwards until the end of the follow-up period. The internal validation set yielded an impressive highest AUC of 0.818 (0.798, 0.844), showcasing the innovative and competitive performance of our model.</p><p id="p0155">Our research reveals that the prediction model we established surpasses the LR model used as the benchmark. We found that our LSTM-based model's performance further enhanced as more recent health checkup records become available compared to the LR model. This implies that the LSTM model could offer more accurate predictions over a longer time span of data. Additionally, as both models employ the same predictive variables, the cost of using either model remains identical. Our validation set results demonstrate that while the LR model's discriminative ability improves with updated health checkup records, its calibration ability decreases. Conversely, our LSTM-based prediction model exhibits greater robustness, stability, and generalizability. Our findings suggest that the LSTM model could serve as a more dependable and precise tool for time-series data prediction, offering superior performance to the LR model.</p><p id="p0160">Although in many studies, BMI was regarded as an important predictor of NAFLD [<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>], we identified the more valid body measurement indicator, body fat percentage. This indicator could help recognize those with normal weight obesity, whose BMI cannot tell [<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Besides, this feature had a roughly increased importance rank over time, showing more value than other body measurement indicators [<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. As a practical, easily measured, and non-invasive indicator, we recommend using body fat percentage to supplement other body measurement indicators. However, further research needs to be done to test whether there exists a causal relationship between BFP and NAFLD. ALT, a standard and commonly used indicator of liver function, was found to have a great impact on the prediction in our study. As an enzyme in the cytosol of hepatocytes, only a low level of ALT can be detected in the serum in a healthy population, elevated ALT level usually indicates the injury or apoptosis of hepatocytes [<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Previous studies have also concluded that the increased ALT value was associated with a higher risk of NAFLD [<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>]. In a cross-sectional study on elderly Chinese man and woman, ALT was observed to have a significant joint association with serum uric acid to NAFLD prevalence [<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], although we haven't considered the joint contribution of the two features in our study, serum uric acid was also found to have a strong impact on the outcome. The global contribution of UA in all five checkups showed that a high level of the feature driving the outcome towards the side of NAFLD. Meanwhile, we also found a non-linear relationship between UA and the outcome that existed in a single checkup. Some cross-sectional studies have demonstrated that serum uric acid was positively associated with the prevalence of NAFLD in Chinses population [<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Besides, a case-control study also indicated that uric acid was an independent predictor of NAFLD [<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. As the end product of purine metabolism, high levels of serum uric acid could induce fat accumulation and then lead to the development of fatty liver [<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Waist circumference was also a significant predictor of NAFLD, consistent finding has been revealed in previous studies [<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Furthermore, our results also showed that direct bilirubin levels from five or more years ago can have a significant and continuous effect on the development of NAFLD, which may hint at its long-term effect on the onset of the disease. Nevertheless, lifestyle habits collected from the questionnaire survey, including dietary condition and smoking status, although proved to be associated with the development of NAFLD by other studies [<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>], were not regarded as important factors in our study. It makes sense when considering the long-time interval between the survey time of these habits and the prediction, along with the possible changeability of these features. From the SHAP algorithms, we also illustrated the interactions between some features. We found that a high BMI could strengthen the impact of certain features on the outcome, including HDLC and education. Specifically, the interactions between high BMI and the two features tended to drive the outcome towards two extremes. Thus, minor changes in laboratory test results for the high BMI population may have a strong impact on the development of NAFLD, which deserves more attention.</p><p id="p0165">We selected a representative sample from the internal validation dataset to show the quantitative and individual-specific impact of features and provide the changing process over time. This sample was predicted to develop NAFLD in the future based on his consecutive 5 checkups. But when regardless of his initial 4 checkups and only his last checkup record was included, he would be predicted as exempted from NAFLD, which appears to be a wrong prediction and is contrary to reality. Specifically, almost all features in his fifth checkup seemed not very abnormal and most were within normal limits, but when compared with his fourth checkup, we can find that there exists a slight increase in BMI, body fat percentage, HDLC, ALT, and many other features. Thus, we can conclude that it was the variation trend contained in the time-series checkup data that prompted the correct prediction. Although in some studies, time-series data were transformed into summary statistics, including mean, minimum and maximum values, to fully harness the information contained in the repeated measurement data [<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], the temporal trends in detail cannot be captured adequately [<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Therefore, instead of focusing on snapshot measurements or the transformed statistics of multiple measurements, the original measurement history and long-term trends of some features also need to be taken into account.</p><p id="p0170">It should be noted that our study was subject to the presence of right censoring as well as potential bias due to loss to follow-up, which are inherent limitations associated with utilizing health checkup data. As presented in Supplementary Tab. 12, we report the number and proportion of participants lost to follow-up at each subsequent health checkup after the sixth one. However, we performed a thorough analysis of participant characteristics between those who were lost to follow-up and those who were not at their sixth health checkup, as presented in Supplementary Tab. 13. Our comparison revealed that there were negligible differences between the two groups, as most indicators did not exhibit statistically significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#160;&gt;&#160;0.05), and the standardized mean difference (SMD) results indicated that almost all indicators had an SMD of less than 0.1 [<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. In addition, we also conducted a separate comparison of baseline characteristics between participants lost to follow-up and those who were not, taking into account the outcome (Supplementary Tab. 14). This allowed for a better comparison with <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The analysis revealed that the distribution of most characteristic differences between different outcomes was similar across both the lost to follow-up and not lost to follow-up groups. These findings partly mitigate the potential impact of loss to follow-up on our results.</p><p id="p0175">While our health check-up database contained data spanning 2003&#8211;2012, we chose to analyze only those individuals with six or more health checkups<bold>.</bold> This decision aimed to balance the trade-off between selecting too few or too many years of data, as the former would not fully reflect changes in the time-series data while the latter would result in an unacceptably small sample size. Supplementary Tab. 15 illustrates the relationship between the number of health checkups included and corresponding sample sizes and NAFLD incidence rates. Although selecting patients with seven or more health checkup records would provide richer data, it would reduce the sample size to below 10,000, compromising the statistical power of our deep learning model. Additionally, if the selected time span is too long, the corresponding population may be relatively healthy, with a low incidence rate of NAFLD, and thus the practical value of the model would be limited. Conversely, choosing five or fewer health check-up records would produce a relatively short time-series that might not capture the full spectrum of changes in the underlying data. Therefore, we opted to focus on patients with at least six recorded health checkups to maintain an optimal balance between sample size and data richness.</p><p id="p0180">We own some strengths in this study. Firstly, we made full use of the routine health checkup data and kept their time-series forms to extract the valuable information contained, and used the SHAP algorithm to visualize changing contributions of top predictors and provided the individual-level model explanation. Secondly, we explored the dynamic prediction by incorporating newly updated checkups to adapt to the evolving health checkup picture, which is more useful than a static one and can provide timely guidance to participants. Thirdly, we focused on developing a prognostic prediction model with a time interval of over one year to help identify high-risk groups at early stages, which may own more value compared with most of the current diagnostic prediction models. Fourthly, we verified the predictive performance of our model through external validation on a completely independent dataset, so the generalization and the practical value of the prediction model are in prospect.</p><p id="p0185">There are still several limitations in our study. Firstly, as the high prevalence rate of NAFLD, we filtered out those diagnosed with NAFLD in their initial five checkups and kept a relatively healthier population, which may limit the application of the model. Secondly, we trained the LSTM model with consecutively updated 5 checkups of each participant. Even though our longitudinal data spanned over 5 years, the checkup records hadn't been renewed at a very high frequency. While the strength of the LSTM algorithm lies in its learning about long-term dependencies, which may partially affect our results [<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Thirdly, our study did not comprehensively investigate the potential differences in missingness patterns between outcome groups and over time during the imputation of missing values, and the use of the LOCF method may not be optimal for our checkup data. Therefore, a more in-depth exploration of missingness imputation techniques is warranted to enhance the robustness of our results. Fourthly, although the MJ Health Screening Center performs calibration of its examination instruments and equipment regularly, the lengthy time frame of our study may still result in natural year-to-year differences in biochemical values. Fifthly, our feature selection process did not consider the longitudinal nature of the data, but instead relied solely on variables obtained during a single checkup, which may partly bias our results. Lastly, despite the relatively high sensitivity exhibited by our prediction model, there are still individuals who are incorrectly predicted as negative, resulting in false negatives. This may be due to the right censoring of data, which could lead to some study participants being diagnosed with NAFLD long after the fifth check-up. Nevertheless, it is essential to recognize that various factors may contribute to the manifestation of false negatives, and their quantification poses a significant challenge.</p><p id="p0190">In conclusion, we developed a dynamic and continuously updated deep learning model based on time-series health checkup data for the prediction of NAFLD in the future checkup and achieved good performance both in calibration and discrimination. Predictors of top significance were identified and their impact on the outcome was visualized both in global settings and individual settings.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Ethics statement</title><p id="p0195">Ethical approval from the Institutional Review Board of Peking University Health Science Center (ID of the approval: IRB00001052-19077) was received by this study. And as all data were de-identified in this study, individual informed consent was waived.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p id="p0200">Yuhan Deng, Yuan Ma and Jingzhu Fu: Conceived and designed the experiments; Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0205">Jianchun Yin, Canqing Yu, Jun Lv: Conceived and designed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data.</p><p id="p0210">Sailimai Man, Bo Wang, Liming Li: Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Funding statement</title><p id="p0240">This work was funded by the <funding-source id="gs1">Ministry of Science and Technology of the People&#8217;s Republic of China</funding-source> (grant number 2020YFC2004703); the <funding-source id="gs2">National Natural Science Foundation of China</funding-source> (grant number 82192901, 82192904, 82192900); and the <funding-source id="gs3">Ministry of Science and Technology of the People&#8217;s Republic of China</funding-source> (grant number 2020YFC2003405).</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec7"><title>Data availability statement</title><p id="p0215">The authors do not have permission to share data.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0225">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>Y.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence, incidence, and outcome of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease in Asia, 1999-2019: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Lancet Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><volume>4</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2468-1253(19)30039-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30902670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marjot</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moolla</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cobbold</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hodson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomlinson</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease in adults: current concepts in etiology, outcomes, and management</article-title><source>Endocr. Rev.</source><volume>41</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>bnz009</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/endrev/bnz009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31629366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paik</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kabbara</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eberly</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Younossi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Younossi</surname><given-names>Z.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global burden of NAFLD and chronic liver disease among adolescents and young adults</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><volume>75</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>1204</fpage><lpage>1217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.32228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34741554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Noureddin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ntanios</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoover</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emir</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predicting NAFLD prevalence in the United States using National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey 2017-2018 transient elastography data and application of machine learning</article-title><source>Hepatol Commun</source><volume>6</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>1537</fpage><lpage>1548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep4.1935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35365931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9234676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A predictive model for the diagnosis of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease based on an integrated machine learning method</article-title><source>Am J Transl Res</source><volume>13</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>12704</fpage><lpage>12713</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34956485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8661138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atsawarungruangkit</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laoveeravat</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Promrat</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Machine learning models for predicting non-alcoholic fatty liver disease in the general United States population: NHANES database</article-title><source>World J. Hepatol.</source><volume>13</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>1417</fpage><lpage>1427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4254/wjh.v13.i10.1417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34786176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8568572</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A machine learning based framework to identify and classify non-alcoholic fatty liver disease in a large-scale population</article-title><source>Front. Public Health</source><volume>10</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">846118</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.846118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9013842</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35444985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ming</surname><given-names>Z.Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison and development of advanced machine learning tools to predict nonalcoholic fatty liver disease: an extended study</article-title><source>Hepatobiliary Pancreat. Dis. Int.</source><volume>20</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.hbpd.2021.08.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34420885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kristinsson</surname><given-names>&#198;.&#214;.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#248;lgaard</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haahr-Raunkj&#230;r</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyhoff</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aasvang</surname><given-names>E.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#248;rensen</surname><given-names>H.B.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prediction of serious outcomes based on continuous vital sign monitoring of high-risk patients</article-title><source>Comput. Biol. Med.</source><volume>147</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">105559</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.compbiomed.2022.105559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35635901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>LeCun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bengio</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinton</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deep learning</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>521</volume><issue>7553</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>436</fpage><lpage>444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26017442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemati</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holder</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Razmi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clifford</surname><given-names>G.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchman</surname><given-names>T.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An interpretable machine learning model for accurate prediction of sepsis in the ICU</article-title><source>Crit. Care Med.</source><volume>46</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>553</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CCM.0000000000002936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29286945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5851825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>London</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Artificial intelligence and black-box medical decisions: accuracy versus explainability</article-title><source>Hastings Cent. Rep.</source><volume>49</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hast.973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30790315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>W.X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The adoption of deep learning interpretability techniques on diabetic retinopathy analysis: a review</article-title><source>Med. Biol. Eng. Comput.</source><volume>60</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>642</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11517-021-02487-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35083634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8791699</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lundberg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.-I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A unified approach to interpreting model predictions</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 31st International Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems</source><year>2017</year><fpage>4768</fpage><lpage>4777</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemesure</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinz</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>N.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predictive modeling of depression and anxiety using electronic health records and a novel machine learning approach with artificial intelligence</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>1980</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33479383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-021-81368-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7820000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zoabi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deri-Rozov</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shomron</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Machine learning-based prediction of COVID-19 diagnosis based on symptoms</article-title><source>NPJ Digit Med</source><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>3</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33398013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41746-020-00372-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7782717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tasci</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuge</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Camphausen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krauze</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bias and class imbalance in oncologic data-towards inclusive and transferrable AI in large scale oncology data sets</article-title><source>Cancers</source><volume>14</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>2897</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35740563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/cancers14122897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9221277</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probabilistic outputs for support vector machines and comparisons to regularized likelihood methods</article-title><source>Advances in Large Margin Classifiers</source><volume>10</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>74</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hochreiter</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidhuber</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long short-term memory</article-title><source>Neural Comput.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>8</issue><year>1997</year><fpage>1735</fpage><lpage>1780</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/neco.1997.9.8.1735</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9377276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Machine learning classifiers for screening nonalcoholic fatty liver disease in general adults</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>3638</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36869105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-023-30750-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9984396</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and application of a novel model to predict the risk of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease among lean pre-diabetics with normal blood lipid levels</article-title><source>Lipids Health Dis.</source><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>149</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36585668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12944-022-01752-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9804963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abeysekera</surname><given-names>K.W.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>F.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton-Shield</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heron</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating future risk of NAFLD in adolescents: a prediction and decision curve analysis</article-title><source>BMC Gastroenterol.</source><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>323</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35773644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12876-022-02401-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9245230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and validation of a nomogram for predicting nonalcoholic fatty liver disease in the non-obese Chinese population</article-title><source>Am. J. Tourism Res.</source><volume>12</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>6149</fpage><lpage>6159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7653603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33194020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saokaew</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanchanasuwan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apisarnthanarak</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charoensak</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charatcharoenwitthaya</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phisalprapa</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical risk scoring for predicting non-alcoholic fatty liver disease in metabolic syndrome patients (NAFLD-MS score)</article-title><source>Liver Int.</source><volume>37</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1535</fpage><lpage>1543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28294515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/liv.13413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rigamonti</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bondesan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rondinelli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cella</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sartorio</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of aspartate transaminase to platelet ratio index (APRI) for the prediction of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) in severely obese children and adolescents</article-title><source>Metabolites</source><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>155</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35208229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/metabo12020155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8879448</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abeysekera</surname><given-names>K.W.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>F.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton-Shield</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heron</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluating future risk of NAFLD in adolescents: a prediction and decision curve analysis</article-title><source>BMC Gastroenterol.</source><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>323</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35773644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12876-022-02401-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9245230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveros</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>V.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sochor</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Jimenez</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The concept of normal weight obesity</article-title><source>Prog. Cardiovasc. Dis.</source><volume>56</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24438734</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pcad.2013.10.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mainous</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rooks</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Medley</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickmann</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Body composition among adults at a healthy body mass index and association with undetected non-alcoholic fatty liver</article-title><source>Int. J. Obes.</source><volume>46</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>1403</fpage><lpage>1405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41366-022-01124-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35461347</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>W.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flamm</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Bisceglie</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Serum activity of alanine aminotransferase (ALT) as an indicator of health and disease</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><volume>47</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>1363</fpage><lpage>1370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18366115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hep.22109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proportion of NAFLD patients with normal ALT value in overall NAFLD patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>BMC Gastroenterol.</source><volume>20</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31937252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12876-020-1165-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6961232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amarapurka</surname><given-names>D.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amarapurkar</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>N.D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nonalcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH) with diabetes: predictors of liver fibrosis</article-title><source>Ann. Hepatol.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16531962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedley</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colantonio</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Massaro</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muntner</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development and validation of the framingham steatosis index to identify persons with hepatic steatosis</article-title><source>Clin. Gastroenterol. Hepatol.</source><volume>14</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1172</fpage><lpage>1180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27046482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cgh.2016.03.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4955680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Joint associations of serum uric acid and ALT with NAFLD in elderly men and women: a Chinese cross-sectional study</article-title><source>J. Transl. Med.</source><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>285</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30333032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12967-018-1657-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6192201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of serum uric acid level with non-alcoholic fatty liver disease: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>J. Hepatol.</source><volume>50</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>1029</fpage><lpage>1034</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19299029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jhep.2008.11.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lonardo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loria</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borsatti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neri</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pulvirenti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fasting insulin and uric acid levels but not indices of iron metabolism are independent predictors of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease. A case-control study</article-title><source>Dig. Liver Dis.</source><volume>34</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11990393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1590-8658(02)80194-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>H.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Uric acid induces fat accumulation via generation of endoplasmic reticulum stress and SREBP-1c activation in hepatocytes</article-title><source>Lab. Invest.</source><volume>94</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>1114</fpage><lpage>1125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25111690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/labinvest.2014.98</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atsawarungruangkit</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laoveeravat</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Promrat</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Machine learning models for predicting non-alcoholic fatty liver disease in the general United States population: NHANES database</article-title><source>World J. Hepatol.</source><volume>13</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>1417</fpage><lpage>1427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34786176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4254/wjh.v13.i10.1417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8568572</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Molina-Molina</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Furtado</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Portincasa</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vieira-Pedrosa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The advantages of physical exercise as a preventive strategy against NAFLD in postmenopausal women</article-title><source>Eur. J. Clin. Invest.</source><volume>52</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e13731</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/eci.13731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34890043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebrahimi Mousavi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dehghanseresht</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dashti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khazaei</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salamat</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The association between Dietary Diversity Score and odds of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease: a case-control study</article-title><source>Eur. J. Gastroenterol. Hepatol.</source><volume>34</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>678</fpage><lpage>685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35352692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MEG.0000000000002344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dairy protein intake is inversely related to development of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease</article-title><source>Clin Nutr</source><volume>40</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>5252</fpage><lpage>5260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34534894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.clnu.2021.08.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and validation of a novel blending machine learning model for hospital mortality prediction in ICU patients with Sepsis</article-title><source>BioData Min.</source><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021 Aug 16</year><fpage>40</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34399809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13040-021-00276-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8365981</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Machine learning prediction models for mechanically ventilated patients: analyses of the MIMIC-III database</article-title><source>Front. Med.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">662340</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmed.2021.662340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8280779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34277655</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez Bernal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soumerai</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gasparrini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A methodological framework for model selection in interrupted time series studies</article-title><source>J. Clin. Epidemiol.</source><volume>103</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29885427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2018.05.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klabjan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predicting ICU readmission using grouped physiological and medication trends</article-title><source>Artif. Intell. Med.</source><volume>95</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30213670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.artmed.2018.08.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6474661</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Statistical Power Analysis for the Behavioral Sciences</part-title><edition>second ed.</edition><year>1988</year><publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hillsdale, <italic toggle="yes">NJ</italic></publisher-loc><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gandin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scagnetto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbati</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interpretability of time-series deep learning models: a study in cardiovascular patients admitted to Intensive care unit</article-title><source>J. Biomed. Inf.</source><volume>121</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">103876</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jbi.2021.103876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34325021</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0230">The following is the Supplementary data to this article.<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Multimedia component 1</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Multimedia component 1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material></p></sec><fn-group><fn id="appsec2" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0235">Supplementary data to this article can be found online at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e18758" id="PC_linkzMRmoa23Ww">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e18758</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>