<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Cardiothorac Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann Cardiothorac Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2130</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">anncardsurg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ACS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Annals of Cardiothoracic Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2225-319X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2304-1021</issn><publisher><publisher-name>AME Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10711405</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10711405.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10711405</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10711405</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38090339</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/acs-2023-adw-17</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">acs-12-06-536</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Keynote Lecture Series</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The role of sex hormones in abdominal aortic aneurysms: a topical review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hultgren</surname><given-names initials="R">Rebecka</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Molecular Medicine and Surgery</institution>, <institution>Karolinska Institute</institution>, <addr-line>Stockholm</addr-line>, <country country="se">Sweden</country>;</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="dept">Department of Vascular Surgery</institution>, <institution>Karolinska University Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Stockholm</addr-line>, <country country="se">Sweden</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><italic toggle="yes">Correspondence to:</italic> Professor Rebecka Hultgren, MD, PhD. Department of Molecular Medicine and Surgery, Karolinska Institute, Stockholm, Sweden; Department of Vascular Surgery, Karolinska University Hospital, S3:01, 17176 Stockholm, Sweden. Email: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="rebecka.hultgren@ki.se">rebecka.hultgren@ki.se</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue>6</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">450721</issue-id><fpage>536</fpage><lpage>548</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>06</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-01-29 00:25:09.870"><day>29</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>2023 Annals of Cardiothoracic Surgery. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Annals of Cardiothoracic Surgery.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><italic toggle="yes">Open Access Statement:</italic> This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 International License (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0), which permits the non-commercial replication and distribution of the article with the strict proviso that no changes or edits are made and the original work is properly cited (including links to both the formal publication through the relevant DOI and the license). See: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="acs-12-06-536.pdf"/><abstract><p>Sex discrepancies have been reported for patients with abdominal aortic aneurysm (AAA) for decades. Men have a higher prevalence of disease, earlier onset, less morphological features obstructing eligibility for repair and better survival, both short and long term. In more recent years, several attempts have been made to identify the biologic or pathogenic factors contributing to these sex differences, including socioeconomic factors though all have failed. The greatest challenge is to reveal the variable mechanism for development of disease for both women and men, and secondly to identify the factors contributing to the progression of disease, and eventual rupture. Evaluations of diagnosed patients have failed to detect any factors associated with development of disease which would give a distinct explanation for the profound sex differences. Considering the obvious earlier trigger for development in men compared to women, excluding smoking, hypertension, hyperlipidemia as certified sole triggers, the remaining factors to explore are sex hormones or biological mechanisms. This topical review explores the contemporary publications on sex hormones and their association with AAA in women and men. The findings confirm the lack of scientific evidence for the influence of female and male sex hormones on development or progression of aneurysm disease. Weak indications support that women probably benefit from a longer reproductive history as a contributing protection against AAA development, influenced by smoking and heredity. There is some evidence that could support that, as for other manifestations of cardiovascular diseases, low testosterone levels in men, can contribute to an increased risk for AAA development. The influence of higher circulating levels of female sex hormones on risk development in men remains to be evaluated. In conclusion, this area will expand during the next decade, by combining registry-based and translational databases in stratified analysis for women and men, giving us more evidence that will contribute to important risk factor estimations for future cohorts at risk of AAA development.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords: </title><kwd>Sex hormone</kwd><kwd>abdominal aortic aneurysm (AAA)</kwd><kwd>treatment</kwd><kwd>gender</kwd><kwd>aortic disease</kwd><kwd>testosterone</kwd><kwd>estradiol</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="sp1">the Swedish Heart-Lung Foundation</funding-source><award-id rid="sp1">No. HLF 20220282</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><sec><title>Profound sex differences in disease distribution</title><p>The question why such profound sex and gender differences are found in abdominal aortic aneurysm (AAA) patient groups has for decades remained unanswered. One can presume that there will not be one answer to such a question, but rather a multitude of responses. The key to exploring this will probably be to intensify the quest for defining the aneurysm phenotypes (<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>).</p><p>The four areas most intensely explored in the AAA field are prevalence rates, onset of disease development, treatment eligibility and mortality. Several of these areas will be reported elsewhere in this edition of the <italic toggle="yes">Annals of Cardiothoracic Surgery</italic>. There are other factors of interest within the AAA field, which goes beyond these aforementioned, such as the rarely debated higher proportion of AAA women with multilevel aortic disease as compared to men, which could influence eligibility rates (<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Additionally, the lack of &#8220;catch-up&#8221; regarding the prevalence of AAA in women as compared to other cardiovascular disease (CVD) patient groups in that women will never develop AAA in a similar proportion as men, in any age group, also requires investigation. These areas could be associated either directly or indirectly with female and male sex hormones (<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>).</p><p>A number of risk factors, both modifiable and non-modifiable, that are associated with disease development or are commonly reported in the AAA patient population have been known for decades, though are commonly not reported in a sex-stratified analysis (<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>-<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig"><italic toggle="yes">Figure 1</italic></xref>). The modifiable risk factors commonly associated with the development and progression of aortic disease are smoking, obesity and hyperlipidemia (<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>-<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Several reported non-modifiable factors in AAA patient groups are male sex, increasing age, heredity, depression, other aneurysms (thoracic/popliteal) and other manifestations of CVD disease (<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>) (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig"><italic toggle="yes">Figure 1</italic></xref>). The published reports on the distribution of these modifiable risk factors in the population, such as smoking or hyperlipidemia cannot be said to explain these profound sex differences regarding aneurysm development. If these gender differences partly explain the much higher proportion of women in rupture, patient groups with a lower ratio (3&#8211;4.1) remain to be explored further. One example serving as an illustration of these gender differences would be hyperlipidemia (<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="f1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Schematic summary of findings regarding risk factors commonly found in cohorts with AAA patients, and possible sex hormone associated factors. (A) In women. (B) In men. AAA, abdominal aortic aneurysm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="acs-12-06-536-f1.jpg"/></fig><p>It is possible that the axis of hypercholesterolemia influencing the later development of AAA exists in some phenotypes, and in these subgroups contributes to explain AAA disease development (<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Since some population-based reports show a higher chance for men to obtain successful treatment, reaching target lipid-levels in greater proportions than women, it is unlikely that this explains the much higher rate of AAA in men in general. Regarding coronary disease, a small but higher association for disease development in men with hypercholesterolemia was reported than for women (<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Overall, there is a demonstrated influence of sex hormone levels on lipid levels, high-density lipoprotein (HDL) as well as low-density lipoprotein (LDL) in both women and men. There could be an even stronger contributing risk factor for AAA occurrence in women than men with respect to increased LDL (<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). The challenge in understanding such an axis is the alterations in lipid levels at the menopausal transition in women, since women have increased LDL levels compared to their premenopausal state or men of the same age. Males with higher circulating testosterone concentrations had higher HDL cholesterol level, which decreases CVD risk (<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Which levels should be considered to influence the risk for disease development, and is the alterations in sex hormone levels to be considered as a surrogate for the influence of lipids?</p><p>Another example, smoking, has historically been more common in men (<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). In the last two decades, women in Sweden have been found to smoke more than men, though the AAA ratio between the sexes is not changing. By using contemporary data for AAA prevalence in men diagnosed by the population-based screening program for all 65-year-old men in Sweden (participation rate at 75%), a true declining rate in men is found (<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>-<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). This can possibly partly be due to the decreasing proportion of smokers nationally but should presumably then change the male:female ratio, which is not true (<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>-<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). A recent paper again also confirms the even more deleterious association between smoking and AAA in women as compared to men (<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Altogether, smoking habits cannot be the sole explanation for the vast sex differences in distribution of AAA (<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Other variables, such as alcohol consumption, obesity and others have been indirectly explored in patient series and cannot explain the four- to six-fold increased risk for men in the population. The remaining area to explore is therefore true biological sex-differences, where sex hormones must be a central factor to consider (<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). There is clearly an unknown impact by sex hormones of the pathophysiology of AAA, which apart from influencing the onset of disease could also influence the sex differences with respect to outcome. This summary includes a topical review of the studies published on patients with AAA with a focus on sex hormone analysis or reproductive history in humans.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>The search for relevant publications in the field was restricted to articles in English. The abstract of the articles in English were extracted by a literature search in the databases PubMed and Web of Science. The final search date was 10<sup>th</sup> April 2023. The studies were identified by using different combinations of keywords and the following chosen terms: &#8220;abdominal aortic aneurysm(s)&#8221;, &#8220;sex differences&#8221;, &#8220;gender differences&#8221;, &#8220;(o)estrogens&#8221;, &#8220;androgens&#8221;, &#8220;17bestradiol&#8221;, &#8220;testosterone&#8221;, &#8220;sex hormones&#8221;, &#8220;natural history&#8221;, and &#8220;risk factors&#8221; [controlled vocabulary medical subject heading (MeSH) and free text].</p><p>In total, 701 articles were primarily found, and 295 articles were determined to be relevant for this review after careful reading of the abstract and reference list by the author. All animal-based studies were excluded from the analysis. The remaining 26 abstracts were evaluated. Only human reports were included based on person-specific data (charts, registry or hormone levels). Due to the low number of reports and heterogeneity of methodology used, no further attempts to perform a meta-analysis was performed. The reports are presented for women and men separately. There is a summary and tabulation of the remaining included relevant reports (seven publications in women and four in men; <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Tables 1-3</italic></xref><xref rid="t2" ref-type="table"/><xref rid="t3" ref-type="table"/>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="t1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Reports regarding reproductive history, including HRT published for women with AAA</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="5.66%" span="1"/><col width="9.64%" span="1"/><col width="13.47%" span="1"/><col width="15.06%" span="1"/><col width="22.43%" span="1"/><col width="15.51%" span="1"/><col width="18.23%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author, publication year</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study design</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample size</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study aim</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reproductive history defines as menarche and menopause</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HRT treatment</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major finding</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Villard, 2011, (<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>)</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Case control questionnaire based</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">140 women with AAA, 140 controls with PAD; controls certified non-AAA</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Reproductive history in controls <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> AAA women reproductive history in women with smaller and larger AAA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Menarche: 13.5 years (PAD) <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 13.5 years (small AAA) <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 13.8 years (large AAA) (P=0.60)</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Ever used: 49% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 42% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 32% (P=0.13)</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Women with larger AAA more frequently had an earlier menopause and shorter reproductive time compared to women with PAD and smaller aneurysms</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1">Menopause: 49.7 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 49.9 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 47.7 years (P=0.011)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1">Reproductive time: 36.7 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 36.4 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 33.9 years (P=0.003)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Nyr&#248;nning, 2019, (<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospectively collected characteristics in HUNT trial</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">201 women with AAA and 19,823 controls (not certified AAA-free)</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Effect of female sex hormones compared with other risk factors for AAA development. S-estradiol levels collected prior to AAA development (n=376)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Menarche 13.7 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 13.6 years (P=0.17)</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Never user: 77% in AAA women <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 71.5% in controls (P=0.11)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strongest risk factor for AAA was smoking, occurrence of CVD and hypertension</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" scope="row">Prospectively collected serum levels of estradiol</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" rowspan="1">Menopause 48.7 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 49.4 years (P=0.15)</td><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1" align="center">HRT showed a non-significant protective effect. Estradiol levels measurable in more controls than AAA women</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1">Estradiol levels detectable in AAA patients 17% <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 24% in controls (P=0.075)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Chou, 2022, (<xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>)</td><td rowspan="4" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Extracted from the WHI database including observational data and three clinical trials</td><td rowspan="4" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">1,125 women with AAA and 101,119 controls (not certified AAA-free)</td><td rowspan="4" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Determine if premature menopause and early menarche influences the risk for AAA, and influence of smoking</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Menarche and menopause not presented separately</td><td rowspan="4" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">HRT usage not presented for groups</td><td rowspan="4" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">The combined effect of smoking and premature menopause with increased risk for AAA development indicates the need for further analysis in the area</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1">Reproductive time not presented separately for AAA and controls</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1">Premature menopause 11.9.% in AAA women <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 9.4% in control cohort</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1">Not significant after multivariable adjustment</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>HRT, hormone replacement therapy; AAA, abdominal aortic aneurysm; PAD, peripheral arterial disease; HUNT, Nord-Tr&#248;ndelag Health Study; CVD, cardiovascular disease.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="t2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Hormone replacement therapy and association with AAA in women, only studies in humans included</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="6.65%" span="1"/><col width="15.16%" span="1"/><col width="10.83%" span="1"/><col width="13.34%" span="1"/><col width="8.57%" span="1"/><col width="21.63%" span="1"/><col width="23.82%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author, publication year</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study design</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample size</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study aim</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reproductive history</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HRT treatment</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major finding</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Hsia, 2004, (<xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>)</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">RCT within the WHI</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">16,608 postmenopausal women. Definition of disease only including hospitalized for peripheral arterial disease; cases not specified</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Effect on peripheral disease requiring hospitalization with estrogens and progestin <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> placebo</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Not reported</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported in numbers</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">No certified significant risk for AAA and HRT</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1">Similar numbers of women with HRT suffered AAA (7 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1">A non-significant higher risk for AAA in HRT group <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> placebo (HR 1.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Hsia, 2006, (<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>)</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">RCT with &#8220;Estrogen alone&#8221; <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> placebo</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">10,739 postmenopausal women with hysterectomy; cases not specified</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Effect on disease development</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Not reported</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported in numbers</td><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">No certified significant risk for AAA and HRT</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1">More women with HRT suffered AAA (14 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1">A non-significant higher risk for AAA in HRT group <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> placebo (HR 2.40, 95% CI: 0.92&#8211;6.23)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iribarren, 2007, (<xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kaiser-permanent population, questionnaires, clinical and laboratory tests (<xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115 AAA women <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 57,868 (490 AAA men and 46,945 controls)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Explore traditional and new risk factors for AAA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19% HRT overall; nonsignificant protection with HRT in the multivariable model; 0.87 (95% CI: 0.55&#8211;1.37)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No certified protection for AAA with HRT</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Lederle, 2008, (<xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>)</td><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Extracted from the WHI database including observational data and three clinical trials</td><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">184 AAA women <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 161,808 controls</td><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Assess association between risk factors and AAA events as repair or rupture</td><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Not reported</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HRT never user 62% AAA women 44% controls</td><td rowspan="2" valign="top" align="center" colspan="1">Further studies will be needed to clarify the effect of hormone therapy on AAA. There are strong positive associations between age, smoking and AAA in women</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1">HRT current user in multivariable model and risk for AAA HR 0.48 (95% CI: 0.31&#8211;0.73)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nyr&#248;nning, 2019, (<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospectively collected characteristics in HUNT trial; prospectively collected serum levels of estradiol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201 AAA cases and <break/>19,823 controls</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">See <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 1</italic></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">See <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 1</italic></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HRT never user: 77% in AAA women <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 71.5% in controls (P=0.11)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strongest risk factor was smoking, CVD and hypertension. HRT showed a non-significant protective effect</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>AAA, abdominal aortic aneurysm; HRT, hormone replacement therapy; RCT, randomized controlled trial; WHI, Women&#8217;s Health Initiative; HR, hazard ratio; CI, confidence interval; CVD, cardiovascular disease.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="t3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Female and male sex hormone levels in men with AAA or without AAA, only including reports on humans</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="5.91%" span="1"/><col width="14.42%" span="1"/><col width="10.45%" span="1"/><col width="15.72%" span="1"/><col width="15.61%" span="1"/><col width="15.63%" span="1"/><col width="22.26%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author, publication year</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study design</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample size</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study aim</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male sex hormones main findings</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female sex hormones main findings</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major finding</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yeap, 2010, (<xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospectively collected biobank within population-based screening program for men aged 65&#8211;83 years (questionnaires, laboratory tests)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">262 men with AAA men and 3,358 controls without AAA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Association between male sex-hormone levels and risk for AAA measured by chemiluminescent immunoassays</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAA men had lower testosterone levels and higher LH levels than controls. Differences remained in multivariable analysis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not included in study</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results reveals a significant and independent inverse association between circulating free testosterone and AAA</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Villard, 2012, (<xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospectively collected pilot study</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 men with AAA; 36 women with AAA; 18 women with PAD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To investigate levels of established biomarkers for AAA in men and women, and to compare biomarker levels in women with and without AAAs</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not analyzed</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men with AAA had higher levels pf circulating estradiol than women (86.5 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 30.0 pmol/L, P&lt;0.001)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The lower levels of estradiol in women with AAAs compared with men suggest that the possible protective effect of endogenous estrogen cannot be explained by a difference in circulating levels of estradiol</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Villard, 2021, (<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospectively collected biobank within population-based screening program for 65-year-old men (questionnaires, laboratory tests)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">230 men with AAA and 222 controls without AAA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Association between male and female sex-hormone levels and risk for AAA measured by electrochemiluminescent immunoassay</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAA men had lower testosterone levels than controls, including more men with non-measurable levels. LH and SHBG similar. Differences did not remain in multivariable analysis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAA men had higher progesterone and estradiol levels than controls. More controls had non-detectable levels of female sex-hormones. Strong association between progesterone levels and risk for AAA remain in multivariable analysis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The higher female sex hormone levels in men with AAA suggest an effect of sex hormones on aneurysm development. The association between progesterone and aortic diameter stresses the importance of focusing on this unconsidered female sex hormone on aneurysm formation</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ohlsson, 2022, (<xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospectively collected biobank within population-based screening program for 65-year-old men (questionnaires, laboratory tests)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147 men with AAA and <break/>251 controls without AAA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Association between male and female sex-hormone levels and risk for AAA measured by high-performance sex steroid assay</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAA men had lower testosterone levels than controls, including more men with non-measurable levels. Differences did not remain in multivariable analysis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAA men had lower progesterone and estradiol levels than controls. Strong association between low progesterone levels and risk for AAA occurrence remain in multivariable analysis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measured by a high-performance sex steroid assay, progesterone and estradiol are inversely associated with AAA in men, independent of known risk factors</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>AAA, abdominal aortic aneurysm; LH, luteinizing hormone; PAD, peripheral arterial disease; SHBG, sex hormone-binding globulin.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="other1"><title>Sex hormones develops as a contributing factor to consider</title><p>The distribution of abdominal aortic disease is always in a ratio of 3&#8211;6:1 in men <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> women, with a considerably lower mean age at diagnosis and development detected in men (<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p><p>The apprehension of female sex as a protective risk factor for development of disease as well as the obvious delayed onset of disease, has intensified the quest for the female sex hormone as a protective underlying mechanism for disease development.</p><p>It is highly probable that the insight from the Women&#8217;s Health Initiative (WHI) and other trials in cardiac disease was a trigger for such interesting studies (<xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>-<xref rid="r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Few epidemiological or population-based studies have been performed in AAA patient groups, presumably mainly due to methodological challenges (mostly asymptomatic disease, slow progression, challenges in collecting reproductive history). The perspectives will be presented below from the large-scale population series to clinical series focused on sex hormones, finalizing with sex hormones analysis in aortic walls and some comments on the reported findings in animal models.</p></sec><sec sec-type="other2"><title>Sex hormones in women</title><p>The apprehension of female sex as a protective risk factor for AAA development has intensified the quest for the female sex hormone as a protective underlying mechanism for disease development. Few epidemiological or population-based studies have been performed, due to methodological challenges (<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Regarding sex hormones, one should discriminate between endogenous and exogenous female sex hormones. An overview of the published papers in the area reveals the paucity of knowledge and the contradictory findings (<xref rid="t1" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Tables 1,2</italic></xref><xref rid="t2" ref-type="table"/>; <xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig"><italic toggle="yes">Figure 1</italic></xref>).</p><sec><title>Endogenous female sex hormones</title><p>Within other cardiovascular patient groups, premature menopause has been reported to increase the risk for earlier onset of events (<xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). It is also shown indirectly as a protective effect on longevity by having a late menopause (<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Interestingly, menarche, early or late, has not shown a similar clear association between development or risk for CVD as menopause, but more indirectly as a factor in the &#8220;reproductive time&#8221;, that is, higher prolonged female sex hormone levels. In some reports, early menarche is associated with increased risk of diabetes and CVD. Later age at menopause and longer reproductive times have been associated with less risk for CVD, but the influence of smoking which lowers the &#8220;reproductive time&#8221; also influences CVD risk indirectly by influencing the hormonal axis (<xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>).</p><p>This has been interpreted as a direct vascular effect especially by estradiol, both in the short and long term (<xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Circulating estradiol will be considerably lower in the peri- and post-menopausal period, which accelerates the arteriosclerotic process. If higher endogenous female sex hormone levels would be protective for other CVDs, it could be postulated that this could contribute to the difference in AAA prevalence between the sexes as well. To explore if a life-span difference in the &#8220;reproductive time&#8221; (fertile period; length of time between ages at menarche and menopause) is different in women with AAA, a questionnaire-based investigation was performed in 2011 (<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). The endogenous reproductive history was then explored for the first time for AAA patient groups. With consideration of the risk that earlier menopause can be triggered also by smoking, which can affect AAA development especially in women, a control group with similar smoking habits was chosen (<xref rid="r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). The association with lower menopausal onset for smoker has been reported (<xref rid="r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). The control group were women with peripheral arterial disease (PAD) and were certified to not have AAA by ultrasound (US) examinations (<xref rid="t1" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 1</italic></xref>). Women with larger AAAs had an earlier menopause compared to non-AAA patients (47.7 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 49.9 years) (<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). The data suggested that the reproductive time, i.e., lower menstruating period in a lifetime, could be interpreted as a surrogate for an overall shorter life-time period of lower levels of circulating estradiol.</p><p>There were not any further attempts to replicate this study, until 2022 (<xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). A WHI-based investigation did an identical analysis in a considerably larger cohort. Unfortunately, the &#8220;controls&#8221; were not US-examined, and therefore a degree of uncertainty about how many of the control populations had AAA remains. Although there are several draw-backs with WHI-based investigations, such as the lack of certified AAA cases and AAA-free controls [by US or computed tomography (CT)] leading to a large underestimation of the AAA prevalence, the report confirms again the importance of smoking on a woman&#8217;s risk of developing AAA (<xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Smoking is, in itself, such a strong contributor to a lower menopausal age, and it is difficult to separate the influence of smoking on AAA development or its action on disease development by altering the reproductive time in these women.</p><p>In the population-based Norwegian Nord-Tr&#248;ndelag Health Study (HUNT) database, the association between postmenopausal hormone therapy (HT) was also evaluated, as well as menarche and menopause were also analyzed (<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). A non-significant lower menopausal age was detected (48.7 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 49.4 years, P=0.15) and a higher menarche age (13.7 <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> 13.6, P=0.15). Unfortunately, this database did not include the reproductive time individually for AAA patients <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> controls, since this was not the objective of the paper (<xref rid="t1" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Tables 1,2</italic></xref><xref rid="t2" ref-type="table"/>).</p><p>The hypothetically very appealing thought that the reproductive time, serving as a prolonged protection against AAA development by estradiol in premenopausal women, is still not scientifically proven, though the literature does indicate that this could be a factor to consider and include in all future population-based trials in women.</p></sec><sec><title>Exogenous female sex hormones</title><p>If the pilot trial on reproductive history published in 2011 was an indication that a lower circulating female sex hormone levels (a shorter individual reproductive time) would indicate an increased proportion of larger aneurysms, one could suspect that exogenous hormone replacement therapy could decrease the risk for development of AAA (<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>).</p><p>One could also replicate other reported knowledge regarding hormone replacement therapy for example in CVD patient groups to AAA (<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Could exogenous HT contribute with a protection of onset of disease? These explorations have predominantly been performed within larger other trials in the US (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 2</italic></xref>).</p><p>Interestingly, the three studies performed in the same WHI cohort from the US showed quite contradictory results (<xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). The investigation published in 2008, which identified 184 women with AAA, suggested a protective effect by HRT on AAA risk, in a population of 160,000 women (<xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). In a smaller subset of the WHI women, published earlier, they failed to demonstrate such association (2004 and 2006) (<xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). During the same time period one population-based study showed a trend, but non-significant protective effect by HRT on AAA risk, and as always smoking dominated as risk factor (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 2</italic></xref>) (<xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p><p>In an attempt to catch the temporal effects by HRT and AAA development a combined clinical registry-based and laboratory analysis was performed in Norway in 2019. This was the hitherto largest study within the field, with &gt;200 women with AAA and &gt;20,000 women in the baseline group as controls (<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Smoking, hypertension and heart disease have a strong correlation with AAA risk in women, but not HRT (n=201/20,024) (<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) (<xref rid="t1" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Tables 1,2</italic></xref><xref rid="t2" ref-type="table"/>).</p><p>It is not confirmed that exogenous hormones protect against AAA development, but it is unlikely that it would hold negative effects for development of aneurysm disease.</p><p>It has never been clarified if female sex hormones, endogenous or exogenous, would influence rupture risk, growth of AAA or mortality in women with AAA with any higher degree of scientific certainty. The overarching methodological challenge is the study design with control populations without US-verified normal aortas as well as the recall bias for reproductive history outside parity.</p></sec><sec><title>Male and female sex hormones in men</title><p>Considering the relatively higher risk that men confer for aneurysm disease development earlier in life and their 3&#8211;6-fold higher risk overall, the lack of investigation in the area is astonishing (<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Historically, some attempts to explore the group of men with prostate cancer, with an iatrogenic induced hormonal imbalance of both estrogen and androgen has been published (<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Due to obvious methodological complexity, little can be extracted from this in order to certify the associations. Secondly, again it is highly probable that sex hormones influence individuals differently, and the phenotyping of AAA patient groups would probably contribute to a better understanding.</p><p>The first unique paper within the field already in 2010, reported lower levels of testosterone in men with AAA <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> controls (<xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>) (<xref rid="t3" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 3</italic></xref>). The second larger paper in the field also included female sex hormones and confirmed the above-mentioned association between lower testosterone and secondly higher levels of female sex hormones. It had been preceded by a smaller pilot study including estradiol measurements in women and men (<xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). These findings support those shown for other CVD patient groups; a low testosterone level is associated with more and earlier disease development (<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>) (<xref rid="t3" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 3</italic></xref>, <xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig"><italic toggle="yes">Figure 1</italic></xref>).</p><p>This paper was followed by an analysis based not on the standard immunohistochemical analysis but using the highly scientific but non-standardized Mass spectroscopy test for hormonal analysis (<xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). This showed that men with AAA had a lower level of female sex hormones compared to controls. How these methodological challenges should be interpreted and used in clinical practice is not clear, but they highlight that this area needs further exploration.</p><p>One factor seldom addressed in population-based risk factor evaluations is prostate cancer treatment (<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). In the above-mentioned study on screened men, with analysis of sex hormone levels, six men in the control group had been treated for prostate cancer, none of whom were AAA patients (<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). In the Australian study these were excluded (<xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). These groups are much too small to give any support for the analysis of such associations. Some reports have tried to explore these associations in larger cohorts but have failed to reach any sharp conclusions.</p><p>So, this question remains unanswered: is a subset of men more susceptible for aneurysmal disease due to deranged circulating sex hormone levels, either female or male? Few studies actually report on prostate cancer, detection or treatment in AAA populations, and vice versa, how is the risk of disease development influenced by prostate cancer treatment such as castration? (<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). How is the risk for AAA expansion and rupture influenced by such risk? Would there be a long-term higher risk for AAA development due to lower circulating testosterone levels in analogue with the reported higher general CVD risk for these patients? Regarding the high general risk for middle-aged and elderly men to develop AAA, CVD and prostate cancer, the lack of knowledge based on cohort studies or registries is also somewhat astonishing, also when considering the large registries within cancer research that exist internationally (<xref rid="r44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). The growing area of cardio-oncology will certainly include these aspects more in the coming decade.</p></sec><sec><title>Wall analysis</title><p>There is a noticeable lack of investigations on the human aortic wall and sex hormone receptors with respect to sex difference, presumably due to the methodological challenges and scarcity of laboratory know-how (<xref rid="r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Sex hormones influence the composition of the wall with respect to elastin, collagen and probably also the vascular smooth muscle cell (VSMC). Estrogen lowers collagen deposition, but increases the elastin deposition, both contrasting the testosterone effect (<xref rid="r45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>)</p><p>The estrogen receptor (ER) beta receptor is similarly expressed in human VSMC for men and women (<xref rid="r46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). In aortic aneurysm wall material, a higher expression of androgen receptor (AR) and lower expression of ER&#946; compared to normal aortic walls could mean that sex hormone vessel wall activity is associated with aneurysm development (<xref rid="r47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). These results are in accordance with the observed susceptibility to AAA formation in men and women with ER&#946; gene polymorphism (<xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>).</p><p>Prior biomarker analysis of aneurysm patients show that women had higher plasma levels of matrix metalloproteinase 9 (MMP9) than men with equivalent aortic diameters (<xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>).</p><p>There are three published reports regarding elastin and collagen in the aortic wall of women and men with AAA, with somewhat contradictory findings, but this is presumably due to methodological issues. The group from Austria showed low elastin and high collagen component in the wall under the thrombus in men compared to women, in contrast to higher elastin in men and similar collagen content in a Swedish study (<xref rid="r48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>-<xref rid="r50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>).</p><p>The contradictory findings in these unique but small studies suggest that more molecular and histological studies are called for in AAA and non-AAA populations in order to understand if the wall structure is truly different between the sexes, before and after onset of disease (<xref rid="r48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>).</p><p>One of the most challenging issues is that wall samples are collected at the end stage of the aneurysm disease, optimal analysis regarding the influence of sex hormones and receptor activity would be performed in the early period of aneurysm development (<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>The lack of coherence between human and animal models</title><p>Studies of animal models for AAA development, growth and rupture have increased the general understanding of hormonal mechanisms and underlying sex differences in AAA (<xref rid="r51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>-<xref rid="r55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). In general, endogenous and exogenous estrogens have protective effects on experimentally induced AAAs, with results differing dependent on the model under study (<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p><p>It is problematic that animal models today still fail to include the postmenopausal aspects of biological sex differences (<xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="r53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). There are no models including the effect of the human menstrual cycle and menopausal transition phase on the aortic wall. Consequently, human studies are crucial to perform. Animal models with ovariectomy does not mimic menopause, since it suddenly eliminates all hormone activity, such as luteinizing hormone (LH), follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) and progesterone/testosterone. In menopause, if not-surgically induced, the ovarian follicle diminishes over time.</p><p>The dominating risk for males to develop AAA, also at a younger age, led to the hypothesis testing and generation of different animal models that confirm that castration of male mice will reduce AAA development in angiotensin II-induced AAA models (<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="r53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Reduced growth rates and lower rupture rates in castrated male mice as well as studies showing increased disease development and growth by exogenous androgen substitution supported the hypothesis that male sex hormones contribute to the pathological increased risk detected in men. Further refinement in animal models move towards identifying that the true carrier of the risk could be AR dysfunction rather than the circulating levels of male sex hormones that influence the risk in male mice. The ARs modulate the inflammatory responses by elevating IL-1&#945; and possibly TGF&#946;1 (<xref rid="r56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>).</p><p>The animal models have in later years also included other species, such as swine, which introduces a model which is somewhat more similar to human aneurysm formation based on a surgically induced elastase-based aneurysm infrarenally (<xref rid="r57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). These studies confirm the higher risk for increased aneurysm growth in animals with intact androgen levels as compared to females and castrated male swine (<xref rid="r58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). In fact, there is notably a pronounced lower growth in castrated <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> female swine. The study elegantly also reports on higher elastin degradation in intact male swine compared to lower in females and castrated specimens, and lower collagen levels overall in females. Estrogen levels were highest in females, but lowest in castrated males. Testosterone was highest in males, and lowest in females, no significant difference between castrated and un-castrated (<xref rid="r57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,<xref rid="r58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>).</p><p>It is possible that the animal models for AAA development and rupture, although well designed and hypothesis generating, also has led the vascular community astray; since the models are very far from imitating AAA development in the aging population, men and women, smokers and non-smokers. Although evidence from animal models suggests a clear role for testosterone to promote AAA, there is little known about a role for endogenous or exogenous testosterone on human AAA, our reports as well as others, rather suggest that too low testosterone levels can be significant for CVD and AAA risk. Here, animal models stand in contrast with the association between low testosterone in human reports (<xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) (<xref rid="t3" ref-type="table"><italic toggle="yes">Table 3</italic></xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>New perspectives</title><p>In a recent publication from a Dutch group the possible importance of FSH was stressed (<xref rid="r59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). The hormones FSH and LH are essential hormones that stimulate the function of ovaries in females and testis in males, contributing to a normal reproduction. These hormones are derived from the pituitary gland, not the reproductive organs, and increase in women after menopause (<xref rid="r59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). In three prior publications on men with AAA, LH has been investigated (<xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Higher LH has been reported to be associated with increased risk for CVD and AAA (<xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="r56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). The authors suggest that increased FSH levels in women during a prolonged period could contribute with an increased AAA risk (<xref rid="r59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). As for all sex hormone circulating levels and AAA risk prediction, much remains to be explored before such an association could be confirmed.</p><p>Other factors to explore further are the differences between circulating sex hormone levels as compared to AR activity and also the different ERs. There is a vast lack of understanding on the effects of testosterone on CVD risk in men and women, for example, showing contradictory findings compared to the more simplified direct effects reported from mouse models (<xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>).</p><p>New perspectives and understanding of disease development could also emerge from inclusion of patient groups with different hormone levels as compared to the average population, such as groups with women diagnosed with Turners syndrome, treated or not with estradiol or in transgender groups treated with sex hormones (<xref rid="r60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). The possible influence of lipid levels and lipoprotein(a) [Lp(a)] is also investigated and could be the target molecule in future trials (<xref rid="r61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>). Associations between AAA onset and expansion with metformin treatment in diabetic or non-diabetic patients have not been analyzed with a sex and gender perspective (<xref rid="r62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). This could be essential to include in future randomized controlled trials (RCTs).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Vast sex differences regarding onset of disease, prevalence, eligibility, and treatment rates and outcomes regarding untreated and treated AAA patients are reported in the literature. The largest remaining key to understanding the basic sex and gender differences is to explore female and male sex hormones. This summary confirms the need for such explorations on all levels: molecular, temporal, registry-based and population-based in women and men. It also stresses the need to use the acquired knowledge obtained in animal models on presumed biological sex hormone wall differences and to apply this in translational research in humans. There is a need for collaborative networks in the field in order to succeed in large enough sample sizes in order to perform and succeed in such translational projects.</p><fig position="float" id="vid" fig-type="video" orientation="portrait"><label>Video</label><caption><p>The role of sex hormones in abdominal aortic aneurysms: a topical review.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="acs-12-06-536-vid.jpg"/><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="acs-12-06-536-vid.mp4" id="d64e1069" position="anchor" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mp4" orientation="portrait"/></fig></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Funding:</italic> The research project has been financially supported by <funding-source rid="sp1">the Swedish Heart-Lung Foundation</funding-source> (<award-id rid="sp1">No. HLF 20220282</award-id>) and the regional ALF agreement (Stockholm County Council/Karolinska Institute) regarding financial compensation for work combining clinical research and medical education.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><italic toggle="yes">Conflicts of Interest:</italic> The author has no conflicts of interest to declare.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakalihasan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katsargyris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Abdominal aortic aneurysms.</article-title><source>Nat Rev Dis Primers</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>34</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41572-018-0030-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30337540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Makrygiannis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Courtois</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drion</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sex differences in abdominal aortic aneurysm: the role of sex hormones.</article-title><source>Ann Vasc Surg</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>1946</fpage>-<lpage>58</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.avsg.2014.07.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25106102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stackelberg</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bj&#246;rck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alcohol consumption, specific alcoholic beverages, and abdominal aortic aneurysm.</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>130</volume>:<fpage>646</fpage>-<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.113.008279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24965567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stackelberg</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bj&#246;rck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadr-Azodi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Obesity and abdominal aortic aneurysm.</article-title><source>Br J Surg</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>360</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bjs.8983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23203847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lederle</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Smokers' relative risk for aortic aneurysm compared with other smoking-related diseases: a systematic review.</article-title><source>J Vasc Surg</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>329</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0741-5214(03)00136-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12891116</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fattahi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenblad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kragsterman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors in 50-year-old men predicting development of abdominal aortic aneurysm.</article-title><source>J Vasc Surg</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>1337</fpage>-<lpage>1346.e1</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvs.2019.11.062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32115319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyr&#248;nning</surname><given-names>L&#197;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hultgren</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albrektsen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prognostic impact of depressive symptoms on all-cause mortality in individuals with abdominal aortic aneurysm and in the general population: a population-based prospective HUNT study in Norway.</article-title><source>BMJ Open</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<elocation-id>e049055</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2021-049055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35039280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8765023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Talvitie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stenman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sex Differences in Rupture Risk and Mortality in Untreated Patients With Intact Abdominal Aortic Aneurysms.</article-title><source>J Am Heart Assoc</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<elocation-id>e019592</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/JAHA.120.019592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33619974</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8174277</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyr&#248;nning</surname><given-names>L&#197;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stenman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hultgren</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Symptoms of Depression and Risk of Abdominal Aortic Aneurysm: A HUNT Study.</article-title><source>J Am Heart Assoc</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<elocation-id>e012535</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/JAHA.119.012535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31642357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6898822</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherliker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sex-Specific Associations of Vascular Risk Factors With Abdominal Aortic Aneurysm: Findings From 1.5 Million Women and 0.8 Million Men in the United States and United Kingdom.</article-title><source>J Am Heart Assoc</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<elocation-id>e014748</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/JAHA.119.014748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32063115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7070225</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vishnevskaya</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High frequency of thoracic aneurysms in patients with abdominal aortic aneurysms.</article-title><source>Ann Surg</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>253</volume>:<fpage>180</fpage>-<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SLA.0b013e3181d96498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20571364</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guetta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>RO</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cardiovascular effects of estrogen and lipid-lowering therapies in postmenopausal women.</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1996</year>;<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>1928</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.cir.93.10.1928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8635273</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nastasi</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moxon</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Potential Benefits and Costs of an Intensified Approach to Low Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol Lowering in People with Abdominal Aortic Aneurysm.</article-title><source>Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>643</fpage>-<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejvs.2021.06.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34507892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singhateh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Total cholesterol as a risk factor for coronary heart disease and stroke in women compared with men: A systematic review and meta-analysis.</article-title><source>Atherosclerosis</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>248</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>-<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.atherosclerosis.2016.03.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27016614</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Middelberg</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spector</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swaminathan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic and environmental influences on lipids, lipoproteins, and apolipoproteins: effects of menopause.</article-title><source>Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1142</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.atv.0000022889.85440.79</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12117729</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shores</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biggs</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Testosterone, dihydrotestosterone, and incident cardiovascular disease and mortality in the cardiovascular health study.</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>2061</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.2013-3576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24628549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4037728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassis</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eghbali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sex Hormones and Sex Chromosomes Cause Sex Differences in the Development of Cardiovascular Diseases.</article-title><source>Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>746</fpage>-<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/ATVBAHA.116.307301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28279969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5437981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wanhainen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hultgren</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linn&#233;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Outcome of the Swedish Nationwide Abdominal Aortic Aneurysm Screening Program.</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>134</volume>:<fpage>1141</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.116.022305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27630132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Svensj&#246;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bj&#246;rck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wanhainen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Update on screening for abdominal aortic aneurysm: a topical review.</article-title><source>Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>659</fpage>-<lpage>67</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejvs.2014.08.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25443524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Svensj&#246;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bj&#246;rck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wanhainen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Current prevalence of abdominal aortic aneurysm in 70-year-old women.</article-title><source>Br J Surg</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>367</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bjs.8984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23192439</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">Tobacco consumption statistics. [Internet]. 2022. Available online: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/statistics-explained/index.php?title=Tobacco_consumption_statistics#Daily_smokers_of_cigarettes" ext-link-type="uri">https://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/statistics-explained/index.php?title=Tobacco_consumption_statistics#Daily_smokers_of_cigarettes</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Villard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hultgren</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abdominal aortic aneurysm: Sex differences.</article-title><source>Maturitas</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.maturitas.2017.12.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29452784</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Villard C, Swedenborg J, Eriksson P, et al. Reproductive history in women with abdominal aortic aneurysms. J Vasc Surg 2011;54:341-5, 345.e1-2.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jvs.2010.12.069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21620618</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyr&#248;nning</surname><given-names>L&#197;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Videm</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romundstad</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Female sex hormones and risk of incident abdominal aortic aneurysm in Norwegian women in the HUNT study.</article-title><source>J Vasc Surg</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>1436</fpage>-<lpage>1445.e2</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvs.2019.02.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31248762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pettinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haring</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of Premature Menopause With Risk of Abdominal Aortic Aneurysm in the Women's Health Initiative.</article-title><source>Ann Surg</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>276</volume>:<fpage>e1008</fpage>-<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SLA.0000000000004581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33156064</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Criqui</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodabough</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Estrogen plus progestin and the risk of peripheral arterial disease: the Women's Health Initiative.</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>620</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.0000115309.63979.92</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14769684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Criqui</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrington</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Conjugated equine estrogens and peripheral arterial disease risk: the Women's Health Initiative.</article-title><source>Am Heart J</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>152</volume>:<fpage>170</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ahj.2005.09.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16824852</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iribarren</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darbinian</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Go</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Traditional and novel risk factors for clinically diagnosed abdominal aortic aneurysm: the Kaiser multiphasic health checkup cohort study.</article-title><source>Ann Epidemiol</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>669</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annepidem.2007.02.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17512215</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baxa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferdova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Abdominal aortic aneurysm in prostate cancer patients: the "road map" from incidental detection to advanced predictive, preventive, and personalized approach utilizing common follow-up for both pathologies.</article-title><source>EPMA J</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>415</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13167-019-00193-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31832115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6882970</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lederle</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Margolis</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Abdominal aortic aneurysm events in the women's health initiative: cohort study.</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>337</volume>:<fpage>a1724</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.a1724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18854591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2658825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeap</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Associations of total testosterone, sex hormone-binding globulin, calculated free testosterone, and luteinizing hormone with prevalence of abdominal aortic aneurysm in older men.</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>1123</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.2009-1696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20061425</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Villard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>W&#229;gs&#228;ter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swedenborg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biomarkers for abdominal aortic aneurysms from a sex perspective.</article-title><source>Gend Med</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>-<lpage>266.e2</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.genm.2012.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22721599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Villard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bogdanovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sex hormones in men with abdominal aortic aneurysm.</article-title><source>J Vasc Surg</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>2023</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvs.2021.06.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34182029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohlsson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langenski&#246;ld</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smidfelt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Low Progesterone and Low Estradiol Levels Associate With Abdominal Aortic Aneurysms in Men.</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>107</volume>:<fpage>e1413</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/clinem/dgab867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34865072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8947245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Design of the Women's Health Initiative clinical trial and observational study. The Women's Health Initiative Study Group.</article-title><source>Control Clin Trials</source><year>1998</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>109</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0197-2456(97)00078-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9492970</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook-Wiens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Age at Menarche and Risk of Cardiovascular Disease Outcomes: Findings From the National Heart Lung and Blood Institute-Sponsored Women's Ischemia Syndrome Evaluation.</article-title><source>J Am Heart Assoc</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<elocation-id>e012406</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/JAHA.119.012406</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31165670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6645646</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boese</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sex differences in vascular physiology and pathophysiology: estrogen and androgen signaling in health and disease.</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>313</volume>:<fpage>H524</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpheart.00217.2016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28626075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5625178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Massart</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menegato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Allelic genes involved in artery compliance and susceptibility to sporadic abdominal aortic aneurysm.</article-title><source>J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>413</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsbmb.2004.10.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15698546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shadyab</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macera</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaffer</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ages at menarche and menopause and reproductive lifespan as predictors of exceptional longevity in women: the Women's Health Initiative.</article-title><source>Menopause</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/GME.0000000000000710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27465713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5177476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ventura-Clapier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dworatzek</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seeland</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sex in basic research: concepts in the cardiovascular field.</article-title><source>Cardiovasc Res</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>113</volume>:<fpage>711</fpage>-<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cvr/cvx066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28472454</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandler</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohlig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Active and passive smoking and the occurrence of natural menopause.</article-title><source>Epidemiology</source><year>1999</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>771</fpage>-<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10535795</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitcomb</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Purdue-Smithe</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szegda</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cigarette Smoking and Risk of Early Natural Menopause.</article-title><source>Am J Epidemiol</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>187</volume>:<fpage>696</fpage>-<lpage>704</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwx292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29020262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5888979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dowsett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cigarette smoking and endogenous sex hormones in postmenopausal women.</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>3184</fpage>-<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.2011-1165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21832108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Narayan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>How to Treat Prostate Cancer With Androgen Deprivation and Minimize Cardiovascular Risk: A Therapeutic Tightrope.</article-title><source>JACC CardioOncol</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>737</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaccao.2021.09.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34988484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8702790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Natoli</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Medley</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahimastos</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sex steroids modulate human aortic smooth muscle cell matrix protein deposition and matrix metalloproteinase expression.</article-title><source>Hypertension</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>1129</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.HYP.0000187016.06549.96</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16230520</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hodges</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tung</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Estrogen receptors alpha and beta: prevalence of estrogen receptor beta mRNA in human vascular smooth muscle and transcriptional effects.</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>1792</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.cir.101.15.1792</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10769279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Villard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kronqvist</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential expression of sex hormone receptors in abdominal aortic aneurysms.</article-title><source>Maturitas</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.maturitas.2016.11.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28041593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schriefl</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohnert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gender differences in biomechanical properties, thrombus age, mass fraction and clinical factors of abdominal aortic aneurysms.</article-title><source>Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>364</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejvs.2013.01.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23395130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Villard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swedenborg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differences in Elastin and Elastolytic Enzymes between Men and Women with Abdominal Aortic Aneurysm.</article-title><source>Aorta (Stamford)</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>-<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12945/j.aorta.2014.14-017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26798738</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4686357</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Villard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanemaaijer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The composition of collagen in the aneurysm wall of men and women.</article-title><source>J Vasc Surg</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>579</fpage>-<lpage>585.e1</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvs.2016.02.056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27234441</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Decreased collagen and increased matrix metalloproteinase-13 in experimental abdominal aortic aneurysms in males compared with females.</article-title><source>Surgery</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>147</volume>:<fpage>258</fpage>-<lpage>67</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.surg.2009.06.047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19767051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3017342</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodrum</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential regulation of aortic growth in male and female rodents is associated with AAA development.</article-title><source>J Surg Res</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>155</volume>:<fpage>330</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jss.2008.07.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19111327</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3205088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ailawadi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eliason</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gender differences in experimental aortic aneurysm formation.</article-title><source>Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>2116</fpage>-<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.ATV.0000143386.26399.84</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15331435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henriques</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Souza</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Orchidectomy, but not ovariectomy, regulates angiotensin II-induced vascular diseases in apolipoprotein E-deficient mice.</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>145</volume>:<fpage>3866</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.2003-1615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15105380</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increased estrogen receptor alpha in experimental aortic aneurysms in females compared with males.</article-title><source>J Surg Res</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>186</volume>:<fpage>467</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jss.2013.07.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23993200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3858525</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Androgen receptor (AR) in cardiovascular diseases.</article-title><source>J Endocrinol</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>229</volume>:<fpage>R1</fpage>-<lpage>R16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1530/JOE-15-0518</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26769913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4932893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r57"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A novel swine model of abdominal aortic aneurysm.</article-title><source>J Vasc Surg</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>252</fpage>-<lpage>260.e2</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvs.2018.09.057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30591288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6591111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r58"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sex-Based Differences Among Experimental Swine Abdominal Aortic aneurysms.</article-title><source>J Surg Res</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>260</volume>:<fpage>488</fpage>-<lpage>98</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jss.2020.11.061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33341252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7946779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r59"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tedjawirja</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nieuwdorp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A Novel Hypothesis: A Role for Follicle Stimulating Hormone in Abdominal Aortic Aneurysm Development in Postmenopausal Women.</article-title><source>Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<elocation-id>726107</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34721292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fendo.2021.726107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8548664</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r60"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meccanici</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schotte</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snoeren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aortic dilation and growth in women with Turner syndrome.</article-title><source>Heart</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>102</fpage>-<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/heartjnl-2022-320922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35705330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r61"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pettinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haring</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lipoprotein(a) levels and risk of abdominal aortic aneurysm in the Women's Health Initiative.</article-title><source>J Vasc Surg</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>1245</fpage>-<lpage>1252.e3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvs.2020.07.106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32882349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7914280</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r62"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thanigaimani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Unosson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Editor's Choice - Association Between Metformin Prescription and Abdominal Aortic Aneurysm Growth and Clinical Events: a Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis.</article-title><source>Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>747</fpage>-<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejvs.2021.06.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34556425</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>