<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2786</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">medicine</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MD</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10174362</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10174362.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10174362</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10174362</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37171350</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000033562</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>4500</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Research Article</subject><subject>Observational Study</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The effect of pain-education nursing based on a mind map on postoperative pain score and quality of life in patients with colorectal cancer</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="S">Shan</given-names></name><degrees>BD</degrees><email>ahc1ahc@163.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaohong</given-names></name><degrees>BD</degrees><email>447403335@qq.com</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="L">Lihua</given-names></name><degrees>BD</degrees><email>328207796@qq.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names initials="C">Cui</given-names></name><degrees>BD</degrees><email>55648289@qq.com</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true" content-type="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0707-5091">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0707-5091</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="D">Dan</given-names></name><degrees>BD</degrees><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="c1" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label> Pain Department Hand Surgery, Wuhan Fourth Hospital, Wuhan, Hubei, China</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label> Department of Surgery, Central Hospital of Enshi Tujia and Miao Autonomous Prefecture, Enshi City, Hubei Province, China</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label> Urology Gastrointestinal Surgery, Wuhan Fourth Hospital, Wuhan Fourth Hospital, Wuhan, Hubei, China.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1">* Correspondence: Dan Li, Urology Gastrointestinal Surgery, Wuhan Fourth Hospital, Wuhan Fourth Hospital, Wuhan, Hubei, China (e-mail: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ahc1ahc@163.com">ahc1ahc@163.com</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>102</volume><issue>19</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">435583</issue-id><elocation-id>e33562</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>14</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>12</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>12</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-05-14 10:25:12.873"><day>14</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial License 4.0 (CCBY-NC)</ext-link>, where it is permissible to download, share, remix, transform, and buildup the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be used commercially without permission from the journal.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="medi-102-e33562.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="medi-102-e33562.pdf"/><abstract><p>Mind mapping is a combination of images and logical thinking in the form of pictures and texts. It presents a natural expression process that conforms to the divergent thinking of the brain, helping patients understand memory. This study aimed to investigate the impact of pain-education nursing with the aid of mind maps on postoperative pain scores and quality of life in patients with colorectal cancer. The medical records of 100 colorectal cancer patients treated from July 2020 to July 2022 were selected as retrospective research participants and divided into control and observation groups. The control group received routine pain care, and the observation group was given pain-education nursing based on a mind map. The effects on quality of life, pain, negative emotions, and comfort after nursing were compared between the 2 groups. There was no significant difference in quality of-life scores between the 2 groups before the nursing intervention (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; .05). After nursing, the physical, emotional, cognitive, and social functions of patients in the observation group were significantly higher than those in the control group. However, the overall quality of life and financial difficulties of patients in the observation group were significantly lower than those in the control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05). The observation group&#8217;s social, physical, and psychological comfort scores were significantly higher than those in the control group after nursing intervention (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05). After nursing, the observation group&#8217;s visual analog scale scores at different times after the operation were significantly lower than those of the control group. The scores on the self-rating anxiety scale and self-rating depression scale in the observation group were significantly lower than those in the control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05). Pain-education nursing based on mind maps can effectively improve the daily living ability, pain symptoms, and quality of life of patients after colorectal cancer, and there is a reference value for post-nursing care of patients after colorectal cancer.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>colorectal cancer</kwd><kwd>mind mapping</kwd><kwd>pain care</kwd><kwd>pain-education nursing</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>With the continuous improvement in people&#8217;s living standards and lifestyle changes, especially the change in dietary structure from high-fiber to low-fiber, high-fat, high-protein, and refined carbohydrates, morbidity and mortality have shown an increasing trend year by year.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> The treatment for colorectal cancer is primarily surgery, supplemented by radiotherapy and chemotherapy, molecular targeted therapy, biological immunotherapy, and other treatment methods.<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> Surgery is still the best treatment for patients with early colorectal cancer, but even if the surgery achieves resection, the presence of residual tumor cells in the body is uncertain; therefore, adjuvant chemotherapy is still needed.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> However, chemotherapy not only kills tumor cells but also causes damage to the body&#8217;s normal tissues, causing various accompanying symptoms and mental distress to patients and seriously reducing the patient&#8217;s quality of life.<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> If the corresponding treatment measures are not taken to intervene, they will have a series of negative effects on the patient&#8217;s follow-up treatment and recovery, including functional status, emotional state, and quality of life. Among them, gastrointestinal reactions and hand and foot syndromes were the most severe side effects.<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup></p><p>Although the patient&#8217;s trauma is minimal, postoperative catheter balloon compression to stop bleeding will lead to bladder spasm, resulting in extreme pain for the patient after surgery. Because psychological and physiological factors and humoral stress induce perioperative pain, all factors should be considered in clinical painless nursing interventions.<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> Implementing a more comprehensive painless intervention plan eases the negative psychology of patients, such as anxiety and fear, and simultaneously providing drugs, health education, and other analgesic care reduces the secretion of stress hormones in the body and the activity of pain sensitivity hormones, thereby, helps reduce the patient&#8217;s pain and encourages the perioperative patients to cooperate with nursing interventions.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup> With the transformation of the traditional biomedical model to the &#8220;physiological-psychological-social&#8221; medical model, traditional evaluation methods, such as the cure rate, survival rate, and survival time of tumors, are no longer the focus of attention.<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup> Colorectal cancer can be cured through early detection, diagnosis, and treatment, but it can also be controlled through appropriate treatment, which results in a better quality of life, thereby prolonging the survival period. Therefore, improving the quality of life of patients with cancer has become an international matter. WHO defines the quality of life as the feelings and experiences of individuals in different cultures and value systems about their goals, expectations, standards, and living conditions, all the things they care about.<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> Therefore, we conducted this study to explore the effect of pain-education nursing with the aid of mind maps on the quality of life and pain scores of patients after colorectal cancer.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>2. Materials and methods</title><sec><title>2.1. Research participants</title><p>The medical records of 100 patients with colorectal cancer who were treated from July 2020 to July 2022 were selected as retrospective research participants and divided them into control and observation groups according to different nursing methods, with 50 cases in each group (Fig. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Diagnostic criteria for Colorectal Cancer:<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup> Charcot triad characterized by abdominal pain, jaundice, and fever, or biliary acute pancreatitis. During acute exacerbation, routine blood examination showed increased white blood cell and neutrophil counts; bilirubin, alkaline phosphatase, gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase, and blood transaminase (ALT, AST) levels were elevated to varying degrees; and amylase and lipase were elevated in patients with acute biliary pancreatitis. Abdominal ultrasonography, CT, MRI/MRCP, or endoscopic ultrasonography suggested or suspected colorectal cancer. This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of Wuhan Fourth Hospital.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Patient allocation into the observation group and control group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medi-102-e33562-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>2.2. Inclusion and exclusion criteria</title><p>Inclusion criteria: All elective surgery patients with complete clinical data; No intellectual or mental disorders, normal language skills, an ability to judge their own symptoms and general conditions, and no major organ dysfunction; Patients with grade 1 or higher colorectal cancer after receiving chemotherapy, accompanied by gastrointestinal side effects and negative emotions. Exclusion criteria: Patients with nerve compression symptoms due to brain metastases or limb metastases, or central or peripheral nervous system lesions due to electrolyte imbalance and other systemic diseases such as severe diabetes, who have received hormones, specific inhibitors, and other treatments, hand and foot pain not caused by chemotherapy drugs, and hand and foot ulceration; Acute pancreatitis or obstructive jaundice, abdominal surgery history, and recent drug use that affect gastrointestinal function; Those who met the inclusion criteria but did not implement the nursing intervention as planned after inclusion, and who had serious adverse reactions during the trial.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>2.3. Methods</title><sec><title>2.3.1. Routine pain care</title><p>The control group implemented routine pain care, namely: Comprehensive pain assessment: the medical staff immediately screened for pain after the patient was admitted to the hospital and assessed the type and nature of the patient&#8217;s pain, pain history, pain intensity, pain location, whether there was referred pain, radiating pain, related factors of pain onset, aggravation, or relief, currently used analgesic drugs, efficacy, adverse reactions, previous analgesic methods, efficacy, adverse reactions, and important social and psychological factors; and other pain-related issues. Analgesic titration treatment was performed immediately. After analgesic treatment, each shift (an 4&#8211;8 hours interval) was used to evaluate the patient&#8217;s pain status. The treatment was based on whether the pain score exceeded 4 points. Patients were assessed and treated with analgesia at 30-minute intervals until their pain score was &lt; 4. For patients with explosive pain, different drug evaluation times were selected according to the onset time of the drugs. The evaluation time of oral drugs was 30 to 60 minutes after drug administration, the evaluation time of intramuscular or subcutaneous injection drugs was 30 minutes after drug administration, and intravenous drug evaluation time was 30 minutes after drug administration. The evaluation time of the injected drug was 30 minutes after the drug was administered to ensure the timeliness, effectiveness, and comprehensiveness of the pain evaluation during the patient&#8217;s hospitalization. Before the patient was discharged from the hospital, the patient and family members were informed of the pain evaluation and recording methods, and the patient was instructed to record their pain; Strengthening health education: After the patient was admitted to the hospital, the responsible nurse communicated with the patient and their family members to assess their knowledge of cancer pain and to enquire about their concerns about drug treatment, such as taking medicine on time and whether there were adverse reactions. Then, during the process of handover rounds and daily treatment and nursing, corresponding pain health education was provided to the patients according to their actual situation, anytime, anywhere, so that the patients could understand the causes of their pain and master how to deal with the pain symptoms. One week after admission, a comprehensive assessment of the patients and their family members&#8217; knowledge was conducted. If there was any doubt, pain health education was conducted again until the patients and their family members had a comprehensive understanding of cancer pain, related knowledge of its treatment, and improved patient compliance; Strengthening medication guidance: The patients were provided with excellent medication guidance, relevant treatment manuals for patients on cancer pain medication were issued, the basic principle of &#8220;3-level analgesia ladder&#8221; was followed, and the therapeutic effects of analgesic drugs were explained. For the prevention and treatment of adverse reactions, patients were instructed not to change or adjust the analgesic drugs and dosages used, and all patients received oral drug therapy. The pain follow-up was continued after discharge, and the patient&#8217;s condition was documented; Promote self-management of patients: Pain scales and precautions for the use of analgesics were posted on the walls of the ward and in front of the patient&#8217;s bed, and patients were asked to self-evaluate their pain several times a day and to inform the doctor immediately once the self-score exceeded 4 points. This was then treated by a doctor. The patients were asked to continue their own pain assessment and management after discharge. When pain occurred, they could listen to music, watch videos, walk, talk, etc, to distract their attention, or adjust the dosage according to the doctor&#8217;s advice to avoid explosive pain; Humanized ward management: A relatively quiet ward was chosen for the patient, a good ward environment was maintained, no more than 2 family members were allowed to accompany the patient, and the patient&#8217;s psychological and family support and comfort was ensured. Treatment and nursing operations were performed on patients 1 to 2 hours after drug treatment. In the process of daily nursing care, gentle nursing operations were instituted to minimize irritation and pain in patients; Prevention of adverse reactions to analgesic drugs: for patients who used opioid analgesia for the first time, they were informed that nausea, vomiting, constipation, and other gastrointestinal reactions could occur and the patient&#8217;s tolerance was assessed. Simultaneously, metoclopramide, domperidone, and other drugs were administered to prevent adverse reactions such as nausea and vomiting. Antiemetic drugs were stopped after the patient&#8217;s gradual adaptation to the drug, and symptoms such as nausea and vomiting were relieved. Those who took opioid analgesics were advised to participate in exercise, drink more water, increase dietary fiber intake, massage the abdomen, and use lactulose and other drugs simultaneously to avoid constipation. For patients with severe gastrointestinal adverse reactions, drugs such as ondansetron were used if necessary, and symptomatic treatments such as oral senna and enemas were also used.</p></sec><sec><title>2.3.2. Pain-education nursing under mind map</title><p>The observation group implemented pain-education nursing based on mind maps of the routine pain care of the control group. The specific measures were as follows: On the day of the patient&#8217;s admission, the researcher brought the mind map to the patient&#8217;s bedside and introduced hospitalization procedures to the patients and their families according to the knowledge on the mind map. Environment, ward rules and regulations, diagnosis and treatment information, and other related content were described; emotional support was provided. One day before the operation, the researcher gradually introduced preoperative intestinal medication, self-hygiene and preparation of items to the patient according to the content of the mind map and instructed patients about the method of preoperative pulmonary function exercise, the main points of defecation training in bed, and patiently addressed the patient&#8217;s concerns to confirm whether the patient really understands the content of the plan. If necessary, the knowledge mind map was placed at the patient&#8217;s bedside for repeated reviewing by the patient; After the patient returned to the ward after the operation, the qualified nurses and postgraduates of the research group introduced the key points of getting out of bed in the early postoperative period, the drainage tube precautions, the exercise and diet guidance during the rehabilitation period, and the replacement of the ostomy bag, etc to the patient in turn with the mind map methods. During the education process, the researchers listened carefully to the patients&#8217; problems and answered them patiently, providing psychological comfort and support to the patients and their families; Preparation for discharge and precautions after discharge: With the popularization of enhanced recovery therapy, patients with colorectal cancer in the department could generally be discharged approximately 1 week after the operation, and the doctor in charge informed them about returning to the hospital for reexamination 1 month after the operation. Therefore, the content of the third component of the education in this study was introduced by the researchers 4 to 7 days after the operation to the patients. It included the medication methods after discharge, abdominal self-assessment methods, and dietary precautions for patients with stoma through face-to-face communication with patients to analyze their cognitive situation and correct their mistakes in a targeted manner. In addition, the knowledge map is provided to patients to improve their mastery of the disease. It enables them to learn to recognize and generalize problems and to deal with them correctly. For example, learning to identify and deal with different symptoms and when to take medication, how to replace the ostomy bag, and dietary precautions so as to enhance their psychological coping ability; Cognitive reconstruction training (once per week for 2 weeks, 2 times in total) was provided to the patients by regular telephone follow-up within 1 month after discharge. First, the researchers used questions to help patients recall the information provided the first 3 times and to correct their poor cognition in a timely manner. During the follow-up process, the researchers encouraged family members to enhance their understanding and support of the patient so that they could feel their own value and enhance their desire to recover from the disease. In addition, behavioral interventions enhanced adherence to self-replacement pouches, primarily by emphasizing to patients and families the importance of a regular diet, use of common medications, and self-care and management. At the same time, patients were asked about their plans post-discharge, such as diet, medication, and exercise. After discussing the problems with the patients, they were provided with information and nursing technical support. Second, after the 4th week of discharge, the patients were reminded by telephone 3 days in advance to return to the hospital for reexamination and on agreed time. After the outpatient reexamination, the questionnaires and scales were measured again in a clinic with a suitable environment to ensure data integrity.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>2.4. Observation indicators</title><p>Pain was evaluated using a visual analog scale (VAS) ranging from 0 to 10, with 0 indicating no pain, 1 to 3 indicating mild pain, 4 to 6 indicating moderate pain, and 7 to 10 indicating severe pain. Cronbach &#945; values measured before use were all &gt;0.914. The patients completed the test independently without any internal or external factors influencing the actual situation, and the test was completed within 30 minutes; Quality of-life score: The Chinese version of the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of-Life Core Scale for Cancer Patients (European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer QLQ-C30) V3.0 was used. The scale contains 30 entries in 15 domains, including 5 functional domains of physical functioning, role functioning, cognitive functioning, emotional functioning, and social functioning; 3 symptom domains of fatigue, nausea and vomiting, and pain; 6 individual symptoms (dyspnea, appetite loss, sleep disturbance, constipation, diarrhea, and financial difficulties); and 1 overall health status domain. The overall health status domain was rated on a 7-point scale from 1 to 7, with 1 indicating &#8220;very poor,&#8221; 7 indicating &#8220;very good,&#8221; and the remaining entries on a 4-point scale, with 1 means &#8220;never,&#8221; 2 means &#8220;a little,&#8221; 3 means &#8220;some,&#8221; and 4 means &#8220;very much.&#8221; The scale was scored by adding the number of items included in each domain and dividing by the number of items included to obtain a crude score for that domain. A higher score in the functional domain and the general health status domain indicated a better functional status and quality of life, while a higher score in the symptom domain indicated more symptoms or problems of the patient and a worse quality of life. The scale has been translated into 43 languages, including Chinese, and is widely used in various countries and regions around the world, with good reliability and validity, a Cronbach&#8217;s &#945; coefficient of 0.648 to 0.865 for each dimension, and a retest reliability of 0.611; Comfort: The comfort assessment included 3 items: social comfort, physical comfort, and psychological comfort, each with a maximum score of 100. A higher score indicates a higher level of comfort; Negative emotions: Negative emotions were evaluated using the self-rating anxiety scale (SAS) and self-rating depression scale (SDS). The SAS and SDS included 20 items and adopted a 4-level scoring system. Higher scores indicated more severe anxiety and depressive symptoms. Cronbach <italic toggle="yes">&#945;</italic> coefficients of the scale were 0.816 and 0.826, respectively, indicating that the SAS and SDS scales had good reliability and validity.</p></sec><sec><title>2.5. Statistical analysis</title><p>Statistical analysis was conducted using SPSS 25.0, and the data were arranged, entered into a computer database, and ensured completeness and accuracy by a cross-check. One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used for measurement of data and expressed as mean &#177; standard deviation. The chi-square test was used to analyze proportional differences. All reported P values were 2-sided. Statistical significance was set at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>3. Results</title><sec><title>3.1. Characteristics of study participants</title><p>The characteristics of the study participants are summarized in Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The observation group comprised 35 men and 15 women, with a mean age of 75.3 years and mean body mass index of 21.53&#8201;kg/m<sup>2</sup>. The control group included 36 men and 14 women, with a mean age of 76.31 years and mean body mass index of 20.94&#8201;kg/m<sup>2</sup>. With regard to educational level, the observation group had 17 with an education level of elementary school and below, 22 with a middle school level, and 11 with a college level and above, whereas the control group had 16 with an education level of elementary school and below, 24 with a middle school level, and 10 with a college level and above. There were no statistically significant intergroup differences in baseline characteristics (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; .05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of general data of the 2 groups.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General data</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observation group (n = 50)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control group (n = 50)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">&#967;</italic>
<sup>
<italic toggle="yes">2</italic>
</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">/t</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (yr)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.30&#8201;&#177;&#8201;3.52</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.31&#8201;&#177;&#8201;3.51</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.437</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.154</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.825</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body mass index (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.53&#8201;&#177;&#8201;3.34</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.94&#8201;&#177;&#8201;4.45</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.455</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Educational level</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.165</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.921</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Elementary school and below</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Middle school</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;College and above</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Underlying disease</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Diabetes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.379</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.538</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Hypertension</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.437</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.509</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Hyperlipidemia</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.709</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.399</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.372</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.542</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Colon cancer</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Rectal cancer</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgery type</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.547</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.761</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Open</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Minimally invasive</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Converted</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>3.2. Nursing comfort comparison</title><p>Before the nursing education intervention, the nursing comfort of the 2 groups was not statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; .05). The social, physical, and psychological comfort scores of the observation group were significantly higher than those of the control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05) after the intervention (Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Comparison of nursing comfort before and after nursing between 2 groups. (A) Social comfort score. (B) Physiological comfort score. (C) Psychological comfort score.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medi-102-e33562-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.3. Comparison of pain scores</title><p>Before the nursing education intervention, there was no significant difference in VAS scores between the 2 groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; .05). After receiving nursing intervention, the VAS scores of the observation group at different times after operation were significantly lower than those of the control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05) (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Comparison of pain scores after nursing between 2 groups.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medi-102-e33562-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.4. Quality of-life score comparison</title><p>Before intervention, there was no significant difference in quality of-life scores between the 2 groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; .05). After the intervention, physical, emotional, cognitive, social, and functional roles in the observation group were significantly higher than those in the control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05). However, the financial difficulty score in the observation group was significantly lower than that in the control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05), Figure <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Comparison of quality-of-life scores before and after nursing between 2 groups. (A) Physical functioning. (B) Emotional functioning. (C) Cognitive functioning. (D) Social functioning. (E) Role functioning. (F) Financial difficulties.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medi-102-e33562-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.5. Comparison of negative emotions</title><p>Before the intervention, there was no significant difference in SAS and SDS scores between the 2 groups (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; .05). After the intervention, the SAS and SDS scores of the observation group were significantly lower than those of the control group (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05), as shown in Figure <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F5" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Comparison of negative emotions between 2 groups. (A) SAS. (B) SDS. SAS = self-rating anxiety scale, SDS = self-rating depression scale.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medi-102-e33562-g005.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>4. Discussion</title><p>The mind mapping application is a new model of nurse training, which lists nursing care plans in the form of illustrations, enabling nurses to better understand and remember nursing content, grasp the focus and direction of nursing care, and prevent unclear thinking and lack of prioritization. Thus, nursing measures can be carried out effectively to ensure the implementation of the overall nursing concept.<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</sup> Mind mapping is very helpful in developing nurses clinical critical thinking.<sup>[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup> Pain-education nursing based on mind mapping has become an integral part of modern nursing. Pain-education nursing based on mind mapping improves patients awareness of self-care, enhances compliance, improves self-care capabilities, delays disease progression, and achieves rapid recovery.<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup> It is an important tool for hospitals to transform from purely therapeutic services into holistic care centers focused on prevention, treatment, nursing, and rehabilitation integrated with health care, which has the advantage of low costs and high output.<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup> It has become an industry consensus to vigorously conduct pain-education nursing based on mind mapping to promote hospital modernization.<sup>[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</sup> However, only a few clinical studies have been conducted on pain-education nursing based on mind mapping in China. Therefore, in this study, we used a mind map to guide nurses in health education for patients with colorectal cancer so that nurses could explain the key points and precautions of perioperative care to patients in a more complete and detailed manner and meet the knowledge needs of patients to the greatest extent, thus improving compliance with treatment and care and reducing noncooperation and nurse-patient disputes.</p><p>In the present study, the social, physical, and psychological comfort scores of the observation group were significantly higher than those of the control group. The pain-education nursing based on mind mapping effectively improved patient comfort; when combined with conventional pain care, this process enhanced the body&#8217;s defense ability and quality of life in patients.<sup>[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</sup> Patients with colorectal cancer may experience marked pain during treatment due to related lesions and the anticancer treatment process.<sup>[<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</sup> Patients experience decreased appetite, reduced resistance, and sleep disorders that greatly impact their quality of life.<sup>[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</sup> Poor pain control not only increases the incidence of anxiety and depression but also reduces treatment confidence and compliance, which directly affects prognosis.<sup>[<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</sup> Pain-education nursing based on mind mapping applies to all disciplines, and the patient can be fully counseled through this system and the most suitable scientific and reasonable comprehensive treatment plan for the patient&#8217;s condition can be formulated.<sup>[<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</sup> The best outcome for the patient is achieved while ensuring medical safety.<sup>[<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</sup> The pain-education nursing model, based on mind mapping, adjusts the psychological state of the patients, provides timely health education, and guides patients in medication use.<sup>[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</sup> By ensuring that patients can consume adequate nutrition and regularly analyze their health status for treatment, they are able to adjust their plans and carry out targeted care promptly and are also responsible for postoperative rehabilitation and self-life recovery exercises.<sup>[<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</sup> Pharmacological analgesia, as the main modality for the treatment of colorectal cancer pain, has formed a 3-step analgesic treatment principle.<sup>[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</sup> However, a large number of studies have found that the therapeutic effect of long-term analgesic drugs is not ideal, and the incidence of adverse reactions in patients after treatment is relatively high, which not only affects the clinical treatment but also has a great impact on the quality of life of patients.<sup>[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</sup> The use of mind mapping in the health education of cancer patients to evaluate the level of pain, medication compliance, and patient satisfaction has enabled patients to control their pain and acquire knowledge about medication after the intervention.<sup>[<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</sup></p><p>Our nursing intervention improved the patient&#8217;s physical and emotional functions, indicating that appropriate TCM nursing methods can improve patients moods and resolve their psychological problems. During the first survey before the intervention, it was found that some patients attributed their bad mood to the tumor, economic burdens, and the toxic side effects of chemotherapy, which caused somatic lesions and a heavy psychological burden.<sup>[<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</sup> Therefore, mood, as a subjective experience, is also influenced by the toxic side effects of chemotherapy.<sup>[<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</sup> Actively managing the side effects of chemotherapy can effectively improve the quality of life of chemotherapy patients with colorectal cancer.<sup>[<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]</sup></p><p>This study had some limitations. Data were collected from only 1 hospital, and because of the limited time, effective follow-up of patients long-term healing was not possible. The impact of cancer staging on the patient&#8217;s quality of life was not considered because of the low number of reports in the literature.</p><p>In conclusion, pain-education nursing based on mind maps can effectively improve the daily life of colorectal cancer patients, adequately improve patients pain symptoms and quality of life, and have a certain reference value for the after-care of patients after colorectal cancer.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> Lihua Zhang.</p><p><bold>Data curation:</bold> Lihua Zhang, Cui Huang.</p><p><bold>Formal analysis:</bold> Lihua Zhang, Cui Huang.</p><p><bold>Funding acquisition:</bold> Lihua Zhang.</p><p><bold>Investigation:</bold> Xiaohong Zhu, Lihua Zhang, Cui Huang.</p><p><bold>Methodology:</bold> Xiaohong Zhu, Lihua Zhang.</p><p><bold>Project administration:</bold> Xiaohong Zhu.</p><p><bold>Resources:</bold> Xiaohong Zhu, Cui Huang.</p><p><bold>Software:</bold> Shan Li, Xiaohong Zhu, Cui Huang.</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold> Shan Li, Xiaohong Zhu, Cui Huang.</p><p><bold>Validation:</bold> Shan Li.</p><p><bold>Visualization:</bold> Shan Li, Dan Li.</p><p><bold>Writing &#8211; original draft:</bold> Shan Li, Dan Li.</p><p><bold>Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing:</bold> Shan Li, Dan Li.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>
<def-list><title>Abbreviations:</title><def-item><term>SAS</term><def><p>self-rating anxiety scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SDS</term><def><p>self-rating depression scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VAS</term><def><p>visual analog scale</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn fn-type="equal"><p>SL and XZ contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>This study was supported by the Construction and implementation of &#8220;Internet plus&#8221; hospital community family trinity continuous nursing service model for enterostomy patients (grant no. JCY2021000003).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>How to cite this article: Li S, Zhu X, Zhang L, Huang C, Li D. The effect of pain-education nursing based on a mind map on postoperative pain score and quality of life in patients with colorectal cancer. Medicine 2023;102:19(e33562).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastie</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The clinical impact of malnutrition on the postoperative outcomes of patients undergoing colorectal resection surgery for colon or rectal cancer: propensity score matched analysis of 2011-2017 US hospitals.</article-title><source>Surg Oncol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>101587</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33915485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.suronc.2021.101587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrillo</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mesa</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burbano</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Skills required in the care of cancer patients who undergo surgery in the hospital-home transition.</article-title><source>J Cancer Educ</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>1364</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33506409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s13187-021-01964-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9550752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Battersby</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juul</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Predicting the risk of bowel-related quality-of-life impairment after restorative resection for rectal cancer: a multicenter cross-sectional study.</article-title><source>Dis Colon Rectum</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>270</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26953985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/DCR.0000000000000552</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crane</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slack</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rationale, development, and design of the altering intake, managing symptoms (AIMS) dietary intervention for bowel dysfunction in rectal cancer survivors.</article-title><source>Contemp Clin Trials</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29567283</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cct.2018.03.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5899669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Tea consumption and the incidence of cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective observational studies.</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer Prev</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>353</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25370683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/CEJ.0000000000000094</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Intestinal microorganisms involved in colorectal cancer complicated with dyslipidosis.</article-title><source>Cancer Biol Ther</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30239257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/15384047.2018.1507255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6343685</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cade</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>CEL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Does adherence to the world cancer research fund/American Institute of Cancer Research cancer prevention guidelines reduce risk of colorectal cancer in the UK Women&#8217;s Cohort Study?</article-title><source>Br J Nutr</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>119</volume>:<fpage>340</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29352814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/S0007114517003622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Porzig</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neugebauer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heckmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of a cancer patient navigation program (&#8220;Onkolotse&#8221;) in terms of hospitalization rates, resource use and healthcare costs: rationale and design of a randomized, controlled study.</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>413</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29871676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12913-018-3226-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5989372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solomkin</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schlossberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Tokyo Guidelines 2018: antimicrobial therapy for acute cholangitis and cholecystitis.</article-title><source>J Hepatobiliary Pancreat Sci</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29090866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jhbp.518</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yokoe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Japanese guidelines for the management of acute pancreatitis: Japanese Guidelines 2015.</article-title><source>J Hepatobiliary Pancreat Sci</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>405</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25973947</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jhbp.259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Itoi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Indications and techniques of biliary drainage for acute cholangitis in updated Tokyo Guidelines 2018.</article-title><source>J Hepatobiliary Pancreat Sci</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>537</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>49</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28834389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jhbp.496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Isoflavone and soyfood intake and colorectal cancer risk: a case-control study in Korea.</article-title><source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e0143228</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26575841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0143228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4648565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowicki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dahms</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Incidence, morbidity and 5-year survival of colorectal cancer patients in the Kujawsko-Pomorskie voivodship in 2005-2011, based on data from the National Health Fund.</article-title><source>Pol Przegl Chir</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5604/01.3001.0011.8175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30220676</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colibaseanu</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osagiede</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spaulding</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The determinants of palliative care use in patients with colorectal cancer: a national study.</article-title><source>Am J Hosp Palliat Care</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>1295</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>303</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29580075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1049909118765092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Intraoperative perfusion assessment of the proximal colon by a visual grading system for safe anastomosis after resection in left-sided colorectal cancer patients.</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>2746</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33531598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-021-82486-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7854740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adelson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fusco</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karapetis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Use of guideline-recommended adjuvant therapies and survival outcomes for people with colorectal cancer at tertiary referral hospitals in South Australia.</article-title><source>J Eval Clin Pract</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>135</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28474459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jep.12757</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Impaired fasting glucose, single-nucleotide polymorphisms, and risk for colorectal cancer in Koreans.</article-title><source>Epidemiol Health</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>e2016002</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26797220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4178/epih/e2016002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4751348</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Francisco</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rankin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Adherence to colorectal cancer and polyps screening recommendations among filipino-americans.</article-title><source>Gastroenterol Nurs</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>384</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25461460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/SGA.0000000000000071</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Micek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gniadek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawalec</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Coffee consumption and colorectal cancer risk: a dose-response meta-analysis on prospective cohort studies.</article-title><source>Int J Food Sci Nutr</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>986</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1006</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30922134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/09637486.2019.1591352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of pelvic floor muscle exercise on faecal incontinence in rectal cancer patients after stoma closure.</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer Care (Engl)</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>449</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>57</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25684312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/ecc.12292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Body mass index and 20 specific cancers: re-analyses of dose-response meta-analyses of observational studies.</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>749</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>57</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29300814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/annonc/mdx819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahoo</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Colon tissues classification and localization in whole slide images using deep learning.</article-title><source>Diagnostics (Basel)</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1398</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34441332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/diagnostics11081398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8394415</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holtedahl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borgquist</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donker</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Symptoms and signs of colorectal cancer, with differences between proximal and distal colon cancer: a prospective cohort study of diagnostic accuracy in primary care.</article-title><source>BMC Fam Pract</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>148</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34238248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12875-021-01452-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8268573</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahnd</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steck</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rural-urban and racial/ethnic trends and disparities in early-onset and average-onset colorectal cancer.</article-title><source>Cancer</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>127</volume>:<fpage>239</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>48</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33112412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cncr.33256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>HZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Predicting changes in quality of life and emotional distress in Chinese patients with lung, gastric, and colon-rectal cancer diagnoses: the role of psychological resilience.</article-title><source>Psychooncology</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>829</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27479936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pon.4237</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Single-cell analysis reveals characterization of infiltrating T cells in moderately differentiated colorectal cancer.</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>620196</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33584715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2020.620196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7873865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Senft</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Br&#252;ck</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Po&#223;-Doering</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Need for nursing care after laparoscopic and open colorectal cancer surgery: a claims data analysis in German primary care.</article-title><source>Langenbecks Arch Surg</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>407</volume>:<fpage>2937</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35761148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00423-022-02592-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9640437</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>[28]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Peri-treatment change of anorectal function in patients with rectal cancer after preoperative chemoradiotherapy.</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>79982</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29108380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/oncotarget.20567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5668113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>[29]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of anchoring sutures at diverting ileostomy after rectal cancer surgery on peritoneal adhesion at following ileostomy reversal.</article-title><source>Ann Surg Treat Res</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>214</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34692593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4174/astr.2021.101.4.214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8506021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>[30]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of multidisciplinary team collaborative nursing model combined with mind mapping teaching method on postoperative complications and mental health of patients with advanced pancreatic cancer.</article-title><source>Iran J Public Health</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>535</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35865063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18502/ijph.v51i3.8929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9276593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>[31]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nursing intervention using a whole-process escort playing a relative role combined with mind mapping in patients undergoing breast cancer surgery: a randomized trial.</article-title><source>Ann Palliat Med</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>12047</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35016413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.21037/apm-21-915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>[32]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McMullen</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bulkley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Altschuler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Greatest challenges of rectal cancer survivors: results of a population-based survey.</article-title><source>Dis Colon Rectum</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>1019</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27749476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/DCR.0000000000000695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5226258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>[33]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van de Velde</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aristei</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boelens</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>EURECCA colorectal: multidisciplinary mission statement on better care for patients with colon and rectal cancer in Europe.</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>2784</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23769991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ejca.2013.04.032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>[34]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boushey</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheer</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of the rectal cancer patient decision aid: a before and after study.</article-title><source>Dis Colon Rectum</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>72</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26855389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/DCR.0000000000000528</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>[35]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Artama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Euler-Chelpin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Colon and rectal cancer risk after bariatric surgery in a multicountry Nordic cohort study.</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>147</volume>:<fpage>728</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31797382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ijc.32770</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>[36]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Finlayson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varma</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Outcomes after rectal cancer surgery in elderly nursing home residents.</article-title><source>Dis Colon Rectum</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>1229</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23135580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/DCR.0b013e318267bfe3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>[37]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kotronoulas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Papadopoulou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burns-Cunningham</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A systematic review of the supportive care needs of people living with and beyond cancer of the colon and/or rectum.</article-title><source>Eur J Oncol Nurs</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>60</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28720267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ejon.2017.05.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>[38]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Exercise and colorectal cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis of exercise safety, feasibility and effectiveness.</article-title><source>Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>122</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32972439</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12966-020-01021-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7513291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>[39]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobbins</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Husson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeCorby</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>School-based physical activity programs for promoting physical activity and fitness in children and adolescents aged 6 to 18.</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>2013</volume>:<fpage>Cd007651</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23450577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD007651.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7197501</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>