<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Spine Surg Relat Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Spine Surg Relat Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3679</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ssrr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Spine Surgery and Related Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2432-261X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Japanese Society for Spine Surgery and Related Research</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10853619</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10853619.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10853619</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10853619</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38343410</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22603/ssrr.2023-0113</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Rates and Characteristics of Patients Leaving against Medical Advice after Spine Surgery</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghali</surname><given-names initials="A">Abdullah</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Momtaz</surname><given-names initials="D">David</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kotzur</surname><given-names initials="T">Travis</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonuguntla</surname><given-names initials="R">Rishi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="R">Rebecca</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santiago-Rodriquez</surname><given-names initials="AC">Alan C.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phan</surname><given-names initials="EN">Eileen N</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seifi</surname><given-names initials="A">Ali</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names initials="D">Darrell</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>Department of Orthopaedics, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, Texas, USA</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>Department of Neurosurgery, UT Health San Antonio, San Antonio, USA</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>Houston Methodist Orthopedics and Sports Medicine, Houston, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>Corresponding author: Abdullah Ghali, <email>abdullah.ghali@bcm.edu</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>27</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">455543</issue-id><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>04</day><month>09</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>10</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-02-12 17:25:09.900"><day>12</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2024 The Japanese Society for Spine Surgery and Related Research</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>Spine Surgery and Related Research is an Open Access journal distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License. To view the details of this license, please visit (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="2432-261X-8-0043.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction </title><p>Leaving against medical advice (AMA) has been associated with higher rates of readmission and worse postoperative outcomes in various surgical fields. Patients who have undergone spine surgery often require careful postoperative follow-up to ensure an uncomplicated recovery. In this study, we aim to investigate the demographic and hospital variables that may have contributed to patients leaving the hospital AMA following spine surgery. </p></sec><sec><title>Methods </title><p>We performed a retrospective analysis of patients receiving spine surgery; we used the data from the Healthcare Cost and Utilization Project (HCUP) database for the years 2011-2020. Demographics, household income status, insurance status, time from admission to operation, length of stay, length of recovery, and discharge disposition were collected and analyzed. Multivariate linear regression was used to determine the odds ratios of each factor and their association to patient decision of leaving AMA. </p></sec><sec><title>Results </title><p>As per our findings, patients aged 30-49 had 1.666 times greater odds of leaving AMA following spine surgery (P&lt;0.001), patients aged 50-64 had 1.222 times greater odds of leaving AMA (P=0.001), and patients older than 65 had 0.490 times lesser odds of leaving AMA (P&lt;0.001). Additionally, black patients were 1.612 times more likely to leave AMA (P&lt;0.001), whereas white patients were 0.675 times less likely to do so (&lt;0.001). Women were 0.555 times less likely to leave AMA than the rest of the population (P&lt;0.001). Moreover, patients with private insurance were 0.268 times less likely to leave AMA (P&lt;0.001), while patients on Medicare and Medicaid were 1.692 times (P&lt;0.001) and 3.958 times more likely to leave AMA (P&lt;0.001) following spine surgery, respectively. Finally, patients in the lowest quartile of income were 1.691 times more likely to leave AMA (P&lt;0.001), while patients in the higher quartile of income were 0.521 times less likely to do so (P&lt;0.001). </p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions </title><p>It is critical that spine surgeons are aware of the factors that predispose patients to leave AMA in order to mitigate postoperative complications. </p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Spine Surgery</kwd><kwd>Against Medical Advice</kwd><kwd>Surgery</kwd><kwd>Orthopedics</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Spine surgery is common in the United States, with approximately 900,000 patients receiving surgery each year<sup><xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>)</sup>. Chronic neck and back pain is a condition that affects a significant portion of the general population<sup><xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>)</sup>. Patients often undergo surgery to address their chronic back pain, which affects 10%-15% of individuals. Although there are a number of treatments available for axial pain, including pain medication and steroid injections, many patients opted to undergo surgery<sup><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Common procedures include anterior cervical discectomy and fusion (ACDF), lumbar laminectomy, and lumbar fusion, as deemed appropriate for the patient<sup><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>)</sup>. Following spine surgery, it is critical that the postoperative course is monitored by a surgeon to ensure positive outcome.</p><p>ACDF has been used to treat patients with cervical stenosis and disc herniation; in fact, it has been demonstrated to be effective in improving short- and intermediate-term symptoms<sup><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>)</sup>. Lumbar laminectomy with or without discectomy is one of the most common spine surgeries in the United States<sup><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>)</sup>. The operation is known to improve symptoms of patients presenting with back pain, radiculopathy, neurogenic claudication, weakness, and decreased sensation<sup><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>)</sup>. Its risk for postoperative complications is at 5.6%<sup><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>)</sup>. Meanwhile, the utilization of lumbar fusion surgery has also increased in the United States over the last 10 years; it may be indicated for the treatment of a wide variety of diseases such as tumors, degenerative diseases, spondylolisthesis, or spinal deformities<sup><xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>)</sup>. The average length of hospital stay for lumbar fusion is 3 days. Risk factors for longer stays include older age, increased body mass index, and more advanced disease<sup><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Leaving against medical advice (AMA) occurs when a patient decides to leave the hospital and discontinue treatment without the recommendation from the admitting physician<sup><xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>)</sup>. Accounting for 1%-2% of all hospital admissions, leaving AMA remains to be a difficult challenge for most physicians in their medical practice<sup><xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>)</sup>. Patients who leave AMA are identified to be at a higher risk for morbidity, including higher readmission rates within 15 days for the same diagnosis, and higher 6-month and 1-year mortality rates<sup><xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>)</sup>. Additionally, patients who leave AMA have up to 50% greater health costs than those who do not<sup><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>)</sup>. Factors that increase the likelihood of leaving AMA include lower socioeconomic status, lack of insurance, and lack of having a primary care physician<sup><xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Spine surgery as a field of orthopedics generally entails positive outcomes in terms of reducing pain and discomfort in patients<sup><xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>)</sup>. However, some studies have found that spine surgery patients suffering from drug use disorders frequently leave AMA, leading to worse postoperative outcomes and loss of follow-up after discharge<sup><xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>)</sup>. Other factors that may contribute to a patient leaving AMA following spine surgery have not been well characterized in previous literature. Thus, in this study, we aim to determine what factors influence a patient's likelihood to leave AMA following spine surgery. We hypothesize that patients who leave AMA more likely belong to a lower socioeconomic category, do not have health insurance, experience longer hospital stay, and experience longer time between admission and operation.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>We performed a retrospective analysis of patients who have undergone spine surgery; we used the data from the Healthcare Cost and Utilization Project (HCUP) database for the years 2011-2020. The HCUP database is a partnership between federal, state, and industry entities sponsored by the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality; this includes academic and community hospitals in its analysis. Each year, data is collected from a random in sample of 20% of the hospitals included in the HCUP database to create a representative sample of all hospitals across the United States.</p><p>Each group was analyzed to compare variables such as concurrent diagnosis, age, gender, household income status, rural or urban setting, and payer type, as well as hospital variables including days from admission to procedure, length of stay, recovery time, total charge, discharge disposition, and mortality rates. Recovery time was defined as time from surgery until the patient was able to leave the hospital. Further, multiple logistic regression models were created to elucidate any relationship between patient decision to leave AMA and the prior mentioned variables. These regression models were controlled for age, sex, ethnicity, and race when feasible.</p><p>Categorical results are reported as counts with column percentages. Continuous data are reported as means standard deviations; standard errors are given where deemed appropriate. Comparison of normally distributed data was performed using independent sample<italic toggle="yes"> t</italic>-tests. For nonnormally distributed data, Wilcoxon rank-sum test was performed. Categorical variables were assessed using Fisher's exact test or chi square test with Kendall Tau. Where deemed appropriate, residuals were assessed for normal distribution, wherein no multicollinearity was observed. Variables with p&lt;0.05 were considered statistically significant. All statistical analyses were conducted using the Statistical Package for the Social Sciences software, version 23.0 (IBM Japan, Inc., Tokyo, Japan).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>In total, 966,128 patients undergoing spine surgery were identified from the HCUP database for the years 2011-2020. Their mean age was 57.88 years old, and 52.58% was female. Additionally, 79.78% was white, 9.05% was black, and 6.64% was Hispanic. Moreover, 7.71% of the patients received care in the rural areas. Also, 8.25% received coverage from Medicaid, whereas 41.61% received insurance from Medicare, and 40.72% had private insurance; coverage refers to how medical services are paid for, which in the United States can be through private insurance, government-sponsored insurance (e.g., Medicare and Medicaid), or self-pay without insurance. Medicare and Medicaid are publicly funded insurance options generally for more socially or medically disadvantaged individuals, such as the poor, elderly, or disabled, among other qualifications. These data are presented in <xref rid="t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. For hospital variable data, patients who left AMA were found to have significantly more days between their admission and procedure (1.130 days vs. 0.368 days), longer length of stay (5.959 days vs. 3.581 days), longer time to recover (4.681 days vs. 3.231 days), and, inevitably, greater hospital cost ($116,967 vs. $163,532) (<xref rid="t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="t001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Relationship between Demographic Variables and Hospital Variables to Patients Leaving AMA.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead style="border-top:solid thin; border-bottom:solid thin;"><tr><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Demographic</italic>
</bold>
</th><th valign="middle" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">No AMA</italic>
</bold>
</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">AMA</italic>
</bold>
</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Total</italic>
</bold>
</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">P-value</italic>
</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody style="border-top:solid thin; border-bottom:solid thin;"><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Number, N (%)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">965002 (99.88)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1126 (0.12)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">966128</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Demographics</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.886 (15.213)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.817 (13.888)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.881 (15.212)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age Category</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46005 (4.77)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (4.71)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46058 (4.77)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30-54</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202219 (20.96)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">350 (31.08)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202569 (20.97)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55-64</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">357115 (37.01)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">472 (41.92)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">357587 (37.01)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;65</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">359624 (37.27)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">251 (22.29)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">359875 (37.25)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">507472 (52.60)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">425 (37.74)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">507897 (52.58)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">457393 (47.40)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">701 (62.26)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">458094 (47.42)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian or Pacific Islander</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13389 (1.46)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (2.10)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13412 (1.46)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83163 (9.04)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156 (14.22)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83319 (9.05)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61072 (6.64)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (8.57)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61166 (6.64)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28186 (3.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (3.83)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28228 (3.07)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">733799 (79.79)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">782 (71.29)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">734581 (79.78)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Household Income by Zipcode</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0-25th Percentile</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225451 (23.78)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">380 (34.99)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225831 (23.79)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26th-50th Percentile</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248653 (26.22)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">258 (23.76)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248911 (26.22)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51st-75th Percentile</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249632 (26.33)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">291 (26.80)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249923 (26.33)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76th-100th Percentile</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">224495 (23.68)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157 (14.46)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">224652 (23.66)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural/Urban</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74173 (7.71)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (7.25)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74253 (7.71)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.601</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">887687 (92.29)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024 (92.75)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">888711 (92.29)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Payer</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medicaid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79278 (8.23)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">318 (28.29)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79596 (8.25)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medicare</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">400973 (41.61)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">449 (39.95)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">401422 (41.61)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Charge</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1187 (0.12)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (0.71)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1195 (0.12)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Hospital Variables</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77131 (8.00)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (6.49)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77204 (8.00)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Private Insurance</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">392558 (40.74)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219 (19.48)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">392777 (40.72)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-pay</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12431 (1.29)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (5.07)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12488 (1.29)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Days from Admission to Procedure</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.368 (1.806)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.130 (2.553)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.369 (1.807)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of Stay</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.581 (4.013)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.959 (7.830)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.584 (4.021)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recovery Time</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.231 (3.388)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.681 (6.428)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.232 (3.394)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Operation Ratio</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046 (0.457)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.143 (0.283)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046 (0.457)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Charge</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116967.985 (104493.367)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163532.222 (154572.202)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117022.370 (104577.823)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discharge Dispostion</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adverse Discharge</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162281 (16.82)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1126 (100.00)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163407 (16.91)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Home Discharge With Care</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145185 (15.05)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145185 (15.03)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="display: inline-block; margin-left:1em;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Routine Discharge</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">657536 (68.14)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">657536 (68.06)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mortality</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1712 (0.18)</td><td valign="top" align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1712 (0.18)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.289</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="t002" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Odds Ratio of Each Predictive Variable to Patients Leaving AMA vs. Not Leaving AMA.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead style="border-top:solid thin; border-bottom:solid thin;"><tr><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Predictor</italic>
</bold>
</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Odds Ratio</italic>
</bold>
</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">CI</italic>
</bold>
</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">P-value</italic>
</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody style="border-top:solid thin; border-bottom:solid thin;"><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Female</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.555</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>[0.491-0.627]</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;30 Years of Age</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.016</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.768-1.343]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.912</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>30-49 Years of Age</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.666</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>[1.465-1.894]</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>50-64 Years of Age</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.222</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>[1.083-1.377]</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>65+ Years of Age</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.490</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>[0.425-0.565]</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Black</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.612</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>[1.36-1.911]</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>White</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.675</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>[0.591-0.77]</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.441</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.953-2.179]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.182</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.956-1.462]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.123</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Medicare</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.692</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>[1.45-1.975]</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Medicaid</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3.958</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>[3.426-4.571]</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Private Insurance</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.268</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>[0.23-0.313]</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Self - pay</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3.154</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>[2.404-4.136]</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1 st -25 th Income Percentile</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.691</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>[1.49-1.919]</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25th-50th Income Percentile</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.898</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.779-1.035]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.137</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51st-75th Income Percentile</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.049</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.915-1.201]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.493</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>76 th -100 th Income Percentile</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.521</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>[0.438-0.62]</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Patients aged 30-49 had 1.666 times greater odds of leaving AMA following spine surgery (P&lt;0.001), patients aged 50-64 had 1.222 times greater odds of leaving AMA (P=0.001), and patients older than 65 had 0.490 times reduced odds of leaving AMA (P&lt;0.001) when controlling for race, gender, insurance status, and income quartile (<xref rid="t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Additionally, when controlling for gender, age, insurance status, and income quartile, black patients were 1.612 times more likely to leave AMA following spine surgery (P&lt;0.001), whereas white patients were 0.675 times less likely to do so (&lt;0.001). Women were 0.555 times less likely to leave AMA than the rest of the population (P&lt;0.001) when controlling for race, age, insurance status, and income quartile. Additionally, patients on Medicaid and patients on Medicare were 3.958 (P&lt;0.001) times and 1.692 (P&lt;0.001) times more likely to leave AMA, respectively, while patients with private insurance were 0.268 times less likely to leave AMA (P&lt;0.001) following spine surgery when controlling for race, age, gender, and income quartile. Finally, patients in the lowest quartile of income were 1.691 times more likely to leave AMA (P&lt;0.001), while patients in the higher quartile of income were 0.521 times less likely to do so (P&lt;0.001) when controlling for race, age, gender, and insurance status. Trends from 2011 to 2020 in terms of the number of patients leaving AMA with respect to gender, age, and race are shown in Fig. <xref rid="g001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, <xref rid="g002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="g003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. Trends in the total patient charges from 2011 to 2020 comparing patients who left AMA to those who did not are shown in <xref rid="g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>; both showed similar patterns of growth over time, but charges for patients leaving AMA have remained to be consistently higher.</p><fig position="float" id="g001" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Odds ratio of each variable and patients leaving AMA.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="2432-261X-8-0043-g001.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="g002" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Patient demographic variables and rate of leaving AMA by year.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="2432-261X-8-0043-g002.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="g003" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Average amount patient was charged and length of patient stay in patients that left AMA and patients that did not leave AMA by year.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="2432-261X-8-0043-g003.jpg"/></fig><p>When comparing patients who underwent spine surgery and left AMA to those who did not, patients who left AMA were found to have more days between their admission and procedure (1.130 days vs. 0.368 days, P&lt;0.001), had longer length of hospital stay (5.959 days vs. 3.581 days, P&lt;0.001), and had longer time to recovery (4.681 days vs. 3.231 days, P&lt;0.001). Also, patients that left AMA had accumulated higher charges for their stay than those patients who opted not to leave AMA following a spine surgery ($163,532 vs. $116,967, P&lt;0.001). No difference was determined in terms of the rate of mortality between patients who left AMA versus those who did not.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>As per our retrospective analysis of the data we gathered from the HCUP database, wherein we examined 966,128 patients who underwent spine surgery, we found that patients who were more likely to leave AMA were male; black; between the ages of 30-64; on Medicare, Medicaid, or self-pay; and in the bottom quartile of income. We also found that patients who left AMA following spine surgery had significantly longer admission to procedure time, longer length of stay, and higher cost of stay.</p><p>In this study, we have determined that the average length of hospital stay was 1.98 days<sup><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>)</sup>. In terms of lumbar laminectomy, one study showed that the average length of hospital stay was 4.12 days; in another study, the 2-year success rate for this operation was between 75% and 80%<sup><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>)</sup>. Meanwhile, another study demonstrated that at 7-12 months post-ACDF, 95% of the patients considered their operation to be successful<sup><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>)</sup>. Patients who received lumbar fusion had an average length of hospital stay of 3.6 days<sup><xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>)</sup>. Improvements in terms of back pain were reported 1 year postoperation, with 81% of the patients reporting &#8220;somewhat&#8221; to &#8220;extreme&#8221; satisfaction<sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>)</sup>. In contrast, our study demonstrated that the average length of stay for individuals who left AMA was 5.959 days, as compared to 3.581 days for those who did not leave AMA. Individuals who left AMA thus had longer hospital stay than the average LOS (length of stay) for other spinal procedures. This increased length of stay might have added to patient dissatisfaction and increased total hospital cost, as well as worse postdischarge outcomes; patients who leave AMA are more likely to have received inadequate treatment for their medical condition, be readmitted for the same problem, and be lost to follow-up<sup><xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>The burden of cost on patient decision-making to leave AMA is not a new phenomenon in the medical field. This is consistent with our findings as we determined that patients on Medicare, Medicaid, or self-pay were more likely to leave AMA than those patients who had private insurance. Similarly, in a study by Menendez et al. examining 7,067,432 patients hospitalized for orthopedic trauma in the United States from the Nationwide Inpatient Sample (NIS) subsection of the HCUP database, low household income and not having private insurance were both significantly associated with patients leaving AMA<sup><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)</sup>. Villarreal et al. have also conducted a retrospective review of 546,856 patients who underwent emergency general surgery in the NIS database and arrived at the same conclusion: patients with private insurance were much less likely to leave AMA than those patients who were on self-pay, Medicare, or Medicaid<sup><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>)</sup>. Cost being a barrier to healthcare has also been documented internationally in other systems. In another study by Popoola et al., they found that among Nigerian patients who left AMA between 2010 and 2011 from an orthopedic hospital, 75.8% could not afford a major orthopedic operation<sup><xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>)</sup>. Moreover, Hasan et al.'s retrospective cohort study of 429 Pakistani patients found that patients unable to afford treatment were 2.38 times more likely to leave AMA than patients who have financial means to do so<sup><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>)</sup>. The burden of healthcare costs has a clear impact on patient decision-making, particularly in leaving AMA. It is thus critical that the growing cost of healthcare is addressed to ensure that patients can prioritize their health.</p><p>Another factor that may contribute to patients leaving AMA is low health literacy. Improving health literacy has been identified as a key factor to reduce health disparities in low- and middle-income countries<sup><xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>)</sup>. Within the United States, patients with lower incomes have lower rates of health literacy than wealthier people<sup><xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)</sup>. In this present study, we found that patients at the bottom quartile of income had 1.691 times greater odds of leaving AMA, as compared to patients in the top quartile of income who had 0.521 times less odds of leaving AMA. Our findings also determined that patients who received Medicare and Medicaid had 1.692 and 3.958 times greater odds of leaving AMA, respectively, as compared to patients who had private insurance (0.268 odds). Additionally, black and Hispanic patients were found to have lower rates of health literacy than white and Asian/Pacific Islander patients<sup><xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)</sup>. We also determined that black patients had a 1.612 times greater odds of leaving AMA, but we did not identify a significant increase in the rate of Hispanic patients leaving AMA. Levy and Janke found that individuals with Medicare, Medicaid, or no health insurance tended to have worse health literacy than patients with private, employer, or military-provided health insurance<sup><xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>)</sup>. We have identified that race, gender, income status, and insurance status were all independently related to patients leaving AMA following spine surgery, but we were unable to determine if these factors had any relationship to health literacy<sup><xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>)</sup>. Although the relationship between our variables of interest and health literacy has been well established, little is known about whether or not health literacy itself contributes to patients leaving AMA. Thus, additional research should be done to elucidate this relationship between health literacy and the rate at which patients leave AMA. With regard to hospital setting, Ibrahim et al. have examined 3,039,050 patients in the NIS database, with 43,678 of these patients identified to have left AMA<sup><xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>)</sup>; moreover, certain hospital characteristics, such as being an urban (OR=1.66, P&lt;0.05), being a medium-sized (OR=1.25, P&lt;0.05), or being a large-sized (OR=1.08, P&lt;0.05) hospital, were found to be independently associated with patients leaving AMA<sup><xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>)</sup>. Interestingly, this particular study also found that being a teaching hospital had a 0.90 (P&lt;0.05) times less odds of patients leaving AMA<sup><xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>)</sup>. Meanwhile, our study did not find any relationship between a hospital being rural or urban and patients leaving AMA.</p><p>This is the first study to quantitatively determine that increased length of hospital stay and longer time between admission and procedure are directly associated with increased odds of patients leaving AMA following spine surgery. This relationship has not been previously documented in previous literature. The amount of time spent waiting may have contributed to patient dissatisfaction, which is a key factor influencing whether or not a patient may choose to leave AMA. Additionally, the amount of time that patients spend in the hospital has been directly related to the increases in the cost of their stay<sup><xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>)</sup>. In a literature review by Albayati et al. wherein 49 studies were examined, it was determined that some of the reasons that patients leave AMA include lacking communication between the care team and providers, lack of respect from the staff, and poor quality of care<sup><xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>)</sup>. Longer wait times in the field of orthopedic surgery are well known to be associated with lower patient satisfaction in both clinic and hospital settings<sup><xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>-<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>)</sup>. While addressing concerns of patient satisfaction may be critical in reducing the likelihood that patients leave AMA, patient satisfaction is multidimensional and thus difficult to assess objectively<sup><xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>)</sup>. Future research should address this gap in the literature.</p><p>Additionally, increased length of hospital stay increases overall cost, which, in turn, contribute to individuals leaving AMA. Hospital costs include postoperative care, nutrition, and occupational and physical therapy, which can add significant financial burden to patients<sup><xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>)</sup>. Our study demonstrates that increasing hospital costs can significantly influence the number of patients leaving AMA, as patients who left AMA had higher total patient charges. Additional research should be performed to determine the effects of length of stay and costs on patients leaving AMA and the effects it may have on a patient's health outcome.</p><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>Although the HCUP database allows us to access a large number of patient information, the use of this database also carries its own limitations in relation to patient reported outcomes. Moreover, this study is retrospective in nature, which also limited the scope of this study. Additionally, the database does not carry detailed case information that may contribute to patients leaving AMA, such as degree of condition prior to surgery.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Surgical patients who leave AMA tend to have higher rates of readmission and postoperative complications. In this study, we have investigated the factors that may have contributed to patients leaving the hospital AMA following spine surgery. As per our findings, patients who left AMA were more likely to be adults, black, and male, have low-income status, and do not have private insurance. Additionally, we found that these patients were more likely to have longer hospital stay, longer time between admission and procedure, and higher cost of treatment. Thus, future research should focus on determining what interventions can be utilized to reduce the number of patients leaving AMA.</p></sec><sec><p content-type="COI-statement">
<bold>Conflicts of Interest: </bold>The authors declare that there are no relevant conflicts of interest.</p></sec><sec><p><bold>Sources of Funding: </bold>None</p></sec><sec><p><bold>Author Contributions: </bold>All authors have contributed significantly to this project.</p></sec><sec><p><bold>Ethical Approval: </bold>HCUP database is IRB approved as it is publicly available de-identified information.</p></sec><sec><p><bold>Informed Consent: </bold>N/A</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cram P, Landon BE, Matelski J, et al. Utilization and outcomes for spine surgery in the United States and Canada. Spine. 2019;44(19):1371-80.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/BRS.0000000000003083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6746582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31261267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pendharkar AV, Shahin MN, Ho AL, et al. Outpatient spine surgery: defining the outcomes, value, and barriers to implementation. Neurosurg Focus. 2018;44(5):E11.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3171/2018.2.FOCUS17790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29712520</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Buttermann GR. Anterior cervical discectomy and fusion outcomes over 10 years: a prospective study. Spine. 2018;43(3):207-14.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/BRS.0000000000002273</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28604488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bydon M, Macki M, Abt NB, et al. Clinical and surgical outcomes after lumbar laminectomy: an analysis of 500 patients. Surg Neurol Int. 2015;6(Suppl 4):S190-3.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/2152-7806.156578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4431053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26005583</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Reisener MJ, Pumberger M, Shue J, et al. Trends in lumbar spinal fusion-a literature review. J Spine Surg. 2020;6(4):752-61.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.21037/jss-20-492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7797794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33447679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Alfandre DJ. &#8220;I'm going home&#8221;: discharges against medical advice. Mayo Clin Proc. 2009;84(3):255-60.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4065/84.3.255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2664598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19252113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Berger JT. Discharge against medical advice: ethical considerations and professional obligations. J Hosp Med. 2008;3(5):403-8.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jhm.362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18951403</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ferari CS, Katsevman GA, Dekeseredy P, et al. Implications of drug use disorders on spine surgery. World Neurosurg. 2020;136(1):e334-41.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.wneu.2019.12.177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7556334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31926361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Arnold PM, Rice LR, Anderson KK, et al. Factors affecting hospital length of stay following anterior cervical discectomy and fusion. Evid Based Spine Care J. 2011;2(3):11-8.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1055/s-0030-1267108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3604758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23532355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gruskay JA, Fu M, Bohl DD, et al. Factors affecting length of stay after elective posterior lumbar spine surgery: a multivariate analysis. Spine J. 2015;15(6):1188-95.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.spinee.2013.10.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24184639</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Evaniew N, Swamy G, Jacobs WB, et al. Lumbar fusion surgery for patients with back pain and degenerative disc disease: an observational study from the Canadian spine outcomes and research network. Global Spine J. 2022;12(8):1676-86.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/2192568220985470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9609527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33406897</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jerrard DA, Chasm RM. Patients leaving against medical advice (ama) from the emergency department-disease prevalence and willingness to return. J Emerg Med. 2011;41(4):412-7.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jemermed.2009.10.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20097503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Menendez M, van Dijk CN, Ring D. Who leaves the hospital against medical advice in the orthopaedic setting? Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2015;473(1):1140-9.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11999-014-3924-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4317430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25187333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Villarreal ME, Schubauer K, Paredes AZ, et al. Leaving against medical advice after emergency general surgery: avoiding a two-hit effect. J Surg Res. 2021;257(1):278-84.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jss.2020.06.058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32866668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Popoola SO, Onyemaechi NOC, Kortor JN, et al. Leave against medical advice (LAMA) from in-patient orthopaedic treatment. SA Orthopaedic J. 2013;12(3):58-61.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hasan O, Samad MA, Khan H, et al. Leaving against medical advice from in-patients departments rate, reasons and predicting risk factors for re-visiting hospital retrospective cohort from a tertiary care hospital. Int J Health Policy Manag. 2019;8(8):474-9.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.15171/ijhpm.2019.26</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6706961</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31441287</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Meherali S, Punjani NS, Mevawala A. Health literacy interventions to improve health outcomes in low- and middle-income countries. Health Lit Res Prac. 2020;4(4):e251-66.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3928/24748307-20201118-01</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7751448</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33313935</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cutilli CC, Bennett IM. Understanding the health literacy of America: results of the national assessment of adult literacy. Orthop Nurs. 2009;28(1):27-32.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/01.NOR.0000345852.22122.d6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2668931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19190475</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Levy H, Janke A. Health literacy and access to care. J Health Commun. 2016;21(Suppl 1):43-50.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/10810730.2015.1131776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4924568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27043757</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Intrator J, Tannen J, Massey DS. Segregation by race and income in the United States 1970-2010. Soc Sci Res. 2016;60:45-60.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ssresearch.2016.08.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5117629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27712688</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ibrahim S, Kwoh CK, Krishnan E. Factors associated with patients who leave acute-care hospitals against medical advice. Am J Public Health. 2007;97(12);2204-8.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2105/AJPH.2006.100164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2089112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17971552</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lott A, Haglin J, Belayneh R, et al. Admitting service affects cost and length of stay of hip fracture patients. Geriatr Orthop Surg Rehabil. 2018;9(1):2151459318808845.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/2151459318808845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6249656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30479850</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Albayati A, Douedi S, Alshami A, et al. Why do patients leave against medical advice? reasons, consequences, prevention, and interventions. Healthcare. 2021;9(2):111.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/healthcare9020111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7909809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33494294</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Teunis T, Thornton E, Jayakumar P, et al. Time seeing a hand surgeon is not associated with patient satisfaction. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2014;23(12):1913-21</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Waters S, Edmondston SJ, Yates PJ, et al. Identification of factors influencing patient satisfaction with orthopaedic outpatient clinic consultation: a qualitative study. Man Ther. 2016;25(1):48-55.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.math.2016.05.334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27422597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rane AA, Tyser AR, Kazmers NH. Evaluating the impact of wait time on orthopaedic outpatient satisfaction using the press Ganey survey. JB JS Open Access. 2019;4(4):e0014.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2106/JBJS.OA.19.00014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6959917</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32043054</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Graham B. Defining and measuring patient satisfaction. J Hand Surg. 2016;41(9):929-31.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jhsa.2016.07.109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27570227</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kaye AD, Urman RD, Cornett EM, et al. Enhanced recovery pathways in orthopedic surgery. J Anaesthesiol Clin Pharmacol. 2019;35(Suppl 1):S35-9.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/joacp.JOACP_35_18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6515716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31142957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>