<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Pain Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Pain Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1405</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jpainres</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jpr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Pain Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1178-7090</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10638919</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10638919.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10638919</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10638919</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37954473</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/JPR.S427411</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">427411</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Race, Ethnicity, and Sustained Opioid Use After Major Abdominal Surgery for Cancer</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Owusu-Agyemang et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Owusu-Agyemang et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0315-3964</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Owusu-Agyemang</surname><given-names initials="P">Pascal</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1165-8046</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names initials="L">Lei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3156-1682</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Cata</surname><given-names initials="JP">Juan P</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Anesthesiology and Perioperative Medicine, University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</institution>, <addr-line>Houston</addr-line>, <addr-line>TX</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Anesthesiology and Surgical Oncology Research Group</institution>, <addr-line>Houston</addr-line>, <addr-line>TX</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Biostatistics, University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</institution>, <addr-line>Houston</addr-line>, <addr-line>TX</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Pascal Owusu-Agyemang, <institution>Department of Anesthesiology and Perioperative Medicine, the University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</institution>, <addr-line>1515 Holcombe Boulevard, Unit 0401</addr-line>, <addr-line>Houston</addr-line>, <addr-line>TX</addr-line>, <addr-line>77030</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>, <phone>Tel + 1 832 465 8964</phone>, Email poagyemang@mdanderson.org</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">425896</issue-id><fpage>3759</fpage><lpage>3774</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>07</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-01-27 01:25:10.603"><day>27</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2023 Owusu-Agyemang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Owusu-Agyemang et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution &#8211; Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jpr-16-3759.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>Sustained opioid use is a well-known complication after surgery. Our objective was to determine whether there is any association between a patient&#8217;s race or ethnicity and the sustained use of opioids in the year following surgery. Opioid use over the initial 3, 6, and 12 postoperative months was categorized as &#8220;sustained early&#8221;, persistent, and chronic, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Patients and Methods</title><p>Single-institution retrospective study of adults (&#8805;18 years) who had undergone open abdominal surgery for cancer. Multivariable logistic regression was used to evaluate the association between race/ethnicity and opioid use.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Of the 3523 patients included in the study, 2543 (72.2%) were non-Hispanic (NH) White, 476 (13.5%) were Hispanic or Latino, 262 (7.4%) were NH-Black, 186 (5.3%) were Asian, and 56 (1.6%) belonged to other racial or ethnic groups. The overall rates of sustained early, persistent, and chronic opioid use were 15.9%, 7.1%, and 2.6%, respectively. In the multivariable analysis, patient race/ethnicity was associated with sustained early postoperative opioid use (p-value=0.037), with Hispanics/Latinos having significantly higher odds than NH-Whites (OR = 1.382 [95% CI: 1.057&#8211;1.808]; p = 0.018). However, neither persistent nor chronic opioid use was associated with race/ethnicity (p = 0.697 and p = 0.443, respectively).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>In this retrospective study of adults who had undergone open abdominal surgery, patient race/ethnicity was not consistently associated with the development of sustained opioid use over the first 12 postoperative months.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>race</kwd><kwd>ethnicity</kwd><kwd>persistent</kwd><kwd>chronic</kwd><kwd>opioids</kwd><kwd>cancer</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="2"/><ref-count count="47"/><page-count count="16"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Pain continues to be one of the most common and debilitating symptoms of cancer.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Recent estimates suggest 30% to 50% of cancer patients experience pain, with 30.6% experiencing pain of a moderate-to-severe nature.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Furthermore, an estimated 33% to 40% of cancer survivors are known to experience chronic pain.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></p><p>Despite the availability of analgesic options, opioids have remained a cornerstone for the treatment of moderate-to-severe pain in cancer patients.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> However, opioid-related adverse effects have been shown to negatively impact the quality of life of cancer patients and survivors.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Particularly concerning is the development of persistent or chronic opioid use, which may not only prolong the disabling adverse effects of opioids but also increase the risk of death related to overdose.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7&#8211;9</xref> In a retrospective study of 19,219 adults who had undergone curative-intent cancer surgery, patients who developed new persistent opioid use had more than twice the risk of opioid overdose compared to non-opioid users.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p><p>Some studies, albeit in patients undergoing non-oncological surgery, have shown an association between patient race or ethnicity and persistent opioid use. Examples include a retrospective study of 1656 patients who had undergone upper extremity surgery, where White race was associated with lesser odds of persistent opioid use,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> and other studies where Black race was associated with higher odds of persistent opioid use after hysterectomy,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> cardiothoracic surgery,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> and spine surgery.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> In addition, race-dependent polymorphisms of the CYP2D6 and mu-opioid receptor genes have been associated with variable potency of some commonly prescribed opioids in NH-Blacks and decreased pain sensitivity among NH-Whites, respectively.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> To date, the interaction between patient race or ethnicity and persistent or chronic opioid use in the surgical oncology patient population is unclear. An assessment of this risk may be considered important since it may help inform prevention strategies and reduce the risk of complications related to persistent opioid use.</p><p>In addition, other factors including adjuvant chemotherapy, type of surgery, and alcohol abuse have been shown to be associated with long-term opioid use.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17&#8211;19</xref> In other studies, the use of epidural analgesia during major abdominal surgery has been shown to reduce short-term incisional pain.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20&#8211;23</xref> However, its effect on the occurrence of persistent or chronic opioid use after cancer-related surgery is less clear.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></p><p>To that end, we conducted a single-institution retrospective study of adults who had undergone open-abdominal surgical procedures, with the primary objective of comparing the rates of early sustained, persistent, and chronic opioid use between patients of different races or ethnicities. Our hypothesis was that the rates of opioid use would be similar across racial/ethnic groups. For our secondary objectives, we sought to evaluate the impacts of adjuvant chemotherapy, type of surgery, alcohol abuse, smoking history, and epidural analgesia on the occurrence of sustained opioid use.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board (IRB) of the University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center on September 27, 2021 (IRB # 2021&#8211;0738). Due to the retrospective nature of this study, written informed consent was not required. The data accessed complied with relevant data protection and privacy regulations. Extracted study variables were stored on the Research Electronic Data Capture web platform hosted by the University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center. Our findings are reported in accordance with the Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) statement.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></p><sec id="s0002-s2001"><title>Patient Selection Process</title><p>We used a dataset from our previous publication on race, ethnicity, and the use of regional anesthesia in patients who had undergone surgical procedures between March 1, 2016, and August 1, 2021.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Unlike our previous publication where patients who had used opioids prior to surgery we included, the patient selection process in this current study (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>) was designed to include only those patients who had undergone open abdominal surgical procedures and had not reported any opioid use within three months of the index surgical procedure. Previously established exclusion criteria including patients of American Society of Anesthesiologists Physical Status (ASA PS) 4 and above, those undergoing emergency, laparoscopic, robotic, minimally invasive, and outpatient procedures were maintained. In addition, patients with missing data on their race and ethnicity were excluded from the current study. To avoid over-representation of individual patients, only data related to their index admission for open abdominal surgery was included.
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>STROBE Flow diagram of the patient selection process.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JPR-16-3759-g0001.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002"><title>Anesthetic Management</title><p>At our institution, the anesthetic management of patients undergoing open abdominal surgery is not standardized. However, a typical regimen consists of the preoperative administration of celecoxib, tramadol, acetaminophen, and midazolam, followed by volatile-based general anesthesia with a regional block.</p><p>The decision to use regional anesthesia is largely influenced by the extensiveness of the surgical procedure to be performed. These types of regional anesthesia include thoracic epidural analgesia or bilateral subcostal transversus abdominis plane with quadratus lumborum blocks. For less extensive procedures, local anesthetic infiltration of the incision is performed by the surgeon. Fentanyl, hydromorphone, and intravenous acetaminophen are commonly administered during surgery, and the use of opioid-free anesthesia is rare.</p><p>The institutional post-anesthesia care unit (PACU) order-set, which is completed by the attending anesthesiologist, has options for the treatment of mild, moderate, and severe pain. Acetaminophen and methocarbamol are included in the options for managing mild pain, while varying dosages of fentanyl, morphine, and hydromorphone are used for the management of mild, moderate, or severe pain.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003"><title>Exposure Variables</title><p>The primary exposure variable was a patient&#8217;s self-reported race or ethnicity. Accordingly, patients were divided into the following groups: Asian, Not-Hispanic or Latino (NH) Black, Hispanic or Latino, NH-White, and NH-Other. The group of NH-Other included patients who self-identified as follows: American Indian or Alaska Native, Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander, and those who self-identified as &#8220;Other race&#8221;.</p><p>The secondary exposure variables were the receipt of adjuvant chemotherapy up to 12 months following the date of surgery, the type of surgical procedure, alcohol abuse prior to the date of surgery, smoking history, and the use of epidural analgesia during surgery.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004"><title>Outcome Measures</title><p>The primary outcome measures were sustained early postoperative opioid use, persistent opioid use, and chronic opioid use. Sustained early postoperative use of opioid was defined as self-reported opioid use during outpatient visits at 1 and 3 months after surgery. Based on previously used definitions, persistent opioid use was defined as self-reported opioid use during outpatient visits at 1, 3, and 6 months after surgery.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26&#8211;29</xref> Accordingly, chronic opioid use was defined as self-reported opioid use during outpatient visits at 1, 3, 6, and 12 months after surgery. Based on conversions used in the Centers for Disease Control Guideline for Prescribing Opioids for Pain, perioperative opioid administration was converted into morphine equivalent daily dose units (MEDD).<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2005"><title>Study Covariates</title><p>Baseline and perioperative variables extracted from subsections of the institutional data warehouse are summarized in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The following demographic and potentially confounding categorical variables were included in the analysis: Race/ethnicity, gender, American Society of Anesthesiologists Physical Status (ASA), history of anxiety/depression, alcohol abuse, smoking status, and cancer stage.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline and Postoperative Characteristics of 3523 Adults Who Had Open Abdominal Surgery</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Variable, No. (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian (n = 186)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black (n = 262)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic/Latino (n = 476)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other (n = 56)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">White (n = 2543)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, yrs (median [IQR])</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (46, 67)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (48, 68)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (44, 66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (44, 67)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (51, 70)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (median [IQR])</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (22, 27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (26, 34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (25, 33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (25, 31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (24, 32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (35.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127 (48.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">210 (44.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (48.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1146 (45.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.079</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 (64.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135 (51.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">266 (55.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (51.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1397 (54.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1&#8211;2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (9.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (7.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (8.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">147 (5.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.195</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;3&#8211;4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">169 (90.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">249 (95)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">441 (92.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (91.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2396 (94.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety/Depression</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">172 (92.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">221 (84.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">390 (81.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (89.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2069 (81.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (7.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (15.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (18.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (10.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">474 (18.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol abuse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">183 (98.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">258 (98.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">472 (99.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (98.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2502 (98.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.798</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (1.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (1.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (1.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">186 (100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">261 (99.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">475 (99.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (98.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2541 (99.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(0.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgery type</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Colorectal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (26.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (31.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">142 (29.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">718 (28.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Endocrine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (3.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (3.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Gastrointestinal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (16.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (15.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 (14.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (8.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">406 (16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;General</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (9.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (11.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (7.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">289 (11.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Sarcoma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (4.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (6.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (10.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">167 (6.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Urology</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (2.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (9.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 (4.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;HPB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (32.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (28.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">122 (25.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (39.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">711 (28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;PSM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (2.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (2.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer stage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(0.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (0.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.288</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (14.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (10.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (17.%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (12.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">162 (14.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (23.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (15.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (19.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (20.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">169 (15.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (30.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (20.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(4.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">260 (23.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (36.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (43.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (41.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (62.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">509 (46)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regional Anesthesia:</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.047</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Epidural</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (19.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (18.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">116 (24.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (39.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">639 (25.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Truncal block</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (29.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (32.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">148 (31.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">776 (30.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (51.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128 (48.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">212 (44.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (35.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1128 (44.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epidural anesthesia:</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150 (80.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">213 (81.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">360 (75.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (60.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1904 (74.9)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (19.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (18.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">116 (24.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (39.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">639 (25.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anesthesia duration, hrs (median [IQR])</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (4.3, 7.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (4.6, 8.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (4.5, 8.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 (4.6, 8.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2 (4.4, 8.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.927</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intraoperative opioid dose, MEDD (median [IQR])</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (10, 46)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (20, 50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (20, 49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (20, 50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (20, 48)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.248</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak PACU pain score:</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&lt; 7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117 (62.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125 (47.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">260 (54.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (42.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1382 (54.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8805; 7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (37.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136 (52.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">216 (45.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (57.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1161 (45.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PACU opioid dose, MEDD (median [IQR])</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (0, 10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (5, 15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (4, 10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (5, 15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (5, 10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Additional surgery within 3 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">159 (85.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">213 (81.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">414 (87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (83.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2211 (86.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.136</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (14.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (18.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (16.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">332 (13.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Additional surgery within 6 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">152 (81.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">193 (73.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">387 (81.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (78.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016 (79.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.141</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (18.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (26.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (18.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (21.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">527 (20.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Additional surgery within 12 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137 (73.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">170 (64.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">358 (75.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1872 (73.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (26.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (35.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118 (24.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">671 (26.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjuvant chemotherapy within 3 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">162 (87.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">223 (85.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">420 (88.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (85.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2265 (89.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.333</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (12.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (14.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (11.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (14.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">278 (10.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjuvant chemotherapy within 6 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">155 (83.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">213 (81.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">402 (84.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (82.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2185 (85.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.253</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (16.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (18.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (15.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (17.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">358 (14.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjuvant chemotherapy within 12 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150 (80.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">201 (76.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">390 (81.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (78.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2120 (83.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.074</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (19.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (23.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (18.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (21.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">423 (16.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sustained early (3 months) opioid use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">161 (86.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">207 (79)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">388 (81.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (76.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2165 (85.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (13.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88 (18.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (23.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">378 (14.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent (6 months) opioid use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">181 (97.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">240 (91.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">436 (91.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (89.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2367 (93.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (8.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (8.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (10.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176 (6.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic (12 months) opioid use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">186 (100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">253 (96.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">460 (96.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (96.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2479 (97.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.131</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (3.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (3.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: IQR, interquartile range; BMI, body mass index; ASA, American Society of Anesthesiologists; HPB, hepato-pancreato-biliary; PSM, peritoneal surface malignancy; MEDD, morphine equivalent daily dose; PACU, Post-Anesthesia Care Unit.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Additionally, the types of surgery, regional anesthesia, epidural analgesia, and the use of a truncal block were included in the analysis.</p><p>Continuous variables of body mass index (BMI), anesthesia duration, and total intraoperative opioid dose were also included. Immediate postoperative variables included total dose of opioids administered in the PACU. The occurrence of the following in the year following surgery was also assessed: additional surgery, adjuvant chemotherapy, and outpatient opioid use.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2006"><title>Statistical Methods</title><p>Patients&#8217; demographics, treatment, and clinical outcomes were summarized through descriptive statistics. Wilcoxon rank sum test or Kruskal&#8211;Wallis test was used to compare location parameters of continuous distributions between or among patient groups. Chi-square test was used to evaluate the association between two categorical variables. A multivariable logistic regression model was fitted to estimate the effects of important covariates on opioid use after surgery. Statistical software SAS 9.4 (SAS, Cary, NC) was used for all the analyses.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003"><title>Results</title><p>Of the 3523 patients included in the study, 2543 (72.2%) were non-Hispanic (NH) White, 476 (13.5%) were Hispanic or Latino, 262 (7.4%) were NH-Black, 186 (5.3%) were Asian, and 56 (1.6%) belonged to other racial or ethnic groups. The majority were male (55.3%), and the median age (interquartile range [IQR]) was 60 years (IQR, 50&#8211;69). The overall rates of sustained early, persistent, and chronic opioid use over the initial 3, 6, and 12 months were 15.9%, 7.1%, and 2.6%, respectively. Other baseline characteristics of the study population are shown in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><p>Among the baseline characteristics, age (p &lt; 0.001), BMI (p &lt; 0.001), anxiety/depression (p = 0.002), and smoking (p = 0.012) were significantly different across racial/ethnic groups. The types of surgeries undergone and the use of epidural analgesia also differed significantly across racial/ethnic groups (p = 0.021 and p = 0.006, respectively). With regard to epidural analgesia, the lowest rate of use (18.7%) was observed in the NH-Black patient population, and the highest rate (39.3%) was in patients of NH-Other race/ethnicity.</p><p>However, in the immediate postoperative period, a significantly higher proportion of PACU pain scores &#8805; 7 was observed among patients of NH-Other race (p = 0.012). PACU opioid consumption varied significantly across racial/ethnic groups (p = 0.024), with the highest median dose observed in the group of NH-Black patients (p = 0.024).</p><p>After being discharged from the hospital, a larger proportion of NH-Black patients required additional surgery within 12 months of the original surgery date (p = 0.032).</p><sec id="s0003-s2001"><title>Sustained Early Postoperative Opioid Use</title><sec id="s0003-s2001-s3001"><title>Race/Ethnicity and Sustained Early Postoperative Opioid Use</title><p>In the univariable analysis (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), the rates of sustained early opioid use varied across racial/ethnic groups (p = 0.013), with the highest rate observed among patients of NH-Other race. With the adjustment of gender, surgery type, alcohol abuse, regional anesthesia with epidural, anesthesia duration, highest PACU pain score, any repeat surgery within the three previous months, and any adjuvant chemotherapy within the 3 months, the multivariable analysis (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>) demonstrates a statistically significant association between the race/ethnicity variable and sustained early opioid use (p = 0.037).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Univariable Analysis of Factors Associated with Sustained Opioid Use After Open Abdominal Surgery for Cancer</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variable, No. (%)</th><th colspan="5" rowspan="1">Sustained Early (3 Months) Opioid Use</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Persistent (6 Months) Opioid Use</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Chronic (12 Months) Opioid Use</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Yes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Yes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Yes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years (median [IQR])</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (49, 69)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">59 (50, 68)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.240</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (49, 69)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">60 (52, 67)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.895</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (50, 69)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">58 (51, 66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.472</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, median [IQR]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (24, 32)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">28 (24, 33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.200</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (24, 32)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">29 (25, 34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (24, 32)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">29 (25, 34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.123</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1308 (83)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">268 (17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1449 (91.9)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">127 (8.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1526 (96.8)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">50 (3.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1656 (85.1)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">291 (14.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1825 (93.7)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">122 (6.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1906 (97.9)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">41 (2.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race:</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Asian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">161 (86.6)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">25 (13.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">181 (97.3)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">5 (2.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">186 (100)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.131</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Black</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">207 (79)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">55 (21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">240 (91.6)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">22 (8.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">253 (96.6)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">9 (3.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Hispanic/Latino</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">388 (81.5)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">88 (18.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">436 (91.6)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">40 (8.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">460 (96.6)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">16 (3.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (76.8)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">13 (23.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (89.3)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">6 (10.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (96.4)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">2 (3.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;White</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2165 (85.1)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">378 (14.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2367 (93.1)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">176 (6.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2479 (97.5)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">64 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASA Score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1&#8211;2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">190 (87.6)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">27 (12.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.154</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">205 (94.5)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">12 (5.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.362</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">209 (96.3)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">8 (3.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.290</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;3&#8211;4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2774 (83.9)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">532 (16.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3069 (92.8)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">237 (7.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3223 (97.5)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">83 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgery type:</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Colorectal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">794 (78.9)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">212 (21.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">883 (87.8)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">123 (12.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">965 (95.9)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">41 (4.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Endocrine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (92.2)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">8 (7.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97 (95.1)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">5 (4.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (97.1)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">3 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Gastrointestinal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">457 (82.9)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">94 (17.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">508 (92.2)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">43 (7.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">540 (98.0)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">11 (2.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;General</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">338 (88.3)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">45 (11.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">367 (95.8)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">16 (4.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">373 (97.4)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">10 (2.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Sarcoma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200 (87.7)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">28 (12.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">220 (96.5)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">8 (3.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">224 (98.2)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4 (1.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Urology</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">158 (94.6)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">9 (5.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">166 (99.4)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">1 (0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">166 (99.4)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">1 (0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;HPB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">839 (84.7)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">152 (15.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">939 (94.8)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">52 (5.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">970 (97.9)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">21 (2.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;PSM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84 (88.4)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">11 (11.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (98.9)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">1 (1.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (100)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer stage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (100)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (100)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (100)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.(0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">196 (87.1)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">29 (12.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">217 (96.4)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">8 (3.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">223 (99.1)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">2 (0.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">214 (85.9)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">35 (14.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">230 (92.4)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">19 (7.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">243 (97.6)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">6 (2.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">281 (78.5)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">77 (21.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">313 (87.4)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">45 (12.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">341 (95.3)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">17 (4.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">563 (81.6)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">127 (18.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">621 (90)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">69 (10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">661 (95.8)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">29 (4.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety/depression</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2458 (84.7)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">444 (15.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2711 (93.4)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">191 (6.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2831 (97.6)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">71 (2.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.270</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">506 (81.5)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">115 (18.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">563 (90.7)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">58 (9.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">601 (96.8)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">20 (3.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol abuse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2927 (84.4)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">543 (15.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3230 (93.1)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">240 (6.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3380 (97.4)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">90 (2.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.748</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (69.8)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">16 (30.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (83)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">9 (17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (98.1)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">1 (1.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regional anesthesia:</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Epidural</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">675 (78.3)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">187 (21.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">766 (88.9)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">96 (11.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">827 (95.9)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">35 (4.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Truncal block</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">924 (85.7)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">154 (14.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1015 (94.2)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">63 (5.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1059 (98.2)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">19 (1.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1365 (86.2)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">218 (13.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1493 (94.3)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">90 (5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1546 (97.7)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">37 (2.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epidural anesthesia:</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2289 (86)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">372 (14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2508 (94.3)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">153 (5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2605 (97.9)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">56 (2.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">675 (78.3)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">187 (21.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">766 (88.9)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">96 (11.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">827 (95.9)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">35 (4.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anesthesia duration, hrs. (median [IQR])</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (4.3, 8.2)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">6.7 (4.8, 9.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (4.4, 8.3)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">6.6 (4.6, 9.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (4.4, 8.4)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">6.6 (4.6, 8.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.200</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intraoperative opioid dose, MEDD (median [IQR])</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (20, 46)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">30 (20, 50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (20, 46)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">34 (20, 50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (20, 48)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">35 (20, 50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.297</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak PACU pain score:</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&lt; 7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1622 (85.0)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">286 (15.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.119</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1783 (93.4)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">125 (6.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.192</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1859 (97.4)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">49 (2.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.949</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8805; 7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1341 (83.1)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">273 (16.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1490 (92.3)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">124 (7.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1572 (97.4)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">42 (2.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak PACU pain score (median [IQR])</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (4, 8)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">6 (4, 8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (4, 8)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">6 (4, 8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (4, 8)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">6 (3, 9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.281</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average PACU pain score (median [IQR])</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (1.3, 3.7)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">2.7 (1.2, 4.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (1.3, 3.7)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">2.7 (1.4, 4.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (1.3, 3.7)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">2.6 (1.4, 4.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.146</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PACU opioid dose, MEDD (median [IQR])</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (5, 10)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">5 (5, 15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.172</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (5, 10)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">5 (5, 15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (5, 10)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">10 (5, 15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Additional surgery within 3 months:</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2640 (86.7)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">404 (13.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">324 (67.6)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">155 (32.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Additional surgery within 6 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2651 (94.9)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">141 (5.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">623 (85.2)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">108 (14.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Additional surgery within 12 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2543 (98.6)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">36 (1.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">889 (94.2)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">55 (5.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjuvant chemotherapy within 3 months after surgery</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2690 (86.3)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">428 (13.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">274 (67.7)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">131 (32.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjuvant chemotherapy within 6 months after surgery</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2861 (95.3)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">140 (4.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">413 (79.1)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">109 (20.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjuvant chemotherapy within 12 months after surgery</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2867 (98.7)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">38 (1.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">565 (91.4)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">53 (8.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: IQR, interquartile range; BMI, body mass index; ASA, American Society of Anesthesiologists; HPB, hepato-pancreato-biliary; PSM, peritoneal surface malignancy; MEDD, morphine equivalent daily dose; PACU, Post-Anesthesia Care Unit.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Independent predictors of sustained early opioid use after open abdominal surgery. Hispanic/Latino patients had 38% higher odds of sustained early opioid use than NH-White patients (odds ratio [OR] = 1.382; 95% confidence interval [CI] = 1.057 &#8722;1.808; p = 0.018). Compared to patients who had undergone peritoneal surface malignancy procedures, patients who had undergone colorectal surgery (OR = 2.284; 95% CI = 1.155&#8211;4.517; p = 0.018) and those who had undergone gastrointestinal surgery (OR = 2.183; 95% CI = 1.090&#8211;4.372; p = 0.028) had higher odds of sustained early opioid use. In addition, alcohol abuse (OR = 2.169; 95% CI = 1.139&#8211;4.130; p = 0.019), the use of epidural anesthesia (OR = 1.399; 95% CI = 1.129&#8211;1.734; p = 0.002), adjuvant chemotherapy within the three month period (OR = 2.591; 95% CI = 2.010&#8211;3.340; p &lt; 0.001), anesthesia duration (OR = 1.101; 95% CI = 1.066&#8211;1.137; p &lt; 0.001), a peak PACU pain score &gt; 7 (OR = 1.318; 95% CI = 1.087&#8211;1.597; p = 0.005), and repeat surgery within the three month period (OR = 2.563; 95% CI = 2.026&#8211;3.244; p &lt; 0.001) were each associated with sustained early postoperative opioid use.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JPR-16-3759-g0002.jpg"/></fig></p><p>Within this association, Hispanic/Latino patients had 38% higher odds of sustained early opioid use than NH-White patients (odds ratio [OR] = 1.382; 95% confidence interval [CI] = 1.057 &#8722;1.808; p = 0.018).</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2001-s3002"><title>Adjuvant Chemotherapy and Sustained Early Postoperative Opioid Use</title><p>In the univariable analysis (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), the rates of sustained early postoperative use were higher in patients who had received adjuvant chemotherapy within the three-month period (32.3% versus 13.7%, p &lt; 0.001). In the multivariable analysis (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>), the receipt of adjuvant chemotherapy within the first three postoperative months was associated with a more than two-fold increase in the risk of developing sustained early postoperative opioid use (OR = 2.591; 95% CI = 2.010&#8211;3.340; p &lt; 0.001).</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2001-s3003"><title>Effect of Surgery Type on Sustained Early Postoperative Opioid Use</title><p>The rates of sustained early opioid use varied significantly across surgery types (p &lt; 0.001), with the highest rate (21.1%) observed in patients who had undergone colorectal surgery. In the multivariable analysis (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>), patients who had undergone colorectal (OR = 2.284; 95% CI = 1.155&#8211;4.517; p = 0.018) and gastrointestinal (OR = 2.183; 95% CI = 1.090&#8211;4.372; p = 0.028) surgeries had significantly higher odds of sustained early opioid use than those who had undergone peritoneal surface malignancy procedures.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2001-s3004"><title>Effect of Alcohol Abuse on Sustained Early Postoperative Opioid Use</title><p>Significantly higher rates of history of alcohol abuse (30.2% versus 15.6%, p = 0.004) were observed in the group of patients who subsequently developed sustained early postoperative opioid use. In the adjusted analysis (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>), a documented history of alcohol abuse at the time of surgery was associated with a two-fold increase in the odds of developing sustained early opioid use (OR = 2.169; 95% CI = 1.139&#8211;4.130; p = 0.019).</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2001-s3005"><title>Regional Anesthesia and Sustained Early Postoperative Opioid Use</title><p>The group of patients who received regional anesthesia had higher rates of sustained early postoperative opioid use than those who did not (17.6% versus 13.8%, p = 0.002). Among the types of regional anesthesia used, patients who received epidural analgesia had higher rates of sustained early postoperative opioid use than those who did not (21.7% versus 14.0%, p &lt; 0.001).</p><p>After adjusting for gender, surgery type, alcohol abuse, regional anesthesia with epidural, anesthesia duration, highest PACU pain score, repeat surgery within the three previous months, and adjuvant chemotherapy within the 3 months, the multivariable analysis (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>) demonstrates a 39.9% increase in the odds of developing sustained early opioid use in patients who received epidural analgesia during surgery (OR = 1.399; 95% CI = 1.129&#8211;1.734; p = 0.002).</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2001-s3006"><title>Effect of Additional Factors</title><p>In the univariable analysis (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), a significantly higher rate of anxiety/depression (18.5% versus 15.3%, p = 0.046) was observed in the group of patients with sustained early postoperative opioid use. In addition, the rate of sustained early opioid use varied by cancer stage (p = 0.024). Anesthesia duration (median [IQR]: 6.7 hr [4.8&#8211;9.4] versus 6.1 hr [4.3&#8211;8.2]; p &lt; 0.001) and intraoperative opioid administration (median [IQR]: 30 MEDD [20&#8211;50], versus median 30 MEDD [20&#8211;46]; p = 0.001) were also comparatively longer in the group of patients with sustained early postoperative opioid use.</p><p>Of the postoperative characteristics, sustained early opioid use was associated with higher average PACU pain scores (median [IQR] 2.7 [1.2&#8211;4.1] versus median, 2.5 [1.3&#8211;3.7]; p = 0.029) and additional surgery within the three-month period (32.4% versus 13.3%, p &lt; 0.001).</p><p>In the multivariable analysis (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>), other factors that were independently associated with the development of sustained early opioid use included anesthesia duration (OR = 1.101; 95% CI = 1.066&#8211;1.137; p &lt; 0.001), a peak PACU pain score &gt; 7 (OR = 1.318; 95% CI = 1.087&#8211;1.597; p = 0.005), and repeat surgery within the 3-month period (OR = 2.563; 95% CI = 2.026&#8211;3.244; p &lt; 0.001).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002"><title>Persistent Opioid Use</title><sec id="s0003-s2002-s3001"><title>Race/Ethnicity and Persistent Opioid Use</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, the rates of persistent opioid use did not differ significantly across racial/ethnic groups (p = 0.071). With the adjustment of age, BMI, gender, anxiety/depression, alcohol abuse, regional anesthesia with epidural, anesthesia duration, PACU opioid dose, highest PACU pain score, repeat surgery within six months, and adjuvant chemotherapy within 6 months (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>), the association between race/ethnicity and persistent opioid use was not significant (p = 0.696).
<fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Independent predictors of persistent opioid use after open abdominal surgery. The association between race/ethnicity and persistent opioid use was not significant (p-value=0.696). Of the secondary exposure variables, the use of epidural anesthesia (OR = 1.581; 95% CI = 1.035&#8211;2.416; p = 0.034) and adjuvant chemotherapy within the six postoperative months (OR = 5.276; 95% CI = 3.663&#8211;7.600; p &lt; 0.001) were each associated with the development of persistent opioid use. Other factors which were associated with persistent opioid use included increasing age (OR = 1.074; 95% CI = 1.004&#8211;1.148; p = 0.037), female gender (OR = 1.743; 95% CI = 1.229&#8211;2.471; p = 0.002), anesthesia duration (OR = 1.086; 95% CI =1.021&#8211;1.154; p = 0.008), and additional surgery within the six month period (OR = 2.293; 95% CI = 1.588&#8211;3.310; p &lt; 0.001).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JPR-16-3759-g0003.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002-s3002"><title>Adjuvant Chemotherapy and the Development of Persistent Opioid Use</title><p>Six months after surgery, a higher rate of persistent opioid use was observed in patients who had received adjuvant chemotherapy within the six-month period (20.9% versus 4.7%, p &lt; 0.001). In the multivariable analysis (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>), the receipt of adjuvant chemotherapy was associated with a more than five-fold increase in the odds of developing persistent opioid use (OR = 5.276; 95% CI = 3.663&#8211;7.600; p &lt; 0.001).</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002-s3003"><title>Effect of Regional Anesthesia on the Development of Persistent Opioid Use</title><p>The group of patients who received regional analgesia had higher rates of persistent opioid use than those who did not (8.2% versus 5.7%, p = 0.004). Furthermore, the group of patients who received epidural analgesia had higher rates of persistent opioid use than those who did not (11.1% versus 5.7%, p &lt; 0.001).</p><p>With the adjustment of age, BMI, gender, anxiety/depression, alcohol abuse, regional anesthesia with epidural, anesthesia duration, total PACU opioid dose, highest PACU pain, any repeat surgery within the six months, and adjuvant chemotherapy within the 6 months (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>), the use of epidural analgesia was associated with a 58.1% increase in the odds of developing persistent opioid use (OR = 1.581; 95% CI = 1.035&#8211;2.416; p = 0.034).</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002-s3004"><title>Effects of Other Potentially Confounding Factors</title><p>In the unadjusted analysis (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), the rates of persistent opioid use were higher in females (8.1% versus 6.3% in males, p = 0.039), patients with anxiety/depression (9.3% versus 6.6%, p = 0.015), alcohol abuse (17.0% versus 6.9%, p = 0.005), and in those with higher BMI (median [IQR], 29 [25&#8211;34] versus median 32 [24&#8211;32]; p = 0.027).</p><p>In addition, the incidence of persistent opioid use varied significantly across surgery types (p &lt; 0.001) and cancer stage (p = 0.004) with higher rates observed among patients who underwent colorectal surgery, and in those with stage 3 cancer. Furthermore, higher rates of persistent opioid use were observed among patients with longer anesthesia duration (median [IQR] 7 hr [5&#8211;9] versus 6 hr [4&#8211;8]; p = 0.007), and in those who received more opioids intraoperatively (median [IQR] 34 MEDD [20&#8211;46] versus 30 MEDD [20&#8211;46]; p = 0.016).</p><p>In the immediate postoperative period, the group of patients with persistent opioid use had higher average PACU pain scores (median [IQR] 2.7 [1.4&#8211;4.2] versus median, 2.5 [IQR, 1.3&#8211;3.7]; p = 0.033).</p><p>Six months after surgery, higher rates of persistent opioid use were observed in patients who required additional surgery within the six-month period (14.8% versus 5.1%, p &lt; 0.001).</p><p>In the adjusted model (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>), increasing age (OR = 1.074; 95% CI = 1.004&#8211;1.148; p = 0.037), female gender (OR = 1.743; 95% CI = 1.229&#8211;2.471; p = 0.002), anesthesia duration (OR = 1.086; 95% CI =1.021&#8211;1.154; p = 0.008), and additional surgery within the 6-month period (OR = 2.293; 95% CI = 1.588&#8211;3.310; p &lt; 0.001) were each associated with increased odds of developing persistent opioid use.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003-s2003"><title>Chronic Opioid Use</title><sec id="s0003-s2003-s3001"><title>Race/Ethnicity and Chronic Opioid Use</title><p>In the univariable analysis (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), the rates of chronic opioid use were similar across racial/ethnic groups (p = 0.131). <xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref> shows results of the multivariable logistic regression model that was fitted to estimate the effects of important covariates on chronic opioid use. The race/ethnicity variable was forced into the model since it was of interest. With the adjustment of BMI, gender, regional anesthesia with epidural, anesthesia duration, repeat surgery within the 12-month period, adjuvant chemotherapy within the 12-month period, the association between race/ethnicity and chronic opioid use was not significant (p = 0.443).
<fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Independent predictors of chronic opioid use after open abdominal surgery. The association between race/ethnicity and chronic opioid use was not significant (p-value=0.443). Of the secondary exposure variables, epidural anesthesia (OR = 1.642; 95% CI = 1.047&#8211;2.576; p = 0.031) and adjuvant chemotherapy within the twelve month period (OR = 6.207; 95% CI = 3.985&#8211;9.666; p &lt; 0.001) were associated with chronic opioid use. Other factors significantly associated with chronic opioid use included female gender (OR = 1.581; 95% CI = 1.031&#8211;2.424; p = 0.037) and additional surgery within the twelve-month period (OR = 2.944; 95% CI = 1.901&#8211;4.560; p &lt; 0.001).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JPR-16-3759-g0004.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2003-s3002"><title>Effect of Adjuvant Chemotherapy on the Occurrence of Chronic Opioid Use</title><p>Patients who required adjuvant chemotherapy had higher rates of persistent opioid use than those who did not (8.6% versus 1.3%, p &lt; 0.001). In the adjusted model (<xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>), adjuvant chemotherapy within the 12-month period was associated with more than a six-fold increase in the odds of developing chronic opioid use (OR = 6.207; 95% CI = 3.985&#8211;9.666; p &lt; 0.001).</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2003-s3003"><title>Epidural Analgesia and Chronic Opioid Use</title><p>The group of patients who received epidural analgesia had higher rates of chronic opioid use than those who did not (4.1% versus 2.1%, p = 0.002). In the adjusted model (<xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>), the receipt of epidural analgesia was associated with a 64.2% increase in the odds of developing chronic opioid use (OR = 1.642; 95% CI = 1.047&#8211;2.576; p = 0.031).</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2003-s3004"><title>Effects of Other Potentially Confounding Factors</title><p>In the univariable analysis, the rate of chronic opioid was higher in females (3.2% versus 2.1% in males, p = 0.047) and varied significantly across surgery types (p = 0.022). Among surgery types, the highest rate was observed in patients who had undergone colorectal surgery (4.1%). In addition, rates of chronic opioid use were higher in patients who required additional surgery within the 12-month period (5.8% versus 1.4%, p &lt; 0.001).</p><p>In the multivariable analysis (<xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>), female gender (OR = 1.581; 95% CI = 1.031&#8211;2.424; p = 0.037) and additional surgery within the twelve-month period (OR = 2.944; 95% CI = 1.901&#8211;4.560; p &lt; 0.001) were each associated with chronic opioid use.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this retrospective study of adults who had undergone open abdominal surgery for cancer, Hispanic/Latino patients had significantly higher odds of sustained early postoperative opioid use than NH-White patients. However, this association was not present 6 or 12 months after surgery.</p><sec id="s0004-s2001"><title>Race/Ethnicity and Sustained Early Opioid Use</title><p>An explanation for the association between race/ethnicity and sustained early postoperative opioid use is not easily discernible from our data. Unfortunately, a lack of comparable studies further limits our ability to derive potential explanations. However, albeit in a study describing persistent opioid use, ours is not the first study to report a higher risk of continuous opioid use in Hispanic patients who had undergone open abdominal surgery. In a multicenter study of 1646 patients who had undergone colorectal surgery at affiliated medical centers in Massachusetts, compared to White patients, Hispanic patients had more than twice the risk of receiving a new opioid prescription between 90 and 180 days after discharge.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> A potential explanation for this significant finding was not provided by the authors. However, as suggested by previous research, it is possible that factors such as opioid prescribing patterns of primary care clinicians may have influenced our findings.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></p><p>In addition, some experimental studies suggest Hispanics/Latinos and NH-Blacks may have a lower threshold and lower tolerance for pain than NH-Whites.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34&#8211;36</xref> The underlying mechanisms for this may include a combination of cultural factors and polymorphisms of the CYP2D6 enzyme and mu-opioid receptor genes.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> The extent to which these findings translate into an increased risk of sustained opioid use is less clear, especially since opioid use may be influenced by factors such as the aforementioned prescribing patterns, socio-cultural factors, and the type of health insurance.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></p><p>Other large-scale studies involving primarily non-surgical cancer patients have reported differing associations between race/ethnicity and persistent opioid use. For example, in a large retrospective study of 106,732 veteran cancer survivors, White race was independently associated with increased odds of having filled 120 days&#8217; or greater supply or 10 or more opioid prescriptions from 1 to 2 years after the start of curative treatment.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> However, using the same definition of persistent opioid use, another large observational study of 33,872 older (&gt;65 years) cancer patients who were undergoing definitive treatment did not find an association between race/ethnicity and persistent opioid use.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> These differences in findings may suggest that associations between race/ethnicity and persistent or chronic opioid use may, at best, be useful in informing local or regional practice patterns and must be used with caution when applied more broadly.</p><p>With regard to our study, the inconsistent nature of our results and the literature showing that Hispanic Americans are less likely to consult a physician for acute or chronic pain makes it plausible that our association between race/ethnicity and sustained early postoperative opioid use may have been a spurious finding.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0004-s2002"><title>Importance of Adjuvant Chemotherapy</title><p>Similar to the findings of previous studies, adjuvant chemotherapy was consistently associated with the development of sustained opioid use in our study population. In another retrospective study of 68,463 patients who underwent curative-intent cancer surgery, patients who received adjuvant chemotherapy had a significantly higher risk of new persistent opioid use across all procedures.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> This observation raises the question as to whether the timing of adjuvant therapies should be considered in the definitions of persistent opioid use after cancer surgery. The most common definition of persistent opioid use relies on the observation that acute post-surgical pain usually resolves within 3 months.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> However, the duration of recovery from acute surgical pain varies for different procedures and may be difficult to define in patients who receive adjuvant chemotherapy, which may result in neuropathic injury in addition to the mechanical injury associated with surgery.</p><p>It has been shown that chemotherapy-induced peripheral neuropathy occurs in approximately 20% of patients who receive standard doses of chemotherapy and in almost 100% of patients treated with high doses.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> This may perhaps explain why the need for adjuvant chemotherapy was consistently associated with sustained opioid use in our study population.</p></sec><sec id="s0004-s2003"><title>Effect of Surgery Type on the Occurrence of Sustained Early Opioid Use</title><p>As would be expected, undergoing additional surgery was associated with an increased risk for early sustained, persistent, and chronic opioid use. Notably, among the surgical procedures included in our study, patients who had undergone colorectal and gastrointestinal procedures had significantly higher odds of sustained early postoperative opioid use compared to those who had surgery for peritoneal surface malignancy. A similar observation was made by Bicket and colleagues, where compared to patients who had undergone urologic procedures, patients who had undergone colorectal surgery had significantly higher odds of persistent opioid use.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> It is possible that the requirement for ostomies and their reversal may have influenced this finding.</p></sec><sec id="s0004-s2004"><title>Epidural Analgesia and Sustained Opioid Use</title><p>Compared to systemic opioids, the use of epidural analgesia has been associated with superior acute pain control after a various surgical procedures.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> However, contrary to what might have been expected, the use of epidural analgesia in our patient population was consistently associated with an increased risk for developing sustained opioid use. The currently available literature does not provide clear evidence that perioperative epidural analgesia reduces the risk for chronic post-surgical pain.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> Several studies have suggested no clear advantage of epidural analgesia over intravenous opioid analgesia in the prevention of chronic post-surgical pain after major abdominal and thoracic surgery procedures,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21&#8211;23</xref> while others have reported it to be inferior.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></p><p>With regard to our study, we speculate that our findings may be confounded by the fact that epidural analgesia is more frequently used for very extensive procedures such as pelvic exenterations, abdominoperineal resections, and cytoreductive surgery.</p></sec><sec id="s0004-s2005"><title>Alcohol Abuse, Acute Pain, Age, Gender, and Anesthesia Duration</title><p>Confirming previous literature, alcohol abuse,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> acute pain of severe intensity,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> increasing age,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> and female gender were associated with the development of early sustained, persistent, or chronic opioid use.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Furthermore, longer anesthesia duration was associated with sustained early and persistent opioid use. We speculate that similar to the findings of a large retrospective study of opioid na&#239;ve patients who had undergone surgery, larger opioid prescription size after more extensive procedures may have placed this group of patients at higher risk for persistent opioid use.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0004-s2006"><title>Study Limitations</title><p>This study is not without its limitations. Firstly, the inherent biases and inaccuracies associated with the retrospective nature of our study may have prevented us from accurately identifying our study endpoints. In addition, the inclusion of multiple surgical procedures may have prevented us from identifying the interaction of race/ethnicity with persistent opioid use after individual surgical procedures. Furthermore, the heterogeneity and low sample size of certain sub-groups may have resulted in significant underpowering.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0005"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In this retrospective study of 3523 patients who had undergone open abdominal surgery for cancer, the association between race/ethnicity and opioid use over the first 12 postsurgical months was inconsistent. Further studies are needed to clearly define whether there is any association between a patient&#8217;s race or ethnicity and their risk of developing persistent or chronic opioid use.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0006"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Guidelines for Cancer-Related Pain: a Systematic Review of Complementary and Alternative Medicine Recommendations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pain Pract</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>454</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>467</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/papr.12964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33197300</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Snijders</surname><given-names>RAH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brom</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Theunissen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Update on Prevalence of Pain in Patients with Cancer 2022: a Systematic Literature Review and Meta-Analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancers</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cancers15030591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9913127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36765547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dalal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bruera</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pain Management for Patients With Advanced Cancer in the Opioid Epidemic Era</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am Soc Clin Oncol Educ Book</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>39</issue>):<fpage>24</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/EDBK_100020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31099619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kaasa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The IASP classification of chronic pain for ICD-11: chronic cancer-related pain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pain</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>160</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>38</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/j.pain.0000000000001363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30586069</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Imam</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>UK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Opioids in Cancer Pain: right or Privilege?</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">J Oncol Pract</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e809</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>e814</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JOP.2016.019216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28557661</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wiffen</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wee</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Derry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Opioids for cancer pain - an overview of Cochrane reviews</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cochrane Database Syst Rev</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>Cd012592</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD012592.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28683172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6483487</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Paice</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Von Roenn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Under- or overtreatment of pain in the patient with cancer: how to achieve proper balance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>1721</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1726</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2013.52.5196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24799468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lillemoe</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Newhook</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vreeland</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Educating Surgical Oncology Providers on Perioperative Opioid Use: results of a Departmental Survey on Perceptions of Opioid Needs and Prescribing Habits</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Surg Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2011</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2018</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1245/s10434-019-07321-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30937660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6907739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Newhook</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vreeland</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dewhurst</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Opioid-prescribing Practices After Oncologic Surgery: opportunities for Improvement and a Call to Action</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Surg</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>271</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e9</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>e10</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SLA.0000000000003595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31478982</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dabas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Outcomes and Healthcare Utilization Among New Persistent Opioid Users and Non-opioid Users After Curative-intent Surgery for Cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Surg</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>277</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e752</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>e758</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SLA.0000000000005109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34334636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Giladi</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shipp</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sanghavi</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Patient-Reported Data Augment Health Record Data for Prediction Models of Persistent Opioid Use after Elective Upper Extremity Surgery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Plast Reconstr Surg</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>152</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>358e</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>366e</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PRS.0000000000010297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11835507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36780362</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Swenson</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kamdar</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seiler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Definition development and prevalence of new persistent opioid use following hysterectomy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Obstet Gynecol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>219</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>486.e1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>486.e7</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajog.2018.06.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6392025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29928864</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brescia</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Waljee</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of Prescribing on New Persistent Opioid Use After Cardiothoracic Surgery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Thorac Surg</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>108</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1107</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1113</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.athoracsur.2019.06.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31447051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6755048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lilly</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Racial Differences in Perioperative Opioid Utilization in Lumbar Decompression and Fusion Surgery for Symptomatic Lumbar Stenosis or Spondylolisthesis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Global Spine J</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>160</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>168</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2192568219850092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32206515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7076601</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Opioid metabolism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mayo Clin Proc</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>613</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>624</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0025-6196(11)60750-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19567715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2704133</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hastie</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>JL</given-names> 3rd</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Ethnicity interacts with the OPRM1 gene in experimental pain sensitivity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pain</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>153</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1610</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1619</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pain.2012.03.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22717102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3683662</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Edelman</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>New Persistent Opioid Use Among Patients With Cancer After Curative-Intent Surgery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<fpage>JCO2017741363</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JCO.2017.74.1363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5736238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29048972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bicket</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Murimi</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of new opioid continuation with surgical specialty and type in the United States</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Surg</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>218</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>818</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>827</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjsurg.2019.04.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31023548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dev</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Palla</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Undocumented alcoholism and its correlation with tobacco and illegal drug use in advanced cancer patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>117</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>4551</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4556</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cncr.26082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21446042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3128208</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lavand&#8217;homme</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>De Kock</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Waterloos</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Intraoperative epidural analgesia combined with ketamine provides effective preventive analgesia in patients undergoing major digestive surgery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Anesthesiology</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>103</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>813</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>820</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000542-200510000-00020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16192774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fassoulaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chassiakos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Melemeni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Intermittent epidural vs continuous wound infusion of ropivacaine for acute and chronic pain control after hysterectomy or myomectomy: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pain Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1603</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1608</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pme.12523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25092211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Can chronic poststernotomy pain after cardiac valve replacement be reduced using thoracic epidural analgesia?</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Anaesthesiol Scand</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>871</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>874</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0001-5172.2004.00437.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15242432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Royse</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Royse</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Persistent pain after cardiac surgery: an audit of high thoracic epidural and primary opioid analgesia therapies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Anesth Analg</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>95</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>820</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>823</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1213/00000539-200210000-00006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12351251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>von Elm</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) statement: guidelines for reporting observational studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epidemiology</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>800</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>804</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/EDE.0b013e3181577654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18049194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Owusu-Agyemang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Porche</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Race, ethnicity, and the use of regional anesthesia in cancer patients undergoing open abdominal surgery: a single-center retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>950444</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2022.950444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9433667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36059836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brummett</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Waljee</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goesling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>New Persistent Opioid Use After Minor and Major Surgical Procedures in US Adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Surg</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>152</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e170504</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2017.0504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28403427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7050825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Delaney</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Waljee</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>New persistent opioid use: definitions and opportunities</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Reg Anesth Pain Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>98</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/rapm-2020-102121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33172903</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jamali</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Chronic opioid use after joint replacement surgery in seniors is associated with increased healthcare utilization and costs: a historical cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Can J Anaesth</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>963</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>973</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12630-022-02240-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35314993</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Darnall</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Incidence of and Risk Factors for Chronic Opioid Use Among Opioid-Naive Patients in the Postoperative Period</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>176</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1286</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1293</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2016.3298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27400458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6684468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dowell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ragan</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>CDC Clinical Practice Guideline for Prescribing Opioids for Pain - United States, 2022</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">MMWR Recomm Rep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.rr7103a1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9639433</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36327391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cavallaro</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bleday</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A multi-center analysis of cumulative inpatient opioid use in colorectal surgery patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Surg</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>220</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1160</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1166</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjsurg.2020.06.038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32684292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Delaney</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gunaseelan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rieck</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>High-Risk Prescribing Increases Rates of New Persistent Opioid Use in Total Hip Arthroplasty Patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Arthroplasty</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2472</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2479.e2</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2020.04.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32389404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8289485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ethnic differences in pain and pain management</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pain Manag</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>219</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>230</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/pmt.12.7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23687518</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3654683</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rahim-Williams</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>JL</given-names> 3rd</string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Herrera</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Ethnic identity predicts experimental pain sensitivity in African Americans and Hispanics</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pain</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>129</volume>(<issue>1&#8211;2</issue>):<fpage>177</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>184</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pain.2006.12.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17296267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1925263</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lawlis</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Achterberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kenner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Ethnic and sex differences in response to clinical and induced pain in chronic spinal pain patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Spine</italic></source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>751</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>754</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007632-198410000-00017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6505845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0036"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rahim-Williams</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A quantitative review of ethnic group differences in experimental pain response: do biology, psychology, and culture matter?</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Pain Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>522</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>540</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1526-4637.2012.01336.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22390201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3349436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0037"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Orton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Chronic Opioid Usage in Surgical Patients in a Large Academic Center</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Surg</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>265</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>722</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>727</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SLA.0000000000001780</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27163960</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5557500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0038"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Breuler</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shabet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Delaney</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prescribed Opioid Dosages, Payer Type, and Self-Reported Outcomes After Surgical Procedures in Michigan, 2018-2020</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Netw Open</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>e2322581</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.22581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37428502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10334228</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0039"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vitzthum</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Riviere</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sheridan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Predicting Persistent Opioid Use, Abuse, and Toxicity Among Cancer Survivors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Natl Cancer Inst</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>112</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>720</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>727</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/djz200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31754696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7357328</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0040"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vitzthum</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nalawade</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Riviere</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Racial, Ethnic, and Socioeconomic Discrepancies in Opioid Prescriptions Among Older Patients With Cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JCO Oncol Pract</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e703</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>e713</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/OP.20.00773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33534647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8258011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0041"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haywood</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>deGuzman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Differential perceptions, behaviors, and motivations among African Americans, Latinos, and whites suspected of heart attacks in two hospital populations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Assoc Acad Minor Phys</italic></source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>60</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>69</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7772934</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0042"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Portenoy</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ugarte</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Population-based survey of pain in the United States: differences among white, African American, and Hispanic subjects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pain</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>317</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>328</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpain.2004.05.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15336636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0043"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schug</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lavand&#8217;homme</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The IASP classification of chronic pain for ICD-11: chronic postsurgical or posttraumatic pain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pain</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>160</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>45</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/j.pain.0000000000001413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30586070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0044"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chemotherapy induced peripheral neuropathic pain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Korean J Anesthesiol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>4</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4097/kjae.2014.67.1.4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25097731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4121493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0045"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effect of postoperative analgesia on major postoperative complications: a systematic update of the evidence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Anesth Analg</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>689</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>702</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1213/01.ane.0000255040.71600.41</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17312231</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0046"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sinatra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Causes and consequences of inadequate management of acute pain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pain Med</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1859</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1871</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1526-4637.2010.00983.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21040438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0047"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Postoperative Opioid Prescribing and New Persistent Opioid Use: the Risk of Excessive Prescribing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Surg</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/SLA.0000000000005392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10537242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35129474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>