<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3211</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jamasd</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JAMA Network Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2574-3805</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>JAMA Network</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10498328</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10498328.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10498328</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10498328</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37698860</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.33251</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zoi230963</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Investigation</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="online-only"><subject>Online Only</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="subject-area"><subject>Equity, Diversity, and Inclusion</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Racial and Ethnic Differences in Receipt of Nonpharmacologic Care for Chronic Low Back Pain Among Medicare Beneficiaries With OUD</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="headline">Race and Ethnicity and Nonpharmacologic Care for Chronic Low Back Pain</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Race and Ethnicity and Nonpharmacologic Care for Chronic Low Back Pain</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhondoekhan</surname><given-names initials="F">Fiona</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees><xref rid="zoi230963aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names initials="BDL">Brandon D. L.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="zoi230963aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shireman</surname><given-names initials="TI">Theresa I.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="zoi230963aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trivedi</surname><given-names initials="AN">Amal N.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="zoi230963aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Merlin</surname><given-names initials="JS">Jessica S.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>PhD</degrees><degrees>MBA</degrees><xref rid="zoi230963aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moyo</surname><given-names initials="P">Patience</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="zoi230963aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="zoi230963aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Epidemiology, Brown University School of Public Health, Providence, Rhode Island</aff><aff id="zoi230963aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Health Services, Policy, and Practice, Brown University School of Public Health, Providence, Rhode Island</aff><aff id="zoi230963aff3"><label>3</label>CHAllenges in Managing and Preventing Pain Clinical Research Center, Division of General Internal Medicine, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania</aff><author-notes><title>Article Information</title><p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> August 3, 2023.</p><p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published:</bold> September 12, 2023. doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.33251</uri></p><p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-license-permissions" ext-link-type="uri">CC-BY License</ext-link>. &#169; 2023 Bhondoekhan F et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic>.</p><corresp id="zoi230963cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Patience Moyo, PhD, Department of Health Services, Policy, and Practice, Brown University School of Public Health, 121 S Main St, Providence, RI 02912 (<email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="patience_moyo@brown.edu">patience_moyo@brown.edu</email>).</corresp><p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Ms Bhondoekhan and Dr Moyo had full access to all of the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Concept and design:</italic> Bhondoekhan, Marshall, Shireman, Merlin, Moyo.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> Bhondoekhan, Marshall, Shireman, Trivedi, Moyo.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Bhondoekhan, Shireman, Moyo.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> All authors.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Statistical analysis:</italic> Bhondoekhan.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Obtained funding:</italic> Moyo.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Moyo.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Supervision:</italic> Marshall, Merlin, Moyo.</p><p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr Marshall reported receiving grants from the National Institutes of Health (NIH) during the conduct of the study and receiving grants from the NIH, Open Society Foundation, and Arnold Ventures outside the submitted work. Dr Shireman reported receiving grants from the National Institute of General Medical Sciences (NIGMS) during the conduct of the study. Dr Merlin reported receiving grants from Cambia Health Care outside the submitted work. Dr Moyo reported receiving grants from the NIH during the conduct of the study, serving as a technical expert panel member for Abt Associates, and being a member of a National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine ad hoc committee on evaluating the effects of opioids and benzodiazepines on all-cause mortality in veterans. No other disclosures were reported.</p><p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> This study was funded by grant P20GM130414 by the COBRE on Addiction and Disease Risk Exacerbation from the NIGMS.</p><p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The NIGMS had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p><p content-type="data-sharing-statement"><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> See <xref rid="note-ZOI230963-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>.</p><p><bold>Additional Contributions:</bold> Stavroula Chrysanthopoulou, PhD (Brown University), Miriam George, MPH (Brown University), Richa Gairola, BDS, MPH (Brown University), and Yoojin Lee, MS (Brown University), provided technical support in the preparation of the analytical data set and manuscript revision and did not receive compensation.</p></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-09-12T10:00"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>9</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>9</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">445244</issue-id><elocation-id>e2333251</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>12</day><month>09</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>09</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-09-14 13:25:09.830"><day>14</day><month>09</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright 2023 Bhondoekhan F et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic>.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2333251.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2333251.pdf">jamanetwopen-e2333251.pdf</self-uri><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.33251"/><abstract abstract-type="teaser" specific-use="electronic"><p>This cohort study assesses receipt of physical therapy and chiropractic care for chronic low back pain among Medicare beneficiaries with opioid use disorder (OUD) from different racial and ethnic groups.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="key-points"><title>Key Points</title><sec id="ab-zoi230963-1"><title>Question</title><p>Are there racial and ethnic differences in receipt of physical therapy (PT) or chiropractic care for chronic low back pain (CLBP) among people with opioid use disorder (OUD)?</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230963-2"><title>Findings</title><p>In this cohort study of 69&#8201;362 Medicare beneficiaries with CLBP and OUD, 10.2% received PT or chiropractic services within 3 months. Black or African American and Hispanic persons had lower odds of chiropractic care compared with non-Hispanic White persons.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230963-3"><title>Meaning</title><p>In this study, PT and chiropractic care use was low overall and racial and ethnic inequities in utilization and time to chiropractic care were observed, underscoring the need for equitable and multimodal pain management among people with OUD.</p></sec></abstract><abstract><sec id="ab-zoi230963-4"><title>Importance</title><p>Nonpharmacologic treatments are important for managing chronic pain among persons with opioid use disorder (OUD), for whom opioid and other pharmacologic therapies may be particularly harmful. Racial and ethnic minority individuals with chronic pain and OUD are vulnerable to suboptimal pain management due to systemic inequities and structural racism, highlighting the need to understand their receipt of guideline-recommended nonpharmacologic pain therapies, including physical therapy (PT) and chiropractic care.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230963-5"><title>Objective</title><p>To assess differences across racial and ethnic groups in receipt of PT or chiropractic care for chronic low back pain (CLBP) among persons with comorbid OUD.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230963-6"><title>Design, Setting, and Participants</title><p>This retrospective cohort study used a 20% random sample of national Medicare administrative data from January 1, 2016, to December 31, 2018, to identify fee-for-service community-dwelling beneficiaries with a new episode of CLBP and comorbid OUD. Data were analyzed from March 1, 2022, to July 30, 2023.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230963-7"><title>Exposures</title><p>Race and ethnicity as a social construct, categorized as American Indian or Alaska Native, Asian or Pacific Islander, Black or African American, Hispanic, non-Hispanic White, and unknown or other.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230963-8"><title>Main Outcomes and Measures</title><p>The main outcomes were receipt of PT or chiropractic care within 3 months of CLBP diagnosis. The time (in days) to receiving these treatments was also assessed.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230963-9"><title>Results</title><p>Among 69&#8201;362 Medicare beneficiaries analyzed, the median age was 60.0 years (IQR, 51.5-68.7 years) and 42&#8201;042 (60.6%) were female. A total of 745 beneficiaries (1.1%) were American Indian or Alaska Native; 444 (0.6%), Asian or Pacific Islander; 9822 (14.2%), Black or African American; 4124 (5.9%), Hispanic; 53&#8201;377 (77.0%); non-Hispanic White; and 850 (1.2%), other or unknown race. Of all beneficiaries, 7104 (10.2%) received any PT or chiropractic care 3 months after a new CLBP episode. After adjustment, Black or African American (adjusted odds ratio, 0.46; 95% CI, 0.39-0.55) and Hispanic (adjusted odds ratio, 0.54; 95% CI, 0.43-0.67) persons had lower odds of receiving chiropractic care within 3 months of CLBP diagnosis compared with non-Hispanic White persons. Median time to chiropractic care was longest for American Indian or Alaska Native (median, 8.5 days [IQR, 0-44.0 days]) and Black or African American (median, 7.0 days [IQR, 0-42.0 days]) persons and shortest for Asian or Pacific Islander persons (median, 0 days [IQR, 0-6.0 days]). No significant racial and ethnic differences were observed for PT.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230963-10"><title>Conclusions and Relevance</title><p>In this retrospective cohort study of Medicare beneficiaries with comorbid CLBP and OUD, receipt of PT and chiropractic care was low overall and lower across most racial and ethnic minority groups compared with non-Hispanic White persons. The findings underscore the need to address inequities in guideline-concordant pain management, particularly among Black or African American and Hispanic persons with OUD.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="H1-1-ZOI230963"><title>Introduction</title><p>Chronic pain and opioid use disorder (OUD) are closely linked: persons with chronic pain are at increased risk of OUD, and the prevalence of chronic pain among persons with OUD (64%) is higher than that in the general population (21%).<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> It is critical to use chronic pain treatment strategies that are able to reduce not only the impact and duration of pain but also the mortality and morbidity from OUD.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Several clinical practice guidelines have recommended a multimodal approach that prioritizes noninvasive, nonpharmacologic treatments for pain, such as physical therapy (PT) and chiropractic care.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup></p><p>Managing chronic pain among persons with OUD, however, is complex as clinicians need to carefully consider guideline-recommended care for both conditions.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> Moreover, persons with chronic pain and OUD often have other undertreated comorbid substance use disorders, making them a population particularly susceptible to systemic and structural inequities.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> As such, negative perceptions of treating persons with overlapping chronic pain and OUD could potentially contribute to racial disparities in the delivery of guideline-concordant pain care.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> The racial and ethnic differences in pain care for persons with chronic pain and OUD are particularly important to investigate, as inequalities in health care access and quality of care can be compounded for racial and ethnic minority groups, contributing to lower receipt of guideline-concordant pain management than their non-Hispanic White counterparts. While the racial and ethnic gap in pain care has been well documented for pharmacologic therapies, few studies have examined whether racial and ethnic disparities exist in receipt of PT and chiropractic care for chronic pain,<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> and, to our knowledge, this question has not been assessed among persons with OUD.</p><p>The objective of this study was to investigate differences in use of PT and chiropractic care among persons diagnosed with chronic pain and OUD across racial and ethnic groups. We analyzed a cohort of Medicare beneficiaries, a population with high reported prevalence of chronic pain among whom rates of OUD are increasing<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> and who had access to Medicare-covered nonpharmacologic treatments, such as PT and chiropractic care. We hypothesized that following a new diagnosis of chronic pain, racial and ethnic minority groups would have lower receipt of PT and chiropractic care compared with non-Hispanic White individuals and that among persons who receive these treatments, racial and ethnic minority groups would have a longer time to receipt of treatment.</p></sec><sec id="H1-2-ZOI230963"><title>Methods</title><p>The Brown University institutional review board determined the study to be exempt from review based on secondary analysis of deidentified data, and informed consent was not required. This study followed the Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/strobe/" ext-link-type="uri">STROBE</ext-link>) reporting guideline.</p><sec id="H2-1-ZOI230963"><title>Study Data and Population</title><p>We conducted a retrospective cohort study using a 20% random sample of national Medicare administrative data from January 1, 2016, to December 31, 2018, linked to publicly available data on community and practitioner characteristics. Diagnoses and dates of service utilization came from MedPAR Part A and Part B claims, excluding long-term and post&#8211;acute care settings. Prescribed medications were obtained from Medicare Part D claims, and the Medicare enrollment file contained information on demographics, enrollment year, and geographic location.</p><p>The study population included Medicare fee-for-service beneficiaries with 2 or more diagnoses for chronic low back pain (CLBP) separated by at least 90 days<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> from July 1, 2016, to June 30, 2018, with the first claim assigned as the index date.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> We focused on CLBP as it is one of the most prevalent pain conditions in the US.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> We identified CLBP using <italic toggle="yes">International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems, Tenth Revision (ICD-10)</italic> codes for radicular and nonradicular back pain in any position on MedPAR Part A and Part B claims (eTable 1 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230963-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> A 6-month look-back period was applied to ensure no CLBP claims occurred prior to the index date; as such, the diagnosis on the index date was considered a new episode of CLBP. When beneficiaries had multiple eligible CLBP episodes during the study period, we randomly selected 1 episode for inclusion in the analysis. We assumed OUD to be present if participants had 1 or more MedPAR Part A or Part B claim for &#8220;opioid abuse&#8221; or &#8220;opioid dependence&#8221; at any time from January 1, 2016, to December 31, 2018, to account for potential underdiagnosis of OUD within claims data. Beneficiaries with any of the following criteria were excluded: not continuously enrolled in Medicare for 12 months; enrolled in Medicare Advantage (due to incomplete claims); in hospice or long-term care facility; 2 or more claims for a cancer diagnosis (treatment for cancer-related chronic pain is distinct from that for noncancer chronic pain and was not the focus of this study)<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>; younger than 18 years; no OUD claims during study period; residing outside the 50 states and Washington, DC, including Puerto Rico, US Virgin Islands, American Samoa, Marianas Islands, and Guam; or missing Federal Information Processing System Codes for States and Counties.</p></sec><sec id="H2-2-ZOI230963"><title>Outcome</title><p>The main outcomes of interest were 2 binary variables representing receipt of active PT or chiropractic care 3 months after the CLBP diagnosis. A third outcome representing receipt of either of these services was also created. Physical therapy and chiropractic care were 2 evidence-based nonpharmacologic pain therapies covered by Medicare during the study period and were identified using <italic toggle="yes">Current Procedural Terminology</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">CPT</italic>) codes from Part B claims (eTable 2 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230963-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). For PT, only <italic toggle="yes">CPT</italic> codes identifying treatment modalities and therapeutic procedures were included, while <italic toggle="yes">CPT</italic> codes for evaluations were excluded from the main analysis as they were deemed not to represent receipt of an active intervention. Claims with both evaluations and treatment modalities or therapeutic procedures billed on the same day were considered to indicate receipt of active PT. The <italic toggle="yes">CPT</italic> codes for PT and/or chiropractic care occurring on the day of CLBP diagnosis were included, as beneficiaries often receive therapeutic or chiropractic services at the time of CLBP diagnosis in outpatient settings. The time to receipt of PT and chiropractic care within the 3-month follow-up period was calculated in days from CLBP diagnosis.</p></sec><sec id="H2-3-ZOI230963"><title>Primary Independent Variable</title><p>The primary independent variable was beneficiary race and ethnicity, which we considered as a social rather than a biologic or genetic construct.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> We used the Research Triangle Institute (RTI) race and ethnicity variable in Medicare enrollment files, which relies on administrative data from the Social Security Administration and an algorithm to impute race and ethnicity from name and geographic location. The validity of the race and ethnicity variables in Medicare data compared with the gold standard of self-report has been evaluated, and findings indicate that the RTI race code is more accurate for Asian or Pacific Islander and Hispanic persons than the Medicare enrollment file beneficiary race code.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> The RTI variable reports race and ethnicity in 7 mutually exclusive groups as American Indian or Alaska Native, Asian or Pacific Islander, Black or African American, Hispanic, non-Hispanic White, other, and unknown. The other category refers to non-Hispanic other race, and a designation of unknown occurs when there are missing data.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> Due to small numbers in the unknown group, we combined it with the group labeled as other, therefore creating a 6-level categorical variable identifying beneficiary race and ethnicity.</p></sec><sec id="H2-4-ZOI230963"><title>Covariates</title><p>Beneficiary characteristics, such as age, sex (as recorded in the enrollment file), current reason for Medicare eligibility, dual eligibility, state and county of residence, and receipt of medication for OUD were measured in the year of CLBP diagnosis from the annual Medicare enrollment file. Comorbidities included cardiovascular conditions, mental health diagnosis, neck pain and fractures, osteoarthritis and joint cartilage conditions, diabetes, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, obesity, alcohol use disorder, hospitalization, surgery, and the Gagne comorbidity score. All were measured 6 months prior to the CLBP diagnosis date using <italic toggle="yes">ICD-10</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">CPT</italic> codes from MedPAR Part A and Part B claims (eTable 3 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230963-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> Opioid prescriptions, excluding medications for OUD, in the 6 months prior to the CLBP diagnosis date were obtained from Part D claims (eTable 4 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230963-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).</p><p>We used the American Community Survey<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> to create variables for social determinants of health at the county level and the Area Health Resources File<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> to determine geographic information and practitioner availability at the state level (eTable 5 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230963-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). Social determinants of health were based on 7 demographic characteristics in the Social Deprivation Index to identify areas at the county level in need for health care resources.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> These variables were calculated using 5-year county-level American Community Survey estimates from 2014 to 2018.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> State-level practitioner availability included the number of physical therapists (including assistants and aides) and number of chiropractors per 100&#8201;000 population in the year of CLBP diagnosis and came from the Area Health Resources File. We linked National Plan and Provider Enumeration System<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> data to the billing health care practitioner in the Part B claims using a National Provider Identifier to identify practitioner specialty. Lastly, US region and rural-urban commuting area codes were obtained from the Area Health Resources File at the county level.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> No missing data were observed for individual-level (demographic, comorbidities, and medication), county-level (social determinants of health), or state-level (practitioner availability, practitioner specialty) data.</p></sec><sec id="H2-5-ZOI230963"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Characteristics of the study population were compared by race and ethnicity using the Kruskal-Wallis test for continuous variables and Pearson &#967;<sup>2</sup> test for binary and categorical variables. We calculated the proportions of beneficiaries within each race and ethnicity group who received (1) any PT or chiropractic care, (2) any PT, and (3) any chiropractic care within 3 months of CLBP diagnosis and used Kaplan-Meier curves to visualize the time to receipt of these treatments. Differences across race and ethnicity in the Kaplan-Meier curves were evaluated using log-rank tests. Multilevel logistic regression models separately estimated the association between race and ethnicity and the 3 outcomes, adjusting for all covariates listed in <xref rid="zoi230963t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and eTable 6 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230963-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref> in addition to receipt of any PT or chiropractic care prior to CLBP diagnosis and addiction specialist encounters during follow-up. State- and county-level variation were accounted for by inclusion of individual random intercepts for states and counties in each model. The results of the models are presented as adjusted odds ratios (AORs) with accompanying 95% CIs.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi230963t1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1. </label><caption><title>Characteristics of the Study Population by Race and Ethnicity</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="16.11%" span="1"/><col width="13.98%" span="1"/><col width="13.98%" span="1"/><col width="13.98%" span="1"/><col width="13.98%" span="1"/><col width="13.98%" span="1"/><col width="13.99%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th colspan="6" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Beneficiaries, No. (%)</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">American Indian or Alaska Native (n&#8201;=&#8201;745)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian or Pacific Islander (n&#8201;=&#8201;444)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black or African American (n&#8201;=&#8201;9822)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic (n&#8201;=&#8201;4124)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Hispanic White (n&#8201;=&#8201;53&#8201;377)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown or other (n&#8201;=&#8201;850)<xref rid="zoi230963t1n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Median (IQR)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.4 (48.9-66.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.2 (51.6-73.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.5 (49.7-65.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.4 (48.2-66.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.8 (52.2-69.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.7 (46.8-68.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &#8805;65 y</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212 (28.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223 (50.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2588 (26.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1276 (30.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#8201;499 (40.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">391 (46.0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">496 (66.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266 (59.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6220 (63.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2501 (60.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32&#8201;147 (60.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">412 (48.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249 (33.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178 (40.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3602 (36.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1623 (39.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 230 (39.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">438 (51.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbidities<xref rid="zoi230963t1n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cardiovascular condition<xref rid="zoi230963t1n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">440 (59.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">304 (68.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7578 (77.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2629 (63.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33&#8201;125 (62.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">487 (57.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mental health diagnosis<xref rid="zoi230963t1n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">356 (47.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189 (42.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4399 (44.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2205 (53.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27&#8201;756 (52.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">411 (48.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Neck pain</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">255 (34.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">152 (34.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3131 (31.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1434 (34.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8201;492 (34.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">280 (32.9)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fractures</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (7.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (6.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">329 (3.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206 (5.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3184 (6.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (6.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Osteoarthritis and joint cartilage conditions</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">290 (38.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162 (36.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4255 (43.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1458 (35.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8201;782 (35.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">298 (35.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diabetes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253 (34.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">173 (39.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3911 (39.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1623 (39.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13&#8201;750 (25.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232 (27.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175 (23.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (19.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2172 (22.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">739 (17.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13&#8201;509 (25.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147 (17.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Obesity</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150 (20.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (13.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2631 (26.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">946 (22.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9050 (17.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148 (17.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Alcohol use disorder</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (3.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (2.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">440 (4.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">143 (3.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2099 (3.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (6.0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitalization</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133 (17.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (15.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1888 (19.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">744 (18.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8723 (16.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157 (18.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgery<xref rid="zoi230963t1n5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (4.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (4.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">445 (4.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170 (4.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2756 (5.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (4.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gagne comorbidity score</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &#8804;0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">304 (40.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">167 (37.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3814 (38.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1532 (37.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#8201;614 (40.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">357 (42.0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175 (23.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (18.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1995 (20.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">931 (22.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#8201;324 (23.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182 (21.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2-3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165 (22.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113 (25.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2215 (22.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">954 (23.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#8201;066 (22.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180 (21.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &#8805;4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (13.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (18.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1798 (18.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">707 (17.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7373 (13.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131 (15.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medication</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Opioid prescription<xref rid="zoi230963t1n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">685 (92.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">365 (82.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8915 (90.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3592 (87.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46&#8201;805 (87.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">686 (80.7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MOUD<xref rid="zoi230963t1n6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>f</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (5.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (4.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">291 (3.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195 (4.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3250 (6.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (6.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geographic location<xref rid="zoi230963t1n6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>f</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Urbanicity</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Metropolitan</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">403 (54.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">410 (92.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8324 (84.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3628 (88.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38&#8201;519 (72.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">679 (79.9)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Urban</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">303 (40.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (7.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1288 (13.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">470 (11.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#8201;986 (24.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158 (18.6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Rural</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (5.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210 (2.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (0.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1872 (3.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (1.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> US region</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Midwest</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111 (14.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (9.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2049 (20.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">346 (8.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8201;068 (18.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168 (19.8)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Northeast</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (2.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (14.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1145 (11.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">817 (19.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8139 (15.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">218 (25.6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> South</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">401 (53.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131 (29.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5662 (57.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1428 (34.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26&#8201;269 (49.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">277 (32.6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> West</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216 (29.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203 (45.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">966 (9.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1533 (37.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8901 (16.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">187 (22.0)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviations: MOUD, medication for opioid use disorder; NR, not reported (sample size &lt;11).</p><fn id="zoi230963t1n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Other refers to non-Hispanic other races, and any missing values were coded as unknown.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230963t1n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p>Assessed 6 months prior to the date of chronic low back pain diagnosis.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230963t1n3"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p>Defined as a diagnosis of heart failure, ischemic heart disease, or hypertension.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230963t1n4"><label>
<sup>d</sup>
</label><p>Defined as a diagnosis of depressive disorder, anxiety disorder, or schizophrenia or related disorder.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230963t1n5"><label>
<sup>e</sup>
</label><p>Refers to 24 procedures associated with postsurgical pain.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230963t1n6"><label>
<sup>f</sup>
</label><p>Assessed in the year of chronic low back pain diagnosis.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>We conducted 2 sensitivity analyses. First, we modified the PT outcome to include <italic toggle="yes">CPT</italic> codes for PT evaluations in addition to treatment modalities and therapeutic procedures because of the potential for beneficiaries to obtain clinical benefit through their interaction with a practitioner during the evaluation. Second, to examine the influence of prior PT or chiropractic care on cohort selection, we restricted the study cohort to beneficiaries without any PT or chiropractic care in the 6 months before CLBP diagnosis. Persons with prior use might have different experiences and attitudes toward nonpharmacologic care that increase their continued engagement or disengagement in care; these experiences could also differ by race and ethnicity.</p><p>All analyses were conducted in SAS, version 9.4 (SAS Institute Inc) and Stata, version 17.0 (StataCorp LLC), and statistical significance was evaluated at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.05 (2-sided test). Data were analyzed from March 1, 2022, to July 30, 2023.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-3-ZOI230963"><title>Results</title><sec id="H2-6-ZOI230963"><title>Study Population Description</title><p>Among the 69&#8201;362 beneficiaries diagnosed with CLBP and OUD (<xref rid="zoi230963f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>), the median age was 60.0 years (IQR, 51.5-68.7 years), 42&#8201;042 (60.6%) were female, and 27&#8201;320 (39.4%) were male (eTable 7 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230963-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). In terms of race and ethnicity, 745 (1.1%) were American Indian or Alaska Native; 444 (0.6%), Asian or Pacific Islander; 9822 (14.2%), Black or African American; 4124 (5.9%), Hispanic, and 53&#8201;377 (77.0%) non-Hispanic White. For 850 beneficiaries (1.2%), no race and ethnicity was reported in the enrollment file (unknown or other). The characteristics of the study population by race and ethnicity are outlined in <xref rid="zoi230963t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Cardiovascular conditions and mental health diagnoses were common among beneficiaries from all race and ethnicity groups. While opioid prescription for pain was common for all groups, only 3845 of 69&#8201;362 beneficiaries (5.5%) used medication for OUD, with lowest use in Black or African American persons (291 of 9822 [3.0%]). The distribution of county-level social determinants of health, state-level practitioner availability, and specialists engaged during follow-up did not differ markedly by race and ethnicity (eTables 6 and 8 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230963-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="zoi230963f1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1. </label><caption><title>Participant Flowchart</title><p>OUD indicates opioid use disorder.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2333251-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="H2-7-ZOI230963"><title>Nonpharmacologic Treatment Use</title><p>Three months after CLBP diagnosis, the prevalence of PT was low but higher (4358 [6.3%]) compared with chiropractic care (3227 [4.7%]). Use of PT was lowest among American Indian or Alaska Native persons (33 of 745 [4.4%]) and highest among Asian or Pacific Islander persons (47 of 444 [10.6%]) (<xref rid="zoi230963t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Chiropractic care was lowest among Black or African American (170 of 9822 [1.7%]) and Hispanic (98 of 4124 [2.4%]) persons and highest among non-Hispanic White persons (2865 of 53&#8201;377 [5.4%]) and those in the unknown or other group (51 of 850 [6.0%]).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi230963t2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2. </label><caption><title>Treatment Use by Race and Ethnicity</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="18.78%" span="1"/><col width="13.53%" span="1"/><col width="13.54%" span="1"/><col width="13.54%" span="1"/><col width="13.53%" span="1"/><col width="13.54%" span="1"/><col width="13.54%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Treatment</th><th colspan="6" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Beneficiaries</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">American Indian or Alaska Native (n&#8201;=&#8201;745)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian or Pacific Islander (n&#8201;=&#8201;444)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black or African American (n&#8201;=&#8201;9822)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic (n&#8201;=&#8201;4124)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Hispanic White (n&#8201;=&#8201;53&#8201;377)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown or other (n&#8201;=&#8201;850)<xref rid="zoi230963t2n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any physical therapy or chiropractic care</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Use prior to CLBP diagnosis, No. (%)<xref rid="zoi230963t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 (14.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 (22.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1411 (14.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">648 (15.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9447 (17.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176 (20.7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Use 3 mo after CLBP diagnosis, No. (%)<xref rid="zoi230963t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (7.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (13.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">713 (7.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">370 (9.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5783 (10.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 (14.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Time to treatment, median (IQR), d<xref rid="zoi230963t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0 (0-40.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 (0-30.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0 (0-43.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 (0-39.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0 (0-34.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 (0-30.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any physical therapy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Use 3 mo after CLBP diagnosis, No. (%)<xref rid="zoi230963t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (4.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (10.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">582 (5.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">283 (6.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3335 (6.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (9.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Time to treatment, median (IQR), d</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0 (1.0-39.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0 (1.0-49.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.0 (2.0-47.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0 (1.0-43.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0 (1.0-48.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5 (1.0-42.0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any chiropractic care</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Use 3 mo after CLBP diagnosis, No. (%)<xref rid="zoi230963t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (3.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (3.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170 (1.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98 (2.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2865 (5.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (6.0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Time to treatment, median (IQR), d<xref rid="zoi230963t2n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 (0-44.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0-6.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 (0-42.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0-33.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0-21.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0-16.0)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviation: CLBP, chronic low back pain.</p><fn id="zoi230963t2n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Other refers to non-Hispanic other races, and any missing values were coded as unknown.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230963t2n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Median time to PT initiation did not differ substantially across racial and ethnic groups; however, American Indian or Alaska Native persons (median, 8.5 days [IQR, 0-44.0 days]) and Black or African American persons (median, 7.0 days [IQR, 0-42.0 days]) had a longer time to receipt of chiropractic care compared with non-Hispanic White persons (median, 0 days [IQR, 0-21.0 days]). Cumulative incidence curves (<xref rid="zoi230963f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>) indicate that the differences in chiropractic care across race and ethnicity occurred in the early period following CLBP diagnosis and widened over time.</p><fig position="float" id="zoi230963f2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2. </label><caption><title>Cumulative Incidence of Physical Therapy and Chiropractic Care by Race and Ethnicity</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2333251-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="H2-8-ZOI230963"><title>Differences in Nonpharmacologic Treatment</title><p>The multilevel logistic regression models showed lower odds of any PT or chiropractic care among American Indian or Alaskan Native (AOR, 0.74; 95% CI, 0.54-0.99), Black or African American (AOR, 0.79; 95% CI, 0.71-0.87), and Hispanic (AOR, 0.84; 95% CI, 0.74-0.96) persons compared with non-Hispanic White persons after adjustment (<xref rid="zoi230963t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> and eTable 9 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230963-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). Separate analysis of any PT and any chiropractic care as outcomes revealed that these findings were driven by lower odds of any chiropractic care use among Black or African American (AOR, 0.46; 95% CI, 0.39-0.55) and Hispanic (AOR, 0.54; 95% CI, 0.43-0.67) persons (eTable 10 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230963-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). Receipt of any PT did not differ across racial and ethnic groups after adjustment (eTable 11 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230963-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi230963t3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3. </label><caption><title>Multilevel Logistic Regression for the Association Between Physical Therapy and Chiropractic Care With Race and Ethnicity</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="16.96%" span="1"/><col width="14.11%" span="1"/><col width="13.57%" span="1"/><col width="14.11%" span="1"/><col width="13.57%" span="1"/><col width="14.11%" span="1"/><col width="13.57%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Race and ethnicity</th><th colspan="6" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Odds ratio (95% CI)</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Any physical therapy or chiropractic care</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Any physical therapy</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Any chiropractic care</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Unadjusted</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjusted<xref rid="zoi230963t3n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unadjusted</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjusted<xref rid="zoi230963t3n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unadjusted</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjusted<xref rid="zoi230963t3n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">American Indian or Alaska Native</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 (0.48-0.85)<xref rid="zoi230963t3n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 (0.54-0.99)<xref rid="zoi230963t3n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 (0.51-1.05)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.55-1.17)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 (0.36-0.81)<xref rid="zoi230963t3n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 (0.45-1.06)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asian or Pacific Islander</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.80-1.41)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.70-1.31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26 (0.92-1.73)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.76-1.51)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.40-1.16)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 (0.45-1.29)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black or African American</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 (0.61-0.72)<xref rid="zoi230963t3n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 (0.71-0.87)<xref rid="zoi230963t3n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 (0.80-0.98)<xref rid="zoi230963t3n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.92-1.14)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 (0.30-0.42)<xref rid="zoi230963t3n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46 (0.39-0.55)<xref rid="zoi230963t3n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 (0.61-0.77)<xref rid="zoi230963t3n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.74-0.96)<xref rid="zoi230963t3n2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 (0.74-0.97)<xref rid="zoi230963t3n3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.87-1.15)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42 (0.34-0.52)<xref rid="zoi230963t3n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 (0.43-0.67)<xref rid="zoi230963t3n4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Hispanic White</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 [Reference]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 [Reference]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 [Reference]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 [Reference]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 [Reference]</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 [Reference]</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown or other<xref rid="zoi230963t3n5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 (0.96-1.43)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.86-1.36)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 (0.97-1.58)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 (0.92-1.55)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.79-1.41)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 (0.65-1.23)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="zoi230963t3n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Adjusted models included demographic characteristics, reason for Medicare eligibility, dual eligibility, any physical therapy or chiropractic care prior to chronic low back pain diagnosis, comorbidities, medication, social determinants of health, state-level practitioner availability, urbanicity, US region, and addiction specialist encounters during follow-up. All models accounted for clustering by county and state.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230963t3n2"><label>
<sup>b</sup>
</label><p><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.01.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230963t3n3"><label>
<sup>c</sup>
</label><p><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.05.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230963t3n4"><label>
<sup>d</sup>
</label><p><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;.001.</p></fn><fn id="zoi230963t3n5"><label>
<sup>e</sup>
</label><p>Other refers to non-Hispanic other races, and any missing values were coded as unknown.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="H2-9-ZOI230963"><title>Sensitivity Analyses</title><p>The first sensitivity analysis including a broader definition of PT yielded similar results as the main analysis (eTable 12 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230963-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). The same models were repeated to obtain estimates for the association between race and ethnicity and any PT, and the associations remained unchanged. The results of a second sensitivity analysis that excluded beneficiaries who received any PT or chiropractic care in the 6 months prior to CLBP diagnosis (n&#8201;=&#8201;11&#8201;887) were also similar to the results for receipt of any PT or chiropractic care; however, only the association for Black or African American persons remained (AOR, 0.84; 95% CI, 0.73-0.96) (eTable 13 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230963-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-4-ZOI230963"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this retrospective cohort study of Medicare beneficiaries with a new episode of CLBP and comorbid OUD, we found that receipt of PT and chiropractic care was minimal, with approximately 1 in 10 beneficiaries receiving either of these services within 3 months of CLBP diagnosis. Our findings point to differential receipt of chiropractic care within subgroups of race and ethnicity. Specifically, Black or African American and Hispanic persons had significantly lower odds of chiropractic care compared with non-Hispanic White persons. These results add to the small but emerging body of literature on use of nonpharmacologic pain treatment in the US among persons with comorbid CLBP and OUD.</p><p>There is little literature in general regarding nonpharmacologic treatment use and disparities, and the few existing studies indicate wide variations across racial and ethnic subgroups.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup> Our study found that pervasive racial and ethnic differences in chronic pain treatment extended to chiropractic care and persons with OUD. We also shed light on the utilization patterns of PT and chiropractic care by evaluating the time to treatment, which revealed disparities in access for American Indian or Alaska Native and Black or African American persons that increased over time and were primarily observed for chiropractic care. Interestingly, the cumulative incidence and time to PT in our study was consistent with other reports from large national databases.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup> Fritz et al<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> reported a PT prevalence of 7% within 90 days of the back pain visit for patients with commercial health insurance, with median time to use of PT of 14 days (IQR, 6-33 days). Compared with other studies evaluating musculoskeletal chronic pain, however, we observed lower use of chiropractic care.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup> The geographic availability of practitioners may contribute to these differential patterns of PT and chiropractic care.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup> It has been reported that labor supply of both PT and chiropractic care is lower in the South and West regions of the US compared with the Northeast and Midwest.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></sup> Variations in local practitioner availability possibly limit access, acceptability, and adoption of these types of pain treatments.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></sup> Limited patient and practitioner knowledge combined with skepticism about the efficacy of nonpharmacologic pain treatment and cultural influences on patient preferences may also impede uptake of these therapies, particularly among patients already receiving opioid therapy.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></sup></p><p>Our findings also call attention to barriers in accessing and using PT and chiropractic care for chronic pain that are compounded by the intersectional nature of racism and OUD-related stigma. Harmful biases about racial and ethnic minority groups with OUD are reinforced in health care settings, resulting in these groups receiving fewer referrals to pain specialists and consequently fewer opportunities to receive nonpharmacologic treatments compared with non-Hispanic White individuals.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup> The new clinical practice guidelines for prescribing opioids for pain by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention recommend that clinicians provide evidence-based medications for persons with OUD.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> Incorporating nonpharmacologic pain therapies along with medication for OUD creates a pain management approach that can minimize safety risks. Accordingly, several trials using behavioral and mind-based therapies to reduce pain and opioid use are currently under way.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230963r58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></sup> Efforts should also prioritize a multidisciplinary and patient-centered approach that involves cultural competency and understanding of systemic and structural inequities to ensure equal opportunities in pain and OUD care.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup> Current health care policies in coverage and financing in Medicare systematically prevent racial and ethnic minority groups from accessing high-quality care.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup> Evidence has consistently demonstrated that Black or African American and Hispanic persons are less likely to receive evidence-based care and age-appropriate diagnostic screenings.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></sup> In addition, practitioners that primarily care for low-income minority groups are more likely to receive lower reimbursements from Medicare under value-based payment programs, while pay-for-performance programs reward practitioners caring for high-income and non-Hispanic White individuals.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></sup> To this end, clinical trials assessing nonpharmacologic treatments of chronic pain and OUD can enlist community partnerships to assist in creating effective, safe, and equitable strategies for treatment of both conditions.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></sup> Additionally, current guidelines can prioritize addressing racial and ethnic inequities in treatment of chronic pain and OUD through comprehensive pain clinical care that incorporates factors at the individual, practitioner, and system levels that contribute to the observed disparities.</p><sec id="H2-10-ZOI230963"><title>Limitations</title><p>Several limitations of the study should be considered. First, Medicare claims data are limited in their ability to accurately determine race and ethnicity. However, in the absence of self-report, the RTI algorithm used is the best alternative.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></sup> Exclusion of beneficiaries residing in Puerto Rico and the US Virgin Islands also limited the study sample of Hispanic persons. However, as most beneficiaries from these territories are enrolled in Medicare Advantage, they would not have met our inclusion criteria. Second, lack of information on whether practitioners differentially referred beneficiaries to PT or chiropractic care (along with individual perspectives and preferences) limits understanding of the underlying mechanisms that explain differences in use of these treatments. Third, due to limited Medicare coverage of nonpharmacologic pain therapies, we could not assess a broader list of treatments aside from PT and chiropractic care. We attempted to characterize cognitive behavioral therapies, but low prevalence limited further assessment by race and ethnicity. Fourth, differential OUD diagnosis by practitioners based on beneficiaries&#8217; racial demographics may contribute to under- or overestimation of the differences in PT or chiropractic care for Black or African American and Hispanic persons, as these groups historically have been underdiagnosed for OUD.<sup><xref rid="zoi230963r65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></sup> Fifth, a limitation inherent with administrative claims data is that we could not capture self-paid services for which Medicare did not provide reimbursement, leading to possible underestimation of chronic pain services among beneficiaries.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-5-ZOI230963"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This cohort study found that receipt of PT and chiropractic care was low overall and lower across most racial and ethnic minority groups compared with non-Hispanic White individuals despite nonpharmacologic approaches to pain management being widely recommended as a strategy to mitigate opioid-related morbidity and mortality. Although there is uncertainty about the individual and practitioner contexts that may explain our findings, historic racial and ethnic disparities in pain treatment appear to persist and are also specifically evident for chiropractic care in persons with OUD. Therefore, efforts are needed to elucidate and address the individual, practitioner, and system-level risk factors that limit racial equity in guideline-recommended pain management in general and for persons with OUD.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="REF-ZOI230963"><title>References</title><ref id="zoi230963r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Orhurhu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Olusunmade</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Urits</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Trends of opioid use disorder among hospitalized patients with chronic pain</article-title>. <source>Pain Pract</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>656</fpage>-<lpage>663</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/papr.12789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31077526</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Delorme</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pennel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brousse</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>TOXIDOL Study Group</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and characteristics of chronic pain in buprenorphine and methadone-maintained patients</article-title>. <source>Front Psychiatry</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<elocation-id>641430</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2021.641430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33981257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8107279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hser</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Saxon</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miotto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Chronic pain among patients with opioid use disorder: results from electronic health records data</article-title>. <source>J Subst Abuse Treat</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>26</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2017.03.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28476267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5424616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Einstein</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cotto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Compton</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Volkow</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Racial and ethnic disparities in drug overdose deaths in the US during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<elocation-id>e2232314</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.32314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36125815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9490498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stenger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schooley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Moving to evidence-based practice for pain management in the critical care setting</article-title>. <source>Crit Care Nurs Clin North Am</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>319</fpage>-<lpage>327</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0899-5885(18)30059-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11866412</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality</collab></person-group>. Evidence-Based Practice Center systematic review protocol project title: noninvasive, nonpharmacological treatment for chronic pain. Accessed Feburary 6, 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://effectivehealthcare.ahrq.gov/sites/default/files/pdf/nonpharma-treatment-pain_research-protocol-amended.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://effectivehealthcare.ahrq.gov/sites/default/files/pdf/nonpharma-treatment-pain_research-protocol-amended.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Qaseem</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wilt</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>Clinical Guidelines Committee of the American College of Physicians</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Noninvasive treatments for acute, subacute, and chronic low back pain: a clinical practice guideline from the American College of Physicians</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>166</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>514</fpage>-<lpage>530</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M16-2367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28192789</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tick</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>; <collab>Pain Task Force of the Academic Consortium for Integrative Medicine and Health</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Evidence-based nonpharmacologic strategies for comprehensive pain care: the Consortium Pain Task Force white paper</article-title>. <source>Explore (NY)</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>177</fpage>-<lpage>211</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.explore.2018.02.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29735382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical practice guidelines for the management of non-specific low back pain in primary care: an updated overview</article-title>. <source>Eur Spine J</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2791</fpage>-<lpage>2803</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00586-018-5673-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29971708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dowell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ragan</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>CDC clinical practice guideline for prescribing opioids for pain&#8212;United States, 2022</article-title>. <source>MMWR Recomm Rep</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>95</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.rr7103a1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36327391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9639433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Deyo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Friedly</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nonpharmacologic therapies for low back pain: a systematic review for an American College of Physicians clinical practice guideline</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>166</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>493</fpage>-<lpage>505</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M16-2459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28192793</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Skelly</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dettori</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. Noninvasive nonpharmacological treatment for chronic pain: a systematic review update. Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality. Accessed July 29, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK556229/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK556229/</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32338846</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>Pennsylvania Department of Health</collab></person-group>. Prescribing guidelines. Accessed February 21, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.health.pa.gov/topics/disease/Opioids/Pages/Prescribing-Guidelines.aspx" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.health.pa.gov/topics/disease/Opioids/Pages/Prescribing-Guidelines.aspx</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gravely</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Racial differences in prescription of opioid analgesics for chronic noncancer pain in a national sample of veterans</article-title>. <source>J Pain</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>447</fpage>-<lpage>455</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpain.2013.12.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24440840</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dunham</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Racial disparities in opioid administration and prescribing in the emergency department for pain</article-title>. <source>Am J Emerg Med</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>-<lpage>173</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajem.2022.02.043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35358938</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Arnsten</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sacajiu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karasz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Providers&#8217; experiences treating chronic pain among opioid-dependent drug users</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>482</fpage>-<lpage>488</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-009-0908-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19189194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2659151</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Meints</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cortes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morais</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Racial and ethnic differences in the experience and treatment of noncancer pain</article-title>. <source>Pain Manag</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>317</fpage>-<lpage>334</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/pmt-2018-0030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31140916</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6587104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wimbish</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Blackwood</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Examining racial, ethnic, and gender disparities in the treatment of pain and injury emergencies</article-title>. <source>HCA Healthc J Med</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>111</fpage>-<lpage>118</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.36518/2689-0216.1425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37424602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10324842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Le Saux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Racial and ethnic disparities in the management of acute pain in US emergency departments: meta-analysis and systematic review</article-title>. <source>Am J Emerg Med</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1770</fpage>-<lpage>1777</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajem.2019.06.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31186154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Trawalter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Axt</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Racial bias in pain assessment and treatment recommendations, and false beliefs about biological differences between blacks and whites</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>113</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>4296</fpage>-<lpage>4301</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1516047113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27044069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4843483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kennel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Withers</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Racial/ethnic disparities in pain treatment: evidence from Oregon emergency medical services agencies</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>924</fpage>-<lpage>929</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MLR.0000000000001208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31730566</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>Medicare Current Beneficiary Survey</collab></person-group>. Chronic pain in the Medicare population. Accessed April 1, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.norc.org/PDFs/MCBS/2018MCBSCPQInfographic.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.norc.org/PDFs/MCBS/2018MCBSCPQInfographic.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rikard</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Strahan</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schmit</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>GP</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Chronic pain among adults&#8212;United States, 2019-2021</article-title>. <source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>379</fpage>-<lpage>385</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7215a1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37053114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10121254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shoff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Trends in opioid use disorder among older adults: analyzing Medicare data, 2013-2018</article-title>. <source>Am J Prev Med</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>850</fpage>-<lpage>855</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2021.01.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33812694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8154702</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kaasa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Korwisi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rief</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Treede</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>; <collab>IASP Taskforce for the Classification of Chronic Pain</collab></person-group>. <article-title>The IASP classification of chronic pain for <italic toggle="yes">ICD-11</italic>: chronic cancer-related pain</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>160</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>38</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/j.pain.0000000000001363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30586069</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Treede</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rief</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A classification of chronic pain for <italic toggle="yes">ICD-11</italic></article-title>. <source>Pain</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>156</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1003</fpage>-<lpage>1007</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/j.pain.0000000000000160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25844555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4450869</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mullins</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of chronic pain among adults in the United States</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>163</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e328</fpage>-<lpage>e332</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/j.pain.0000000000002291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33990113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mikosz</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haegerich</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Indication-specific opioid prescribing for US patients with Medicaid or private insurance, 2017</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<elocation-id>e204514</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.4514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32391892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7215258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">National Cancer Institute. Cancer pain (PDQ)&#8212;patient version. Accessed April 23, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/pain/pain-pdq" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/treatment/side-effects/pain/pain-pdq</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Refiguring &#8220;race&#8221;: epidemiology, racialized biology, and biological expressions of race relations</article-title>. <source>Int J Health Serv</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>211</fpage>-<lpage>216</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2190/672J-1PPF-K6QT-9N7U</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10707306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Filice</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Joynt</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Examining race and ethnicity information in Medicare administrative data</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>e170</fpage>-<lpage>e176</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MLR.0000000000000608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29135782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jarr&#237;n</surname><given-names>OF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nyandege</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Grafova</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Validity of race and ethnicity codes in Medicare administrative data compared with gold-standard self-reported race collected during routine home health care visits</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e1</fpage>-<lpage>e8</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MLR.0000000000001216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31688554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6904433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessing the validity of race and ethnicity coding in administrative Medicare data for reporting outcomes among Medicare Advantage beneficiaries from 2015 to 2017</article-title>. <source>Health Serv Res</source>. Published online June 25, 2023. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1475-6773.14197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37356821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10480088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Chronic non-cancer pain among adults with substance use disorders: prevalence, characteristics, and association with opioid overdose and healthcare utilization</article-title>. <source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>209</volume>:<elocation-id>107902</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.107902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32088587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7127943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huskamp</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Raja</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrotra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Disruptions in care for Medicare beneficiaries with severe mental illness during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<elocation-id>e2145677</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.45677</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35089352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8800078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gagne</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Glynn</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Avorn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schneeweiss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A combined comorbidity score predicted mortality in elderly patients better than existing scores</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>749</fpage>-<lpage>759</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2010.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21208778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3100405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zedler</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Joyce</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vick</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Murrelle</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Validation of a screening risk index for serious prescription opioid-induced respiratory depression or overdose in a US commercial health plan claims database</article-title>. <source>Pain Med</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>68</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pm/pnx009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28340046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5939826</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>US Census Bureau</collab></person-group>. American Community Survey (ACS). Accessed August 19, 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.census.gov/programs-surveys/acs" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.census.gov/programs-surveys/acs</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>Health Resources &amp; Services Administration</collab></person-group>. Area Health Resources Files. Accessed August 19, 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://data.hrsa.gov/data/download" ext-link-type="uri">https://data.hrsa.gov/data/download</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Petterson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bazemore</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Measures of social deprivation that predict health care access and need within a rational area of primary care service delivery</article-title>. <source>Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>2, pt 1</issue>):<fpage>539</fpage>-<lpage>559</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1475-6773.2012.01449.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22816561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3626349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>National Plan and Provider Enumeration System</collab></person-group>. NPI files. Accessed July 18, 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://download.cms.gov/nppes/NPI_Files.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://download.cms.gov/nppes/NPI_Files.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Weeks</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goertz</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Meeker</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marchiori</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Public perceptions of doctors of chiropractic: results of a national survey and examination of variation according to respondents&#8217; likelihood to use chiropractic, experience with chiropractic, and chiropractic supply in local health care markets</article-title>. <source>J Manipulative Physiol Ther</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>533</fpage>-<lpage>544</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmpt.2015.08.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26362263</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sandstrom</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bruns</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Disparities in access to outpatient rehabilitation therapy for African Americans with arthritis</article-title>. <source>J Racial Ethn Health Disparities</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>599</fpage>-<lpage>606</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40615-016-0263-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27400913</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Keeney</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jette</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cabral</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Racial differences in patterns of use of rehabilitation services for adults aged 65 and older</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2707</fpage>-<lpage>2712</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgs.15136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29114848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5729093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Choo</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Livingston</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McConnell</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Increased use of complementary and alternative therapies for back pain following statewide Medicaid coverage changes in Oregon</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>676</fpage>-<lpage>682</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-020-06352-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33443692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7947103</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chevan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Riddle</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Factors associated with care seeking from physicians, physical therapists, or chiropractors by persons with spinal pain: a population-based study</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Sports Phys Ther</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>467</fpage>-<lpage>476</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2519/jospt.2011.3637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21654096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Childs</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wainner</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Primary care referral of patients with low back pain to physical therapy: impact on future health care utilization and costs</article-title>. <source>Spine (Phila Pa 1976)</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>25</issue>):<fpage>2114</fpage>-<lpage>2121</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/BRS.0b013e31825d32f5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22614792</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gellhorn</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Friedly</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Management patterns in acute low back pain: the role of physical therapy</article-title>. <source>Spine (Phila Pa 1976)</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>775</fpage>-<lpage>782</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/BRS.0b013e3181d79a09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21099735</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3062937</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carlesso</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nahin</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Management of patients with a musculoskeletal pain condition that is likely chronic: results from a national cross sectional survey</article-title>. <source>J Pain</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>7-8</issue>):<fpage>869</fpage>-<lpage>880</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpain.2019.11.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31837448</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Association between chiropractic utilization and opioid prescriptions among people with back or neck pain: evaluation of the Medical Expenditure Panel Survey</article-title>. <source>J Manipulative Physiol Ther</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>315</fpage>-<lpage>322</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmpt.2022.08.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36195475</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goertz</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Insurer coverage of nonpharmacological treatments for low back pain&#8212;time for a change</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<elocation-id>e183037</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2018.3037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30646214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Naylor</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tootoo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yakusheva</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shipman</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bynum</surname><given-names>JPW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Geographic variation in spatial accessibility of U.S. healthcare providers</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<elocation-id>e0215016</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0215016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30964933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6456202</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zimbelman</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Juraschek</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>VWH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Physical therapy workforce in the United States: forecasting nationwide shortages</article-title>. <source>PM R</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1021</fpage>-<lpage>1029</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pmrj.2010.06.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21093838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dorflinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Edmond</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heapy</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fraenkel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Barriers and facilitators to use of non-pharmacological treatments in chronic pain</article-title>. <source>BMC Fam Pract</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>41</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12875-017-0608-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28320337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5359906</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Racial bias in the US opioid epidemic: a review of the history of systemic bias and implications for care</article-title>. <source>Cureus</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<elocation-id>e3733</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.3733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30800543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6384031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kehne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lagisetty</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. Improving access to primary and pain care for patients taking opioids for chronic pain in Michigan. University of Michigan Institute for Healthcare Policy &amp; Innovation. Accessed July 15, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ihpi.umich.edu/paincare" ext-link-type="uri">https://ihpi.umich.edu/paincare</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r57"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">HOPE Consortium trial to reduce pain and opioid use in hemodialysis. ClinicalTrials.gov identifier: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT04571619">NCT04571619</ext-link>. Updated July 12, 2023. Accessed April 2, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://classic.clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT04571619" ext-link-type="uri">https://classic.clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT04571619</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r58"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">An adaptive walking intervention to manage chronic pain in veterans with opioid use disorder engaged in opioid agonist treatment.ClinicalTrials.gov identifier: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT05051644">NCT05051644</ext-link>. Updated March 13, 2023. Accessed April 2, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://classic.clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT05051644" ext-link-type="uri">https://classic.clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT05051644</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r59"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">American Academy of Family Physicians. Chronic pain management and opioid misuse: a public health concern (position paper). Accessed April 3, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.aafp.org/about/policies/all/chronic-pain-management-opiod-misuse.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.aafp.org/about/policies/all/chronic-pain-management-opiod-misuse.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r60"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality. 2019 National healthcare quality and disparities report. Accessed July 15, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ahrq.gov/research/findings/nhqrdr/nhqdr19/index.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ahrq.gov/research/findings/nhqrdr/nhqdr19/index.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r61"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yearby</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Structural racism in historical and modern US health care policy</article-title>. <source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>187</fpage>-<lpage>194</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2021.01466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35130059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r62"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gilman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hockenberry</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Milstein</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Safety-net hospitals more likely than other hospitals to fare poorly under Medicare&#8217;s value-based purchasing</article-title>. <source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>398</fpage>-<lpage>405</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2014.1059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25732489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r63"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ashburn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boateng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cheatle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. Prescribing guideline. Accessed April 3, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.health.pa.gov/topics/disease/Opioids/Pages/Prescribing-Guidelines.aspx" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.health.pa.gov/topics/disease/Opioids/Pages/Prescribing-Guidelines.aspx</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r64"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>US Department of Health and Human Services</collab></person-group>. Office of Inspector General data brief: inaccuracies in Medicare&#8217;s race and ethnicity data hinder the ability to assess health disparities. Accessed December 10, 2022. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://oig.hhs.gov/oei/reports/OEI-02-21-00100.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://oig.hhs.gov/oei/reports/OEI-02-21-00100.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230963r65"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. Examining racial/ethnic differences in patterns of opioid prescribing: results from an urban safety-net healthcare system. <source>J Racial Ethn Health Disparities</source>. Published online March 9, 2023.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40615-023-01555-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9997438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36892815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><notes notes-type="supplementary-material" id="note-ZOI230963-1"><supplementary-material id="note-ZOI230963-1-s" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplement 1.</label><caption><p><bold>eTable 1.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">ICD-10</italic> codes for chronic back pain and opioid use disorder from MedPAR Part A and Part B claims</p><p><bold>eTable 2.</bold> Physical therapy and chiropractic care <italic toggle="yes">CPT</italic> codes from Part B claims</p><p><bold>eTable 3.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">ICD-10</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">CPT</italic> codes for comorbidities from MedPAR Part A and Part B claims</p><p><bold>eTable 4.</bold> Generic drug names for opioid prescriptions, excluding buprenorphine, in Part D claims</p><p><bold>eTable 5.</bold> Data sources and definitions for county-level social determinants of health, geographic characteristics, and state-level practitioner availability</p><p><bold>eTable 6.</bold> Additional characteristics of the study population by race and ethnicity</p><p><bold>eTable 7.</bold> Characteristics of overall study population</p><p><bold>eTable 8.</bold> Practitioner encounters after chronic low back pain diagnosis by race and ethnicity</p><p><bold>eTable 9.</bold> All multilevel logistic regressions for the association between any physical therapy or chiropractic care and race and ethnicity</p><p><bold>eTable 10.</bold> All multilevel logistic regressions for the association between any chiropractic care and race and ethnicity</p><p><bold>eTable 11.</bold> All multilevel logistic regressions for the association between any physical therapy and race and ethnicity</p><p><bold>eTable 12.</bold> All multilevel logistic regressions for the association between any physical therapy (including n&#8201;=&#8201;209 with evaluations only) and race and ethnicity</p><p><bold>eTable 13.</bold> All multilevel logistic regressions for the association between any physical therapy or chiropractic care and race and ethnicity (excluding 11&#8201;887 individuals with any physical therapy or chiropractic care prior to chronic low back pain diagnosis)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2333251-s001.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplement 2.</label><caption><p>
Data Sharing Statement
</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2333251-s002.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></notes></back></article></pmc-articleset>