<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2277</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">frontpubhealth</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Public Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2296-2565</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10073750</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10073750.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10073750</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10073750</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37033050</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2023.1120671</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Public Health</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Association between radiotherapy for surgically treated oral cavity cancer and secondary lung cancer</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names initials="D">Dongjie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1593047/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="J">Jun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Ying</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1802128/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="P">Peiwen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1701770/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="G">Gaiyan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1593193/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names initials="H">Hao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1593038/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qiming</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qiuju</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names initials="S">Siying</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2170781/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Radiation Oncology, Tangdu Hospital, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Air Force Military Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Xi'an</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Otolaryngology, Tangdu Hospital, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Air Force Military Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Xi'an</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Traditional Chinese Medicine, The Sixth Medical Center of PLA General Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Lorenzo Manti, University of Naples Federico II, Italy</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Boukje Van Dijk, Integral Cancer Center Netherlands (IKNL), Netherlands; Ali-Farid Safi, Craniologicum&#8212;Center for Craniomaxillofacial Surgery, Switzerland</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Siying Zhu <email>zsy_333333@163.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Radiation and Health, a section of the journal Frontiers in Public Health</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn002"><p>&#8224;These authors have contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">427737</issue-id><elocation-id>1120671</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>22</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>06</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-04-10 12:11:19.920"><day>10</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 He, Zhang, Xiang, Wu, Li, Chang, Wang, Shao and Zhu.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>He, Zhang, Xiang, Wu, Li, Chang, Wang, Shao and Zhu</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fpubh-11-1120671.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>There is limited research on the incidence of secondary lung cancer (SLC) after radiotherapy (RT) for oral cavity cancer (OCC). Therefore, we investigated the association between RT for OCC and the risk of SLC and the overall survival of these patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Patients diagnosed with OCC between 1975 and 2015 were selected from the Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results database. The cumulative incidence of SLC, relative risk (RR) of RT vs. no RT (NRT), standardized incidence ratios (SIR), and survival outcomes were assessed.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>A total of 10,936 patients with OCC were included. Of these, 429 (3.92%) patients developed SLC, where 136 (5.02%) received RT and 293 (3.56%) did not. The cumulative incidence of SLC during follow-up was 6.89% and 4.84% in the RT and NRT patients, respectively. RT was associated with a higher risk of SLC. In the subset analysis, the results showed that a higher risk of developing SLC among patients with index OCC in most subgroups. Dynamic RR and SIR revealed a decreased risk of SLC with increasing latency time. No difference was observed in the 10-year survival rates for patients with SLC who received RT or not or compared with primary lung cancer.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>RT was associated with a higher risk of SLC, and patients diagnosed with OCC could be followed for 5&#8211;10 years after diagnosis.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>oral cavity cancer</kwd><kwd>radiotherapy</kwd><kwd>secondary lung cancer</kwd><kwd>SEER</kwd><kwd>survivors</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="50"/><page-count count="12"/><word-count count="6691"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Summary</title><p>This study aimed to investigate the association between radiation given as treatment for surgically treated oral cavity cancer and the occurrence of lung cancer as secondary cancer. Here, we show that radiation has a greater risk of causing secondary lung cancer, particularly 5&#8211;10 years after the oral cancer diagnosis. In addition, these findings support extended follow-up time in patients who have received radiation for oral cavity cancer.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Oral cavity cancer (OCC) is one of the most common malignancies of the head and neck and the sixth most common cancer worldwide (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). In the United States, the annual incidence of OCC is estimated to be between 4 and 4.3 cases per 100,000, and the burden of OCC cases is steadily increasing (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). OCC also represents a growing health concern since, in 2018, it was estimated to have a death toll of 119,700 men and 57,700 women worldwide (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). However, the number of survivors of OCC has been increasing, indicating that cancer treatment is advancing (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Unfortunately, these survivors experience an elevated risk of developing a second primary cancer (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), which is the leading cause of mortality in these patients (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p><p>Currently, the standard treatment for early-stage resected OCC with high-risk features is adjuvant radiochemotherapy, and the strategy for advanced OCC is surgical resection, adjuvant radiotherapy (RT), and chemotherapy (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). However, the adverse effects caused by RT for OCC are significant, including severe disruption of the patient's quality of life and long-term side effects, such as radiation injury and second primary cancers (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). In addition, lung cancer is becoming increasingly common as a second primary malignancy. Several retrospective studies have reported a phenomenon that RT was associated with an increased risk of developing secondary lung cancer (SLC) following head and neck cancer (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Similarly, RT for some pelvic cancer has also been reported to increase the risk of SLC (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). However, there is limited research on the association between RT and SLC incidence in patients with OCC.</p><p>Therefore, this retrospective study aimed to evaluate the association between RT for OCC and the incidence of SLC, as well as the survival rate of SLC after RT in patients with OCC.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>2. Materials and methods</title><sec><title>2.1. Patient selection</title><p>The Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results (SEER) database, which includes nine population-based registries from the USA between 1975 and 2015, was used for patient se-lection and data collection (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Patients meeting the following criteria were included: a diagnosis of OCC (site codes C003-009, C020-023, C030-039, C040-050, C053-059, and C060-069) (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>); primary cancer; and an accurate record of surgical interventions. The exclusion criteria were as follows: death certificate or autopsy records, multiple cancers, age &lt;20 years, distant and unknown stage at diagnosis according to the SEER Combined Summary Stage and Historic Stage A variables, unknown or no surgical information, unknown modality of radiation therapy, and survival of &lt;60 months after oral cavity diagnosis (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1</xref> shows a flow diagram of the inclusion/exclusion criteria and the study design.</p><p>The following data were collected from the SEER database for each patient: age, sex, race, marital status, anatomic sites, histology, grade, stage, chemotherapy, and follow-up time. Patients with OCC were categorized into the following two groups: RT and no RT (NRT). Informed patient consent was not required to access or use the SEER data. Therefore, the requirement for ethical approval and informed consent was waived for the present study. This study followed the Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) reporting guidelines.</p></sec><sec><title>2.2. Definition of SLC and follow-up</title><p>Given the complexity of SLC diagnosis and the high likelihood of incident malignancy detection immediately after OCC diagnosis, follow-up for the analysis of SLC was initiated 60 months following the diagnosis of OCC, considering the minimum latency for radiation-induced cancerization (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Therefore, the latency period for SLC began 5 years after OCC diagnosis and ended at the date of diagnosis of any SLC, all-cause death, or after 30 years of follow-up, whichever occurred first (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>2.3. Statistical analyses</title><p>Fine-Gray models were used to assess the cumulative incidence and risks of SLC after the diagnosis of OCC (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). The occurrence of non-SLC and all-cause mortality were considered competing events. These factors were considered in calculating hazard ratios (HRs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) for developing SLC (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Multivariable competitive regression and Poisson regression were used to assess the risk of SLC development. Subgroup analysis was performed using a competing risk regression model. Relevant clinical interventions were included in the model.</p><p>Poisson regression was used to compare the RT-relative risk (RR) and 95% CI of developing SLC in patients with OCC who received RT and NRT. In addition, the standardized incidence ratio (SIR) and 95% CI were estimated using a Poisson regression analysis. SIR was estimated using SEER<sup>*</sup>Stat 8.4.0.1. In the RR and SIR adjustment model, we included the following three variables in our retrospective study: age at OCC diagnosis, year of OCC diagnosis, and latency time of SLC diagnosis. To further evaluate the dynamic risks and incidence of SLC associated with RT, we calculated RR and SIR stratified by latency time since OCC diagnosis, age at OCC diagnosis, and year of OCC diagnosis.</p><p>Propensity-score matching was used to reduce bias. A one-to-one nearest neighbor matching algorithm was used (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). We matched the baseline characteristics of SLC, including age, sex, race, years of diagnosis, marital status, sites, grade, histology, stage, surgery, radiation, and chemotherapy, to assess survival in the RT vs. NRT group for SLC. The 10-year overall survival (OS) of SLC between RT and NRT groups was compared using Kaplan&#8211;Meier curves before and after propensity-score matching. To compare the 10-year OS between PLC and SLC after OCC, we also matched SLC according to their baseline characteristics, including age, sex, race, years of diagnosis, marital status, sites, grade, histology, stage, surgery, radiation, and chemotherapy. Differences in OS were compared using the log-rank test. All analyses were performed using R Statistical Software 4.1.1 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.R-project.org</ext-link>, The R Foundation) and Free Statistics software version 1.7.0 (Based on R statistical software 3.2.2) (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). A <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>3. Results</title><sec><title>3.1. Baseline characteristics of patients with OCC</title><p>A total of 10,936 patients who were diagnosed with OCC and underwent surgery were identified according to the eligibility criteria, and their baseline characteristics are shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. In addition, 29.9% of adult patients with tumors at the localized and regional stages survived for more than 5 years. Of these, 24.8% and 75.2% of the patients were treated with and without RT, respectively. The median age at diagnosis was 60 years, the median follow-up time was 140 months, and the median latency time was 113 months. The RT group was younger (58 years), more often male (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1,626, 60.0%), less often white (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 2,266, 83.6%), more often diagnosed in later years, less often had grade I/II OCC (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1,805, 66.6%), more often squamous cell carcinoma (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 2,293, 84.6%), less often localized staging (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 938,34.6%), and more often received chemotherapy (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 413, 15.2%), compared with the NRT group. Of the 10,936 identified cases, 429 (3.92%) developed SLC during the follow-up period, with 136 (5.02%) and 293 (3.56%) in the RT and NRT groups, respectively.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of patients with surgically treated OCC.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variables</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Radiotherapy</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>No radiotherapy</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,936 (100.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,710 (24.8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,226 (75.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, median (IQR), year</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.0 (51.0, 69.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.0 (51.0, 67.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.0 (51.0, 69.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Age</bold>, <italic toggle="yes"><bold>n</bold></italic>
<bold>(%), year</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#8211;49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,418 (22.1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">602 (22.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,816 (22.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#8211;69</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,983 (54.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,586 (58.5)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,397 (53.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;70</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,535 (23.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">522 (19.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,013 (24.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Sex</bold>, <italic toggle="yes"><bold>n</bold></italic>
<bold>(%)</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,639 (42.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,084 (40.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,555 (43.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,297 (57.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,626 (60.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,671 (56.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,505 (86.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,266 (83.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,239 (88.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">686 (6.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">236 (8.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">450 (5.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other/unknown<xref rid="TN1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">745 (6.8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208 (7.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">537 (6.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year, median (IQR)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,996 (1,986, 2,005)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,997 (1,987, 2,006)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,995 (1,985, 2,005)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Year</bold>, <italic toggle="yes"><bold>n</bold></italic>
<bold>(%)</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1975&#8211;1984</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,429 (22.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">518 (19.1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,911 (23.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1985&#8211;1994</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,738 (25.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">666 (24.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,072 (25.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1995&#8211;2004</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,878 (26.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">751 (27.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,127 (25.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;2005</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,891 (26.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">775 (28.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,116 (25.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Marital status</bold>, <italic toggle="yes"><bold>n</bold></italic>
<bold>(%)</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,476 (13.5)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">397 (14.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,079 (13.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,406 (58.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,584 (58.5)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,822 (58.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other/unknown<xref rid="TN2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,054 (27.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">729 (26.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,325 (28.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Anatomic sites</bold>, <italic toggle="yes"><bold>n</bold></italic>
<bold>(%)</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lip</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">919 (8.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (1.5)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">878 (10.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tongue</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,285 (30.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">778 (28.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,507 (30.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gum</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,188 (10.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">346 (12.8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">842 (10.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Floor of mouth</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,775 (25.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">773 (28.5)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,002 (24.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">947 (8.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">196 (7.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">751 (9.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,822 (16.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">576 (21.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,246 (15.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Grade</bold>, <italic toggle="yes"><bold>n</bold></italic>
<bold>(%)</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade I/II</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,496 (68.5)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,805 (66.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,691 (69.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade III/IV</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">995 (9.1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">448 (16.5)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">547 (6.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,445 (22.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">457 (16.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,988 (24.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Histology</bold>, <italic toggle="yes"><bold>n</bold></italic>
<bold>(%)</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.409</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Squamous cell carcinoma</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,832 (80.8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,293 (84.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,539 (79.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,104 (19.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">417 (15.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,687 (20.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Localized</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,361 (67.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">938 (34.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,423 (78.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regional</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,575 (32.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,772 (65.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,803 (21.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Chemotherapy</bold>, <italic toggle="yes"><bold>n</bold></italic>
<bold>(%)</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,473 (95.8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,297 (84.8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,176 (99.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">463 (4.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">413 (15.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up time, median (IQR), months</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140.0 (94.0, 211.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.0 (88.0, 191.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145.0 (97.0, 218.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Secondary lung cancer, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">429 (3.92)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136 (5.02)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">293 (3.56)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Latency time, median (IQR), months</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113 (81, 165)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 (77, 138)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">119 (82, 170)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>IQR, interquartile range; OCC, oral cavity cancer.</p><fn id="TN1"><label>a</label><p>Other including American Indian/AK Native, Asian/Pacific Islander.</p></fn><fn id="TN2"><label>b</label><p>Other including Divorced, Separated, Widowed, Unmarried or Domestic partner.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>3.2. Cumulative incidence of SLC</title><p>The cumulative incidence of SLC was calculated at 6.89% and 4.84% in the RT and NRT groups, respectively, using a Fine-Gray model (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). The incidence of SLC in the RT group was higher than that in the NRT group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). Similarly, patients showed a significant increase in mortality with RT compared to NRT (80.60% vs. 76.54%; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001; <xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>). Furthermore, we performed a stratified analysis on the occurrence of SLC by stage. The incidence of SLC in the RT group was higher than that in the NRT group for localized disease (HR = 1.64, 95% CI: 1.27&#8211;2.12; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.002) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). The incidence of SLC was not different in the RT and NRT groups for regional disease (HR =1.16, 95% CI: 0.90&#8211;1.50; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.320) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref>). As shown in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, the multivariate competing risk model revealed that a radiation history of patients with OCC was an independent risk factor for SLC (HR = 1.35, 95% CI: 1.11&#8211;1.65; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.010). Poisson regression was used to assess the relative risk of SLC without considering competing events. Multivariate Poisson regression analyses showed that patients with OCC who received RT significantly increased the RR of SLC vs. those with NRT (RR = 1.33, 95% CI: 1.09&#8211;1.60; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.015; <xref rid="SM4" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Cumulative incidence of SLC between patients who received RT and those who did not received RT. <bold>(A)</bold> Overall cohort. <bold>(B)</bold> Localized disease. <bold>(C)</bold> Regional disease. NRT, no radiotherapy; RT, radiotherapy.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fpubh-11-1120671-g0001.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Competing risk regression model for developing SLC in OCC.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variables</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>Univariate analysis</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>Multivariate analysis</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>HR (95% CI)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">
<bold>p</bold>
</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>HR (95% CI)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">
<bold>p</bold>
</italic>
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<bold>Age</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#8211;49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#8211;69</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25 (1.78&#8211;2.85)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85 (1.45&#8211;2.36)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;70</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.75&#8211;1.37)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.950</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 (0.72&#8211;1.34)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.910</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<bold>Sex</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45 (1.23&#8211;1.72)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 (1.07&#8211;1.53)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<bold>Race</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 (0.85&#8211;1.55)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.460</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.79&#8211;1.46)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.700</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other<xref rid="TN3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 (0.37&#8211;0.88)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.46&#8211;1.10)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.200</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<bold>Year</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1975&#8211;1984</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1985&#8211;1994</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 (0.73-1.07)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.280</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 (0.81&#8211;1.19)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.870</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1995&#8211;2004</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68 (0.55-0.83)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.65&#8211;1.01)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;2005</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 (0.28-0.56)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 (0.33&#8211;0.67)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<bold>Marital status</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 (0.99&#8211;1.71)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.120</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21 (0.92&#8211;1.60)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.250</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other/unknown<xref rid="TN4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39 (1.04&#8211;1.86)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.065</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 (1.01&#8211;1.85)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<bold>Site</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lip</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tongue</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.57&#8211;1.14)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.310</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 (0.56&#8211;1.15)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.320</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gum</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 (0.62&#8211;1.40)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.790</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.64&#8211;1.49)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.920</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Floor of mouth</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97 (1.43&#8211;2.72)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62 (1.16&#8211;2.26)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 (0.35&#8211;0.93)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.060</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.56&#8211;1.58)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.850</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34 (0.94&#8211;1.89)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.170</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41 (0.98&#8211;2.04)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.120</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<bold>Grade</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade I/II</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade III/IV</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 (0.86&#8211;1.48)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.470</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.77&#8211;1.34)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.930</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.82&#8211;1.20)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.960</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.88&#8211;1.30)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.570</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<bold>Histology</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Squamous cell carcinoma</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44 (0.34&#8211;0.58)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 (0.39&#8211;0.72)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<bold>Stage</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Localized</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regional</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34 (1.14&#8211;1.58)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.83&#8211;1.22)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.960</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<bold>Chemotherapy</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 (0.92&#8211;2.04)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.190</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 (0.76&#8211;1.75)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.560</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<bold>Radiotherapy</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48 (1.25&#8211;1.75)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 (1.11&#8211;1.65)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>SLC, second primary lung cancer; OCC, oral cavity cancer; HR, hazard ratio; CI, confidence interval, Ref., Reference.</p><fn id="TN3"><label>a</label><p>Other including American Indian/AK Native, Asian/Pacific Islander.</p></fn><fn id="TN4"><label>b</label><p>Other including Divorced, Separated, Widowed, Unmarried or Domestic partner.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Subgroup analyses were performed to compare the risk of developing SLC in patients with OCC with or without previous RT. The results of the competing risk analysis (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>; <xref rid="SM5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S2</xref>) showed a higher risk of developing SLC among patients with OCC who were aged between 50 and 69 years (HR = 1.37, 95% CI: 1.09&#8211;1.71), female (HR = 1.51, 95% CI: 1.09&#8211;2.11), white (HR = 1.40, 95% CI: 1.13&#8211;1.73), married (HR = 1.43, 95% CI: 1.12&#8211;1.81), diagnosed with squamous cell carcinoma (HR = 1.40, 95% CI: 1.14&#8211;1.71), diagnosed with localized diseases (HR = 1.61, 95% CI: 1.23&#8211;2.08) or received no chemotherapy (HR = 1.29, 95% CI: 1.06&#8211;1.58).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of risk of SLC between subgroups by estimating HRs through competing risk analyses. NRT, no radiotherapy; RT, radiotherapy; HRs, hazard ratios.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fpubh-11-1120671-g0002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.3. Dynamic risk and incidence evaluation for SLC</title><p>To further evaluate the risk of SLC associated with RT, we analyzed the RR plot of the latency time after OCC diagnosis, diagnosis year of OCC, and age at primary OCC diagnosis. The results of the multivariate Poisson regression revealed that RT was associated with elevated risks of SLC in patients aged 50&#8211;69 years with OCC (RR = 1.48, 95% CI: 1.21&#8211;1.81, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.001; <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>). No significant changes were observed in other age groups (20&#8211;49: RR = 0.99, 95% CI: 0.58&#8211;1.61, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.978; &#8805;70: RR = 1.64, 95% CI: 1.03&#8211;2.58, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.073; <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>). In the RR plots for the years since diagnosis, we found that the risk increased and reached a maximum between 2005 and 2015 (1975&#8211;1984: RR = 1.35, 95% CI: 0.99&#8211;1.82; 1985&#8211;1994: RR = 1.39, 95% CI 1.03&#8211;1.86; 1995&#8211;2004: RR = 1.41, 95% CI: 0.99&#8211;1.97; &#8805;2005: RR = 4.23, 95% CI 2.26&#8211;8.08; <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>). However, in the RR plot of latency time, we found that the risk of SLC decreased with the prolongation of latency time of OCC diagnosis (60&#8211;119: RR = 1.40, 95% CI: 1.12&#8211;1.75; 120&#8211;239: RR = 1.18, 95% CI: 0.86&#8211;1.58; 240&#8211;360: RR = 1.09, 95% CI: 0.48&#8211;2.20; <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Adjusted relative risk plots of SLC of patients with OCC treated with RT or without RT. <bold>(A)</bold> Age at OCC diagnosis. <bold>(B)</bold> Year of OCC diagnosis. <bold>(C)</bold> Latency time. RR, relative risk; OCC, oral cavity cancer; RT, radiotherapy; SLC, second primary lung cancer.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fpubh-11-1120671-g0003.jpg"/></fig><p>In addition, we evaluated the SIR of SLC in the US population in patients with OCC with or without a prior history of RT, grouped by the latency time after OCC diagnosis, year of primary OCC diagnosis, and age at primary OCC diagnosis. We found that the patients with OCC who received RT (SIR: 3.07, 95% CI: 2.78&#8211;3.38, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) and those who did not (SIR: 2.41, 95% CI: 2.22&#8211;2.61, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) had a higher risk of SLC than the general population (<xref rid="SM3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>3.4. Survival outcome of SLC</title><p>We compared the OS of patients with SLC who received RT with the NRT group, and the 10-year survival rates were not significantly different (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>). Therefore, to reduce bias, we performed a propensity score (<xref rid="SM6" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S3</xref>), and the 10-year survival rates were 4.6% and 4.7% for the RT and NRT groups, respectively. However, no significant difference was observed in the 10-year survival (HR = 1.23, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.096) (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref>). To further analyze the survival of SLC, we matched SLC to primary lung cancer (PLC) separately (<xref rid="SM7" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S4</xref>, <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>). The 10-year survival rates of SLC and PLC were 3.9% and 4.4% in the NRT group, and 4.6% and 2.2% in the RT group. In addition, no difference was found in survival between SLC and PLC (PLC vs. SLC, HR = 1.02, 95% CI: 0.87&#8211;1.20, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.811, <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4C</xref>; PLC vs. SLC, HR = 0.80, 95% CI: 0.63&#8211;1.02, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.078, <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4D</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Survival outcome of patients with SLC. <bold>(A)</bold> Overall survival after diagnosis of second lung cancer before matching. <bold>(B)</bold> Overall survival of second lung cancer between RT and NRT groups after matching. <bold>(C)</bold> Overall survival between PLC and SLC after matching in the NRT group. <bold>(D)</bold> Overall survival between PLC and SLC after matching in the RT group. SLC, second primary lung cancer.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fpubh-11-1120671-g0004.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><title>4. Discussion</title><p>RT effectively improves OS and local progression-free survival in patients with OCC (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). However, it remains unclear whether RT is associated with SLC. Therefore, we investigated this association by selecting patients with OCC from the SEER database and comparing those with and without a history of RT. First, our findings show that, RT was associated with an increased risk of SLC in patients with OCC. Second, in the US population, the risk of patients with SLC who received RT was higher than that of those who did not receive RT. Third, the risk of developing SLC after RT in patients with OCC increased with increasing age at diagnosis and year of diagnosis and decreased with increasing latency between OCC and SLC diagnoses. Fourth, no significant difference was observed in the survival of patients with SLC who had or had not received RT and that of those with SLC or with PLC.</p><p>Previous studies have shown that the risk of developing lung cancer in patients with laryngeal cancer treated with RT (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). In addition, the study showed that RT of the first primary tumor might result in developing secondary solid tumors in 8% of patients (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). However, evidence from several studies has shown that RT is not associated with an increase in the diagnosis of second primary cancers (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Therefore, developing secondary tumors after RT for head and neck tumors remains controversial, and there are few studies on SLC after RT for OCC. Previous studies have reported that most head and neck tumors develop distant metastases within 2 years (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>), and radiotherapy-induced tumors develop within more than 5 years (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). To remove these confounding factors, we included patients who survived for at least 5 years and had an interval of 5 years or more between the two tumors. Our study showed that the patients who received RT had a higher risk of developing SLC than those who did not. We further performed a stratified analysis by stage and found that the patients with localized disease had a higher risk of SLC in the RT group than in the NRT group. Simultaneously, no difference was found between the two in the regional disease. The following subgroup analysis of the multivariate competing risk model also reflects this result. A possible explanation is that patients with localized stage have better survival and are more likely to develop SLC (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). To better illustrate these results, we used both the competitive risk model (HR = 1.35, 95% CI: 1.11&#8211;1.65; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.010) and the Poisson regression model (RR = 1.33, 95% CI: 1.09&#8211;1.60; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.015) to obtain similar results. The subgroup analysis revealed that prior RT history exhibited a higher risk of developing SLC for patients who were aged 50&#8211;69 years, white, diagnosed with squamous cell carcinoma, diagnosed with localized diseases, or had not received chemotherapy. These results are consistent with previous reports showing an increased risk of SLC secondary to RT in patients with nasopharyngeal carcinoma (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>).</p><p>In this study, we dynamically evaluated the relationship between RT and SLC according to age, year of OCC, and latency to SLC. The results showed that a higher risk of SLC in the RT group was found between the ages of 50 and 69 years, there. This phenomenon can also be observed in PLC survivors (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). It is possible that a history of smoking may increase the risk of SLC in patients who are between the ages of 50 and 69 years. Therefore, the potential mechanism should be explored. We also showed that the risk of SLC increased with more recent years of diagnosis. The most likely explanation for this is that newer RT techniques have increased the delivery time of treatments, thus increasing the exposure time to normal tissue (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Our results are inconsistent with previous reports showing no difference in the risk of secondary tumors after the update in RT techniques. However, this may be due to the short duration of radiation exposure used in the inclusion criteria (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). We also evaluated the relationship between the time of primary OCC and SLC diagnosis and demonstrated that the risk was reduced with longer follow-up. Therefore, RT-associated SLC should be given more attention for 5&#8211;10 years after RT for OCC.</p><p>We also evaluated the risk of SLC associated with RT in the general population. The results suggest that the risk increased in the general population (NRT: SIR = 2.41, range 2.22&#8211;2.61; RT: SIR = 3.07, range 2.78&#8211;3.38). Previous study also reported that there is a difference in outcome comparisons between the incidence of such speciation in the general population (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). We believe that the cause of SLC may be related to a combination of genetics, smoking, and lifestyle factors (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). In addition, the risk of finding SLC in patients with previous HNSCC was 2.5 times higher than that in those without tumors (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). In particular, tumors that have undergone curative treatment are at a higher risk of developing SLC (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). With this study, we hope to raise awareness of the problem of SLC in patients with OCC.</p><p>Many factors, such as lifestyle habits, genetic mutations, and age, may contribute to SLC. Radiation-associated secondary tumors are related to the volume and dose of radiation to surrounding organs (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). Lung cancer is the most common of these radiation-associated solid tumors (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). One possible explanation is that low doses of radiation cause DNA damage, leading to malignant transformation (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Another possible explanation is the larger volume of irradiated normal tissue in the out-of-field or scattered radiation, leading to an increased risk of secondary tumor development (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Therefore, there is a need to further investigate the mechanisms of SLC in patients surviving RT.</p><p>Propensity-score matching was performed to further explore RT-associated SLC. We found no difference in OS after SLC between the NRT and RT groups either before or after matching to SLC. However, the potential mechanism requires further investigation. In addition, we explored the OS of SLC vs. PLC and no differences were found between the two groups of patients. In addition, we explored the OS of SLC vs. PLC and found no differences between the two groups of patients. Similarly, recent data suggest that patients with SLC or PLC have a comparable OS (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>).</p><p>This study had some limitations. First, the SEER database does not record smoking status or duration, which is an important factor when considering lung cancer. Some studies have suggested an increased risk of SLC in patients with a heavy smoking history (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). There may also be an interaction between tobacco and radiation in SLC (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Conversely, other reports have shown that the risk of developing SLC was similar between smokers and never-smokers (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). Without further investigations, conclusions cannot be drawn regarding the association between the presence of SLC and smoking. Therefore, we believe that this factor had a relatively small influence on our conclusions. Second, there are limited data in the SEER database on the indication, dose, and frequency of radiation therapy, specific information on chemotherapy, and molecular information on lung cancer. Third, RT was not randomized, and some retrospective biases may have affected the risk of SLC after RT vs. NRT. Fourth, it is challenging to distinguish PLC from distant metastasis since it is not always opportune to collect tumor tissue of the lung to be compared against the primary tumor. Our results demonstrate that RT may increase the risk of SLC in patients with oral cancer, but further studies are required to answer these questions.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>5. Conclusion</title><p>RT for patients with primary OCC was associated with a higher risk of developing SLC than in those who were not exposed to RT. However, no significant difference was found in the survival of patients with OCC, SLC, and PLC. Nevertheless, we recommend 5&#8211;10 years of monitoring of the risk of SLC in patients with a history of RT for OCC.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s7"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>Publicly available datasets were analyzed in this study. This data can be found here: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.seer.cancer.gov" ext-link-type="uri">www.seer.cancer.gov</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="s8"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>All data used was based on publicly available data in the SEER database. Ethical review and approval was therefore not required for the study on human participants in accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements. The Ethics Committee waived the requirement of written informed consent for participation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s9"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Conceptualization and methodology: GL, JZ, SZ, and YX. Data analysis and writing&#8212;original draft preparation: DH and YX. Writing&#8212;review and editing: SZ and QS. Figure and table preparation: HC, PW, and QW. Supervision: GL and YX. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank the Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results Program (National Cancer Institute) for developing the SEER database. We would like to thank Editage (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.editage.cn" ext-link-type="uri">www.editage.cn</ext-link>) for English language editing.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s10"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s11"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpubh.2023.1120671/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpubh.2023.1120671/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Figure S1</label><caption><p>Flowchart of the study cohort. PSM, Propensity Score Matching.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.PDF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM2" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Figure S2</label><caption><p>Cumulative incidence and cumulative mortality of SLC between patients who received RT and those who did not receive RT.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_2.PDF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM3" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Figure S3</label><caption><p>SIR for SLC by age at diagnosis, latency, and year of OCC diagnosis.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_3.PDF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM4" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Table S1</label><caption><p>Poisson regression model for developing SLC in OCC.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_1.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM5" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Table S2</label><caption><p>Subgroup analyses of competing risk regression for the risk of developing SLC.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_2.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM6" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Table S3</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of patients with SLC in the original/matched data set.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_3.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM7" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Table S4</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of patients with SLC and matched PLC in OCC.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_4.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Current concepts in management of oral cancer surgery</article-title>. <source>Oral Oncol.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>394</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>401</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2008.05.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18674952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4130348</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stepan</surname><given-names>KO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazul</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pipkorn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puram</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Changing epidemiology of oral cavity cancer in the United States</article-title>. <source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>2022</volume>:<fpage>1945998221098011</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/01945998221098011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35503657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10154079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colombet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soerjomataram</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parkin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pi&#241;eros</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Estimating the global cancer incidence and mortality in 2018: GLOBOCAN sources and methods</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>144</volume>:<fpage>1941</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijc.31937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30350310</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ettinger</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ganry</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Oral cavity cancer</article-title>. <source>Oral Maxillofac Surg Clin North Am.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>29</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coms.2018.08.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30454788</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coca-Pelaz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigo</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su&#225;rez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#228;kitie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanabria</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The risk of second primary tumors in head and neck cancer: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Head Neck.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>456</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hed.26016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31750595</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertolini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trudu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banchelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schipilliti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Napolitano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alberici</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Second primary tumors in head and neck cancer patients: the importance of a &#8220;tailored&#8221; surveillance</article-title>. <source>Oral Dis.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1412</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/odi.13681</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33051941</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Association between postoperative radiotherapy for young-onset head and neck cancer and long-term risk of second primary malignancy: a population-based study</article-title>. <source>J Transl Med.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>405</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12967-022-03544-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36064552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9446763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heudel</surname><given-names>P-E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fervers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chabaud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michallet</surname><given-names>A-S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Second primary cancers: a retrospective analysis of real world data using the enhanced medical research engine ConSoRe in a French comprehensive cancer center</article-title>. <source>Int J Clin Oncol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>1793</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>804</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10147-021-01963-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34091824</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adjei Boakye</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinyard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osazuwa-Peters</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schootman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piccirillo</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Incidence and risk of second primary malignant neoplasm after a first head and neck squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>JAMA Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>144</volume>:<fpage>727</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaoto.2018.0993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30027284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6142994</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebadi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Govindarajan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An updated review on head and neck cancer treatment with radiation therapy</article-title>. <source>Cancers (Basel).</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>4912</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cancers13194912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34638398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8508236</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Babar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woody</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghanem</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunlap</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schymick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Outcomes of post-operative treatment with concurrent chemoradiotherapy (CRT) in high-risk resected oral cavity squamous cell carcinoma (OCSCC): a multi-institutional collaboration</article-title>. <source>Curr Oncol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>2409</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>19</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/curroncol28040221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34209302</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8293216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#246;ring</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mast</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolvius</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verduijn</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sijtsema</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Osteoradionecrosis after postoperative radiotherapy for oral cavity cancer: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Oral Oncol.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>133</volume>:<fpage>106056</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2022.106056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35933938</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Min</surname><given-names>S-K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>K-W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Won</surname><given-names>Y-J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Second primary cancers in patients with oral cavity cancer included in the Korea Central Cancer Registry</article-title>. <source>Oral Oncol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2019.05.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31345385</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohideen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emami</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Second primary cancers in patients with laryngeal cancer: a population-based study</article-title>. <source>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>427</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0360-3016(02)04613-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12738317</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maddams</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parkin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darby</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The cancer burden in the United Kingdom in 2007 due to radiotherapy</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>129</volume>:<fpage>2885</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijc.26240</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21671469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of second primary malignancies associated with radiotherapy in prostate cancer patients: competing risk analysis</article-title>. <source>Future Oncology.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>445</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/fon-2021-0332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35018785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical characteristics and risk of second primary lung cancer after cervical cancer: a population-based study</article-title>. <source>PLoS One.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>e0231807</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0231807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32756555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7406086</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Second primary malignancies associated with radiation therapy in cervical cancer patients diagnosed between 1975 and 2011: a population-based competing-risk study</article-title>. <source>Ann Transl Med.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1375</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/atm-21-1393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34733927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8506544</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A population-based analysis of mucoepidermoid carcinoma of the oral cavity</article-title>. <source>Laryngoscope.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>131</volume>:<fpage>E857</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.28905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32692861</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adjei Boakye</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinyard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stamatakis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osazuwa-Peters</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk and outcomes for second primary human papillomavirus-related and -unrelated head and neck malignancy</article-title>. <source>Laryngoscope.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>129</volume>:<fpage>1828</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.27634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30582167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tammem&#228;gi</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plevritis</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk stratification for second primary lung cancer</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>2893</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/jco.2017.72.4203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28644772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5946715</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of radiotherapy for rectal cancer and second gynecological malignant neoplasms</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e2031661</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.31661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33416884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7794669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Is lobectomy superior to sub-lobectomy in non-small cell lung cancer with pleural invasion? A population-based competing risk analysis</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>541</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12885-022-09634-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35562694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9102677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between preadmission metformin use and outcomes in intensive care unit patients with sepsis and type 2 diabetes: a cohort study</article-title>. <source>Front Med.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>640785</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2021.640785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33855034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8039324</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between wait time for transthoracic echocardiography and 28-day mortality in patients with septic shock: a cohort study</article-title>. <source>J Clin Med.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>4131</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm11144131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35887895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9321017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>LQM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Head and neck cancer</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>382</volume>:<fpage>60</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>72</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra1715715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31893516</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arsanjani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liem</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffelt</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>KRJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Second malignancies in early stage laryngeal carcinoma patients treated with radiotherapy</article-title>. <source>J Laryngol Otol.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>116</volume>:<fpage>190</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1258/0022215021910500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11893260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Gonzalez</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kry</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamart</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Proportion of second cancers attributable to radiotherapy treatment in adults: a cohort study in the US SEER cancer registries</article-title>. <source>Lancet Oncol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>353</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1470-2045(11)70061-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21454129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3086738</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farhadieh</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>CGG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salardini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smee</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Radiotherapy in larynx squamous cell carcinoma is not associated with an increased diagnosis of second primary tumours</article-title>. <source>Clin Oncol (R Coll Radiol).</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>315</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clon.2009.01.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19233627</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#246;derholm</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pukkala</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindqvist</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teppo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of new primary cancer in patients with oropharyngeal cancer</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer.</source> (<year>1994</year>) <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>784</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/bjc.1994.148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8142267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1968814</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garavello</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciardo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spreafico</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaini</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for distant metastases in head and neck squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>132</volume>:<fpage>762</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archotol.132.7.762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16847186</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kadowaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oze</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masuishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Narita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bando</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of second primary malignancies after definitive treatment for esophageal cancer: a competing risk analysis</article-title>. <source>Cancer Med.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>394</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>400</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cam4.2688</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31730285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6943156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Second primary malignancies in patients with colorectal cancer: a population-based analysis</article-title>. <source>Oncologist.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>e644</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1634/theoncologist.2019-0266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31943509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7160402</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>JCH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>AHP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>K-M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>VHF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>C-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Second primary cancer after intensity-modulated radiotherapy for nasopharyngeal carcinoma: a territory-wide study by HKNPCSG</article-title>. <source>Oral Oncol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>111</volume>:<fpage>105012</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2020.105012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32980659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nien</surname><given-names>H-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>L-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>P-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shueng</surname><given-names>P-W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Advances in image-guided radiotherapy in the treatment of oral cavity cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancers (Basel).</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>4630</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cancers14194630</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36230553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9561985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazonakis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Damilakis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Out-of-field organ doses and associated risk of cancer development following radiation therapy with photons</article-title>. <source>Phys Med.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>73</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejmp.2021.09.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34563834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pollom</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Second cancer risk after primary cancer treatment with three-dimensional conformal, intensity-modulated, or proton beam radiation therapy</article-title>. <source>Cancer.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>126</volume>:<fpage>3560</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cncr.32938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32426866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adjei Boakye</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osazuwa-Peters</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of second primary cancers in individuals diagnosed with index smoking- and non-smoking- related cancers</article-title>. <source>J Cancer Res Clin Oncol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>146</volume>:<fpage>1765</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>79</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00432-020-03232-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32356175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11804670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aredo</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanyal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Tobacco smoking and risk of second primary lung cancer</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Oncol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>968</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>79</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtho.2021.02.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33722709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8159872</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grantzau</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomsen</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>V&#230;th</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Overgaard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of second primary lung cancer in women after radiotherapy for breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Radiother Oncol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>111</volume>:<fpage>366</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.radonc.2014.05.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24909095</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grauer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sukari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagasaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Incidence of second primary lung cancer after low-dose computed tomography vs chest radiography screening in survivors of head and neck cancer: a secondary analysis of a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>147</volume>:<fpage>1071</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaoto.2021.2776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34709369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8554690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crippen</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eloy</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baredes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>RCW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Second primary lung malignancy following head and neck squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Laryngoscope.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>129</volume>:<fpage>903</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.27422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30565703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#246;rr</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer induction by radiotherapy: dose dependence and spatial relationship to irradiated volume</article-title>. <source>J Radiol Prot.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>A117</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/0952-4746/22/3a/321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12400959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Second malignant neoplasms following radiotherapy</article-title>. <source>IJERPH.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>4744</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph9124744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23249860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3546788</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tubiana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Can we reduce the incidence of second primary malignancies occurring after radiotherapy? A critical review</article-title>. <source>Radiother Oncol.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>91</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.radonc.2008.12.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19201045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Varlotto</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Voland</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeCamp</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rava</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maxfield</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The rates of second lung cancers and the survival of surgically-resected second primary lung cancers in patients undergoing resection of an initial primary lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Lung Cancer.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>147</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lungcan.2020.07.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32688194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>She</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Z-Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>C-X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>S-X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F-Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical characteristics and survival of lung cancer patients associated with multiple primary malignancies</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e0185485</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0185485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28957405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5619777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tandberg</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chino</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Amico</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ready</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelsey</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Smoking history predicts for increased risk of second primary lung cancer: a comprehensive analysis</article-title>. <source>Cancer.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>121</volume>:<fpage>598</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>604</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cncr.29095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25283893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ripley</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sima</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Second primary lung cancers: smokers v. nonsmokers after resection of stage I lung adenocarcinoma</article-title>. <source>Ann Thorac Surg.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>968</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.athoracsur.2014.04.098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25038021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4410355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farhat</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hotaling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raza</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>African American race as a risk factor associated with a second primary lung cancer after initial primary head and neck cancer</article-title>. <source>Head Neck.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>2069</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hed.27107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35713967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9543059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>