<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="case-report" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1900</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">dermather</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Dermatology and Therapy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2193-8210</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2190-9172</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10307742</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10307742.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10307742</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10307742</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37266889</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13555-023-00940-0</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">940</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Case of Concurrent Psoriasis and Hidradenitis Suppurativa Successfully Treated with Tildrakizumab</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Damsin</surname><given-names initials="T">Thomas</given-names></name><address><email>th.damsin@chuliege.be</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411374.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8607 6858</institution-id><institution>Department of Dermatology, </institution><institution>CHU du Sart Tilman, </institution></institution-wrap>Avenue de L&#8217;H&#244;pital 1, 4000 Li&#232;ge, Belgium </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>7</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>7</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">439433</issue-id><fpage>1611</fpage><lpage>1615</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>02</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>30</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-06-30 02:25:10.167"><day>30</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="13555_2023_Article_940.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par1">Plaque psoriasis and hidradenitis suppurativa are chronic inflammatory skin conditions with common pathogenetic pathways.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">We report the case of a 38-year-old man with 15-year history of psoriasis and hidradenitis suppurativa successfully treated with tildrakizumab for both conditions. After treatment failure to adalimumab, secukinumab, and guselkumab, tildrakizumab therapy was initiated and resulted in complete remission of psoriasis and the achievement of hidradenitis suppurativa clinical response after 40&#160;weeks, without reporting adverse events. These responses were maintained at week 52.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par3">Tildrakizumab may be an effective and safe therapeutic option for concomitant psoriasis and hidradenitis suppurativa.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Case report</kwd><kwd>Hidradenitis suppurativa</kwd><kwd>Psoriasis</kwd><kwd>Tildrakizumab</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Almirall R&amp;D, Barcelona, Spain</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; Springer Healthcare Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2023</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="d32e239"><title>Key Summary Points</title><p id="Par4">
<table-wrap id="Taba" position="float" orientation="portrait"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A case of concomitant psoriasis and hidradenitis suppurativa previously unresponsive to the standard treatment is described.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tildrakizumab therapy was initiated after treatment failure to adalimumab, the only biologic approved for the treatment of moderate-to-severe hidradenitis suppurativa, secukinumab, and guselkumab.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">To the best of our knowledge, this is the first reported case on successful treatment of concomitant psoriasis and hidradenitis suppurativa with tildrakizumab.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Further studies in larger cohorts are required to establish conclusions that can be applied to patients with concurrent psoriasis and hidradenitis suppurativa in clinical practice.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">Both plaque psoriasis and hidradenitis suppurativa are chronic inflammatory skin diseases sharing risk factors, such as obesity or cigarette smoking, and inflammatory mediators, including tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-&#945;) or the interleukin (IL)-12/IL-23, and IL-17 pathways, which has been the rationale for selective targeting of these inflammatory pathways using biologics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Furthermore, a positive association has been observed between psoriasis and hidradenitis suppurativa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], and the co-occurrence of both diseases significantly impacts on patient quality of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">Tildrakizumab is an IL-23p19 inhibitor approved for the treatment of moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis with demonstrated long-term effectiveness and a favorable safety profile [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. We present a case of treatment response to tildrakizumab in a patient with psoriasis and hidradenitis suppurativa previously unresponsive to standard therapies.</p><p id="Par345">As this is a single case report, ethics committee approval was not required. All procedures followed were in accordance with the Helsinki Declaration of 1964 and its later amendments. The patient in this manuscript has given written informed consent to publication of his case details and images.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Case report</title><p id="Par7">A 38-year-old man was referred to our dermatology department for the first time in August 2018 (at the age of 33&#160;years) with two inflammatory dermatoses evolving concomitantly since 2008 (when he was 23&#160;years old): severe plaque psoriasis and severe hidradenitis suppurativa. His medical history included schizophrenia (since age 16&#160;years) and surgery for lumbar disk herniation. The patient was receiving daily treatment with olanzapine and zuclopenthixol for schizophrenia. The patient&#8217;s weight was 117&#160;kg, and his height was 183&#160;cm. Thus, his body mass index was 34.9&#160;kg/m<sup>2</sup>, fulfilling the criteria for obesity. He had smoked 1&#8211;2 packs of cigarettes per day since he was 14&#160;years and had excessive alcohol consumption (50&#160;g/day).</p><p id="Par8">Previous treatments for psoriasis, including topical corticosteroids and psoralen plus ultraviolet A irradiation, and previous treatments for hidradenitis suppurativa, including oral lymecycline and combined antibiotic therapy with clindamycin and rifampicin, were not effective. The patient had also been treated with the TNF-&#945; inhibitor adalimumab (40&#160;mg per week given by subcutaneous injection) for 6&#160;months without clinical improvement in hidradenitis suppurativa, although good control of psoriasis was achieved (&#8805;&#8201;90% improvement in Psoriasis Area and Severity Index [PASI]).</p><p id="Par9">In August 2018, the patient started treatment with methotrexate (15&#160;mg/week), with poor results on either psoriasis or hidradenitis suppurativa. Hence, treatment with an IL-17 inhibitor (secukinumab) was initiated in October 2018, after monitoring of fecal calprotectin levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Subcutaneous secukinumab 300&#160;mg was administered every week for 5&#160;weeks (induction phase) followed by 300&#160;mg every 4&#160;weeks. In January 2019, although the psoriasis was controlled, secukinumab treatment was switched to the IL-23p19 inhibitor guselkumab owing to worsening of hidradenitis suppurativa symptoms. Guselkumab 100&#160;mg was administered by subcutaneous injection at weeks 0 and 4, followed by a maintenance dose every 6&#160;weeks with a 50% improvement in the overall disease condition until January 2022, when the patient had a treatment failure of hidradenitis suppurativa, presenting skin lesions on both right and left axillary and inguinal regions, with a Hurley stage of 2 and a Hidradenitis Suppurativa-Physician Global Assessment (HS-PGA) score of 4 (i.e., severe) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. His abscess and inflammatory nodule count was 13 (3 abscesses and 10 inflammatory nodules), and his draining fistula count was 2 (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Hidradenitis suppurativa lesions in the right axillary region of patient before treatment with tildrakizumab</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13555_2023_940_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par10">In February 2022, guselkumab treatment was switched to 200&#160;mg of subcutaneous tildrakizumab every 12&#160;weeks after the initial loading dose at weeks 0 and 4. At week 40, the Hidradenitis Suppurativa Clinical Response (HiSCR) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] was achieved, with an abscess and nodule count of 4 (4 inflammatory nodules) and without any draining fistula. The Hurley stage was 2, and the HS-PGA score was reduced to 2 (i.e., mild) (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). A complete remission of psoriasis was also observed at week 40, with the patient achieving a PASI 100 response. These responses were maintained at week 52. No adverse events were reported during the 52-week treatment period.<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Hidradenitis suppurativa lesions in the right axillary region of the patient after 40&#160;weeks of treatment with tildrakizumab</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13555_2023_940_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par11">We present herein the case of a patient with concomitant psoriasis and hidradenitis suppurativa. Hidradenitis suppurativa is a highly stigmatizing inflammatory disease whose pathogenesis is not fully understood, although IL-23 cytokine pathway may be involved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The IL-23 axis is also implicated in the pathogenesis of psoriasis, which was reported to be associated with hidradenitis suppurativa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. In fact, it is estimated that 6% of patients with hidradenitis suppurativa also suffer from psoriasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p><p id="Par12">The patient presented herein was initially treated with adalimumab, the only biologic approved for the treatment of moderate-to-severe hidradenitis suppurativa, and the IL-17 inhibitor secukinumab, which has recently been proved to be clinically effective in two phase III trials involving patients with moderate-to-severe hidradenitis suppurativa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. However, after 3&#160;months, the treatment was switched to the IL-23p19 inhibitor guselkumab, owing to lack of efficacy, and both diseases improved drastically. Of note, clinical response to IL-23 antagonism in hidradenitis suppurativa has recently been found to be associated with male gender [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Despite the long-term control with guselkumab for 3&#160;years, the treatment was switched to tildrakizumab 200&#160;mg, owing to a relapse of hidradenitis suppurativa. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first reported case on successful use of tildrakizumab to treat concomitant psoriasis and hidradenitis suppurativa, with the patient achieving HiSCR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] and PASI 100 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] responses after only four tildrakizumab doses. These results suggest that clinical effect of IL-23p19 inhibitors might be influenced by genetic background or gene interactions, showing a different effect depending on the anti-IL-23p19 agent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], although the use of a higher dose (200&#160;mg) could also play a role. Nine cases of hidradenitis suppurativa successfully treated with off-label use of tildrakizumab have been described in literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], and there is also one mention of the use of tildrakizumab as an effective treatment option in patients with PASH syndrome, which is characterized by the presence of pyoderma gangrenosum, acne, and hidradenitis suppurativa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par13">Tildrakizumab 200&#160;mg may be a safe and effective alternative for patients with concurrent hidradenitis suppurativa and psoriasis even when patients switched from another IL-23p19. More studies in a larger cohort of patients are needed to validate these results.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank the patient for agreeing to publication of his case.</p><sec id="FPar2"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par14">Sponsorship for this publication and Rapid Service Fee were funded by Almirall R&amp;D, Barcelona, Spain.</p></sec><sec id="FPar1"><title>Medical Writing and Editorial Assistance</title><p id="Par15">Editorial assistance in the preparation of this article was provided by Eva Mateu, PhD of TFS HealthScience. Support for this assistance was funded by Almirall R&amp;D, Barcelona, Spain.</p></sec><sec id="d32e414"><title>Author Contributions</title><p id="Par16">Thomas Damsin confirms sole responsibility for the conception of the work and acquisition of data. He revised the work critically for important intellectual content and approved the version to be published.</p></sec><sec id="d32e419" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Disclosures</title><p id="Par17">Thomas Damsin has no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p></sec><sec id="d32e424"><title>Compliance with Ethics Guidelines</title><p id="Par18">As this is a single case report, ethics committee approval was not required. All procedures followed were in accordance with the Helsinki Declaration of 1964 and its later amendments. The patient in this manuscript has given written informed consent to publication of his case details and images.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p id="Par19">Data sharing not applicable to this article as no datasets were generated or analysed.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vossen</surname><given-names>ARJV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Zee</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prens</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hidradenitis suppurativa: a systematic review integrating inflammatory pathways into a cohesive pathogenic model</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>2965</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2018.02965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30619323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6302105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kridin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schonmann</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shalom</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Comaneshter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Psoriasis and hidradenitis suppurativa: a large-scale population-based study</article-title><source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source><year>2018</year><volume>S0190&#8211;9622</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>32962</fpage><lpage>32971</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jaad.2018.11.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30502412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merola</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qureshi</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vleugels</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of concomitant psoriasis and hidradenitis suppurativa (HS): experience of a tertiary medical center</article-title><source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source><year>2015</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>701</fpage><lpage>702</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2015.06.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26369843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gau S-Y, Preclaro IAC, Wei JC-C, Lee C-Y, Kuan Y-H, Hsiao Y-P, et al. Risk of psoriasis in people with hidradenitis suppurativa: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Frot Immunol. 2022;13:1033844.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2022.1033844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9752046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36532043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tha&#231;i</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piaserico</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantrell</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Draelos</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Five-year efficacy and safety of tildrakizumab in patients with moderate to severe psoriasis who respond at week 28: pooled analyses of two randomised phase 3 clinical trials (reSURFACE 1 and reSURFACE 2)</article-title><source>Br J Dermatol</source><year>2021</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>334</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bjd.19866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33544883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsianakas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwichtenberg</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierchalla</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diemert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Korge</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Real-world effectiveness and safety of tildrakizumab in long-term treatment of plaque psoriasis: Results from the non-interventional, prospective, multicentre study TILOT</article-title><source>J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol</source><year>2023</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jdv.18572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36066998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10087575</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Brizzi</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Babino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buononato</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Argenziano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the role of faecal calprotectin in the management of psoriatic patients under treatment with biologic drugs</article-title><source>Biomedicines</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2968</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biomedicines10112968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36428539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9687727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alikhan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sayed</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alhusayen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brassard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burkhart</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>North American clinical management guidelines for hidradenitis suppurativa: a publication from the United States and Canadian hidradenitis suppurativa foundations: part i: diagnosis, evaluation, and the use of complementary and procedural management</article-title><source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source><year>2019</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2019.02.067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30872156</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9131894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amat-Samaranch</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agut-Busquet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilarrasa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New perspectives on the treatment of hidradenitis suppurativa</article-title><source>Ther Adv Chronic Dis</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>20406223211055920</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/20406223211055920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34840709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8613896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimball</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jemec</surname><given-names>GBE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kageleiry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Signorovitch</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okun</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessing the validity, responsiveness and meaningfulness of the Hidradenitis Suppurativa Clinical Response (HiSCR) as the clinical endpoint for hidradenitis suppurativa treatment</article-title><source>Br J Dermatol</source><year>2014</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>1434</fpage><lpage>1442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bjd.13270</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25040429</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimball</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sobell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zouboulis</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sundaram</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HiSCR (Hidradenitis Suppurativa Clinical Response): a novel clinical endpoint to evaluate therapeutic outcomes in patients with hidradenitis suppurativa from the placebo-controlled portion of a phase 2 adalimumab study</article-title><source>J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol</source><year>2016</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>989</fpage><lpage>994</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jdv.13216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26201313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5034809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kokolakis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rech</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biermann</surname><given-names>MHC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#228;berle</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Multmeier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hidradenitis suppurativa and concurrent psoriasis: comparison of epidemiology, comorbidity profiles, and risk factors</article-title><source>Dermatol Ther</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>721</fpage><lpage>734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13555-020-00401-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7367943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32500484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimball</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jemec</surname><given-names>GBE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reguiai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bechara</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Secukinumab in moderate-to-severe hidradenitis suppurativa (SUNSHINE and SUNRISE): week 16 and week 52 results of two identical, multicentre, randomised, placebo-controlled, double-blind phase 3 trials</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2023</year><volume>401</volume><fpage>747</fpage><lpage>761</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(23)00022-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36746171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Flora A, Kozera EK, Jepsen R, Gill K, Xu J, Frew JW. Baseline clinical, hormonal and molecular markers associated with clinical response to IL-23 antagonism in hidradenitis suppurativa: a prospective cohort study. Exp Dermatol. 2023;Online ahead of print.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/exd.14789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36933897</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Balak</surname><given-names>DMW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez-Chada</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mita</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Definitions of remission in psoriasis: a systematic literature review from the National Psoriasis Foundation</article-title><source>J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol</source><year>2022</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>2291</fpage><lpage>2300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jdv.18477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35924437</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjaersgaard Andersen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clemmensen</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hjelmborg</surname><given-names>JVB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#216;dum</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jemec</surname><given-names>GBE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evidence of gene-gene interaction in hidradenitis suppurativa: a nationwide registry study of Danish twins</article-title><source>Br J Dermatol</source><year>2022</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bjd.20654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34289077</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kok</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolopoulos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varigos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolianitis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tildrakizumab in the treatment of moderate-to-severe hidradenitis suppurativa</article-title><source>Australas J Dermatol</source><year>2020</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>e488</fpage><lpage>e490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ajd.13377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32627843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kok</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolopoulos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolianitis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tildrakizumab as a potential long-term therapeutic agent for severe Hidradenitis Suppurativa: A 15 months experience of an Australian institution</article-title><source>Australas J Dermatol</source><year>2021</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>e313</fpage><lpage>e316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ajd.13559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33729553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kok</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolopoulos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varigos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolianitis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tildrakizumab in the treatment of PASH syndrome: A potential novel therapeutic target</article-title><source>Australas J Dermatol</source><year>2020</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>e373</fpage><lpage>e374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ajd.13285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32285437</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>