<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">ERJ Open Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">ERJ Open Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3083</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">erjor</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ERJOR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>ERJ Open Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2312-0541</issn><publisher><publisher-name>European Respiratory Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12208605</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12208605.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12208605</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12208605</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40589911</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/23120541.00869-2024</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">00869-2024</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="VoR">Version of Record</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research Article</subject><subj-group><subject>Asthma</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>2</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Treatment choice for adult patients with moderate-to-severe asthma: the TAILOR study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8797-0883</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeannetot</surname><given-names initials="D">Daniel</given-names></name><xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Ridder</surname><given-names initials="M">Maria</given-names></name><xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9301-8565</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Mosseveld</surname><given-names initials="M">Mees</given-names></name><xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names initials="L">Lars</given-names></name><xref rid="af2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lapi</surname><given-names initials="F">Francesco</given-names></name><xref rid="af3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marconi</surname><given-names initials="E">Ettore</given-names></name><xref rid="af3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4470-2736</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names initials="EH">Eng Hooi</given-names></name><xref rid="af4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0388-3403</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Delmestri</surname><given-names initials="A">Antonella</given-names></name><xref rid="af4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prieto-Alhambra</surname><given-names initials="D">Daniel</given-names></name><xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="af4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Der Deijl</surname><given-names initials="M">Marielle</given-names></name><xref rid="af5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7021-8505</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Brusselle</surname><given-names initials="G">Guy</given-names></name><xref rid="af6" ref-type="aff">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8162-4904</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Verhamme</surname><given-names initials="K">Katia</given-names></name><xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1"><label>1</label>Department of Medical Informatics, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands</aff><aff id="af2"><label>2</label>Department of Clinical Epidemiology, Aarhus University, Aarhus, Denmark</aff><aff id="af3"><label>3</label>SIMG &#8211; Italian College of General Practitioners and Primary Care, Florence, Italy</aff><aff id="af4"><label>4</label>Centre for Statistics in Medicine, Nuffield Department of Orthopaedics, Rheumatology and Musculoskeletal Sciences, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK</aff><aff id="af5"><label>5</label>Global Medical Affairs, Chiesi Farmaceutici, S.p.A, Parma, Italy</aff><aff id="af6"><label>6</label>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Ghent University Hospital, Ghent, Belgium</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author: Daniel Jeannetot (<email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="d.jeannetot@erasmusmc.nl">d.jeannetot@erasmusmc.nl</email>)
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">488021</issue-id><elocation-id>00869-2024</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>02</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>30</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>30</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-07-01 16:25:31.627"><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169;The authors 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This version is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Licence 4.0. For commercial reproduction rights and permissions contact <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mailto:permissions@ersnet.org">permissions@ersnet.org</email></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="00869-2024.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>In patients with uncontrolled asthma treated with medium dose inhaled corticosteroid/long-acting &#946;<sub>2</sub>-agonist (ICS/LABA), the Global Initiative for Asthma (GINA) recommends to increase to high-dose ICS/LABA or to start therapy consisting of medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA (long-acting muscarinic antagonist). Adding LAMA on top of high-dose ICS/LABA is not recommended for Step 4 asthma patients, yet it is used in the real world. Patient characteristics influencing treatment step-up are unknown. The objectives of the present study were to identify determinants of step-up option (high-dose ICS/LABA, medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA, high-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA) in patients with moderate to severe asthma.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>A retrospective cohort study using three primary care databases (IPCI, HSD, CPRD GOLD) and one prescription database (Aarhus) included asthma patients with step-up after &#8805;3&#8197;months use of medium-dose ICS/LABA, from January 2010 to April 2020. Characteristics of patients were described, and determinants of choice for medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA or high dose ICS/LABA were investigated.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>492&#8201;639 adults with asthma and &#8805;1&#8197;year of database history were identified and 25&#8201;558 were eligible for analysis. 6126 patients stepped-up to medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA and 18&#8201;947 patients stepped-up to high-dose ICS/LABA. Determinants for step-up to medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA were higher age and presence of COPD whereas history of atopy lowered this choice. Other covariates were differentially associated with specific treatment step-up depending on the databases.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>In uncontrolled asthma patients on medium-dose ICS/LABA, treatment step-up with add-on LAMA was more likely than step-up to high-dose ICS/LABA in older patients, current smokers, with a history of asthma exacerbations and concomitant diagnosis of COPD.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="short" id="abstract-1"><title id="title-1">Shareable abstract</title><p><bold>This study describes asthma treatment, including combinations not in GINA guidelines. Implications for asthma treatment are important and given the large population and multicountry set up, the findings are robust and generalisable.</bold>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://bit.ly/3ZF1Z0K" ext-link-type="uri">https://bit.ly/3ZF1Z0K</ext-link></p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Asthma is a chronic respiratory condition affecting 300&#8211;400 million people worldwide [<xref rid="C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. It is a cause of disability, resource utilisation, reduced quality of life and is currently incurable. Asthma can generally be controlled through treatment as described by existing asthma management guidelines [<xref rid="C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Real-world surveys among asthmatic patients indicate that the incidence of asthma exacerbations is higher than in clinical trials [<xref rid="C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. These exacerbations are associated with increased mortality and healthcare costs, and decreased quality of life [<xref rid="C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p>Inhaled corticosteroids (ICS) are the cornerstone of asthma treatment. In some patients, additional medication is required to prevent exacerbations. The preferred add-on medication in asthmatic patients is a long-acting &#946;<sub>2</sub>-agonist (LABA). Other options are leukotriene receptor antagonists (LTRA) or long-acting muscarinic antagonists (LAMA).</p><p>In patients treated with medium-dose ICS/LABA whose asthma remains uncontrolled, Global Initiative for Asthma (GINA) recommends to either increase to high-dose ICS/LABA or to start therapy consisting of medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA [<xref rid="C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Although adding LAMA on top of high-dose ICS/LABA is only recommended by GINA in severe asthma (GINA treatment step 5), it is likely that this treatment regimen is also prescribed in real-world settings in patients with non-severe asthma.</p><p>Randomised controlled trials (RCTs) investigating the efficacy of a fixed combination of ICS/LABA+LAMA (triple therapy) in patients with asthma have demonstrated that triple therapy (in comparison to dual therapy of ICS/LABA) improves lung function and reduces the risk of severe asthma exacerbations (SAEs) [<xref rid="C5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. A <italic toggle="yes">post hoc</italic> analysis of two phase 3 RCTs has reported that the addition of LAMA to ICS/LABA may be particularly beneficial compared to ICS/LABA alone in a phenotype of asthma patients with persistent airflow limitation, defined by post-bronchodilator forced expiratory volume in 1&#8197;s (FEV<sub>1</sub>) &#8804;80% of predicted normal, and a post-bronchodilator FEV<sub>1</sub>/forced vital capacity (FVC) ratio &#8804;0.7 [<xref rid="C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>Currently, real world evidence is lacking on which patients would benefit most by stepping up from medium-dose ICS/LABA to high-dose ICS/LABA and which patients would benefit most from triple therapy.</p><p>The objectives of this study were to quantify the absolute and relative number of asthma patients in the different treatment step-up scenarios and to identify the main determinants of which treatment step-up was chosen (high-dose ICS/LABA, medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA, high-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA). This analysis was performed using real world data from four electronic health record (EHR) databases.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Setting</title><p>We conducted a retrospective cohort study using EHR data from four databases, each from a different European country. Three primary care databases were used: IPCI (the Netherlands) [<xref rid="C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], HSD (Italy) [<xref rid="C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and CPRD GOLD [<xref rid="C9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] (UK) and one prescription database from Aarhus (Denmark) [<xref rid="C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The databases represent between 3% and 13% of the total population of the respective countries. The total patient population represented by the aggregation of the databases accounts for &#8764;15 million individuals. Each database is representative of the country-specific population. All the participating databases are part of the EU-ADR Alliance (Exploring and Understanding Adverse Drug Reactions by Integrative Mining of Clinical Records and Biomedical Knowledge), comply with the European Union guidelines on the use of medical data for medical research and have been validated for pharmaco-epidemiological research. More information on the different databases is provided in the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://publications.ersnet.org/lookup/doi/10.1183/23120541.00869-2024#supplementary" ext-link-type="uri">supplementary material</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Study period</title><p>The study period was from 1 January 2010 to 1 April 2020. For Aarhus, data were available from 1 January 2010 to 31 December 2016.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Study population and inclusion criteria</title><p>The study population consisted of patients 18&#8197;years of age or older, with at least 1&#8197;year of database history and a diagnosis or treatment code for asthma before (<italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic> prevalent asthma) or during the study period (<italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic> incident asthma). We next identified patients stepping up treatment from medium-dose ICS/LABA to one of three options during the study period:
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>high-dose ICS/LABA</p></list-item><list-item><p>medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA</p></list-item><list-item><p>high-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA</p></list-item></list>Regarding the two triple therapy options, this could consist of a fixed combination of all three ingredients or the fixed combination of ICS/LABA with another inhaler of LAMA on top. To fulfil the inclusion criteria for this study, the total length of exposure periods of medium-dose ICS/LABA in the year prior to treatment step-up had to be at least 90&#8197;days; the window between the treatment end date of medium-dose ICS/LABA and treatment step-up had to be &lt;60&#8197;days.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Exposure to respiratory drugs and treatment step-up</title><p>Prescriptions for respiratory drugs were extracted through an automatic search on ATC codes [<xref rid="C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] of the drugs of interest. From individual prescriptions, episodes of use were created accounting for potential overlap and gaps. If the subsequent prescription overlapped the previous prescription, the two prescriptions were combined into one episode and the stop date of that episode was the stop date of the second prescription. In case of a gap of &lt;60&#8197;days between two prescriptions, prescriptions were also combined into one episode. For all prescriptions of fixed ICS/LABA combination, the daily dose was calculated based on strength and dosing information and prescriptions were labelled as medium-dose ICS or high-dose ICS using GINA classification [<xref rid="C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. For Denmark, dosing was derived from the pattern of subsequent dispensing. The data encompasses both the use of two separate inhalers (ICS/LABA+LAMA) and single triple inhaler (ICS/LABA/LAMA).</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Other covariates</title><p>The following covariates were used: age, sex, body mass index (BMI), smoking status (current, past, none or status unknown), number of SAEs in the previous year, spirometry, comorbidity, primary care visits, use of SABA and/or oral corticosteroids (OCS), and lab measurements (serum total immunoglobulin E (IgE) and blood eosinophil count). Age at asthma onset was based on age at first asthma diagnosis recorded in the databases, categorised into childhood onset (age below 18&#8197;years), adult onset (age 18&#8211;39&#8197;years) and late onset (age 40&#8197;years and older).</p><p>A severe asthma exacerbation was defined as acute use of systemic corticosteroids, or an emergency department visit or hospitalisation for reasons of asthma. Acute use of systemic corticosteroids was defined as use of oral steroids for a duration of minimum 3&#8197;days and maximum 30&#8197;days or use of parenteral steroids [<xref rid="C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>Comorbidities assessed in the complete history prior to the index date were atopy (allergic rhinitis, atopic eczema/dermatitis), chronic rhinosinusitis, nasal polyposis, gastro-oesophageal reflux disease (GERD), depression and anxiety, overweight and obesity (based on disease codes and/or BMI values) and diabetes mellitus. To assess diabetes mellitus and anxiety/depression, we used presence of disease codes and current or previous use of antidiabetic drugs or use of anxiolytics and antidepressants respectively. Healthcare resource usage was measured using the number of GP office visits (excluding phone calls for prescription renewal) and home visits in the year prior to start of treatment step-up. Finally, the Charlson Comorbidity Index (CCI) at time of treatment step-up was calculated [<xref rid="C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Statistical methods</title><p>Each database was analysed separately. Descriptive statistics were used to describe numbers, proportions, medians and interquartile range of characteristics in the three different treatment step-up groups. To investigate the drivers of step-up treatment choice, a binary logistic regression model for outcome &#8220;step-up treatment medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA&#8221; <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> &#8220;high-dose ICS/LABA&#8221; was fitted. Drivers of treatment step-up to high-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA could not be investigated because of low numbers in this group. As data on blood eosinophils, IgE, BMI and spirometry were often missing, imputation for these variables was not possible and it was decided not to include them in the model. The following variables were included: sex, age, smoking status, age at asthma onset, comorbidities and CCI, and number of SAEs, number of GP visits and number of rescue medications (SABA and short-term OCS for indication asthma exacerbation) in the previous year. Because of the high correlation between number of SAEs and number of short-term OCS prescriptions, only the first was used for modelling. In each of the four databases, we applied backward step regression to the starting covariate group of the above variables. After completing this training, we created a uniform model and applied this in each database individually. This contained all variables selected in the first step. Finally, we conducted a meta-analysis on risk factors of treatment step-up to medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> high-dose ICS/LABA.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Characteristics</title><p>During the study period, 492&#8201;639 adult patients with asthma and with at least 1&#8197;year of database history were identified: 169&#8201;840 (34.5%) in IPCI, 16&#8201;419 (3.3%) in Aarhus, 48&#8201;797 (9.9%) in HSD and 257&#8201;583 (52.3%) in CPRD GOLD.</p><p>Within this cohort we identified the first episode of treatment step-up in asthma patients treated with medium dose ICS+LABA (for at least 90&#8197;days in the 1&#8197;year prior). A maximum of 60&#8197;days was allowed between the end of treatment with medium-dose ICS/LABA and the treatment step-up regimen. There were 6126 patients who stepped up to medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA (1098 IPCI, 93 Aarhus, 528 HSD and 4407 CPRD), and 18&#8201;947 patients who stepped-up to high-dose ICS/LABA (2218 IPCI, 541 Aarhus, 1243 HSD and 14&#8201;945 CPRD). The number of individuals who stepped up to high-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA was low in all four databases (60 in IPCI, &lt;5 in Aarhus, 57 in HSD and 338 in CPRD GOLD).</p><p>Characteristics of individuals in the different treatment step-up cohorts are described in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://publications.ersnet.org/lookup/doi/10.1183/23120541.00869-2024#supplementary" ext-link-type="uri">supplementary table S2</ext-link>. In all cohorts, the proportion of females was higher. The high-dose ICS/LABA cohorts had the lowest mean age across databases: from 45.6&#8197;years (Aarhus) to 47.8&#8197;years (HSD). For those individuals where information on smoking status was available, the proportion of current smokers was lower for the high-dose ICS/LABA treatment step-up compared to medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA: 24.0% <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> 36.1% in IPCI; 24.4% <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> 39.4% in Aarhus; 25.1% <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> 49% in CPRD; and 43.1% <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> 50.1% in HSD.</p><p>The proportion of patients without a history of SAEs in the year prior to treatment step-up was the highest for Aarhus (62&#8211;83%) and was 32&#8211;71% for IPCI, 46&#8211;59% for HSD and 40&#8211;53% for CPRD GOLD. This proportion was the highest for the high-dose ICS/LABA exposure cohort in all databases.</p><p>Comorbidities are summarised in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>, showing the highest prevalences for obesity/overweight, anxiety/depression, GERD and atopy with notable differences between databases for the two main categories of treatment. Comparing treated step-up cohorts, a notable difference was observed for COPD with much larger prevalence for those exposure cohorts containing LAMA compared to the high-dose ICS/LABA cohort.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Prevalence of underlying comorbidity at time of treatment. Database locations: Aarhus (Denmark), CPRD (United Kingdom), HSD (Italy), IPCI (Netherlands). y-axis differs per comorbidity. GERD: gastro-oesophageal reflux disease; ICS: inhaled corticosteroid; LABA: long-acting &#946;<sub>2</sub>-agonist; LAMA: long-acting muscarinic antagonist.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="00869-2024.01.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Determinants of choice of treatment step-up</title><p>Multivariate logistic regression showed that the main determinants for treatment step-up to medium-dose ICS/LAMA+LAMA (<italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> high-dose ICS/LABA) were age and comorbid COPD, whereas atopy (<italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic> history of allergic rhinitis and/or atopic dermatitis) reduced this probability. Other covariates (CCI, GERD, number of SABA prescriptions, number of SAEs and smoking status) were associated with medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA as type of treatment step-up in some databases (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://publications.ersnet.org/lookup/doi/10.1183/23120541.00869-2024#supplementary" ext-link-type="uri">supplementary table S3</ext-link>).</p><p>Results from the meta-analysis showed that (older) age, COPD, the timings of GP visits, GERD, the number of SAEs and current or past smoking increased the probability of treatment step-up with medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA (<italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> high-dose ICS/LABA) (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figures 2</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). For some of these determinants, heterogeneity was high (I<sup>2</sup>&gt;75%), <italic toggle="yes">e.g.</italic> for COPD with odds ratio 8.13 in CPRD GOLD and 3.09&#8211;3.22 in the other databases. Atopy reduced the probability of being treated with medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2</xref> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://publications.ersnet.org/lookup/doi/10.1183/23120541.00869-2024#supplementary" ext-link-type="uri">supplementary table S4</ext-link>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Odds ratio (OR) for factors of step-up treatment to medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA instead of high-dose ICS/LABA: meta-analysis. Each graph indicates the odds ratio for patients to be stepped up to medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA if they have one of these factors. Reference category for visits to general practitioner (GP) practice was number of visits to GP practice in first quarter. Reference category for number of SABA prescriptions in previous year was &#8211; Low: 0 in HSD, 0&#8211;1 in IPCI and Aarhus, 0&#8211;6 in CPRD GOLD; Medium: 1 in HSD, 2&#8211;4 in IPCI and Aarhus, 7&#8211;10 in CPRD GOLD; High: &#8805;2 in HSD, &#8805;5 in IPCI and Aarhus, &#8805;11 in CPRD GOLD. GERD: gastro-oesophageal reflux disease; ICS: inhaled corticosteroid; LABA: long-acting &#946;<sub>2</sub>-agonist; LAMA: long-acting muscarinic antagonist; SABA: short-acting &#946;<sub>2</sub>-agonist; N SABA: number of SABA prescriptions.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="00869-2024.02.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Drivers of step-up treatment to medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA instead of high-dose ICS/LABA (continued): meta-analysis. Each graph indicates the odds ratio (OR) for patients to be stepped up to medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA if they have one of these factors. Reference category for Adult and Late onset asthma was Childhood onset asthma, and for CCI categories CCI=1. CCI: Charlson Comorbidity Index; ICS: inhaled corticosteroid; LABA: long-acting &#946;<sub>2</sub>-agonist; LAMA: long-acting muscarinic antagonist.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="00869-2024.03.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>Drivers of step-up treatment to medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA instead of high-dose ICS/LABA (continued): meta-analysis. Each graph indicates the odds ratio (OR) for patients to be stepped up to medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA if they have one of these factors. N exacerbations: number of exacerbation events. Reference category for exacerbations was No exacerbations in previous year. Reference category for smoking was Never-smoker. ICS: inhaled corticosteroid; LABA: long-acting &#946;<sub>2</sub>-agonist; LAMA: long-acting muscarinic antagonist.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="00869-2024.04.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this multinational, multi-database study we describe &gt;25&#8201;000 asthma patients who stepped up from fixed medium-dose ICS/LABA treatment to either high-dose ICS/LABA (74%), medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA (24%) or high-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA (2%). Analysing the four databases separately, drivers of treatment step-up to medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA (compared to high-dose ICS/LABA) were increasing age and comorbid COPD. A history of atopic diseases (allergic rhinitis and/or atopic dermatitis) reduced the probability of step-up treatment to medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA. After meta-analysis, GERD, the number of GP visits, the number of SAEs and current or past smoking came up as determinants of choice for medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA.</p><p>A review paper by T<sc>rivedi</sc>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. [<xref rid="C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] also describes that patient characteristics such as female sex, higher age, comorbid COPD and current smoking are more often reported for users of medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA (<italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> high-dose ICS/LABA). Investigators from the Italian Severe Asthma Network reported similar results for patients with uncontrolled severe asthma receiving LAMA tiotropium. They found that older age, current smoking and higher rates of SAEs were associated with the LAMA tiotropium add-on therapy [<xref rid="C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. A recent retrospective cohort study by B<sc>uhl</sc>
<italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> [<xref rid="C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] using CPRD data describes treatment step-up following a treatment period with medium-dose ICS+LABA. The proportions of individuals on medium-dose ICS/LABA who stepped up to high-dose ICS/LABA or to medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA were comparable (namely 23.4% and 22.9%), whereas in our study the proportion of individuals treated with high-dose ICS/LABA was much higher. However, it is difficult to compare both studies as inclusion criteria were different [<xref rid="C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p><p>Our findings highlight that drivers for treatment step-up from medium-dose ICS/LABA to medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA include age and comorbid COPD diagnosis, while atopy is a protective factor against step-up to that latter treatment. Importantly, the CAPTAIN study showed greater reduction in exacerbations by increasing the ICS dose as compared with adding LAMA in patients with uncontrolled moderate-to-severe asthma and elevated biomarkers of type 2 inflammation (<italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic> increased blood eosinophil counts or increased FeNO levels) [<xref rid="C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In contrast, adding the LAMA umeclidinium to ICS/LABA improved lung function irrespective of type 2 biomarker levels. Due to limited availability of blood eosinophil measurements in the EHR databases used in this study, we were not able to investigate a possible relation between blood eosinophil counts with choice of step-up treatment.</p><p>Given current GINA guidelines, the observation that only a very low proportion of patients (<italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic> 2%) immediately changed treatment from medium-dose ICS/LABA to high-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA is not surprising.</p><p>In the exposure cohorts across all databases, the proportion of females was higher than the proportion of males. Patients in those exposure cohorts containing LAMA were older, more often smokers and with a higher proportion of ACO compared to the high-dose ICS/LABA exposure cohort. In all databases, the proportion of patients without SAEs in the year prior to treatment step-up was the highest for the high-dose ICS/LABA exposure cohort (53% in CPRD, 59% in HSD, 71% in IPCI and 83% in Aarhus).</p><sec id="s4a"><title>Strengths and limitations</title><p>The main strength of this study is the use of &gt;25&#8201;000 patients from various European countries with detailed covariates on drug exposure, comorbidity and resources utilisation. In addition, the data is collected during routine clinical practice, making our findings generalisable to asthma patients in the real world.</p><p>However, important differences exist between databases, particularly in patient characteristics and comorbidities. Health systems, health access and health information architecture are different in each country and therefore may lead to the sometimes wide differences between the databases, which is both a weakness and a strength.</p><p>Additionally, the observational nature of EHR data is also prone to certain biases. First, these data rely on the assumption that everybody accesses healthcare equally. Yet, it has been shown that not everyone utilises healthcare in a timely manner, due to lack of health literacy or healthcare access. The varied nature of our databases and their large number of asthma patients could potentially offset such an accessibility bias. Yet, disadvantaged populations tend to have a lower or no healthcare access, and thus may not be accurately represented in these data while often being more prone to uncontrolled asthma [<xref rid="C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Another possible bias is that EHR data are primarily meant for patient management rather than for research purposes. Therefore, events may be left out of the registration if considered irrelevant for patient management.</p><p>Correct recording of drug dosage, number of drugs prescribed and duration of treatment are key for an optimal calculation of daily dose, but might be challenging in EHR. Therefore, misclassification of ICS dose is possible. Our cohort of patients with asthma was based on physician-diagnosed asthma and thus created based on the presence of an asthma disease code in combination with asthma-related drugs [<xref rid="C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Asthma can pose difficulties in terms of diagnosis and recording, and while GPs are trained to enter the right disease code matching their diagnosis, errors do happen, and the large amount of data prevents manual validation. Incomplete availability of patient history may cause misclassification of age of asthma onset. Moreover, the lack of blood eosinophil count and spirometry data across databases prevents us from testing their impact on treatment choice. Nonetheless, the characteristics of the patients with asthma as described in our study in terms of sex, age at onset and comorbidities are in line with publications from other research groups [<xref rid="C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p><p>As comorbidities are registered the same way as asthma, misclassification may have occurred. This could explain for example differences in prevalences of comorbidities between the databases despite the common mapping through the Unified Medical Language System and verification by database custodians before extraction for analysis.</p><p>Even with these limitations, the varied sources of our data (<italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic> four different EHR databases, based on primary care and prescriptions data) as well as the use of a representative and specific cohort definition allows this study to have a high external validity. Indeed, the large scale and the fact that these patients were all treated in routine clinical practice leads to the generalisability of our findings.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study aimed at understanding which factors are related to the choice of step-up treatment for patients with moderate-to-severe asthma. Using large, real-world EHR databases from four European countries, we demonstrated that increasing age and comorbid COPD were the main determinants for step-up from medium-dose ICS/LABA to medium-dose ICS/LABA+LAMA instead of high-dose ICS/LABA (without LAMA). History of atopy lowered this probability. In subsequent research the impact of biological therapies for severe asthma needs to be investigated; moreover, we will explore whether the choice of asthma treatment step-up affects treatment response and clinical outcomes.</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>Provenance: Submitted article, peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>Conflict of interest: F. Lapi and E. Marcona have provided consultations in protocol preparation for epidemiological studies and data analyses for AstraZeneca, GSK and Chiesi. M. Van Der Deijl is an employee of Chiesi. G. Brusselle reports fees for advisory boards and speaker's fees from AstraZeneca, Boehringer Ingelheim, Chiesi, GSK, Novartis, Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme (MSD) and Sanofi Regeneron. All other authors have nothing to disclose.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="supplementary" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/23120541.00869-2024.Supp1</object-id><p><bold>Please note:</bold> supplementary material is not edited by the Editorial Office, and is uploaded as it has been supplied by the author.</p><p>Supplementary material <fig id="SS1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="00869-2024.SUPPLEMENT.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></fig>00869-2024.SUPPLEMENT</p></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="C1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="standard"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>. Chronic respiratory diseases. Date last accessed: September 2024. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/health-topics/chronic-respiratory-diseases#tab=tab_1" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/health-topics/chronic-respiratory-diseases#tab=tab_1</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="standard">Global Asthma Network. <person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Global Asthma Report</collab></person-group><year>2018</year>. Date last accessed: September 2024. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://globalasthmareport.org/2018/index.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://globalasthmareport.org/2018/index.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>To</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stanojevic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moores</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Global asthma prevalence in adults: findings from the cross-sectional world health survey</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2012</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>204</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-12-204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22429515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3353191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="standard"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Global Initiative for Asthma (GINA)</collab></person-group>. Global Strategy for Asthma Management and Prevention. <year>2019</year>. Date last accessed: March 2024. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ginasthma.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/GINA-Main-Report-2019-WMSA.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://ginasthma.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/GINA-Main-Report-2019-WMSA.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Virchow</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kuna</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Paggiaro</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Single inhaler extrafine triple therapy in uncontrolled asthma (TRIMARAN and TRIGGER): two double-blind, parallel-group, randomised, controlled phase 3 trials</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>394</volume>: <fpage>1737</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1749</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(19)32215-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31582314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Virchow</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Canonica</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Determinants of response to inhaled extrafine triple therapy in asthma: analyses of TRIMARAN and TRIGGER</article-title>. <source>Respir Res</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>285</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-020-01558-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33121501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7597025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>de Ridder</surname><given-names>MAJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>de Wilde</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>de Ben</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Data resource profile: the integrated primary care information (IPCI) database, The Netherlands</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source><year>2022</year>; <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>e314</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>e323</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyac026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35182144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9749682</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cazzola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Puxeddu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bettoncelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>The prevalence of asthma and COPD in Italy: a practice-based study</article-title>. <source>Respir Med</source><year>2011</year>; <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>386</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>391</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rmed.2010.09.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20951017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nissen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mullerova</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Validation of asthma recording in the Clinical Practice Research Datalink (CPRD)</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source><year>2017</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e017474</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2017-017474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5724126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28801439</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A population-based Danish data resource with possible high validity in pharmacoepidemiological research</article-title>. <source>J Med Syst</source><year>1994</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>38</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00999322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8064206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fuhlbrigge</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peden</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Apter</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Asthma outcomes: exacerbations</article-title>. <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2012</year>; <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>S34</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>S48</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2011.12.983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22386508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3595577</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="standard"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization (WHO) Collaborating Centre for Drug Statistics Methodology</collab></person-group>. Guidelines for ATC classification and DDD assignment 2013. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.whocc.no/filearchive/publications/1_2013guidelines.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">www.whocc.no/filearchive/publications/1_2013guidelines.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Uzzo</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Why summary comorbidity measures such as the Charlson Comorbidity Index and Elixhauser Score Work</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>e65</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>e72</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MLR.0b013e318297429c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23703645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3818341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Charlson</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pompei</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ales</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>A new method of classifying prognostic comorbidity in longitudinal studies: development and validation</article-title>. <source>J Chronic Dis</source><year>1987</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>373</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>383</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0021-9681(87)90171-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3558716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Trivedi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Denton</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Asthma in children and adults: what are the differences and what can they tell us about asthma?</article-title><source>Front Pediatr</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>256</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fped.2019.00256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31294006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6603154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Puggioni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brussino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Canonica</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Frequency of tiotropium bromide use and clinical features of patients with severe asthma in a real-life setting: data from the severe asthma network in Italy (SANI) registry</article-title>. <source>J Asthma Allergy</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>599</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>604</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/JAA.S274245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33204116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7667506</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Buhl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heaney</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Loefroth</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>One-year follow up of asthmatic patients newly initiated on treatment with medium- or high-dose inhaled corticosteroid-long-acting beta(2)-agonist in UK primary care settings</article-title>. <source>Respir Med</source><year>2020</year>; <volume>162</volume>: <fpage>105859</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rmed.2019.105859</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31916534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bailes</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Efficacy and safety of once-daily single-inhaler triple therapy (FF/UMEC/VI) versus FF/VI in patients with inadequately controlled asthma (CAPTAIN): a double-blind, randomised, phase 3A trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(20)30389-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32918892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zaeh</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ramsey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>The impact of adherence and health literacy on difficult-to-control asthma</article-title>. <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol Pract</source><year>2022</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>386</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>394</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaip.2021.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34788658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10207170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boulet</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lavoie</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Raherison-Semjen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Addressing sex and gender to improve asthma management</article-title>. <source>NPJ Prim Care Respir Med</source><year>2022</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>56</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41533-022-00306-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36539451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9764319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carleton</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Prosser</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>The added burden of comorbidity in patients with asthma</article-title>. <source>J Asthma</source><year>2009</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>1021</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1026</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/02770900903350473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19995140</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YU</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>The prevalence of multiple chronic conditions and medical burden in asthma patients</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><year>2023</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>e0286004</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37200347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0286004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10194904</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="C23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cricelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mazzaglia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Samani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Prevalence estimates for chronic diseases in Italy: exploring the differences between self-report and primary care databases</article-title>. <source>J Public Health Med</source><year>2003</year>; <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>254</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>257</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pubmed/fdg060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14575204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>