<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Anesthesiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Anesthesiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">11</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcanes</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Anesthesiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2253</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11384694</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11384694.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11384694</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11384694</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39256673</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12871-024-02704-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2704</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Different ethanol exposure durations affect cytochrome P450 2E1-mediated sevoflurane metabolism in rat liver</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names initials="W">Wei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="M">Min</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names initials="R">Rui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="X">Xinghao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names initials="Y">Youbo</given-names></name><address><email>zuoyb2519@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05k3sdc46</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.449525.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1798 4472</institution-id><institution>Department of Anesthesiology, School of Clinical Medicine of North Sichuan Medical College, </institution></institution-wrap>Nanchong, 637000 Sichuan China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01673gn35</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.413387.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1758 177X</institution-id><institution>Department of Anesthesiology, </institution><institution>Affiliated Hospital of North Sichuan Medical College, </institution></institution-wrap>Nanchong, 637000 Sichuan China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">452039</issue-id><elocation-id>321</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>10</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>10</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-09-12 07:25:29.523"><day>12</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12871_2024_Article_2704.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Chronic alcohol users often exhibit an increased minimum alveolar concentration (MAC) of sevoflurane, yet the specific mechanism remains unclear. It has been reported that ethanol exposure can upregulate the protein expression and enzyme activity of cytochrome P450 2E1 (CYP2E1). CYP2E1 is a key enzyme that converts 2&#8211;5% of sevoflurane into equimolar amounts of hexafluoroisopropanol (HFIP) and F<sup>&#8722;</sup>. This study aims to explore whether ethanol exposure could alter sevoflurane metabolism through CYP2E1 modulation, potentially explaining the increased MAC observed in alcohol users.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Eighty adult male Sprague-Dawley (SD) rats were randomly divided into two groups and received either 50% ethanol (dose: 3&#160;g/kg) or 0.9% saline twice daily by gavage. After 1, 2, 3, and 4 weeks of gavage, ten rats were randomly selected from each group to undergo 1-hour anesthesia with 2.3% sevoflurane. Blood samples were collected after anesthesia to measure the concentration of free HFIP using gas chromatography. Additionally, the left lobe tissue of the liver was collected for the analysis of CYP2E1 protein expression by Western blot and CYP2E1 enzyme activity by colorimetric assay. Correlations between these parameters were analyzed using Pearson&#8217;s correlation.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">In the ethanol group, CYP2E1 expression, activity, and the concentration of free HFIP were significantly higher at all time points compared to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05), except for protein expression in the first week (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05). Within-group comparisons indicated no significant changes in any of the parameters for the control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05). In the ethanol group, there was no difference in free HFIP concentration between the first and second weeks (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05), but a significant increase was observed in the third and fourth weeks (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01); protein expression and enzyme activity significantly varied over time, especially showing a notable increase from the first to the third and fourth weeks (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Correlation analysis revealed strong positive correlations between free HFIP concentration and CYP2E1 activity (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.7898), free HFIP concentration and CYP2E1 expression (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.8418), and CYP2E1 activity and expression (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.8740), all with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Ethanol exposure increased both the expression and enzymatic activity of CYP2E1, consequently enhancing the metabolism of sevoflurane.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12871-024-02704-5.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Ethanol</kwd><kwd>CYP2E1</kwd><kwd>Sevoflurane</kwd><kwd>Hexafluoroisopropanol (HFIP)</kwd><kwd>Inhalation anesthesia</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par5">
Alcohol abuse is a global public health problem, placing a significant burden on both society and individual health. In 2016, around 2.3&#160;billion individuals were identified as alcohol consumers, with alcohol-related diseases resulting in an estimated 3&#160;million deaths [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. In medical environments, particularly during emergency surgeries, anesthesiologists frequently encounter difficulties in managing patients with underreported alcohol abuse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Long-term drinkers exhibit increased tolerance to various anesthetic drugs, including sevoflurane, fentanyl, and propofol, necessitating higher dosages to achieve effective anesthesia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. For example, they have a higher minimum alveolar concentration (MAC) of sevoflurane, a phenomenon whose underlying mechanism remains to be fully elucidated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">
Ethanol is primarily metabolized in the body by alcohol dehydrogenase (ADH) and the Microsomal Ethanol Oxidizing System (MEOS) enzyme cytochrome P450 2E1 (CYP2E1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. CYP2E1 is a substrate-inducible enzyme, and long-term or excessive ethanol exposure can increase its expression and activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. It is noteworthy that CYP2E1 not only participates in the metabolism of ethanol but also serves as a critical enzyme for the metabolism of sevoflurane [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">
Sevoflurane, a widely used inhalation anesthetic, undergoes metabolism primarily through CYP2E1, with 2&#8211;5% being converted into equimolar production of hexafluoroisopropanol (HFIP) and inorganic fluoride (F<sup>&#8722;</sup>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. The majority of HFIP is conjugated with glucuronic acid and subsequently excreted in the urine. However, about 15% or less of HFIP remains in the bloodstream in its free form, noted for its high solubility. This characteristic is demonstrated by a saline/gas partition coefficient of 263 and a blood/gas partition coefficient of 452 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Additionally, free HFIP has a half-life of 19&#160;h, indicating its slow elimination from the body [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. These characteristics establish free HFIP as a reliable biological marker for evaluating the metabolic degradation of sevoflurane.</p><p id="Par8">
In this study, our primary objective is to investigate the impact of ethanol exposure on the expression and enzymatic activity of the CYP2E1 protein, as well as the concentration of free HFIP in the bloodstream. By exploring these elements, we intend to clarify the relationship between the duration of ethanol exposure and sevoflurane metabolism.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Materials</title><p id="Par9">Sevoflurane (Hengrui, China), HFIP (Sigma Aldrich, US), pentobarbital sodium (xiya, China), Anti-CYP2E1 Antibody (Abcam, ab28146,), Anti-&#946;-actin Antibody (Abclonal, AC026). Goat Anti-Rabbit IgG (H&#8201;+&#8201;L) HRP (Affinity, S0001), HRP Goat Anti-Mouse IgG (H&#8201;+&#8201;L) (Abclonal, AS003), BCA protein Assay Kit (Beyotime, P0009).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Animal</title><p id="Par10">All experimental procedures involving animals were approved by the North Sichuan Medical College (NSMC) Animal Ethics Committee under license number [2023]018. All animal experiments adhered to the ARRIVE guidelines and were conducted in accordance with the guidelines of the National Institutes of Health. Measures were taken to minimize the number of animals used and to reduce their suffering. A total of 80 healthy adult male SD rats, weighing 180&#8211;210&#160;g, were obtained from the Animal Experimental Center of North Sichuan Medical College. The rats were housed in an Animal Facility and acclimatized to a 12-hour light-dark cycle, with temperatures maintained between 20 and 24&#8451; and humidity at 50&#8201;&#177;&#8201;10%. Food and water were provided ad libitum. The rats underwent a one-week acclimatization period in the laboratory environment before the commencement of the experiments.</p><p id="Par11">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Experimental protocol</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e318" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12871_2024_2704_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Experimental groups and treatments</title><p id="Par12">After a one-week acclimatization period, 80 rats were randomly divided into two groups by an independent party using a random number generator: an ethanol group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;40) and a control group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;40). Rats in the ethanol group received 50% ethanol via oral gavage at a dosage of 3&#160;g/kg twice daily, with an 8-hour interval, for a continuous period of 4 weeks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. In contrast, the control group was given 0.9% saline solution via oral gavage, adjusted for their body weight (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The gavage procedure was performed by researchers not involved in the study&#8217;s daily observations.</p><p id="Par13">At the end of each week (1, 2, 3, and 4 weeks after gavage), ten rats from each group were randomly selected by an independent individual. Following a 12-hour fasting period, rats were transferred to the animal operating room. There, they were anesthetized with an intraperitoneal injection of pentobarbital sodium (60&#160;mg/kg). Upon cessation of movement, a tracheotomy was performed, and a 14# PE tube was inserted, then connected through a T-tube to a small animal ventilator, initiating mechanical ventilation. Before starting mechanical ventilation, a simulated lung was used with an oxygen flow of 0.5&#160;L/min. The vaporizer was adjusted to maintain the sevoflurane concentration at 2.3% in the circuit, as measured by gas chromatography (GC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The respiratory parameters were established as follows: a tidal volume (VT) of 10&#160;ml/kg, a respiratory rate (RR) of 65 breaths per minute, an inspiratory-to-expiratory ratio of 1:2, and a positive end-expiratory pressure maintained at 0 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Pulse rate, oxygen saturation, rectal temperature, and ventilatory pressures, including mean and plateau pressures, were continuously monitored. Rectal temperature was measured via a rectal thermometer and regulated within the range of 36.5&#8211;37.5&#8451; using a circulating heating pad. Sevoflurane concentration in the circuit was measured at 5, 15, 30, and 45&#160;min after the start of anesthesia using GC, with necessary vaporizer adjustments made to maintain the sevoflurane concentration at approximately 2.3%. After one hour of anesthesia, 5&#160;ml of blood was collected via ventral aortic puncture using a sterile, sealed syringe for the analysis of free HFIP and sevoflurane concentrations. The left lateral lobe of the liver was subsequently excised, immediately frozen at -80&#8451;, and preserved for later analysis of CYP2E1 protein expression by Western blot and CYP2E1 enzyme activity using a colorimetric assay. Following the collection of tissues, euthanasia was conducted using sodium pentobarbital (150&#160;mg/kg, iv) while the rats were under sevoflurane anesthesia.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>The concentrations of free HFIP and sevoflurane</title><p id="Par14">Gas chromatograph (Agient 7890&#160;A, Beijing, China), six-port valve, and capillary column (HP-5) were used in the study. The operating parameters were set as follows: injector temperature: 70&#8451;, column oven temperature: 30&#8451;, hydrogen flame detector temperature: 200&#8451;, hydrogen flow rate: 30 mL/min, air flow rate: 300 mL/min, and nitrogen flow rate: 20 mL/min. Using these parameters, high concentrations of sevoflurane and low concentrations of HFIP can be distinctly separated in the chromatogram.</p><p id="Par15">The laboratory temperature was maintained at 25&#8451;. A small quantity of HFIP liquid sample was extracted and weighed, then injected into a sealed conical bottle under negative pressure (0.08Mpa) and left to stand until completely evaporated. After a stabilization period, the pressure inside and outside the conical bottle was equalized without any leakage. The concentration of the prepared standard gas was calculated using the formula C&#8201;=&#8201;W &#215; R &#215;T / (MW &#215; Vx). C represents the concentration of the HFIP standard gas. W is the weight of the HFIP liquid sample. R is the ideal gas constant, valued at 0.08206&#160;L&#183;atm/(mol&#183;K). T denotes the temperature in Kelvin, which is 298&#160;K in this study. MW stands for the molar mass of HFIP, which is 168.05&#160;g/mol. Vx is the volume of the sealed conical bottle. The standard gas was repeatedly diluted by half. Subsequently, a gas chromatograph was used to construct the calibration curve equation, which relates the concentration to the corresponding peak area. This calibration curve equation can be utilized to detect the concentration of free HFIP in blood. It is crucial to ensure that the concentration range encompasses the expected analyte concentration, and R<sup>2</sup>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.999 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p><p id="Par16">After blood collection, air was drawn into the syringe already containing 5&#160;ml of blood to increase its volume to 17.5&#160;ml. The syringe was then placed in a constant-temperature air bath oscillator set at 37&#8451; and oscillated to promote the evaporation of free HFIP. After 90&#160;min, additional air was drawn to adjust the volume to 20&#160;ml, and the oscillation continued for another 60&#160;min. This process ensures the gradual evaporation of free HFIP from the blood into the gas phase, reaching equilibrium between the two phases. The gas within the syringe was then analyzed using a gas chromatograph, and the concentration of HFIP in the gas phase (Cg) was determined using the previously established calibration curve equation. The concentration of free HFIP in the blood (C) was calculated with the formula C = (Vg / V&#8201;+&#8201;&#955;) &#215; Cg, where Vg is the volume of gas in the syringe after equilibration (15&#160;ml), V represents the total volume of gas and blood within the syringe (20&#160;ml), and &#955; is the blood/gas partition coefficient of free HFIP in rats (452) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The standard curve establishment and GC detection method for sevoflurane is the same as that for HFIP.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Western blotting assay</title><p id="Par17">After weighing, liver tissues were placed into homogenization tubes. Then, 3&#160;mm steel beads and Radio-Immunoprecipitation Assay (RIPA) buffer with protease inhibitors were added at a weight-to-buffer ratio of 1:10. The tubes were then homogenized using a high-speed, low-temperature tissue homogenizer at -20&#160;&#176;C for 60&#160;s per cycle, repeated four times, and then lysed on ice for 30&#160;min. Centrifugation at 4&#160;&#176;C and 12,000&#160;rpm was subsequently performed for 10&#160;min. The supernatant was collected and stored at -80&#160;&#176;C. Protein concentration was assessed using the BCA Protein Assay Kit. SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE) was conducted with a 5% stacking gel and a 10% resolving gel, loading 30&#160;&#181;g of protein per well. After electrophoresis, proteins were transferred onto a PVDF membrane. The membrane was blocked with 5% skim milk in Tris-Buffered Saline with Tween 20 (TBST) on a shaker for 2&#160;h at room temperature, then incubated overnight at 4&#160;&#176;C with primary antibodies against CYP2E1 (1:5000, Abcam, UK) and &#946;-actin (1:50000, Abclonal, China). Following this, it was incubated with secondary antibodies for 2&#160;h at room temperature: Goat Anti-Rabbit IgG (H&#8201;+&#8201;L) HRP (1:5000, Affinity, USA) and HRP Goat Anti-Mouse IgG (H&#8201;+&#8201;L) (1:5000, Abclonal, China). The ECL reagent was evenly applied to the membrane, and signal detection was performed using the Fusion FX system (Vilber Lourmat). Band densities were quantified using ImageJ software. With &#946;-actin serving as the internal control, the grayscale ratio of CYP2E1 to &#946;-actin was computed to determine relative protein expression levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>The enzyme activity of CYP2E1</title><p id="Par18">The activity of <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-nitrophenol hydroxylase (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-NPH), as the diagnostic marker for CYP2E1, involves the hydroxylation of <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-nitrophenol to <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-nitrocatechol. This reaction product can be detected at a wavelength of 510&#160;nm, allowing for the quantitative measurement of CYP2E1 activity using spectrophotometry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. This experimental procedure was performed using the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="GMS18021.1">GMS18021.1</ext-link> kit from GeneMe (Shanghai). 480&#160;&#181;l of GENMED buffer, reaction liquid, and base color liquid were added into a 1.5&#160;ml centrifuge tube. 20&#160;&#181;l of the supernatant with a protein concentration of 100&#160;&#181;g was added to the sample tube, while 20&#160;&#181;l of negative control containing DDC (diethyldithiocarbamate) was added to the background tube. DDC is a selective mechanism-based inhibitor of CYP2E1 and significantly inhibits the CYP2E1-catalyzed <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-nitrophenol hydroxylase (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-NPH) activity. After incubating at 37&#8451; for 30&#160;min, 100&#160;&#181;l of stop solution was added, followed by centrifugation at 10,000&#160;g for 5&#160;min. The supernatant was then transferred and mixed with 300&#160;&#181;l of neutralizing liquid. The resulting mixture was immediately measured using a spectrophotometer (Shimadzu UV-26001, Suzhou, China). The enzyme activity of the sample was calculated based on the absorbance values (sample tube reading - background tube reading) and the extinction coefficient of 9.53&#160;L/(mmol&#183;cm) for <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-nitrocatechol, expressed as nmol <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-nitrocatechol/min/mg protein.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par19">We used G-Power software to calculate the sample size, choosing a one-tailed t-test with an anticipated power of 0.8 and a significance level of 0.05. Based on the mean concentration of free HFIP observed in our preliminary study, the total sample size was determined to be 80.</p><p id="Par20">Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS 26.0 software. The Shapiro-Wilk test was used to assess the normality of the data. Results are presented as mean&#8201;&#177;&#8201;standard deviation (x&#8201;&#177;&#8201;s). Two-way repeated measures analysis of variance (2-way RM-ANOVA) was conducted to examine the interaction between groups and time. When the F statistic was significant, Bonferroni correction was used for multiple comparisons. Correlations between the measured variables were analyzed using Pearson&#8217;s correlation, with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05 indicating statistical significance.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p id="Par21">During the experimental period, no accidental deaths occurred among the rats. Rats in the ethanol group exhibited signs of drowsiness, reduced activity levels, decreased appetite, and irritability, with a significantly slower rate of weight gain compared to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001, Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). During sevoflurane inhalation anesthesia, the rats&#8217; toe end skin appeared ruddy. The rats&#8217; pulse rates remained above 254&#160;bpm, and their rectal temperatures were maintained within the range of 36.5&#8211;37.5&#8451;. All rats consistently maintained an oxygen saturation level above 98%, while the airway pressure stayed within a 0&#8211;2 mmHg range. Statistical analysis included data from all 80 rats.</p><p id="Par22">
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>The graph illustrates the mean (SD) weekly weight (g) rats subjected to different gavage regimens. At corresponding time points, the ethanol gavage group showed significantly lower weights compared to the control group, denoting a statistically significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e436" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12871_2024_2704_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par23">
<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>GC chromatogram of a blood sample of a sevoflurane-anesthetized rat</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e446" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12871_2024_2704_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><sec id="Sec11"><title>Free HFIP concentration</title><p id="Par24">The GC chromatogram of free HFIP in the blood sample of a rat anesthetized with sevoflurane is displayed as shown in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>.</p><p id="Par25">In the examination of free HFIP concentration, 2-way RM-ANOVA was utilized to analyze any interaction between the &#8216;Groups&#8217; (Ethanol vs. Control) and &#8216;Time&#8217; (across four weeks). Mauchly&#8217;s Test was employed to ascertain the assumption of sphericity, which the data successfully fulfilled (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.411). The analysis revealed significant effects due to group differences (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;500.22, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001, Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), time variations (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;9.20, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001, Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), and crucially, the interaction between these elements (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;9.29, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001, Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), indicating distinct variations in free HFIP concentration between the ethanol and control groups across the observed periods.</p><p id="Par26">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The free HFIP concentration in the blood of the two groups of rats (mean, SD; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;10)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control(%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ethanol(%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.019&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.003</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.026&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.002<sup>C</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.74</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.017&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.004</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.030&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.002<sup>BC</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.83</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.018&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.002</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.035&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.003<sup>A</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">221.52</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.018&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.003</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.035&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.003<sup>AB</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">118.94</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.69</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;0.05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">overall test</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">group&#160;(<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500.22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">time&#160;(<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">interact&#160;(<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The results of the two-way RM ANOVA demonstrated a significant interaction between different gavage treatments and time on the generation of free HFIP in the blood (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;9.29, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001). Bonferroni correction was applied for multiple comparisons. For within-group comparisons, differences were denoted using alphabetical letters (A, B, C). Groups sharing the same letter indicate non-significant differences, while different letters indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01). Although the ethanol group values at weeks 3 and 4 appear identical, they are rounded values. The comparison between weeks 2 and 4 yielded a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value of 0.051, which is not statistically significant</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par2700">After identifying significant F-values, Bonferroni correction was applied for comprehensive comparisons. This demonstrated that the ethanol group consistently had higher free HFIP concentrations than the control at all measured points (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic> values ranging from 33.74 to 221.52, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001, Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Within-group analysis revealed constant HFIP levels in the control group throughout the study (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.69, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05, Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), in marked contrast to the ethanol group, which experienced significant fluctuations (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;28.14, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001, Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Specifically, HFIP concentrations in the ethanol group progressively increased, peaking in the third week. Although no significant differences were noted between weeks 1 and 2 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05, Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), significant differences emerged between week 1 and both weeks 3 and 4, as well as between weeks 2 and 3 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01, Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par27">Collectively, these findings suggest that prolonged ethanol consumption increased free B-HFIP concentration.</p><p id="Par28">
<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Influence of different gavage methods and time on CYP2E1 protein expression, analyzed by two-way RM-ANOVA with Bonferroni correction. Relative CYP2E1 expression in livers normalized to &#946;-actin as an internal control. Data presented as mean (SD); <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;3. For within-group comparisons, differences were denoted using alphabetical letters (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>, <bold>c</bold>). Groups sharing the same letter indicate non-significant differences, while different letters indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). No significant differences across four time points in control group. * indicates between-group differences at the same time points (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The blots came from separate membranes for optimal sensitivity. We maintained consistent loading and uniform processing for reliability. Full-length blots are presented in Supplementary Fig.&#160;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e741" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12871_2024_2704_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>CYP2E1 protein expression</title><p id="Par29">To investigate the potential influence of ethanol on CYP2E1, we employed the Western Blot method to assess the expression of CYP2E1 protein in the rat liver. Our findings demonstrated that as the duration of gastric administration extended, the CYP2E1 protein expression in the ethanol group gradually amplified, reaching the highest levels by week 4 (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Within the ethanol group, a significant divergence was discerned between weeks 1&#8211;2 and weeks 3&#8211;4 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05, Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). In contrast, no significant differences were noted within the control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05, Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). In comparisons between the groups, the ethanol group displayed substantially higher CYP2E1 expression compared to the control group at weeks 2, 3, and 4 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05, Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). These results indicate that continuous gastric administration of ethanol augments the expression levels of CYP2E1.</p><p id="Par30">
<fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>The changes in rat liver CYP2E1 activity at different gavage durations. Data are presented as mean (SD); <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;10. For within-group comparisons, differences were denoted using alphabetical letters (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>B</bold>, <bold>C</bold>). Groups sharing the same letter indicate non-significant differences, while different letters indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01). *** represents significant between-group differences (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e797" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12871_2024_2704_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>CYP2E1 enzyme activity</title><p id="Par31">Our study utilized two-way RM-ANOVA to assess CYP2E1 enzyme activity, examining interactions between groups (Ethanol vs. Control) and time over four weeks. Mauchly&#8217;s Test confirmed the sphericity assumption (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.063), indicating equal variance across group combinations. Significant findings included effects due to group differences (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;110.55, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001), time (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;4.90, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01), and their interaction (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;3.75, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05), showing distinct changes in CYP2E1 enzyme activity over time between the groups, markedly altered by ethanol exposure.</p><p id="Par32">Further analysis with Bonferroni correction revealed that the ethanol group consistently exhibited higher CYP2E1 activity compared to the control across all time points (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic> values ranging from 26.39 to 66.15, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001). Within-group contrasts showed no significant changes in enzyme activity for the control (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.087, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05), unlike the ethanol group, which demonstrated significant variations (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;17.48, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001). Statistically significant differences were observed between week 1 and weeks 3&#8211;4 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01, Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). The results highlight that continuous gastric administration of ethanol enhances the enzymatic activity of CYP2E1.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Sevoflurane concentration</title><p id="Par33">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The sevoflurane concentration in the blood of the two groups of rats (mean, SD; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;10)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ethanol (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1week</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.729&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.050</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.734&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.047</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.728&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.048</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.725&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.038</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.737&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.047</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.724&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.044</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4weeks</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.750&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.035</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.743&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.043</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">overall test</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">group(<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">time(<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.66</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">interact(<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;0.05</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par34">The GC chromatogram (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) shows the second peak at 2.141, which corresponds to sevoflurane. The data are detailed in Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. The results of the two-way repeated measures ANOVA (RM ANOVA) indicate that, after implementing strict control measures and a standardized inhalation process, there was no significant interaction between different gavage treatments and time on the sevoflurane concentration in the blood (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.10, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05). Neither the main effect of time (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.66, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05) nor the main effect of group (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.38, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05) was statistically significant (Figs. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).</p><p id="Par35">
<fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Correlation between CYP2E1 activity and free HFIP concentration (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.7898, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001). The linear regression equation is <italic toggle="yes">Y</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;122.4<italic toggle="yes">X</italic>&#8201;+&#8201;0.1075 (<italic toggle="yes">r&#178;</italic> = 0.6239, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001). Correlation between CYP2E1 expression and free HFIP concentration (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.8418, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001). The linear regression equation is <italic toggle="yes">Y</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;193.9<italic toggle="yes">X</italic> &#8722;&#8201;2.609 (<italic toggle="yes">r&#178;</italic> = 0.7087, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1031" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12871_2024_2704_Fig6_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par36">
<fig id="Fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Correlation between CYP2E1 activity and CYP2E1 expression (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.8740, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001). The linear regression equation is <italic toggle="yes">Y</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.7710<italic toggle="yes">X</italic>&#8201;+&#8201;1.220 (<italic toggle="yes">r&#178;</italic> = 0.7639, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1061" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12871_2024_2704_Fig7_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par37">To examine the relationships between free B-HFIP levels and liver CYP2E1 activity and expression, we conducted Pearson correlation analyses, which indicated significant positive correlations between free B-HFIP levels and CYP2E1 activity (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.7898), free B-HFIP levels and CYP2E1 expression (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.8418), and CYP2E1 activity and expression (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.8740), all with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001, underscoring the potential role of CYP2E1 in the metabolism of sevoflurane.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par38">To explore the impact of prolonged ethanol exposure on the metabolism of sevoflurane, we conducted a four-week ethanol gavage study in rats, periodically assessing changes in the expression and activity of CYP2E1, as well as variations in the concentration of free HFIP. The findings reveal that with the extension of ethanol gavage duration, enzyme activity and the concentration of free HFIP significantly increased during the initial three weeks, while protein expression continued to rise throughout the four weeks. These results suggest that ethanol exposure augments the metabolism of sevoflurane through the upregulation of CYP2E1.</p><p id="Par39">Alcohol metabolism primarily involves converting alcohol to acetaldehyde by ADH. However, when ADH is saturated, MEOS, notably CYP2E1, plays a crucial role in converting alcohol to acetaldehyde as a secondary pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Our experimental findings, along with those from other studies, underscore the substrate-inducible nature of CYP2E1, demonstrating that ethanol exposure significantly upregulates CYP2E1 expression and activity. Lu et al. observed a marked increase in CYP2E1 protein expression in rats continuously fed with ethanol at 9&#160;g/kg BW per rat over an 8-week period, showing higher levels than in the control group [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Furthermore, the in vitro experiments conducted by Jin et al. reveal that a short exposure to 50 mM ethanol for 6&#160;h can induce a 150% increase in CYP2E1 protein expression in SVGA astrocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Similarly, Ge et al.&#8217;s research, involving continuous gastric administration of 50% (v/v) ethanol at 8&#8211;12&#160;ml/kg/day to rats for six weeks, reported a 96% increase in CYP2E1 activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Additionally, I. Dupont and colleagues, utilizing the 6-hydroxychlorzoxazone test, measured CYP2E1 activity and found it increased by four-fold in alcoholics compared to non-alcoholic patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. These outcomes collectively highlight the significant role of CYP2E1 in alcohol metabolism, illustrating how ethanol exposure increases the enzyme&#8217;s expression and activity.</p><p id="Par40">Our experimental results showed an increase in the concentration of free HFIP, suggesting an acceleration of sevoflurane metabolism. This observation corresponds with the findings of Malan TP et al., where continuous administration of 16% ethanol to rats for a 14-day period, followed by sevoflurane anesthesia, resulted in a 68% increase in serum fluoride ions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Previous studies assessing sevoflurane metabolism often measured fluoride ion concentrations. However, this approach lacks specificity as fluoride ions are not unique markers and are prevalent in various environmental sources, including water, tea, beverages, fluoride supplements, and dental products. Furthermore, once absorbed, approximately 50% of fluoride ions deposit in bones and teeth within 24&#160;h [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. In contrast, free HFIP originates solely from the metabolism of sevoflurane and exhibits a slow metabolic rate, making it a reliable indicator of blood HFIP concentration and the extent of sevoflurane metabolism.</p><p id="Par41">The increase in free HFIP concentration indicates an accelerated metabolism of sevoflurane, necessitating higher concentrations of sevoflurane to maintain a stable blood/brain partial pressure difference. This may partially explain the observed increase in the MAC of sevoflurane in chronic alcohol users. The significance of enzymatic interactions and alterations in sevoflurane metabolism has received less attention. Previous studies on how alcohol changes the effectiveness of anesthetics have mainly focused on the impact of ethanol on GABA<sub>A</sub> receptors, the primary ionotropic receptors for fast inhibitory neurotransmission in the central nervous system. GABA<sub>A</sub> receptors, which are targets for both alcohol and sevoflurane, have specific ethanol binding sites. Alcohol enhances Cl<sup>&#8722;</sup> influx, mimicking GABAergic substances. Chronic alcohol consumption reduces the sensitivity of GABA<sub>A</sub> receptors to GABAergic substances, leading to an increased tolerance to sevoflurane [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>].</p><p id="Par42">The observed increase in free HFIP concentration raises concerns due to its notable solubility and extended half-life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Administering high doses of sevoflurane over lengthy periods in individuals with chronic alcohol use could lead to significant free HFIP accumulation. Importantly, Eger EI et al. have reported that the MAC of free HFIP is only 0.0044%, highlight the risk of excessive anesthesia or delayed recovery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], These concerns need further clinical studies for investigation.</p><p id="Par43">CYP2E1 is not only involved in the metabolism of ethanol and sevoflurane, but also participates in the biotransformation processes of many other drugs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The upregulation of CYP2E1 expression and enzyme activity could affect their metabolic rates. This study establishes a foundation for future investigations into the effects of ethanol exposure on the processing of drugs metabolized by CYP2E1.</p><p id="Par44">Administering ethanol at a dosage of 3&#160;g/kg twice daily has been shown to maintain stable blood ethanol levels, reduce the risk of mortality from ethanol overdose in rats, and significantly influence CYP2E1 expression levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. This study utilized tracheal intubation for sevoflurane delivery, instead of the anesthesia chamber frequently used in previous sevoflurane metabolism experiments. The anesthesia chamber might cause respiratory depression and reduce minute ventilation, potentially lowering the alveolar concentration of sevoflurane. Tracheal intubation with mechanical ventilation allows for precise control of the concentration of sevoflurane in the circuit, reducing bias caused by weight differences due to alcohol gavage.</p><p id="Par45">This study has some limitations. First, there are species differences between humans and rats. Although the literature indicates that the CYP2E1 gene is highly conserved across multiple species, and rats are considered a reliable model for studying CYP2E1 expression, catalytic function, and substrate screening [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], the direct applicability of animal model research results to humans remains uncertain.</p><p id="Par46">Secondly, in calculating the concentration of free HFIP, this study utilized the blood/gas partition coefficient of 452, as measured in another experiment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. However, this coefficient may vary among individual rats, which could potentially impact the study results.</p><p id="Par47">Lastly, the study measured the concentration of free HFIP in rat blood only 1&#160;h after anesthesia. Although free HFIP can be detected within 5&#160;min post-inhalation anesthesia, its peak concentration typically occurs 5.5&#160;h afterwards [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. The choice of this time point may have limited a comprehensive understanding of the dynamic changes in free HFIP concentration.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par48">This study observed that after ethanol gavage, there was a significant increase in the expression and enzymatic activity of rat CYP2E1 protein, along with a significant rise in the concentration of free HFIP, suggesting an acceleration in the metabolism of sevoflurane. This metabolic change may be a potential reason for the observed increase in the MAC of sevoflurane in chronic drinkers.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12871_2024_2704_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12871_2024_2704_MOESM2_ESM.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 2</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12871_2024_2704_MOESM3_ESM.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 3</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#8217;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to express their gratitude to North Sichuan Medical College for providing resources for this research. The authors would also like to acknowledge the support and assistance provided by the Animal Center during this study.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>WJ conducted the literature review, designed the study, participated in the molecular biology studies, and drafted the manuscript. MZ processed data, analyzed and interpreted the findings. RC performed animal experiments and collected data. XHW performed animal experiments. YBZ designed the experiment, managed the project administration, and revised the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets used and/or analyzed during this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par49">All animal experiments adhered to the ARRIVE guidelines and were conducted in accordance with the guidelines of the National Institutes of Health. All experimental procedures involving animals were approved by the NSMC Animal Ethics Committee under license number [2023]018.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par50">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par51">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ADH</term><def><p id="Par52">Alcohol dehydrogenase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MEOS</term><def><p id="Par53">Microsomal Ethanol Oxidizing System</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MAC</term><def><p id="Par54">Minimum alveolar concentration</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CYP450 2E1</term><def><p id="Par55">Cytochrome P450 2E1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HFIP</term><def><p id="Par56">Hexafluoroisopropanol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>F<sup>&#8722;</sup></term><def><p id="Par57">Fluoride ions</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GABA</term><def><p id="Par58">&#947;-aminobutyric acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NSMC</term><def><p id="Par59">North Sichuan Medical College</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RIPA buffer</term><def><p id="Par60">Radio-Immunoprecipitation Assay Buffer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TBST</term><def><p id="Par61">Tris-Buffered Saline with Tween 20</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Organization WH. Global status report on alcohol and health 2018. World Health Organization; 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Alcohol use and burden</collab></person-group><article-title>For 195 countries and territories, 1990&#8211;2016: a systematic analysis for the global burden of Disease Study 2016</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2018</year><volume>392</volume><issue>10152</issue><fpage>1015</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)31310-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30146330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6148333</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Alcohol use and burden. For 195 countries and territories, 1990&#8211;2016: a systematic analysis for the global burden of Disease Study 2016. Lancet. 2018;392(10152):1015&#8211;35.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30146330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)31310-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6148333</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoonpongsimanont</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghanem</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahota</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrios</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Underreporting of Alcohol Use in Trauma patients: a retrospective analysis</article-title><source>Subst Abus</source><year>2021</year><volume>42</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08897077.2019.1671936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31638887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7174101</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Hoonpongsimanont W, Ghanem G, Chen Y, Sahota PK, Carroll C, Barrios C, et al. Underreporting of Alcohol Use in Trauma patients: a retrospective analysis. Subst Abus. 2021;42(2):192&#8211;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31638887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08897077.2019.1671936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7174101</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rolfzen</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikulich-Gilbertson</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Natvig</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrico</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lobato</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association between alcohol use disorder and hospital outcomes in colectomy patients - a retrospective cohort study</article-title><source>J Clin Anesth</source><year>2022</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>110674</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinane.2022.110674</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35168136</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Rolfzen ML, Mikulich-Gilbertson SK, Natvig C, Carrico JA, Lobato RL, Krause M, et al. Association between alcohol use disorder and hospital outcomes in colectomy patients - a retrospective cohort study. J Clin Anesth. 2022;78:110674.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35168136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinane.2022.110674</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of alcohol &amp; smoking on the surgical management of gastrointestinal patients</article-title><source>Best Pract Res Clin Gastroenterol</source><year>2017</year><volume>31</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>589</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpg.2017.10.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29195679</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Kennedy ND, Winter DC. Impact of alcohol &amp; smoking on the surgical management of gastrointestinal patients. Best Pract Res Clin Gastroenterol. 2017;31(5):589&#8211;95.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29195679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpg.2017.10.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic alcoholism increases the induction dose of propofol</article-title><source>Acta Anaesthesiol Scand</source><year>2011</year><volume>55</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1113</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-6576.2011.02497.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22092209</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Liang C, Chen J, Gu W, Wang H, Xue Z. Chronic alcoholism increases the induction dose of propofol. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2011;55(9):1113&#8211;7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22092209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-6576.2011.02497.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ransom</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Safety considerations in the use of drug combinations during general anaesthesia</article-title><source>Drug Saf</source><year>1997</year><volume>16</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00002018-199716020-00002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9067121</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Ransom ES, Mueller RA. Safety considerations in the use of drug combinations during general anaesthesia. Drug Saf. 1997;16(2):88&#8211;103.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9067121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00002018-199716020-00002</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aranake</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mashour</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avidan</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Minimum alveolar concentration: ongoing relevance and clinical utility</article-title><source>Anaesthesia</source><year>2013</year><volume>68</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>512</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/anae.12168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23414556</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Aranake A, Mashour GA, Avidan MS. Minimum alveolar concentration: ongoing relevance and clinical utility. Anaesthesia. 2013;68(5):512&#8211;22.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23414556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/anae.12168</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cederbaum</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CYP2E1 and oxidative liver injury by alcohol</article-title><source>Free Radic Biol Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>44</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2007.11.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18078827</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2268632</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Lu Y, Cederbaum AI. CYP2E1 and oxidative liver injury by alcohol. Free Radic Biol Med. 2008;44(5):723&#8211;38.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18078827</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2007.11.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2268632</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kumar S, Singla B, Singh AK, Thomas-Gooch SM, Zhi K, Singh UP. Hepatic, extrahepatic and extracellular vesicle cytochrome P450 2E1 in alcohol and acetaminophen-mediated adverse interactions and potential treatment options. Cells. 2022;11(17).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/cells11172620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9454765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36078027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D-K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>H-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Estrogen-related receptor &#947; controls hepatic CB1receptor-mediated CYP2E1 expression and oxidative liver injury by alcohol</article-title><source>Gut</source><year>2013</year><volume>62</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1044</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2012-303347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23023167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3812689</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Kim D-K, Kim Y-H, Jang H-H, Park J, Kim JR, Koh M, et al. Estrogen-related receptor &#947; controls hepatic CB1receptor-mediated CYP2E1 expression and oxidative liver injury by alcohol. Gut. 2013;62(7):1044&#8211;54.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23023167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2012-303347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3812689</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Induction of brain CYP2E1 by chronic ethanol treatment and related oxidative stress in hippocampus, cerebellum, and brainstem</article-title><source>Toxicology</source><year>2012</year><volume>302</volume><issue>2&#8211;3</issue><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tox.2012.08.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22960445</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Zhong Y, Dong G, Luo H, Cao J, Wang C, Wu J, et al. Induction of brain CYP2E1 by chronic ethanol treatment and related oxidative stress in hippocampus, cerebellum, and brainstem. Toxicology. 2012;302(2&#8211;3):275&#8211;84.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22960445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tox.2012.08.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kharasch</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Artru</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karol</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical sevoflurane metabolism and disposition. II. The role of cytochrome P450 2E1 in fluoride and hexafluoroisopropanol formation</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><year>1995</year><volume>82</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1379</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000542-199506000-00009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7793652</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Kharasch ED, Armstrong AS, Gunn K, Artru A, Cox K, Karol MD. Clinical sevoflurane metabolism and disposition. II. The role of cytochrome P450 2E1 in fluoride and hexafluoroisopropanol formation. Anesthesiology. 1995;82(6):1379&#8211;88.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7793652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000542-199506000-00009</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kharasch</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biotransformation of sevoflurane</article-title><source>Anesth Analg</source><year>1995</year><volume>81</volume><issue>6 Suppl</issue><fpage>S27</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000539-199512001-00005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7486145</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Kharasch ED. Biotransformation of sevoflurane. Anesth Analg. 1995;81(6 Suppl):S27&#8211;38.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7486145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000539-199512001-00005</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Eger EI 2nd, Ionescu P, Laster MJ, Gong D, Hudlicky T, Kendig JJ, et al. Minimum alveolar anesthetic concentration of fluorinated alkanols in rats: relevance to theories of narcosis. Anesth Analg. 1999;88(4):867&#8211;76.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00000539-199904000-00035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10195540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X-B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>W-G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X-L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the level of free hexafluoro-isopropanol in adults&#8217; blood and the incidence of Emergence Agitation after Anesthesia with different concentrations of sevoflurane in laparoscopic gastrointestinal surgery: a Randomized Controlled Clinical Trial</article-title><source>Clin Ther</source><year>2019</year><volume>41</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2263</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinthera.2019.08.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31561881</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Feng Y, Chen X-B, Yuan W-G, Huang S, Li M, Yang X-L. Comparison of the level of free hexafluoro-isopropanol in adults&#8217; blood and the incidence of Emergence Agitation after Anesthesia with different concentrations of sevoflurane in laparoscopic gastrointestinal surgery: a Randomized Controlled Clinical Trial. Clin Ther. 2019;41(11):2263&#8211;72.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31561881</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinthera.2019.08.022</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haufroid</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardinal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Licot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villalpando</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Obbergh</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clippe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biological monitoring of exposure to sevoflurane in operating room personnel by the measurement of hexafluoroisopropanol and fluoride in urine</article-title><source>Biomarkers</source><year>2000</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/135475000230451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23885951</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Haufroid V, Gardinal S, Licot C, Villalpando ML, Obbergh LV, Clippe A, et al. Biological monitoring of exposure to sevoflurane in operating room personnel by the measurement of hexafluoroisopropanol and fluoride in urine. Biomarkers. 2000;5(2):141&#8211;51.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23885951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/135475000230451</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herzog-Niescery</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seipp</surname><given-names>H-M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellgardt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herzog</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belyaev</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uhl</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of 3 methods to assess Occupational Sevoflurane exposure in Abdominal surgeons: a single-Center Observational Pilot Study</article-title><source>Anesth Analg</source><year>2020</year><volume>131</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1213/ANE.0000000000004301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31295179</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Herzog-Niescery J, Seipp H-M, Bellgardt M, Herzog T, Belyaev O, Uhl W, et al. Comparison of 3 methods to assess Occupational Sevoflurane exposure in Abdominal surgeons: a single-Center Observational Pilot Study. Anesth Analg. 2020;131(2):537&#8211;43.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31295179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1213/ANE.0000000000004301</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forsyth</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farhadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rangan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakate</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaikh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide-mediated Intestinal Injury is required for Alcohol&#8208;Induced Gut leakiness and liver damage</article-title><source>Alcohol Clin Exp Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>33</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1220</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1530-0277.2009.00946.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19389191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2950098</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Tang Y, Forsyth CB, Farhadi A, Rangan J, Jakate S, Shaikh M, et al. Nitric oxide-mediated Intestinal Injury is required for Alcohol&#8208;Induced Gut leakiness and liver damage. Alcohol Clin Exp Res. 2009;33(7):1220&#8211;30.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19389191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1530-0277.2009.00946.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2950098</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#252;ller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pl&#246;chl</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reiter</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stimpfl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baron-Stefaniak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effect of oral &#8710;-9-tetrahydrocannabinol on the minimal alveolar concentration of sevoflurane</article-title><source>Eur J Anaesthesiol</source><year>2021</year><volume>38</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/EJA.0000000000001295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32833854</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">M&#252;ller J, Pl&#246;chl W, Reiter B, Stimpfl T, Graf A, Baron-Stefaniak J, et al. The effect of oral &#8710;-9-tetrahydrocannabinol on the minimal alveolar concentration of sevoflurane. Eur J Anaesthesiol. 2021;38(1):58&#8211;63.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32833854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/EJA.0000000000001295</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruells</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stabley</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCullough</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Behnke</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanical ventilation reduces rat diaphragm blood flow and impairs oxygen delivery and uptake*</article-title><source>Crit Care Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2858</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CCM.0b013e31825b933a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22846782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3455118</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Davis RT, Bruells CS, Stabley JN, McCullough DJ, Powers SK, Behnke BJ. Mechanical ventilation reduces rat diaphragm blood flow and impairs oxygen delivery and uptake*. Crit Care Med. 2012;40(10):2858&#8211;66.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22846782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CCM.0b013e31825b933a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3455118</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sha</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lung injury induced by short-term mechanical ventilation with hyperoxia and its mitigation by deferoxamine in rats</article-title><source>BMC Anesthesiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>188</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12871-020-01089-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32738874</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7395352</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Wang XX, Sha XL, Li YL, Li CL, Chen SH, Wang JJ, et al. Lung injury induced by short-term mechanical ventilation with hyperoxia and its mitigation by deferoxamine in rats. BMC Anesthesiol. 2020;20(1):188.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32738874</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12871-020-01089-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7395352</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao Yy, Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong Aj</surname><given-names>ZW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aplysin protects against Alcohol-Induced Liver Injury Via alleviating oxidative damage and modulating endogenous apoptosis&#8208;related genes expression in rats</article-title><source>J Food Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>83</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2612</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.14320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30192013</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Ge N, Liang H, Zhao Yy, Liu Y, Gong Aj ZW. Aplysin protects against Alcohol-Induced Liver Injury Via alleviating oxidative damage and modulating endogenous apoptosis&#8208;related genes expression in rats. J Food Sci. 2018;83(10):2612&#8211;21.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30192013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.14320</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cossec</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Binet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of rat hepatic 2E1 activity in function of age, sex and inducers: choice of an experimental model capable of testing the hepatotoxicity of low molecular weight compounds</article-title><source>Toxicol Lett</source><year>1999</year><volume>106</volume><issue>2&#8211;3</issue><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-4274(99)00058-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10403661</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Morel G, Cossec B, Lambert AM, Binet S. Evaluation of rat hepatic 2E1 activity in function of age, sex and inducers: choice of an experimental model capable of testing the hepatotoxicity of low molecular weight compounds. Toxicol Lett. 1999;106(2&#8211;3):171&#8211;80.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10403661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-4274(99)00058-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>A-g</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protective effect of Aplysin on hepatic injury in ethanol-treated rats</article-title><source>Food Chem Toxicol</source><year>2013</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2013.08.071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24001440</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Ge N, Liang H, Liu Y, Ma A-g, Han L. Protective effect of Aplysin on hepatic injury in ethanol-treated rats. Food Chem Toxicol. 2013;62:361&#8211;72.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24001440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2013.08.071</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lu N-S, Chiu W-C, Chen Y-L, Peng H-C, Shirakawa H, Yang S-C. Fish oil up-regulates hepatic autophagy in rats with chronic ethanol consumption. J Nutr Biochem. 2020, 77.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jnutbio.2019.108314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31884243</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ande</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of cytochrome P450 2e1 expression by ethanol: role of oxidative stress-mediated pkc/jnk/sp1 pathway</article-title><source>Cell Death Dis</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e554</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cddis.2013.78</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23519123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3615729</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Jin M, Ande A, Kumar A, Kumar S. Regulation of cytochrome P450 2e1 expression by ethanol: role of oxidative stress-mediated pkc/jnk/sp1 pathway. Cell Death Dis. 2013;4(3):e554.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23519123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cddis.2013.78</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3615729</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dupont</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bod&#233;nez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berthou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bardou</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytochrome P-450 2E1 activity and oxidative stress in alcoholic patients</article-title><source>Alcohol Alcohol</source><year>2000</year><volume>35</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/alcalc/35.1.98</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10684785</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Dupont I, Bod&#233;nez P, Berthou F, Simon B, Bardou LG, Lucas D. Cytochrome P-450 2E1 activity and oxidative stress in alcoholic patients. Alcohol Alcohol. 2000;35(1):98&#8211;103.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10684785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/alcalc/35.1.98</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malan</surname><given-names>TP</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kadota</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frink</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Jr. Renal function after sevoflurane or enflurane anesthesia in the Fischer 344 rat</article-title><source>Anesth Analg</source><year>1993</year><volume>77</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1213/00000539-199310000-00028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8214671</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Malan TP Jr., Kadota Y, Mata H, Frink EJ Jr., Brown BR. Jr. Renal function after sevoflurane or enflurane anesthesia in the Fischer 344 rat. Anesth Analg. 1993;77(4):817&#8211;21.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8214671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1213/00000539-199310000-00028</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Remete</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ponikvar-Svet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sedgwick</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chemical aspects of Human and Environmental overload with fluorine</article-title><source>Chem Rev</source><year>2021</year><volume>121</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>4678</fpage><lpage>742</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.chemrev.0c01263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33723999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8945431</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Han J, Kiss L, Mei H, Remete AM, Ponikvar-Svet M, Sedgwick DM, et al. Chemical aspects of Human and Environmental overload with fluorine. Chem Rev. 2021;121(8):4678&#8211;742.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33723999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.chemrev.0c01263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8945431</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mihic</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wick</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koltchine</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krasowski</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finn</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sites of alcohol and volatile anaesthetic action on GABA(A) and glycine receptors</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1997</year><volume>389</volume><issue>6649</issue><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/38738</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9311780</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Mihic SJ, Ye Q, Wick MJ, Koltchine VV, Krasowski MD, Finn SE, et al. Sites of alcohol and volatile anaesthetic action on GABA(A) and glycine receptors. Nature. 1997;389(6649):385&#8211;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9311780</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/38738</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Qiu J, Shi P, Mao W, Zhao Y, Liu W, Wang Y. Effect of apoptosis in neural stem cells treated with sevoflurane. BMC Anesthesiol. 2015;15(1).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12871-015-0018-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4359390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25774088</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC10885635"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brohan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goudra</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of GABA receptor agonists in Anesthesia and Sedation</article-title><source>CNS Drugs</source><year>2017</year><volume>31</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>845</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40263-017-0463-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29039138</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Brohan J, Goudra BG. The role of GABA receptor agonists in Anesthesia and Sedation. CNS Drugs. 2017;31(10):845&#8211;56.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29039138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40263-017-0463-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ghosh Dastidar S, Warner JB, Warner DR, McClain CJ, Kirpich IA. Rodent models of alcoholic liver disease: role of binge ethanol administration. Biomolecules. 2018, 8(1).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biom8010003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5871972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29342874</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martignoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Groothuis</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Kanter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Species differences between mouse, rat, dog, monkey and human CYP-mediated drug metabolism, inhibition and induction</article-title><source>Expert Opin Drug Metab Toxicol</source><year>2006</year><volume>2</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>875</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1517/17425255.2.6.875</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17125407</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Martignoni M, Groothuis GM, de Kanter R. Species differences between mouse, rat, dog, monkey and human CYP-mediated drug metabolism, inhibition and induction. Expert Opin Drug Metab Toxicol. 2006;2(6):875&#8211;94.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17125407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1517/17425255.2.6.875</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>