<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pain</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pain</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2035</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">lwwopen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JOP</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Pain</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0304-3959</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1872-6623</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Lippincott Open Access</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10723645</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10723645.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10723645</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10723645</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37782553</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/j.pain.0000000000003023</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PAIN-D-22-01180</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Development and internal validation of a prediction model for long-term opioid use&#8212;an analysis of insurance claims data</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3105-5840</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Held</surname><given-names initials="U">Ulrike</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forzy</surname><given-names initials="T">Tom</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><email>3e6forzytom@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Signorell</surname><given-names initials="A">Andri</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><email>andri.signorell@helsana.ch</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deforth</surname><given-names initials="M">Manja</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><email>manjaelisabeth.deforth@uzh.ch</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgstaller</surname><given-names initials="JM">Jakob M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><email>Jakob.Burgstaller@usz.ch</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wertli</surname><given-names initials="MM">Maria M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref><email>Maria.Wertli@ksb.ch</email></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Biostatistics at Epidemiology, Biostatistics and Prevention Institute, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Master Program Statistics, ETH Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Health Sciences, Helsana, D&#252;bendorf, Switzerland</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Institute of Primary Care, University and University Hospital Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Cantonal Hospital Baden KSB, Baden, Switzerland</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>Department of General Internal Medicine University Hospital Bern, University of Bern, Switzerland</aff><aff>Sponsorships or competing interests that may be relevant to content are disclosed at the end of this article.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding Author. Address. Department of Biostatistics at Epidemiology, Biostatistics and Prevention Institute, University of Zurich, Hirschengraben 84, 8001 Zurich, Switzerland. E-mail address: <email>Ulrike.Held@uzh.ch</email> (Ulrike Held).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>165</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">451131</issue-id><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>02</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>05</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-01-29 02:25:20.013"><day>29</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. on behalf of the International Association for the Study of Pain.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0 (CCBY-NC-ND)</ext-link>, where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially without permission from the journal.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jop-165-044.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jop-165-044.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p>Supplemental Digital Content is Available in the Text.</p><p>To investigate whether patients at risk for long-term opioid use can be identified early-on, a prognostic model was developed to identify these patients with high accuracy.</p></abstract><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>In the United States, a public-health crisis of opioid overuse has been observed, and in Europe, prescriptions of opioids are strongly increasing over time. The objective was to develop and validate a multivariable prognostic model to be used at the beginning of an opioid prescription episode, aiming to identify individual patients at high risk for long-term opioid use based on routinely collected data. Predictors including demographics, comorbid diseases, comedication, morphine dose at episode initiation, and prescription practice were collected. The primary outcome was long-term opioid use, defined as opioid use of either &gt;90 days duration and &#8805;10 claims or &gt;120 days, independent of the number of claims. Traditional generalized linear statistical regression models and machine learning approaches were applied. The area under the curve, calibration plots, and the scaled Brier score assessed model performance. More than four hundred thousand opioid episodes were included. The final risk prediction model had an area under the curve of 0.927 (95% confidence interval 0.924-0.931) in the validation set, and this model had a scaled Brier score of 48.5%. Using a threshold of 10% predicted probability to identify patients at high risk, the overall accuracy of this risk prediction model was 81.6% (95% confidence interval 81.2% to 82.0%). Our study demonstrated that long-term opioid use can be predicted at the initiation of an opioid prescription episode, with satisfactory accuracy using data routinely collected at a large health insurance company. Traditional statistical methods resulted in higher discriminative ability and similarly good calibration as compared with machine learning approaches.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords:</title><kwd>Long-term opioid use</kwd><kwd>Morphine equivalent</kwd><kwd>Clinical prediction model</kwd><kwd>Validation</kwd><kwd>Insurance claims data</kwd><kwd>Pain medication</kwd><kwd>Chronic pain</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>SDC</meta-name><meta-value>T</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>special-property</meta-name><meta-value>video</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>1. Introduction</title><sec id="s1-1"><title>1.1. Background and objectives</title><p>In the United States, a public health crisis of opioid abuse and addiction as a result of liberal opioid regulation and use has been observed.<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> In Europe, the monitoring system indicates an increased use of opioids and there is some evidence of increased opioid addiction.<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> Increasing prescriptions of opioids in the United States were a result of physicians' accepting low-quality studies' evidence that opioids are effective and harmless to treat chronic pain.<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> Given the potential personal, societal, public health, and economic costs of opioid dependency and opioid-related adverse events, preventive measures should be implemented to prevent unintended long-term opioid use.</p><p>Opioids are intended to relieve acute severe pain in patients with active cancer, but strong opioids are not recommended for long-term use in patients with chronic noncancer pain since nonopioid alternatives exist.<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> In chronic pain, opioids are not more effective than nonopioid medications but may also have unintended adverse events.<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> Common adverse events after opioid prescriptions are emergency department visits, infections, hospitalizations, ICU admissions, or death, and these are known to occur with an increased risk with increase in daily dosage and with increased duration of opioid use.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> Thus, although the short-term use of opioid therapy may be beneficial, long-term use of opioids is generally not associated with benefit and is associated with risk for these adverse events. Therefore, it would be clinically important to know at the initiation of an opioid prescription episode, who will be at high risk to evolve into long-term opioid use.</p><p>In this study, we aimed to develop and validate a prognostic multivariable clinical prediction model for the outcome long-term opioid use that may help to identify individual patients at risk for long-term opioid use. We used a patient cohort with opioid use and assessed a large set of risk factors for long-term opioid use. We hypothesized that socioeconomic, episode-specific, and prescription-specific factors, as well as comorbidities and comedication use may help to identify individuals at high risk for long-term opioid use.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2"><title>2. Methods</title><p>The reporting of this study was performed according to the transparent reporting of a multivariable prediction model for individual prognosis or diagnosis (TRIPOD) guidelines.<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup></p><sec id="s2-1"><title>2.1. Source of data</title><p>This study is based on data of one of the largest insurance companies in Switzerland, the Helsana insurance group. The patient-level linked database provided information on sociodemographic data, prescribed drugs, and healthcare encounters.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>2.2. Participants</title><p>The study cohort consisted of all consecutive adult patients (aged 18 years and older) of the Helsana insurance company with at least one opioid claim between January 1, 2013, and December 31, 2018. Opioid prescriptions were identified using unique codes of the WHO pharmacological Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical (ATC) classification system. Each opioid prescription is associated with a morphine conversion factor that can be used to calculate morphine equivalent doses to compare different opioids. Excluded were those patients who were in an opioid use disorder treatment program.<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>2.3. Definition of an opioid episode</title><p>The methods used to develop opioid episodes have been previously described.<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> In brief, an opioid episode was defined as a continuous time interval in which we assumed daily opioid use. The first day of an episode begins with an initial opioid prescription, that is, claim. The duration of an opioid episode was calculated as the difference in days between the date of the initial prescription and the run-out date of the last prescription plus 1. If 3 months after the calculated run-out date no new claim was filed, the episode ended.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>2.4. Average daily opioid dose at episode initiation</title><p>The average daily dose was calculated based on the morphine equivalent dose (MED) per prescription.<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> In cases of multiple claims, the MED per treatment day was calculated across the multiple claims. For the calculation of the initial dose category, the daily MED dose between claims was categorized into 4 groups of average daily dosage, &lt;20, 20 to &lt;50, 50 to &lt;100, and &#8805;100 mg MED per day.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>2.5. Outcome</title><p>The primary outcome to be predicted in this study was the development of long-term opioid use. Following the definition by von Korff et al.,<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> long-term opioid use is defined as an episode of opioid use of either &gt;90 days duration and &#8805;10 opioid claims or &gt;120 days, independent of the number of opioid claims. All other episodes of opioid prescriptions were considered short-term (ie, acute or subacute). The outcome categorization was performed retrospectively for all patients included in the analysis. It was assessed independently from the predictor variables at episode start.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>2.6. Predictors</title><p>The predictors considered in this study covered different aspects of risk for long-term opioid use in each patient. Predictors were defined a priori by consulting the relevant literature<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> and during discussions within the interdisciplinary research group. There was no variable selection performed based on methodological criteria. The timing when each of the predictors was assessed was at the beginning of each opioid episode since the prediction model is intended to be used at the time of episode initiation.</p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>2.7. Predictor domains included</title><p>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>(1) Demographic variables: age in categories &lt;50 years (reference category), 50 to &lt;60, 60 to &lt;70, 70 to &lt;80, and &#8805;80 and sex</p></list-item><list-item><p>(2) Socioeconomic variables: place of residence in a non-German language speaking vs German-speaking canton of Switzerland, insurance type (additional private or semiprivate insured), and managed care model</p></list-item><list-item><p>(3) Episode specific variables: initial dosage category categorized into &lt;20, 20 to &lt;50, 50 to &lt;100, and &#8805;100 mg MED per day; prescriber variables (indicating whether the patient had a single vs multiple prescribers of opioids); previous opioid use categorized into never, &gt;2 years ago, 6 months to 2 years ago, and within last 6 months</p></list-item><list-item><p>(4) Disease specific risk factors: comorbidities and comedication use.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p>Although in Switzerland, the level of inequality is relatively low compared with other countries,<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> there are some differences in social status. The socioeconomic variables include proxies such as the place of residence (French/Italian-speaking parts as compared with German-speaking parts of Switzerland are associated with a lower index of socioeconomic position),<sup><xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> additional private or semiprivate insurance is more expensive, and managed care models are less expensive than standard policies.</p><p>Comorbid diseases were identified using the Chronic Disease Score (CDS). The CDS has been associated with healthcare use.<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> Chronic diseases included chronic infections, inflammatory disease, renal disease, endocrinologic disease, diabetes, lung or pulmonary disease, neurological disease, cardiovascular disease, hyperlipidemia, glaucoma, acid peptic disease, thyroid disease, gout, psychiatric disease or depression, spine disease, musculoskeletal disease, and cancer. Comorbid diseases were included as binary predictors.</p><p>Comedication use included stimulants, bisphosphonates, muscle relaxants, nonopioid analgesic use, and benzodiazepines, all of them also coded as binary predictors assessed at episode initiation.</p></sec><sec id="s2-8"><title>2.8. Sample size</title><p>The initial number of patients for the development and validation of the prediction model was 266,476. This allows the simultaneous evaluation of all the predictor variables without any restrictions.<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="s2-9"><title>2.9. Missing data</title><p>The number of patients with missing values in one or more of the predictor variables was 53 patients, representing less than 0.02% of the patients. Given the computational complexity of a methodological solution for missing values in a database of this size, the decision to exclude these patients seemed adequate.</p></sec><sec id="s2-10"><title>2.10. Statistical analysis methods</title><p>All analyses were performed with the use of the statistical programming language R<sup><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> (version 4.2.0) and specific additional packages, in a fully scripted and reproducible way. In the primary analysis, a multiple logistic regression model (generalized linear model) with fixed effects was fitted to the outcome of long-term opioid use. In this model, no interaction terms between predictor variables were evaluated. No variable selection was performed. Model assumptions were verified.</p><p>As a sensitivity analysis, a generalized linear mixed effects model with random intercepts was fitted to account for the correlation of repeated episodes within patients. We also performed another sensitivity analysis using machine learning approaches. We fitted 2 random forest models using the same predictor variables and outcome as before. Random forest models are bagged decision tree models that are fitted on subsets of the full data set. The use of random forest models can be justified by their flexibility. Random forest models are typically adequate for large data sets, are robust to outliers, and still allow for the assessment of relative variable importance. The first random forest model was fitted on default bootstrap samples, meaning that the training sets for the decision trees were sampled randomly with replacement from the full data set. To control imbalance in the initial data set regarding the outcome categories, a second random forest model was fitted on stratified random samples. This means that the data set is divided in strata before the random sampling. In the random forest framework, potential interactions are naturally considered. For fitting the random forests, the R-package randomForest<sup><xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> was used.</p></sec><sec id="s2-11"><title>2.11. Model derivation and validation, model performance</title><p>We used an internal&#8211;external validation approach for the logistic regression model, and the random forests, by repeatedly splitting the data set into a training and a validation set of sizes 90% and 10%, respectively. Model performance was assessed for discrimination ability and calibration across validation sets. Discrimination was quantified with the area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUC) with bootstrap 95% confidence intervals (CI).<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Calibration was visualized with calibration plots by dividing the obtained predictions of event for every individual into groups and then measuring how close the average prediction is to the actual proportion of events within the group. The calibration plots show the observed event rate as a function of the predicted rate. We have one point for every group, from which we create a smooth calibration curve by fitting restricted cubic splines using 3 knots. Calibration was assessed overall and in subgroups of patients with different covariate patterns, as suggested by Van Calster et al.<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> The scaled Brier score was calculated as a measure to quantify overall accuracy of the predicted probabilities. The scaled Brier score typically ranges from 0% to 100%, and its interpretation is that higher values indicate better overall accuracy. The scaled Brier score's interpretation is similar to Pearson R<sup>2</sup> statistic, and thus, resulting estimates can be interpreted accordingly.<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> In addition, mean decrease in accuracy and mean decrease in Gini coefficient were evaluated graphically for the random forest approach with random sampling.</p></sec><sec id="s2-12"><title>2.12. Risk groups and thresholding</title><p>A threshold of 10% predicted probability for long-term opioid use in the final logistic regression model was chosen to classify episodes into high risk vs low risk. The threshold was chosen because a risk for long-term opioid use of 10% may be considered acceptable when assuming that a conservative estimate of 2.5% of those patients will eventually develop an opioid use disorder.<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> The thresholding may simplify a clinical decision based on the risk prediction model's probabilities estimated from logistic regression. Patients with a predicted probability of &#8805;10% were considered at high risk for the development of a long-term opioid episode, whereas patients below the threshold were considered at low risk. This allowed the direct comparison between the results from the logistic regression analysis with the random forest approaches. Overall accuracy, as measured with percentage of correctly classified episodes, as well as sensitivity, specificity, and positive and negative predictive value were estimated. The same threshold of &#8805; 10% of the derivation set was also used in the validation set.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>3. Results</title><p>Between January 1, 2013, and December 31, 2018, 418,625 episodes of opioid prescriptions were observed in a population of 266,476 patients. Of these, 61 episodes (53 patients) had missing data for one or more predictor variables and were excluded from the analyses (Fig. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). In total, 418,564 (71,863 [17%] long-term) episodes in 266,423 patients were analyzed. The median duration of an episode was 7 days (interquartile range, IQR, 3-50 days), and the mean duration was 106 days (standard deviation, SD = 301 days).</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Flow chart of study population and study set used for analysis. N_epi indicates the number of episodes. N indicates the number of patients.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jop-165-044-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>Patient characteristics of the episodes at the initiation of opioid use are summarized in Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Most patients were 70 years or older (37.1%), female (59.7%), living in a German-speaking region (71.4%), and had no additional insurance or managed care model. Most episodes started with opioid doses &lt;20 mg MED (39.4%) and only in a minority of episodes multiple prescribers were observed (1.6%). Most patients had no prior episode (63.7%). Most frequently observed comorbid diseases in the overall population were inflammatory diseases (20.3%), cardiovascular disease (29.1%), acid peptic disease (32.3%), and musculoskeletal disease (13.6%). Comedications included nonopioid analgesics (66.0%), muscle relaxants (11.1%), and benzodiazepines (12.5%).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Descriptive statistics at episode initiation among long-term and short-term opioid users.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long-term opioid use</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Only short-term opioid use</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(N = 71,863)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(N = 346,701)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(N = 418,564)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&lt;50 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,709 (16.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110,174 (31.8%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121,883 (29.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;50 to &lt;60 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,843 (15.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59,131 (17.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69,974 (16.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;60 to &lt;70 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,294 (17.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59,374 (17.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71,668 (17.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;70 to &lt;80 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,464 (22.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61,634 (17.8%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78,098 (18.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8805;80 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,553 (28.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56,388 (16.3%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76,941 (18.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46,740 (65.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">202,983 (58.5%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249,723 (59.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25,123 (35.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143,718 (41.5%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168,841 (40.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Language region</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;French or Italian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,704 (27.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99,933 (28.8%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">119,637 (28.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Swiss German</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52,159 (72.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">246,768 (71.2%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">298,927 (71.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Semi) private insurance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,012 (18.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64,393 (18.6%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77,405 (18.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Managed care model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28,972 (40.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176,978 (51.0%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205,950 (49.2%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial MED mg dose category</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&lt;20 (category D)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40,214 (56.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124,859 (36.0%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165,073 (39.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;20 to &lt;50 (category C)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,822 (22.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124,078 (35.8%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139,900 (33.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;50 to &lt;100 (category B)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8863 (12.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77,669 (22.4%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86,532 (20.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8805;100 (category A)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6964 (9.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,095 (5.8%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,059 (6.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple prescribers</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1376 (1.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5473 (1.6%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6849 (1.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prior episode</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No prior episode</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40,310 (56.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">226,113 (65.2%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266,423 (63.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Previous episode &lt;6 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,821 (20.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33,403 (9.6%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48,224 (11.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Previous episode 6 months to 2 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,573 (18.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63,193 (18.2%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76,766 (18.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Previous episode &gt;2 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3159 (4.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23,992 (6.9%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,151 (6.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbid diseases</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Chronic infections</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6329 (8.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4243 (1.2%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,572 (2.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Inflammatory disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35,290 (49.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49,713 (14.3%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85,003 (20.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Renal disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">943 (1.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">633 (0.2%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1576 (0.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Endocrinologic disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1197 (1.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">776 (0.2%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1973 (0.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Diabetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,663 (16.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,446 (3.6%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24,109 (5.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Lung disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,048 (19.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,111 (3.2%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25,159 (6.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Neurological disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4700 (6.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2897 (0.8%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7597 (1.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Cardiovascular disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52,184 (72.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69,415 (20.0%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121,599 (29.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Hyperlipidemia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,941 (29.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,929 (4.9%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37,870 (9.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Glaucoma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6108 (8.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2749 (0.8%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8857 (2.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Acid peptic disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51,278 (71.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83,771 (24.2%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135,049 (32.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Thyroid disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7938 (11.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6430 (1.9%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,368 (3.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Gout</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4475 (6.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3268 (0.9%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7743 (1.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Psychiatric dis. or depression</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31,317 (43.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21,129 (6.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52,446 (12.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Spine disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7739 (10.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3958 (1.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,697 (2.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Musculoskeletal disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29,114 (40.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,743 (8.0%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56,857 (13.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9443 (13.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,315 (6.4%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31,758 (7.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comedications</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Stimulants</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">637 (0.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">417 (0.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1054 (0.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Bisphosphonates</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5473 (7.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2457 (0.7%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7930 (1.9%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Muscle relaxants</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,711 (19.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32,877 (9.5%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46,588 (11.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Nonopioid analgesics</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65,194 (90.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">210,903 (60.8%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">276,097 (66.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Benzodiazepines</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26,243 (36.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26,005 (7.5%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52,248 (12.5%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>A higher proportion of patients with long-term episodes were aged 70 years or older (51.5% vs 34.1%), had episodes with an initial opioid dose &lt;20 mg MED (56.0% vs 36.0%), and had a prior episode of less than 6 months ago (20.6% vs 9.6%). Patients with long-term episodes had more inflammatory diseases (49.1% vs 14.3%), lung diseases (19.5% vs 3.2%), diabetes (16.2% vs 3.6%), cardiovascular disease (72.6% vs 20.0%), acid peptic disease (71.4% vs 24.2%), psychiatric diseases or depression (43.6% vs 6.1%), musculoskeletal disease (40.5% vs 8.0%), and cancer (13.1% vs 6.4%). Patients with long-term episodes were more likely to have additional nonopioid analgesics (90.7% vs 60.8%) and benzodiazepines (36.5% vs 7.5%). Patients with short-term opioid episodes were younger (48.9% aged 59 or younger), in a managed care model (51.0% vs 40.3%), had a higher proportion with initial MED dose between 50 and 100 mg (22.4% vs 12.3%), and had no prior episode (65.2% vs 56.1%).</p><sec id="s3-1"><title>3.1. Logistic regression model</title><p>The final logistic regression model with fixed effects (Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) showed an increased risk for long-term opioid use in patients aged 80 years and older (OR 1.525, 95% CI 1.468-1.585), with multiple prescribers (OR 1.222, 95% CI 1.124-1.328), and a previous episode within the last 6 months (OR 1.789, 95% CI 1.732-1.848). The presence of comorbid diseases and comedications increased the odds for long-term opioid use.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Estimated coefficients, standard errors, odds ratios, and 95% confidence intervals of the final logistic regression model.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Domain</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Label</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coefficient</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI for OR</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intercept</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;4.069</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016&#8211;0.018</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Age group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 50 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 to &lt;60 years</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.031</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.969</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.933&#8211;1.007</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 to &lt;70 years</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.151</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.860</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.827&#8211;0.894</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 to &lt;80 years</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.099</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.906</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.872&#8211;0.942</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;80 years</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.422</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.525</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.468&#8211;1.585</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.994&#8211;1.043</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Socioeconomic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Language region</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Swiss German</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">French or Italian</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.068</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.934</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91&#8211;0.959</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Insurance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No additional insurance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Semi) private insurance</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.193</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.824</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.799&#8211;0.85</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Managed care</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No managed care model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Managed care model</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.096</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.909</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.887&#8211;0.93</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Episode specific</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Initial MED (mg) dose category</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.567</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.567</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.543&#8211;0.593</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 to &lt;100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.276</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.279</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27&#8211;0.289</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 to &lt;50</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.869</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.420</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.408&#8211;0.432</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Prescriber</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">One prescriber</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1 prescriber</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.222</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.124&#8211;1.328</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Prior episode</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No prior episode</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous episode &lt;6 months</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.582</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.789</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.732&#8211;1.848</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous episode 6 months to 2 years</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.023</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.977</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.948&#8211;1.007</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous episode &gt;2 years</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.313</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.731</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.694&#8211;0.77</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disease specific</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Comorbidities</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No comorbidities</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic infections</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.926</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.525</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.384&#8211;2.675</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inflammatory disease</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.578</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.783</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.735&#8211;1.831</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Renal disease</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.196</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.079</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.217</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.043&#8211;1.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endocrinologic disease</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.638</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.892</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.651&#8211;2.167</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.453</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.573</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.513&#8211;1.636</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung disease</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.894</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.446</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.353&#8211;2.542</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurological disease</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.913</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.493</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.329&#8211;2.668</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiovascular disease</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.165</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.206</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.122&#8211;3.291</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyperlipidemia</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.055</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.989&#8211;2.123</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glaucoma</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.232</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.429</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.215&#8211;3.657</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acid peptic disease</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.892</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.382&#8211;2.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thyroid disease</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.665</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.944</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.853&#8211;2.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gout</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.575</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.777</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.665&#8211;1.896</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychiatric disease or depression</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.381</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.981</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.871&#8211;4.093</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spine disease</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.639</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.489&#8211;2.797</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Musculoskeletal disease</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.129</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.093</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.007&#8211;3.182</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.136</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.093&#8211;1.181</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comedications</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No comedications</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stimulants</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.107</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.094</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.025</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.514&#8211;3.64</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bisphosphonates</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.204</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.332</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.113&#8211;3.565</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Muscle relaxants</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.468</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.597</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.544&#8211;1.651</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-opioid analgesic use</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.363</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.287&#8211;2.441</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benzodiazepines</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.802</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.167&#8211;2.295</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>CI, confidence interval; OR, odds ratio; SE, standard error.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The final fixed-effects model resulted in an AUC value of 0.927 (95% CI 0.924-0.931), Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, and a scaled Brier score of 48.5% in the validation set. As a sensitivity analysis, random forests with bootstrap samples and with stratified samples were trained. The resulting AUC values were 0.909 (0.905-0.913) and 0.921 (0.918-0.925), respectively. Mean decrease in accuracy (eFig. 1, available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/PAIN/B902" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/PAIN/B902</ext-link>) and mean decrease in Gini coefficient (eFig. 2, available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/PAIN/B902" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/PAIN/B902</ext-link>) were evaluated graphically for the random forest with bootstrap samples. Both plots indicate that the predictors' psychiatric disease or depression and cardiovascular disease are most relevant for accuracy and homogeneity of the random forest, respectively. The ROC curves of the random forest approaches can be found in eFig. 3 (available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/PAIN/B902" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/PAIN/B902</ext-link>). The scaled Brier scores were 46.0% and 29.1%, respectively.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>ROC curve of the logistic regression model (GLM).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jop-165-044-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>Regarding the models' calibration, the calibration plots for the fixed effects logistic regression, the random forest with bootstrap samples, and the random forest with stratified sample were shown and revealed that the calibration of the former 2 models (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> left and middle) were comparably good, whereas the latter calibration plot (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> right) showed unsatisfactory calibration. Calibration was assessed in subgroups of patients with different covariate patterns. In eFig. 4 (available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/PAIN/B902" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/PAIN/B902</ext-link>), calibration for the fixed-effects logistic regression model is shown in subgroups of sex and age groups.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Faceted calibration plots, left: logistic regression (GLM), middle: random forest with bootstrap samples (RF), right: random forest with stratified samples (stratified RF). On the x-axis, bin midpoints represent the central values within each bin or interval; they are computed as the mean value of the lower and upper bonds of the bin. On the y-axis, the event rates for the observations in the bin are shown.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jop-165-044-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>3.2. Thresholding</title><p>Using a threshold of &#8805; 10% predicted probability of long-term opioid use, indicating patients at high risk, the overall accuracy of the fixed-effects logistic regression was 81.6% (95% CI from 81.2% to 82.0%). The corresponding sensitivity was 90.5%, and specificity was 80.8%, resulting in a positive predictive value of 48.5% and negative predictive value of 97.5%. The corresponding results for the random forest with bootstrap samples were 86.5% overall accuracy (95% CI from 86.1 to 86.8), sensitivity of 83.2%, and specificity of 87.2%. For the selected random forest with stratified samples, the corresponding overall accuracy was 77.5% (95% CI from 77.1 to 77.9), sensitivity was 93.4%, and specificity was 74.2%.</p></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>3.3. How to use the prediction model</title><p>The prediction model resulting from the logistic regression analysis can be used by multiplying the risk factor information of each new patient in the initial phase of an opioid episode with the corresponding coefficient as shown in Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref> (including the intercept) and adding them up, resulting in S. The result needs to be transformed to the probability scale by calculating <inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#8289;</mml:mo><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as the returned individual's predicted probability for the episode developing into one with long-term opioid use.</p><p>In this context, 6 patient scenarios were derived to demonstrate the usefulness of the model for clinical practice. A low-risk scenario would be a 65-year-old male person, living in the Italian-speaking part of Switzerland, is in a managed care model, has a semiprivate insurance, received an initial dose of 30 mg from one prescriber, had no prior episode, does not have any comorbid diseases, and takes no comedication. For this man, the predicted probability to develop a long-term episode is extremely low (0.44%). A high-risk scenario would be a 70-year-old woman, living in the German-speaking part of Switzerland, is in no managed care model, with an initial dose of 30 mg from one prescriber, with a prior episode of opioid use within the last 6 months, with lung disease, musculoskeletal and neurological disease, and currently taking bisphosphonates and benzodiazepines at the start of the opioid episode. For this woman, the predicted probability to develop a long-term opioid episode is with 62% very high. More scenarios are presented in the style of a study by Oliva et al.,<sup><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> together with the resulting predicted probabilities for long-term opioid use, in Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Patient scenarios and their resulting estimated probabilities for long-term opioid use.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Language region</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insurance model</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial opioid dose</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prescriber(s)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prior episode</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbidities</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comedication</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probability for long-term opioid use</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Managed care (Semi) private insurance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 mg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">German</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No managed care model<break/>No additional insurance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 mg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within past 6 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung disease<break/>Musculoskeletal disease<break/>Neurological disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bisphosphonate<break/>Benzodiazepine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.9%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">German</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No managed care model<break/>No additional insurance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;20 mg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within past 6 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic infection<break/>Cardiovascular disease<break/>Psychiatric disease<break/>Musculoskeletal disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benzodiazepine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.2%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">French</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Managed care<break/>No additional insurance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 mg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Between 6 months and 2 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiovascular disease<break/>Psychiatric disease<break/>Musculoskeletal disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bisphosphonate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.7%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">German</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Managed care<break/>No additional insurance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;100 mg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within past 6 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inflammatory disease<break/>Cardiovascular disease<break/>Psychiatric disease<break/>Musculoskeletal disease<break/>Neurological disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bisphosphonate<break/>Benzodiazepine<break/>Nonopioid analgesic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.2%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Managed care<break/>No additional insurance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;100 mg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiovascular disease<break/>Musculoskeletal disease<break/>Neurological disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nonopioid analgesic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.7%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>4. Discussion</title><p>The prevalence of chronic pain in the U.S. adult population has been estimated to be 20%, with a dramatic increase in the elderly.<sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> Older adults are also more likely to need surgery, a risk factor for initiating an opioid therapy. Owing to an impaired kidney function, other pain medications may not be an option, and thus, opioids are needed to control pain. Although opioids in chronic pain are no more effective than other pain medications, stopping opioid treatment has been shown to be challenging.<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> In our study, we showed that the development of long-term opioid use can be predicted with satisfactory accuracy, as measured with discriminative ability and calibration, if demographic information, episode specific information, comorbidities, and comedication use are known. In our model, comorbidities (chronic, inflammatory and lung diseases, diabetes, cardiovascular and acid peptic disease, musculoskeletal disease, psychiatric disease or depression, and cancer) were associated with an increased risk for long-term opioid use. Other factors that increased risk for long-term opioid use were patients aged 80 years and older, multiple prescribers, a previous episode within the past 6 months, and comedication use. Higher initial opioid dose was associated with reduced risk of long-term opioid use.</p><p>The results of our study are in line with similar models that were recently published.<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Oliva et al.<sup><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> derived a predictive risk model for the outcome overdose-related or suicide-related event in a Veterans Health Administration population with an opioid prescription. They found that mental health disorders including posttraumatic stress, major depression, bipolar disorder, and other mental health disorders increased the odds for overdose or suicide-related events substantially. In our study, psychiatric disease or depression were found to be the comorbidities with the largest estimated effect as compared with all other comorbidities. Sullivan and Howe<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> argue that long-term opioid use is recommended only for patients with persistent pain in the absence of a history of substance abuse. Although individuals in opioid use disorder treatment programs were not included in our study, we found that comedication use such as benzodiazepines and stimulants increased the risk for long-term opioid use. Apart from previous opioid use, we did not have any other documentation of individuals who might have a history of substance abuse in our study. Sullivan and Howe<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> describe a seemingly adverse selection of patients for long-term opioid use in which patients with substance use or mental health disorders are overrepresented in a population of opioid users.</p><p>Other publications were focused on the identification on strongest predictors among the set of potential predictor variables, and they found that older age, White race, hourly wage, low back pain, and osteoarthritis were the strongest predictors besides calendar year.<sup><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> Another publication identified comorbidities to be indicative of incident chronic use, but the comparison group was patients without opioid prescriptions, therefore, not directly comparable with our study.<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> None of the above publications reported on overall performance of their models regarding discrimination or calibration, and their final models were not validated. In our application, logistic regression with a generalized linear model showed better discriminative ability than the 2 machine learning approaches. Calibration was comparable across the logistic regression model and the random forest with bootstrap samples. These findings are in line with systematic evaluations of Gravesteijn et al.<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> in which the authors found that the performance of machine learning approaches was generally not better than regression-based approaches in the field of traumatic brain injury. Christodoulou et al.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> systematically evaluated the literature on clinical prediction models to evaluate whether there was evidence for superior performance of machine learning over logistic regression for binary outcomes. In clinical prediction models at low risk of bias, the authors found no evidence for a performance benefit of machine learning approaches. Calibration levels for risk prediction models were recently defined,<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> and our final model's calibration plots shows that predicted risks correspond well to observed event rates, not only overall but also for age groups and sex patterns, indicating a strong calibration level.</p><p>The population in our study included cancer and noncancer patients, whereas in other publications, the cancer patients were explicitly excluded. This makes our prediction model useful for all settings in which opioid use may be indicated. With a threshold of 10% or higher as cut-off for patients at high-risk for long-term opioid use, our model showed high accuracy overall, as well as high sensitivity and specificity.</p><sec id="s4-1"><title>4.1. Limitations and strengths</title><p>The data used for the derivation and validation of the prediction model were retrospective, and initially, the data were not collected for the purpose of the development of a clinical prediction model for long-term opioid use. The data were collected at Helsana health insurance group covering 1,2 million individuals and representing approximately 12 to 14% of the Swiss population across all 26 administrative regions (cantons) of Switzerland. A health insurance is compulsory in Switzerland. The data underlying the study may be seen as representative because comparisons of the Helsana population against the Swiss population revealed no evidence for differences in age and sex distribution. Helsana has good coverage across all Swiss cantons, and it was deemed representative for the Swiss population in recent publications on laboratory testing and antidepressant prescriptions.<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> In Switzerland, opioid prescriptions require a separate narcotic prescription that is filed by the pharmacy and reimbursed by the insurance company (tiers payant). Opioids are not sold over the counter, and thus, a high level of ascertainment is guaranteed.</p><p>Insurance claims data do not provide information on clinical diagnosis and the reasons for the opioid prescription. Although using insurance or routinely collected data often are not ideal and have limitations, they provide real-world evidence; they are readily available and may help to identify patients at risk for long-term opioid use. We assessed the burden of disease in patients by using CDC categories that are derived from individual medication use associated with specific comorbidities. The final prediction model had a high scaled Brier score of 48.5%, with an interpretation corresponding to that of an R<sup>2</sup> value of a linear regression model, and thus, it is rather unlikely that additional essential areas of information were missing. In our definition of an opioid episode, the actual opioid intake could be overestimated, if a patient did not use all prescribed opioids. In the assessment of whether a prior episode of opioid consumption was observed, there may be underreporting in the sense that patients might have had prior episodes in times where they were not covered by Helsana health insurance. We set a threshold for high-risk patients to develop long-term opioid use at 10% predicted probability. This threshold was based on an assumed estimate of 2.5% of patients eventually developing an opioid use disorder. Although a definition of a threshold for the overall risk for adverse events may be preferable, this may result in a very high number of patients at risk. According to a Cochrane systematic review, between 6 and 85% of patients suffered from any opioid related adverse event and between 2.5 and 22% from a serious adverse event.<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></p><p>Our study has several strengths. These include the representativeness of the large number of observations collected across Switzerland. The number of events per variable was sufficient to fit logistic regression models and random forest models using all risk factors simultaneously, and no variable selection was necessary. A systematic evaluation in the field of clinical prediction models in oncology by Dhiman et al.<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> reported poor methodological conduct of studies using machine learning. By contrast, we aimed at a rigorous internal&#8211;external validation approach for the model derivation and validation, for both strategies including logistic regression and the random forest approaches. Subsequently, we aimed for a neutral comparison of model performance across the 2 strategies.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>4.2. Implications for clinical practice</title><p>The prediction model has several implications for clinical practice. First, at the time of an initial prescription, the beginning of an opioid episode, it is possible to predict with satisfying accuracy whether the episode will become long-term. An external validation of the prediction model should be performed to evaluate the model's performance in new and prospectively collected patients. This may be performed using other insurance data bases or a prospective collection of patients in a clinical setting. Furthermore, the development of new prediction models for long-term opioid use in other insurance companies and healthcare systems, similar to the implementation of the STORM risk scores derived from the Veteran Health Administration population in the United States, could be enhanced.<sup><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> For patients at high risk for long-term opioid use, early goal directed therapies with multimodal approaches should be discussed, and the awareness of the treating physician should be raised. A collaboration between health insurance company, patients, and physicians may thus result in improved outcome and prevent the need for long-term opioid use. An impact study would reveal the net benefit of the proposed prediction model in clinical practice.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><title>5. Conclusions</title><p>Our study demonstrated that long-term opioid use can be predicted at the initiation of an opioid prescription episode, with satisfactory accuracy using data routinely collected at a large health insurance company. Traditional statistical methods resulted in higher discriminative ability and similarly good calibration as compared with machine learning approaches.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p>The authors have no conflict of interest to declare.</p></sec><sec><title>Appendix A. Supplemental digital content</title><supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><p>Supplemental digital content associated with this article can be found online at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/PAIN/B902" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/PAIN/B902</ext-link>.</p></supplementary-material></sec><sec><title>Supplemental video content</title><supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><p>A video abstract associated with this article can be found on the journal Web site. </p></supplementary-material></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><fig id="s001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jop-165-044-s001.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></fig></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Analysis preregistration: The outline of the research project was described in May 2021. The abstract can be found under <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.biostat.uzh.ch/fileadmin/biostat/user/Master_thesis_abstract___Pain_Medication.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.biostat.uzh.ch/fileadmin/biostat/user/Master_thesis_abstract___Pain_Medication.pdf</ext-link>. No formal preregistration of the research project was performed.</p><p>Author contributions: AS, UH, and TF had full access to all the data. UH and TF take the responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p>Concept and design: UH and MW; Acquisition, analysis, and interpretation of data: AS, UH, TF, MD, JB, and MW; Drafting of the manuscript: UH. Critical revision of the manuscript for intellectual content: TF, MD, AS, JB, and MW. Statistical analysis: TF. Supervision: UH and MW. Analytical code transparency and research materials transparency. Data underlying the study belong to a third party and cannot be made publicly available. This study is based on administrative, deidentified insurance claims data handled in compliance with privacy law and regulations. The analyses were performed within the premises of the Department of Health Sciences at the Helsana, and only aggregated data were shared. Aggregated data can be made available on reasonable request after assessment and permission of the data owner (Helsana Insurances Group). Data requests can be made to Department of Health Sciences, Helsana, Z&#252;richstrasse 130, CH-8600 D&#252;bendorf, Switzerland (website: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.helsana.ch/de/private" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.helsana.ch/de/private</ext-link>, phone: +41 58 340 18 80, email: <email>Gesundheitskompetenz@helsana.ch</email>). The authors confirm that they did not have any special access to these data which other researchers would not have. The statistical analysis code will be made available on request to the corresponding author.</p><p>Ethics declarations.</p><p>This study was based on administrative deidentified insurance claims data handled in compliance with privacy law and regulations. According to the local ethical committee (Ethical Committee of the Canton Zurich, Switzerland), no institutional review board (IRB) approval was required. The study was conducted following the principles of good clinical practice and in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>Sponsorships or competing interests that may be relevant to content are disclosed at the end of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Supplemental digital content is available for this article. Direct URL citations appear in the printed text and are provided in the HTML and PDF versions of this article on the journal's Web site (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.painjournalonline.com" ext-link-type="uri">www.painjournalonline.com</ext-link>).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedene</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lijfering</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arbous</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosendaal</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dahan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Dorp</surname><given-names>ELA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Association between prescription opioid use and unplanned intensive care unit admission and mortality in the adult population of The Netherlands: a registry study</article-title>. <source>Br J Anaesth</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>129</volume>:<fpage>254</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35752474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bja.2022.05.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beliveau</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McMahan</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arenander</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angst</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kushel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coffin</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Stimulant use for self-management of pain among safety-net patients with chronic non-cancer pain</article-title>. <source>Subst Abus</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>86</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33798030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/08897077.2021.1903654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8791072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgstaller</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Held</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Signorell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blozik</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steurer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wertli</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Increased risk of adverse events in non-cancer patients with chronic and high-dose opioid use-A health insurance claims analysis</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>e0238285</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32925928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0238285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7489518</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bithell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bootstrap confidence intervals: when, which, what? A practical guide for medical statisticians</article-title>. <source>Stat Med</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1141</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10797513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/(sici)1097-0258(20000515)19:9&lt;1141::aid-sim479&gt;3.0.co;2-f</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Christodoulou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steyerberg</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verbakel</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Calster</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A systematic review shows no performance benefit of machine learning over logistic regression for clinical prediction models</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30763612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2019.02.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reitsma</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moons</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Transparent reporting of a multivariable prediction model for individual prognosis or diagnosis (TRIPOD): the TRIPOD statement</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>350</volume>:<fpage>g7594</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25569120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.g7594</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhiman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>CLA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Speich</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bullock</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Damen</surname><given-names>JAA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hooft</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirtley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Calster</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moons</surname><given-names>KGM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Methodological conduct of prognostic prediction models developed using machine learning in oncology: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Bmc Med Res Methodol</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35395724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12874-022-01577-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8991704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Els</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunyk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lappi</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sonnenberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagtvedt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolahdooz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Straube</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Adverse events associated with medium- and long-term use of opioids for chronic non-cancer pain: an overview of Cochrane Reviews</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>CD012509</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29084357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD012509.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6485910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eriksen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sjogren</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruera</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekholm</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Critical issues on opioids in chronic non-cancer pain: an epidemiological study</article-title>. <source>PAIN</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>125</volume>:<fpage>172</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16842922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pain.2006.06.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Federal Statistical Office</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Income distribution</article-title>. In: <source>CaLC Section Income editor</source>, <year>2020</year>. Available at. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/en/home/statistics/economic-social-situation-population/economic-and-social-situation-of-the-population/inqualities-income-ditribution/income-distribution.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/en/home/statistics/economic-social-situation-population/economic-and-social-situation-of-the-population/inqualities-income-ditribution/income-distribution.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gravesteijn</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nieboer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ercole</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lingsma</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Calster</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steyerberg</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collaborators</surname><given-names>C-T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Machine learning algorithms performed no better than regression models for prognostication in traumatic brain injury</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>122</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>107</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32201256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2020.03.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haller</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watzke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blozik</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosemann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antidepressant prescription practice and related factors in Switzerland: a cross-sectional analysis of health claims data</article-title>. <source>BMC Psychiatry</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>196</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31234895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12888-019-2178-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6591836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Properties of R-2 statistics for logistic regression</article-title>. <source>Stat Med</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1383</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16059870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/sim.2300</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosemann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blozik</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Napflin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Markun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Trends in micronutrient laboratory testing in Switzerland: a 7-year retrospective analysis of healthcare claims data</article-title>. <source>Int J Gen Med</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1341</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33293852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/IJGM.S275406</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7719331</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneeweiss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Signorell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Improved prediction of medical expenditures and health care utilization using an updated chronic disease score and claims data</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>1118</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23845184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2013.04.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shover</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohnert</surname><given-names>ASB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandeau</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caulkins</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuellar</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hurd</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juurlink</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lembke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mackey</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larrimore Ouellette</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suffoletto</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Timko</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Responding to the opioid crisis in north America and beyond: recommendations of the stanford-lancet commission</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>399</volume>:<fpage>555</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>604</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35122753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)02252-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9261968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ripoll</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beakley</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calixto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolden</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urman</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manchikanti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prescription opioid abuse in chronic pain: an updated review of opioid abuse predictors and strategies to curb opioid abuse (Part 2)</article-title>. <source>Pain Physician</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>S111</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>S133</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28226334</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klimas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorfinkel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fairbairn</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amato</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahamad</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nolan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simel</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Strategies to identify patient risks of prescription opioid addiction when initiating opioids for pain A systematic review</article-title>. <source>Jama Netw Open</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.3365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6503484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31050783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shau</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Predicting healthcare utilization using a pharmacy-based metric with the WHO's anatomic therapeutic chemical algorithm</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>1031</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21945973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MLR.0b013e31822ebe11</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madras</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The surge of opioid use, addiction, and overdoses responsibility and response of the US health care system</article-title>. <source>Jama Psychiat</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>441</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2017.0163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28355456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mallon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brettschneider</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Konig</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luck</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rohr</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weyerer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Werle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mosch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weeg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pentzek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleineidam</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heser</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riedel-Heller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiese</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scherer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grp</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grp</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of pain and its associated factors among the oldest-olds in different care settings - results of the AgeQualiDe study</article-title>. <source>Bmc Fam Pract</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29885656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12875-018-0768-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5994256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edlund</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeVries</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Braden</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term chronic opioid therapy discontinuation rates from the TROUP study</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>1450</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21751058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11606-011-1771-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3235603</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valenti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Britt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayram</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Drugs causing adverse events in patients aged 45 or older: a randomised survey of Australian general practice patients</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e003701</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3796276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24114371</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abner</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fardo</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moga</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Patterns and predictors of chronic opioid use in older adults: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Plos One</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0210341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6329525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30633773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliva</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tavakoli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiechers</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avoundjian</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Medhanie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trafton</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Development and applications of the Veterans health administration's stratification tool for opioid risk mitigation (STORM) to improve opioid safety and prevent overdose and suicide</article-title>. <source>Psychol Serv</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>34</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>49</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28134555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1037/ser0000099</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Panczak</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berlin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Voorpostel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zwahlen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The Swiss neighbourhood index of socioeconomic position: update and re-validation</article-title>. <source>Swiss Med Wkly</source><year>2023</year>;<volume>153</volume>:<fpage>40028</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36652707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.57187/smw.2023.40028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pensa</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galusha</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantley</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Patterns of opioid prescribing and predictors of chronic opioid use in an industrial cohort, 2003 to 2013</article-title>. <source>J Occup Environ Med</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>457</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29135839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/JOM.0000000000001231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5943140</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>[28]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buist</surname><given-names>DSM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fishman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gurwitz</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raebel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chronic disease score as a predictor of hospitalization</article-title>. <source>Epidemiology</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>340</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11964937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00001648-200205000-00016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>[29]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>R Development Core Team</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>: <source>A language and environment for statistical computing</source>. <publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name>, <year>2022</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>[30]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ensor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snell</surname><given-names>KIE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrell</surname><given-names>FE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reitsma</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moons</surname><given-names>KGM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Smeden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Calculating the sample size required for developing a clinical prediction model</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>368</volume>:<fpage>m441</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32188600</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.m441</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>[31]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogal</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chinman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gellad</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mor</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mauro</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hale</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliva</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trafton</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yakovchenko</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hausmann</surname><given-names>LRM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Tracking implementation strategies in the randomized rollout of a Veterans Affairs national opioid risk management initiative</article-title>. <source>Implement Sci</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32576214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13012-020-01005-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7313133</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>[32]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt-Hansen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilgart</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Oxycodone for cancer pain in adult patients</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Assoc</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>314</volume>:<fpage>1282</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2015.8556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26393852</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>[33]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seyler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giraudon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mounteney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Is Europe facing an opioid epidemic: what does European monitoring data tell us?</article-title><source>Eur J Pain</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1072</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33428812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ejp.1728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>[34]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>CQ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Opioid therapy for chronic pain in the United States: promises and perils</article-title>. <source>PAIN</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>154</volume>(<issue>suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>S94</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>S100</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24036286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pain.2013.09.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4204477</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>[35]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Calster</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nieboer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vergouwe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Cock</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pencina</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steyerberg</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A calibration hierarchy for risk models was defined: from utopia to empirical data</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26772608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2015.12.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>[36]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Von Korff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolodny</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deyo</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term opioid therapy reconsidered</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>155</volume>:<fpage>325</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21893626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1059/0003-4819-155-5-201109060-00011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3280085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>[37]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Von Korff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas Ray</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boudreau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merrill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silverberg</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banta-Green</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weisner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>De facto long-term opioid therapy for noncancer pain</article-title>. <source>Clin J Pain</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>521</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18574361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/AJP.0b013e318169d03b</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3286630</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>[38]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wertli</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Signorell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgstaller</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steurer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Held</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Changes over time in prescription practices of pain medications in Switzerland between 2006 and 2013: an analysis of insurance claims</article-title>. <source>BMC Health Serv Res</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28241764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12913-017-2086-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5327558</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>[39]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiener</surname><given-names>ALaM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Classification and regression by randomForest</article-title>. <source>R News</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>[40]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yarborough</surname><given-names>BJH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stumbo</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoneburner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobscha</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deyo</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morasco</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Correlates of benzodiazepine use and adverse outcomes among patients with chronic pain prescribed long-term opioid therapy</article-title>. <source>Pain Med</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1148</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30204893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/pm/pny179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6544552</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>[41]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mullins</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of chronic pain among adults in the United States</article-title>. <source>PAIN</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>163</volume>:<fpage>e328</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>e332</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33990113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/j.pain.0000000000002291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>