<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1609</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmjo</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMJ Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2044-6055</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10314422</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10314422.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10314422</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10314422</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37336537</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2022-070820</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen-2022-070820</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Public Health</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1506</subject><subject>1724</subject></subj-group><series-title>Original research</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Estimate of the prevalence of subjects with chronic diseases in a province of Northern Italy: a retrospective study based on administrative databases</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-81757623" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Airoldi</surname><given-names initials="C">Chiara</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-95960198" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9058-8535</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Pagnoni</surname><given-names initials="F">Federico</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-103546319" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cena</surname><given-names initials="T">Tiziana</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-103546320" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ceriotti</surname><given-names initials="D">Daniele</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-103546321" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Ambrosi</surname><given-names initials="D">Damiano</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-103546322" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Vito</surname><given-names initials="M">Marta</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-84480226" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faggiano</surname><given-names initials="F">Fabrizio</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">Department of Translational Medicine</institution>, <institution>Universit&#224; degli Studi del Piemonte Orientale</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Novara</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">Epidemiologic Unit of the Local Health Authority of Vercelli</institution>, <institution>Osservatorio Epidemiologico ASL</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Vercelli</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><author-notes><corresp><label>Correspondence to</label> Dr Federico Pagnoni; <email>federico.pagnoni@uniupo.it</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>6</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">437839</issue-id><elocation-id>e070820</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>19</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>02</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-07-03 04:25:09.690"><day>03</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2023. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense" start_date="2023-06-19">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See:&#160;<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-070820.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-070820.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="reviewers-comments-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-070820.reviewer_comments.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="draft-revisions-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-070820.draft_revisions.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Objective</title><p>To find a definition of chronic disease based on literature review and to estimate the population-based prevalence rate of chronicity in a province in Northern Italy.</p></sec><sec><title>Design</title><p>Retrospective observational study based on administrative databases.</p></sec><sec><title>Data sources/setting</title><p>Archives of the National Health Service that contain demographic and administrative information linked with the archives of ticket exemptions (2000&#8211;2019), the hospital discharge and drug prescriptions (2016&#8211;2019).</p></sec><sec><title>Participants</title><p>Subjects who lived in Vercelli Local Health Authority, a Northern Italian province (Piedmont region), and were alive in December 2019.</p></sec><sec><title>Main outcome measures</title><p>Prevalence of subjects with at least one chronic disease identified by administrative sources and stratification of population according to the number of comorbidities. The pathologies considered were: chronic ischaemic heart disease, congestive heart failure, cardiac arrhythmias, hypertension, stroke, neoplasm, asthma, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, diabetes, thyroid disorders, osteoporosis, rheumatoid arthritis, chronic kidney disease, dementia, autism spectrum disorder, depression, schizophrenia, hepatitis, HIV and substance use disorders.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Our target population was about 164 344 subjects. The overall prevalence of subjects with at least one chronic condition was 21.43% (n=35 212): 19 541 were female and 15 671 were male with a raw prevalence of 22.96% and 19.77%, respectively. The overall prevalence increases with age until 85 years old, then a decrease is observed. Moreover, 16.39% had only one pathology, 4.30% two diseases and 0.74% had a more complex clinical condition (more than three diseases).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Despite the difficulty of having a unique definition of chronic disease, the prevalence obtained was coherent with the estimates reported by other national surveillance systems such as Passi and Passi d&#8217;Argento. Underestimates were observed when international comparisons were done; however, when we used less stringent definitions of chronic diseases, similar results were obtained.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>EPIDEMIOLOGY</kwd><kwd>EPIDEMIOLOGIC STUDIES</kwd><kwd>PUBLIC HEALTH</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group specific-use="FundRef"><award-group id="funding-1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Ministero dell'Istruzione, dell'Universit&#224; e della Ricerca</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>20177BR-JXS</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>special-feature</meta-name><meta-value>unlocked</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>STRENGTHS AND LIMITATIONS OF THIS STUDY</title></caption><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>It is an automatic procedure that can be quickly and easily replicated throughout the country.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Administrative databases do not require additional procedures or costs to use them.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Administrative databases are not always complete and may not fully reflect reality.</p></list-item></list></boxed-text><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Life expectancy has grown significantly over the past hundred years. This was possible thanks to the progress made in various sectors, first of all, the medical one. The improvements in lifestyle, the greater availability of resources in addition to the introduction of antibiotics and vaccinations have been crucial in pushing life expectancy forward.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> However, with the improvement in the average life expectancy, another problem has arisen and linked to the ageing of the population: the increase in the number of people being diagnosed with non-communicable diseases (NCDs), causing a dramatic decrease in the quality of life of these people in a very short time.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></p><p>NCDs, also known as chronic diseases, are the result of a combination of genetic, physiological, environmental and behavioural factors.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> The most common NCDs are cardiovascular diseases, cancer, diabetes and chronic respiratory diseases, being the leading causes of death globally and accounting for 70% of deaths worldwide.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> In 2019, there were almost 400 million of disability-adjusted life years (DALYs) for cardiovascular disease and over 250 million of DALYs for neoplasms.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Moreover, in 2019, there were almost 4 million deaths caused by NCDs in Western Europe.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> One of the countries that is more involved in this phenomenon is Italy: in fact, 22% of the total population consists of people aged over 65 years, and it was estimated that until 2065, this percentage will rise until 33%.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></p><p>In Italy, there is an estimated standardised prevalence rate of 15% for &#8216;high-impact&#8217; chronic diseases, a composite index constructed by aggregating data on diabetes, cancer, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), dementia and mental health disease.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Alarmingly, people aged 65 years or above have a prevalence of at least one chronic disease among 60.8%.</p><p>Given this alarming forecast, the WHO has asked to pay attention to this problem, finding ways to monitor it, prevent it, draw it to the attention of the scientific and medical community and provide all sick people, wherever they live, with support and care they need.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></p><p>Chronic disease management has been identified as a key health system concern among developed countries given the rising prevalence and burden of chronic illness.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></p><p>Despite this worrying situation, finding possible solutions is challenging given that there is no standard and uniquely recognised definition of chronic disease, meaning that it may be impossible to have unique prevalence estimates. Many authors have tried to give a definition of chronic disease but different approaches can be made. For example, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention defines chronic pathologies in this way: &#8216;Diseases can neither be defined as conditions that persist for a long period and continue medically or limit life activities or both. Not being cured by drugs simply disappear.&#8217;<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> A similar definition is given by the Florida Department of Health Chronic diseases: &#8216;have a long course of illness. They rarely resolve spontaneously, and they are generally not cured by medication or prevented by vaccine.&#8217;<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p><p>Instead, Friedman <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> define chronic disease as a condition that lasts 12 months or longer and meets one or both of the following tests: (1) it places limitations on self-care, independent living and social interactions; and (2) it results in the need for ongoing intervention with medical products, services and special equipment.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></p><p>Another significant fact is the absence in literature of any systematic reviews concerning this topic. As a result, lists of chronic conditions may vary, and the accuracy and precision of the estimation of the magnitude of occurrence, burden and associated costs are compromised.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p><sec id="s1-1"><title>Aim</title><p>To estimate the population-based prevalence rate of chronicity in terms of subjects affected by at least one chronic disease and to stratify the population according to the number of chronic diseases in a province in Northern Italy. To do this, first, a definition based on literature review of chronic diseases was performed. Second, we have developed a standardised model based on administrative databases able to calculate the prevalence of chronic diseases within a population in a standardised way.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Method</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Chronicity definition</title><p>We decided to select the following pathologies as chronic: chronic ischaemic heart disease, congestive heart failure, cardiac arrhythmias, hypertension, stroke, neoplasm, asthma, COPD, diabetes, thyroid disorders, osteoporosis, rheumatoid arthritis, chronic kidney disease, dementia (including Alzheimer&#8217;s and other senile dementias), autism spectrum disorder, depression, schizophrenia, hepatitis, HIV and substance use disorders (drug and alcohol). This list was prepared by choosing among the pathologies identified as chronic by other authors. Particularly, three expert physicians critically reviewed the literature concerning similar works performed in the past<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9 10 12</xref> and they selected those judged to have a more significant impact on the population both in terms of prevalence and in terms of health effects.</p><p>Then, the pathologies were grouped into macro-categories: circulatory system diseases (chronic ischaemic heart disease, congestive heart failure, cardiac arrhythmias, hypertension, stroke), respiratory diseases (asthma, COPD), neoplasms, endocrine system diseases (diabetes, thyroid disorders, osteoporosis), autoimmune disorders (rheumatoid arthritis), kidney diseases (chronic kidney disease), psychiatric diseases (autism spectrum disorder, depression, schizophrenia, etc), dementia (including Alzheimer&#8217;s and other senile dementias), liver diseases (hepatitis), infectious diseases (HIV) and addictions (drug and alcohol).</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Population and data sources</title><p>A retrospective observational study based on administrative sources was conducted.</p><p>We used the data of subjects who lived in Vercelli Local Health Authority (LHA), an Italian province in Piedmont (Northern Italy). All subjects who were alive on 31 December 2019 were included in the analysis.</p><p>These inhabitants were identified using the archives of the National Health Service (NHS) that contain demographic and administrative information. Particularly, for each subject, we removed the personal data such as name, surname and fiscal code, and we used an anonymous identification code to preserve the individual&#8217;s privacy. The individual data available were sex and age in December 2019.</p><p>To obtain clinical data, this database was linked with the archives of (1) ticket exemptions (2000&#8211;2019) that recorded information on all co-payment exemptions, (2) the hospital discharge (2016&#8211;2019) that contains all the private and public hospitalisation, and (3) the outpatient and hospital drug prescriptions (2016&#8211;2019) that reported the list of all reimbursable drugs and their quantities both with drugs dispensed during hospitalisation.</p><p>For the (1) ticket exemption, we decided to use all the exemptions available from 2000, the date in which they were electronically recorded. Despite knowing the starting and the ending data, we decided to consider all records and not only the active ones as we assumed that a chronic disease could not regress, but ending data were related only to administrative reason. Only exemptions of chronic disease were considered.</p><p>The (2) hospital discharge was available for the years 2016&#8211;2019. We find the presence of a chronic disease considering the principal and up to five secondary diagnoses. They were categorised using the International Classification of Diseases-Ninth Revision, Clinical Modification code and different precision levels were considered based on the pathology.</p><p>Finally, for the (3) drug prescription database, data on quantity and therapeutic, pharmacological and chemical properties, based on Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical Classification (ATC) system, were available for the period 2016&#8211;2019. In particular, we used the outpatients&#8217; drug prescription database reporting all dispensations of drugs reimbursable by the NHS and the list of drugs supplied during the hospitalisation or directly by the hospital pharmacy. We joined the two databases, and we included only subjects with at least three prescriptions of drugs that identified a chronic condition during 1&#8201;year. Particularly, the time interval between the first and the third prescription of drugs for each chronic disease separately should be less than 365.25&#8201;days. Prescriptions in the same data were not considered.</p><p>The codes used to identify each pathology from the three databases are reported in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 1</xref>. The codes for ticket exemption and for hospital discharge were identified from the Ministry of Health website.<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13 14</xref> The ATC codes for drug prescriptions were collected from some articles found in literature.<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15&#8211;26</xref></p><supplementary-material id="SP1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2022-070820.supp1</object-id><label>Supplementary data</label><p>
<inline-supplementary-material xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="SS1" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-070820supp001.pdf" content-type="local-data"/>
</p></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>After a cleaning phase of sources in which all mistakes were resolved and records with missing data removed, all the sources were linked into a unique database. The population analysed was described through the use of absolute and relative frequencies for categorical variables and mean and SD or median and IQR for numerical ones, as appropriate.</p><p>First, the analyses were conducted separately for each source considered (exemptions, hospital discharges and drug prescriptions), and prevalence at December 2019 with 95%&#8201;CI for each chronic disease was reported. Second, to avoid an overestimate and/or underestimate of the number of subjects with at least one pathology, some considerations on joined databases were conducted. Particularly, for each condition, we evaluated if it was identified by one, two or three sources. Based on literature and on our clinical knowledge, we decided to identify the presence of a chronic condition if a pathology was found by at least two databases except for osteoporosis for which an exemption code did not exist, so we considered at least one database. Then, we calculated the prevalence separately for age category (&lt;20, 20&#8211;29, 30&#8211;39, 40&#8211;49, 50&#8211;59, 60&#8211;69, 70&#8211;79, 80+) and sex. To estimate the impact of multimorbidity and stratify the population based on the number of clinical conditions identified, prevalence was also reported considering the number of chronic diseases. Finally, different graphical representations were proposed to understand the prevalence trend over a single age.</p><p>Sensitivity analysis was conducted excluding subjects with hypertension and Hashimoto&#8217;s disease as these pathologies do not have a substantial impact on life expectancy and the quality of life in those affected. This assumption was valid only when these conditions are optimally controlled by constantly taking the indicated therapy and maintaining optimal blood pressure and thyroid-stimulating hormone values.</p><p>All the analyses were conducted using SAS V.9.4.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Patient and public involvement</title><p>Patients or the public were not involved in the design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of our research.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>Our target population was about 164 344 subjects who lived in an area of 92 villages in the Vercelli LHA. The population was predominantly composed of women (52.8%), and about 50% of subjects were aged 50 years or more with a median age of 51 (IQR 30&#8211;67) years old.</p><p>The overall prevalence of subjects with at least one chronic condition was 25.94% (95% CI 25.73%, 26.15%) considering the ticket exemptions, 6.94% (95% CI 6.82%, 7.06%) using the hospital discharges and 40.38% (95% CI 40.14%, 40.62%) based on the drug prescriptions. More details on prevalence separately for disease are reported in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>. Interestingly, osteoporosis was not identified by exemption (as an exemption code did not exist) and hospital discharge databases but only through drug prescriptions. Moreover, using the exemption databases, about 10% of subjects suffered from circulatory and endocrine system disease, followed by neoplasms present in about 7% of Vercelli&#8217;s population. The more frequent cause of hospitalisation for chronic disease was related to circulatory system disease (4.08%), and it was followed by neoplasm that was identified in 2.26% of the population. Finally, using the drug prescriptions, we can observe that more than 30% of the population assumed drugs for circulatory problems, and also a high prevalence of use of drugs for kidney diseases was estimated (22.92%). Antipsychotic drugs were also assumed by 7.88% of residents.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Absolute and relative percentage of subjects with different chronic diseases in the Vercelli LHA identified using the exemption, the hospital discharge (HD) and the drug prescription databases</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Diseases</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="2">Exemption</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="2">HD</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="2">Drug</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune diseases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">611</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1156</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory system diseases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3552</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.16</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">904</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9044</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neoplasms</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#8201;381</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.93</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3708</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2473</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Circulatory system diseases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#8201;701</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.77</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6708</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.08</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52&#8201;046</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kidney diseases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">811</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">605</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37&#8201;671</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dementias</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">700</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endocrine system diseases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16&#8201;302</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.92</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1365</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#8201;263</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver diseases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1372</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">304</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infectious diseases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">595</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Addictions</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">848</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychiatric disorders</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1264</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">535</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#8201;945</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.88</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteoporosis</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2351</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42&#8201;625</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.94</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#8201;407</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.94</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66&#8201;361</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.38</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T1_FN1"><p>Prevalence is calculated using the population of Vercelli LHA in December 2019 (164 344 subjects) as the denominator.</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN2"><p>LHA, Local Health Authority.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Then, the analyses, considering the linkage between databases, were performed, and results of specific intersection among sources are reported in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 2</xref>. Of 45.09% (n=74 109) of subjects with at least one chronic disease, considering at least one database, about 17% (n=28 309) were identified using only the drug prescriptions and 4% (n=6582) considering only the exemptions; the hospital discharge contributes with a 0.33% (n=543) to the overall estimates. The more frequent overlap of sources was observed considering exemptions and drugs (n=27 811, 16.92%). <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> summarises the prevalence of each chronic disease considering if a subject was identified by at least one, two or three different databases. As expected, using a more inclusive definition of the presence of chronic disease, the prevalence was higher (at least one database: 45.09%) and it decreased when a more specific definition was considered (at least two: 20.69%, all three databases: 2.97%).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Absolute and relative percentage of subjects with different chronic diseases in the Vercelli LHA considering at least one, at least two or at least three databases in which each pathology was identified</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diseases</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="2">At least one database</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="2">At least two databases</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="2">At least three databases</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune diseases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1533</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">281</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory system diseases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8201;392</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.32</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2940</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neoplasms</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#8201;748</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.76</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4075</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">739</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Circulatory system diseases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53&#8201;329</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.45</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#8201;080</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.22</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3046</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kidney diseases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37&#8201;838</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.02</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1041</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dementias</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">823</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endocrine system diseases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#8201;533</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#8201;393</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.54</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1004</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver diseases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1462</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">254</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infectious diseases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">820</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Addictions</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">944</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychiatric disorders</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13&#8201;321</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.11</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1205</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">218</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteoporosis</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2351</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.11</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74&#8201;109</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.28</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34&#8201;002</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.69</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4886</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T2_FN1"><p>Prevalence is calculated using the population of Vercelli LHA in December 2019 (164 344 subjects) as the denominator.</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN2"><p>LHA, Local Health Authority.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>We decided to define subjects with chronic disease as those residents who had at least one pathology identified by two or three databases (20.69%), except for osteoporosis.</p><p>So, we defined 35 212 (34 002+1210 with osteoporosis) subjects with chronic disease, and the general prevalence was 21.43 (95% CI 21.23, 21.63). Of them, 19 541 were female and 15 671 were male, with a raw prevalence of 22.96% (95% CI 22.68%, 23.25%) and 19.77% (95% CI 19.50%, 20.05%), respectively. The overall prevalence increased with categorical age starting from 2.39% for young subjects (&lt;20 years) and ending with 52.82% in older people (80+ years). Particularly, until age 40&#8211;49 years, the proportion of subjects with at least one chronic condition was less than 10%, doubled for those 50&#8211;59 years old. Other important increments were estimated for the subsequent age period: 34.59% for 60&#8211;69 years and 47.46% for 70&#8211;79 years. This increased trend was maintained considering women and men separately. Interestingly, until 60&#8211;69 years, women suffered more from chronic disease than men, while for those 70+ years, a reversal trend was observed. More details are reported in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 3</xref>.</p><p><xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> shows the absolute number (upper panel) and prevalence (lower panel) of women and men with at least one chronic condition among the total population of Vercelli LHA. The absolute frequencies help to identify the demographic structures of the population and the real impact in terms of the number of subjects who require healthcare. Particularly, in Vercelli, the population is predominantly composed of older people and they are the more frail residents. Moreover, the distribution of prevalence underlines that the proportion of patients with chronic disease increases until 85 years old, and then a decrease is observed.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Upper panel: absolute number of women (red) and men (blue) with at least one chronic condition (darker colour) among the total population of Vercelli LHA (light colour). Lower panel: prevalence of women (red) and men (blue) with at least one chronic condition among the total population of Vercelli LHA. Estimates were made considering at least two databases. LHA, Local Health Authority.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-070820f01.jpg"/></fig><p>The multimorbidity in terms of co-presence of more than one pathology is then described in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>, separately for sex and age category, while the graphical representation considering single age is reported in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental figure 1</xref>. For 26 932 (16.39%) of Vercelli inhabitants, only one chronic pathology was identified; 7065 (4.30%) had two diseases, while 1215 (0.74%) had a more complex clinical condition (more than three diseases). Increasing the age increases not only the proportion of subjects with a disease but also increases the individual with more pathology; for ages 70&#8211;79 and 80+ years, more than 13% of people had two or more chronic diseases. These considerations are consistent when analyses are proposed separately for women and men.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Distribution of the number of chronic diseases by age, considering the whole population and separating female and male</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="4" rowspan="1">All (n=164 344)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Number of chronic diseases</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&lt;20</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#8201;989 (97.61)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">628 (2.36)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (0.03)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;20&#8211;29</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#8201;653 (96.32)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">473 (3.60)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (0.08)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;30&#8211;39</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8201;572 (94.59)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">840 (5.10)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (0.28)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (0.03)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;40&#8211;49</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#8201;627 (90.19)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2040 (8.92)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189 (0.83)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (0.07)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;50&#8211;59</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#8201;802 (79.82)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4642 (16.99)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">770 (2.82)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (0.37)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;60&#8211;69</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#8201;851 (65.41)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5951 (26.21)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1640 (7.22)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">262 (1.15)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;70&#8211;79</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9986 (52.54)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6275 (33.01)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2304 (12.12)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">443 (2.33)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;80+</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7652 (47.18)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6083 (37.50)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2096 (12.92)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">389 (2.40)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Female (n=85 097)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Number of chronic diseases</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&lt;20</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#8201;633 (97.88)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">267 (2.07)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (0.05)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;20&#8211;29</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5998 (95.77)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">259 (4.14)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (0.10)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;30&#8211;39</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7627 (93.15)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">537 (6.56)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (0.27)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.02)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;40&#8211;49</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8201;106 (88.42)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1203 (10.53)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111 (0.97)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (0.08)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;50&#8211;59</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8201;807 (78.32)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2483 (17.99)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">454 (3.29)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (0.40)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;60&#8211;69</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7628 (65.37)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3032 (25.98)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">864 (7.40)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145 (1.24)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;70&#8211;79</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5609 (54.20)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3277 (31.66)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1220 (11.79)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">243 (2.35)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;80+</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5148 (49.06)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3851 (36.70)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1270 (12.10)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225 (2.14)</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Male (n=79 247)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Number of chronic diseases</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3+</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="indent">&#8195;</named-content>&lt;20</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13&#8201;356 (97.35)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">361 (2.63)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (0.02)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="ndash" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="indent">&#8195;</named-content>20&#8211;29</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6655 (96.81)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214 (3.11)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (0.07)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="ndash" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="indent">&#8195;</named-content>30&#8211;39</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7945 (96.01)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">303 (3.66)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (0.29)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (0.04)</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="ndash" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="indent">&#8195;</named-content>40&#8211;49</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8201;521 (91.95)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">837 (7.32)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (0.68)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (0.05)</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="ndash" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="indent">&#8195;</named-content>50&#8211;59</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8201;995 (81.35)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2159 (15.97)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">316 (2.34)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (0.34)</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="ndash" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="indent">&#8195;</named-content>60&#8211;69</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7223 (65.46)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2919 (26.45)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">776 (7.03)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117 (1.06)</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="ndash" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="indent">&#8195;</named-content>70&#8211;79</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4377 (50.55)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2998 (34.62)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1084 (12.52)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200 (2.31)</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="plus" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="indent">&#8195;</named-content>80+</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2504 (43.73)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2232 (38.98)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">826 (14.43)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">164 (2.86)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T3_FN1"><p>Absolute number of subjects and row profiles are reported considering the population of Vercelli LHA as the denominator. Estimates were made considering at least two databases, except for osteoporosis.</p></fn><fn id="T3_FN2"><p>LHA, Local Health Authority.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The more frequent combinations of diseases (observed in at least 50 subjects) are reported in <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 4</xref>.</p><p>Finally, sensitivity analysis was performed excluding subjects with hypertension and Hashimoto&#8217;s disease. Using a more parsimonious approach, about 8787 subjects from exemptions, 890 from hospital discharge and 6516 from drug prescription were lost. The estimates of prevalence, considering the presence of at least one chronic condition separated from the source, were 20.59% (95% CI 20.39%, 20.79%), 6.40% (95% CI 6.28%, 6.52%) and 36.41% (95% CI 36.18%, 36.65%) for exemptions, hospital discharge and drug prescription, respectively. Moreover, when the calculation, including only chronic diseases identified by at least two databases except for osteoporosis, was replicated, the prevalence decreased to 16.03% (95% CI 15.85%, 16.21%) compared with the 21.43% found in the main analysis. Despite the reduction in terms of absolute and relative numbers, no modification on distribution by age was observed.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this work, we used a cohort of 164 344 individuals corresponding to the residential population of the Vercelli LHA located in the North-West of Italy. We found a prevalence of chronic diseases equal to 21.43% considering the subjects of all ages who appear in at least two clinic databases, except for osteoporosis. The number of subjects with at least one pathology increases with age, and a similar trend was observed among men and women.</p><p>Nineteen macro-categories were selected that represent the main chronic diseases diagnosed in Italy. In particular, the selection of pathologies was carried out in line with the previous literature. Goodman <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> presented a selection of 20 chronic conditions identified according to the definition of chronicity, prevalence and potential interest for public health in terms of impact and possible prevention.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> This study differs in the choice of excluding hyperlipidaemia as we consider it a risk factor rather than a chronic condition. Furthermore, our work takes into consideration only rheumatoid arthritis, differentiating arthritis from arthrosis because in Italy, there are no exemptions, hospital discharge and specific drugs for this condition, unlike in America. In the literature, there are other studies comparable with ours, such as the ones conducted by Pefoyo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> and Moin <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, who have identified roughly the same pathologies.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9 12</xref></p><p>We decided to not include hypertension in the selected pathologies because we considered it more like a risk condition than a disease. Moreover, if this condition is properly treated, it does not have a substantial impact on life expectancy and quality of life of those affected. In fact, individuals who take indicated therapy and maintain correct blood pressure values have the same life expectancy as the population who is not affected by hypertension.</p><p>We have used three different databases to limit the chances that some subjects could escape our search, as choosing a single database would not have given sufficient guarantee to our results. For example, in the database of exemptions, not all subjects with chronic diseases actually request the exemption, either because they can be unaware of this procedure, or because the exemption itself does not lead to considerable advantages in economic terms or access to visits.</p><p>Moreover, the values may be underestimated as many individuals may have an income or disability exemption and therefore do not use the disease exemption. However, we decided not to include these two types of exemptions in the main analyses because we would have otherwise had an excessive overestimation due to the fact that not all of these exemptions are granted for chronic diseases. The hospital discharge database is reliable because any patient who has ever had hospitalisation also has a discharge card related to it. However, using data from the hospital discharge database has few downsides. First of all, the fast-paced work in the hospital often leads to inaccurate input by the medical staff, which leads to forgetfulness in reporting the chronic pathologies from which hospitalised patients are affected. Moreover, not all patients suffering from chronic diseases are hospitalised, as very often they can be safely managed from home; therefore, unless an acute event takes place that brings these patients to hospital, they are not identified. The drug database, on the other hand, may have the opposite problem: it is impossible to exactly match a drug to a disease, so we will find many patients who take drugs indicated for chronic diseases without actually having one; this involves a significant overestimation in the results obtained. Conversely, there are many types of drugs for which it is possible that some have not been included in this review, leading to the exclusion of patients who take them. It should also be considered that despite the existence of guidelines, every physician decides independently which drugs to administer based on individual evaluations; this means that among different doctors and different patients, the therapies assigned are very different, making it very difficult to assign the pathologies to different subjects.</p><p>A few focus on some pathologies can be done. Osteoporosis was identified only through the use of drugs. This is because there is no exemption for osteoporosis according to the Italian Ministry of Health. Furthermore, there are not even subjects identified by hospital discharge although the relative code exists. We suspect this may be because clinicians tend to enter only the codes that are most relevant to the reason for admission. From this, it follows that by using the intersection of two databases, no patient suffering from osteoporosis will be present, as can be seen in the analyses described above. Another point of interest is the strong discrepancy between subjects with kidney disease identified between the ATC codes compared with the other two databases, which could be explained by the fact that the drugs used for chronic renal failure are very often the same as those used for cardiovascular diseases. Therefore, the data are overestimated compared with the real one identified by overlapping with the other databases, which are more specific for kidney diseases.</p><p>Results obtained in terms of prevalence among age groups and gender are coherent with expectancy. Particularly, when we performed a graphical representation of prevalence of chronic diseases in the study population, we observed that the graph assumes a curvilinear trend with a peak of prevalence at the age of about 80 years; growth from birth up to 50 years is constant and slow, then after 50 years, the increase becomes more marked up to 80 years where the curve begins to decrease. We can suggest that this fact occurs due to a selection related to several factors: both genetic and behavioural. We suppose that a patient suffering from one or more chronic conditions has a lower life expectancy than those who are not affected. This fact leads to the number of subjects with chronic diseases who are older than 80 years to be a minority; this is also indirectly found by DuGoff <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> who note that as the chronic diseases of an individual increase, his life expectancy decreases.<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Moreover, when we focus our attention on people suffering from multiple pathologies, we observed that after the age of 80 years, more than 13% of subjects have at least two chronic diseases. This should make us reflect because not only is there a high prevalence of sick people in the elderly, but also of complex multipathological clinical pictures that have a major economic and clinical impact on the health system.</p><p>There are other national and international studies that have done research like ours.</p><p>Passi, for example, is a national surveillance system that continuously investigates aspects relating to the state of health of the Italian population through interviews and questionnaires, presenting data in the 3-year period.<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> In Italy, according to the Passi survey (period 2017&#8211;2020), 18.4% (Piedmont 19.2%) of subjects between 18 and 69 years of age claim to have received a diagnosis of one or more of the following pathologies: renal failure, chronic bronchitis, emphysema, respiratory failure, bronchial asthma, stroke or cerebral ischaemia, diabetes, myocardial infarction, cardiac ischaemia or coronary artery disease, other heart diseases, tumours, liver disease or cirrhosis. When we restricted our analysis to this age group, we observed a prevalence of at least one chronic disease of 16.05% (95% CI 15.83%, 16.27%). A similar reasoning can be applied by comparing the data from the Passi d&#8217;Argento Surveillance (population over 65, period 2017&#8211;2020). Based on Passi d&#8217;Argento Surveillance, the prevalence of Italian subjects with at least one chronic disease is 60.8%: 49.5% in Piedmont and 47.08% (95% CI 46.62%, 47.54%) in Vercelli.<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> We noted that our values are coherent with those proposed by Passi and Passi D&#8217;Argento. We assumed that little discrepancies between results could be related to different methodological approaches used: the data of the national surveillance must be self-reported by the population through telephone interviews and different pathologies included.</p><p>International comparisons were also done. Pefoyo <italic toggle="yes">et al,</italic> based on the data provided by the National Insurance System, calculated the prevalence of 16 chronic diseases in the population of Ontario in Canada (12 242 273): arthritis (excluding rheumatoid arthritis), hypertension, asthma, depression, diabetes, cancer, chronic coronary syndrome, cardiac arrhythmia, osteoporosis, COPD, congestive heart failure, renal failure, dementia, rheumatoid arthritis, stroke and acute myocardial infarction. They find that 43% of the population examined had at least one chronic disease, a prevalence significantly higher than the 21.64% estimated by our study. However, when we analysed the data defining chronic disease, a subject that was identified by at least one database (situation more similar to that presented in Pefoyo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> work), the prevalence was very similar as we obtained 45.28%. Interestingly, we observed that a similar age trend was observed: the prevalence increased as the age increased, but a little decrease was observed for subjects aged 90+ years. Moreover, the proportion of subjects with multimorbidity conditions is higher in older age. Finally, differences observed in estimates could be linked to different reasons including lifestyles, environmental conditions and different geographical areas.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Another important study was conducted by Barnett <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> using a national dataset held by the Primary Care Clinical Informatics Unit at the University of Aberdeen, UK, which contained data corresponding to one-third of the Scottish population. They extracted data on 40 morbidities and identified subjects with one or more chronic conditions. The prevalence was found to be 42.2%, and 23.2% were multimorbid.<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> This is a higher value than that identified in our study probably due to a less restricted definition of chronic disease (in our analysis, we considered only 19 diseases).</p><p>In summary, our study presents certain limitations. First of all, the selection of the chronic diseases included was conducted without specific literature references; in fact, every cited author who conducted similar studies has chosen to include different pathologies. This fact happened because there is not a clear definition of &#8216;chronic pathology&#8217;, so each author gives his own definition. Another limitation may be the choice to require at least two databases (except osteoporosis). We decided to use this strategy because the number of subjects who had at least one chronic disease using this approach was roughly the same as the one in the Passi survey. Moreover, we decided to use one database only for osteoporosis, which is the unique pathology considered that does not have an exemption code; in fact, we can detect this disease only by using the ATC codes. However, we cannot be totally sure that this is the best choice. In addition, as we have explained before, even the three databases considered have some issues: for example, the database of exemptions underestimates the number of individuals with chronic conditions because not all of them make the exemption request. Considering the hospital discharge records, they have two important problems: first, they are often compiled approximately, and second, not all the individuals with chronic conditions are hospitalised. Finally, even the drug database has several problems, for example, many patients who take drugs indicated with a chronic condition do not really have it; in addition, every physician decides independently which type of drugs to prescribe to a single patient. Therefore, this leads to the impossibility to make completely accurate evaluations with this database.</p><p>Finally, considering the generalisability of our results, we can affirm that our conclusions could be extended to other Italian regions; in fact, we assume that the prevalence of chronic disease that we found in Vercelli&#8217;s area is quite similar to the prevalence of chronic disease in the entire Italian population; in fact, many conditions such as age, risk factors and healthcare system are roughly the same in all the Italian regions. Therefore, we can say that our results are generalisable to Italy. Conversely, it is more difficult to apply our results to the European or world population; in fact, the demographic, clinical and risk factor characteristics are totally different from the Italian ones.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Despite the limitations described in our work as the difficulty to have a unique chronic definition, an important result of our study is having built a method to identify the prevalence of chronic diseases in the population with a fair degree of accuracy. The algorithm performed is particularly easy and simple to use and it could be proposed for other Italian LHAs. Particularly, these estimates could be useful to make comparisons between different national and international realities and could be the basis for new healthcare programmes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="d64e137" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Reviewer comments</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-070820.reviewer_comments.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="d64e138" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Author's
manuscript</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-070820.draft_revisions.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Chiara Aleni for the English revision.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Contributors:</bold> All the authors conceived and designed the analysis. TC collected the data. CA and TC contributed data or analysis tools. CA performed the analysis. CA, FP, DC, DDA and MDV wrote the paper. FP edited the paper. FF conceptualised and supervised the project. FF is responsible for the overall content as the guarantor. All authors reviewed the final version of the manuscript and approved it for submission.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The authors acknowledge the support from MIUR-PRIN 2017 (project number 20177BR-JXS).</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> None declared.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient and public involvement:</bold> Patients and/or the public were not involved in the design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Supplemental material:</bold> This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>All data relevant to the study are included in the article or uploaded as supplemental information.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement"><title>Ethics statements</title><sec><title>Patient consent for publication</title><p content-type="ethics-consent-to-publish">Not required.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethics approval</title><p content-type="ethics-approval">This study was conducted in the context of the epidemic surveillance function of the Epidemiologic Unit of the Local Health Authority of Vercelli. No ethical committee approval was required for the current study based on administrative databases according to the rules of the Italian Drugs Agency.</p></sec></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Oeppen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vaupel</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Demography. broken limits to life expectancy</article-title>. <source>Science</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>296</volume>:<fpage>1029</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1069675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12004104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fries</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Measuring and monitoring success in compressing morbidity</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>139</volume>:<fpage>455</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-139-5_part_2-200309021-00015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12965976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>. <source>Noncommunicable diseases</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>, <year>2021</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/noncommunicable-diseases">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/noncommunicable-diseases</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>. <source>Noncommunicable diseases progress monitor, 2017</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>, <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation (IHME)</collab></person-group>. <source>GBD Compare [Internet]</source>. <publisher-loc>Seattle, WA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IHME, University of Washington</publisher-name>, <year>2015</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://vizhub.healthdata.org/gbd-compare/">https://vizhub.healthdata.org/gbd-compare/</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Istituto Nazionale di Statistica</collab></person-group>. <source>Popolazione e famiglie</source>. <publisher-name>Istituto Nazionale di Statistica</publisher-name>, <year>2015</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www4.istat.it/it/anziani/popolazione-e-famiglie">https://www4.istat.it/it/anziani/popolazione-e-famiglie</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>The European House-Ambrosetti S.p.A</collab>, <collab>The European House-Ambrosetti S.p.Ar</collab></person-group>. <source>Le coordinate della salute [Internet]</source>. <publisher-loc>Milan</publisher-loc>, <year>2020</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://eventi.ambrosetti.eu/meridiano-sanita-15/wp-content/uploads/sites/141/2020/11/3.ReportMS15.pdf">https://eventi.ambrosetti.eu/meridiano-sanita-15/wp-content/uploads/sites/141/2020/11/3.ReportMS15.pdf</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>. <source>Global status report on noncommunicable diseases 2014</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>, <year>2014</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/148114/9789241564854_eng.pdf">https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/148114/9789241564854_eng.pdf</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/STROKEAHA.115.008097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25873596</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pefoyo</surname><given-names>AJK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bronskill</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gruneir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The increasing burden and complexity of Multimorbidity</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<elocation-id>415</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-015-1733-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25903064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4415224</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Defining and measuring chronic conditions: Imperatives for research, policy, program, and practice</article-title>. <source>Prev Chronic Dis</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<elocation-id>E66</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5888/pcd10.120239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23618546</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3652713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Elixhauser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Costly hospital Readmissions and complex chronic illness</article-title>. <source>Inquiry</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>408</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5034/inquiryjrnl_45.04.408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19209836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moin</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Glazier</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kuluski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Examine the association between key determinants identified by the chronic disease indicator framework and Multimorbidity by rural and urban settings</article-title>. <source>J Multimorb Comorb</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<elocation-id>26335565211028157</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/26335565211028157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34262879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8252380</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Ministero della Salute</collab></person-group>. <source>Esenzioni per malattie croniche [Internet]</source>. <publisher-loc>Rome</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ministero della Salute</publisher-name>, <year>2017</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.salute.gov.it/portale/esenzioni/dettaglioContenutiEsenzioni.jsp?lingua=italiano&amp;id=1017&amp;area=esenzioni&amp;menu=vuoto">https://www.salute.gov.it/portale/esenzioni/dettaglioContenutiEsenzioni.jsp?lingua=italiano&amp;id=1017&amp;area=esenzioni&amp;menu=vuoto</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Ministero della Salute</collab></person-group>. <source>Elenco sistematico delle malattie [Internet]</source>. <publisher-loc>Rome</publisher-loc>, <year>2009</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.salute.gov.it/imgs/C_17_pubblicazioni_2251_ulterioriallegati_ulterioreallegato_2_alleg.pdf">https://www.salute.gov.it/imgs/C_17_pubblicazioni_2251_ulterioriallegati_ulterioreallegato_2_alleg.pdf</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pezzotti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Orzella</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Can we use the pharmacy data to estimate the prevalence of chronic conditions? a comparison of multiple data sources</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<elocation-id>688</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-11-688</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21892946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3223740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maggioni</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Orso</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Calabria</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The real-world evidence of heart failure: findings from 41 413 patients of the ARNO database</article-title>. <source>Eur J Heart Fail</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>402</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ejhf.471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26754527</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Profili</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maciocco</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bellini</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and clustering of chronic diseases in Tuscany (central Italy): evidence from a large administrative data warehouse</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Prev</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>385</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.19191/EP20.5-6.P385.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33706491</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schuemie</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pasqua</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Monitoring compliance with standards of care for chronic diseases using Healthcare administrative databases in Italy: strengths and limitations</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<elocation-id>e0188377</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0188377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29232365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5726627</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baviera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Roncaglioni</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tettamanti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Diabetes mellitus: a risk factor for seizures in the elderly-a population-based study</article-title>. <source>Acta Diabetol</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>863</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00592-017-1011-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28631057</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Notaro</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Usman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Secondary prevention in concurrent coronary artery, cerebrovascular, and chronic kidney disease: focus on pharmacological therapy</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc Ther</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>199</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>215</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1755-5922.2009.00087.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19689620</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Biffi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Comoretto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Arf&#232;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Can Healthcare utilization data reliably capture cases of chronic respiratory diseases? a cross-sectional investigation in Italy</article-title>. <source>BMC Pulm Med</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>20</fpage>.:<elocation-id>20</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12890-016-0362-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28103865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5248488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maccagnano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Notarnicola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pesce</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The prevalence of fragility fractures in a population of a region of Southern Italy affected by thyroid disorders</article-title>. <source>Biomed Res Int</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>2016</volume>:<elocation-id>6017165</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2016/6017165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27807539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5078635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Garbutt</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacotherapy for alcohol dependence</article-title>. <source>Evid Rep Technol Assess (Summ)</source><year>1999</year>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4781062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11487800</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marcellusi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Viti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sciattella</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Economic aspects in the management of diabetes in Italy</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open Diabetes Res Care</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<elocation-id>e000197</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjdrc-2016-000197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5073526</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27843551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pagano</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>De Rosa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The relative burden of diabetes complications on Healthcare costs: the population-based CINECA-SID ARNO diabetes Observatory</article-title>. <source>Nutr Metab Cardiovasc Dis</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>944</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.numecd.2016.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27289165</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Douaihy</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Medications for substance use disorders</article-title>. <source>Soc Work Public Health</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>264</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>78</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/19371918.2013.759031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23731419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3767185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>DuGoff</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Canudas-Romo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Buttorff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Multiple chronic conditions and life expectancy: a life table analysis</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>688</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MLR.0000000000000166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25023914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Istituto Superiore di Sanit&#224;</collab></person-group>. <source>Sorveglianza PASSI [Internet]</source>. <publisher-loc>Rome</publisher-loc>, <year>2013</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.epicentro.iss.it/passi/dati/croniche">https://www.epicentro.iss.it/passi/dati/croniche</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Istituto Superiore di sanit&#224;</collab></person-group>. <source>Sorveglianza Passi d&#8217;Argento</source>. <publisher-loc>Rome</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Istituto Superiore di Sanit&#224;</publisher-name>, <year>2014</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.epicentro.iss.it/passi-argento/dati/croniche">https://www.epicentro.iss.it/passi-argento/dati/croniche</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Norbury</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology of Multimorbidity and implications for health care, research, and medical education: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>380</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(12)60240-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22579043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>