<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2757</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cureus</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11456982</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11456982.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11456982</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11456982</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39376891</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.68775</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Emergency Medicine</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Pharmacology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Substance Use and Addiction</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Systematic Review of Phenibut Withdrawals</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names initials="A">Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names initials="JR">John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names initials="C">Christopher</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simonsen</surname><given-names initials="H">Hunter</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Satyasi</surname><given-names initials="SK">Savitha K</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names initials="N">Nauman</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sukpraprut-Braaten</surname><given-names initials="S">Suporn</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Medicine, Kansas City University, Joplin, USA </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Psychiatry, Freeman Health System, Joplin, USA </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Christopher Stewart <email>chrisstewartbyu@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>6</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>9</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">469782</issue-id><elocation-id>e68775</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>06</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>07</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-10-08 09:25:42.293"><day>08</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2024, Stewart et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Stewart et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000068775.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/281164-a-systematic-review-of-phenibut-withdrawals">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/281164-a-systematic-review-of-phenibut-withdrawals</self-uri><abstract><p>Phenibut is an anxiolytic agent that was originally used as a treatment for anxiety, depression, post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), and insomnia. It is a gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA) mimetic, which stimulates GABA receptors in the brain. This increases the inhibitory effects of GABA leading to a greater chance of a sedative response and risk for abuse. It is not currently registered in Western countries but is easily accessible online as a supplement. This is a systematic review of case reports of phenibut patients with withdrawal symptoms published in the PubMed database between January 2010 and October 2023. Following the inclusion criteria application, 15 articles were included. Descriptive statistics were used to analyze the results. The average age of patients with phenibut withdrawals was 31.8 years (SD=12.66 years), and 13 cases (87%) were males. The average dosage was 13.6 g/day (SD=8 g), ranging from 1.5 to 28.5 g/day. Nine cases (60%) presented at an emergency department, and three cases (17%) were presented at a clinic setting facility. The most common history of patients who took phenibut was alcohol or drug abuse (73%). A history of anxiety and depression (60%) was also seen in the majority of patient presentations. Phenibut is never prescribed in the United States, and there are no official guidelines for phenibut use. Educating all physicians about the potentially harmful supplements available to patients and their biological mechanisms is essential. This review highlights the importance of collecting a thorough patient history, including supplements, to help prevent phenibut misuse and subsequent withdrawals.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>addiction</kwd><kwd>online supplement</kwd><kwd>phenibut</kwd><kwd>supplement abuse</kwd><kwd>withdrawal symptoms</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction and background</title><p>Overview of phenibut</p><p>Phenibut is an anxiolytic substance developed in Russia for the treatment of anxiety, depression, post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), and insomnia [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Initially designed as an anxiolytic agent for astronauts, it functions as a gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA) mimetic, meaning it stimulates GABA receptors by increasing the influx of chloride ions through ligand-gated channels [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. While phenibut targets both GABAB and GABAA receptors, it targets GABAB receptors to a much greater extent [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. This causes a muscle-relaxing and a calming effect as GABA is the main inhibitory neurotransmitter of the CNS [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Although phenibut is not currently registered in Western countries, it is readily accessible online without a prescription as a supplement and is also marketed under various names including Anvifen, Fenibut, and Noofen on eBay and other online retailers [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>-<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Despite its efficacy in improving these conditions, users can quickly develop dependence [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].&#160;</p><p>Clinical challenges</p><p>Phenibut presents unique challenges in clinical settings. As a GABA agonist, symptoms of phenibut resemble those caused by substances such as benzodiazepines and barbiturates [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. However, phenibut does not show up on any standard drug tests, and no commercial tests are available for its detection [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. This complicates the diagnosis of phenibut abuse and dependence, particularly if patients do not disclose its use [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Since phenibut is often advertised as a supplement, patients may not consider its pharmaceutical properties and fail to mention it in their medical history.</p><p>Accessibility and risks</p><p>One challenge in addressing phenibut abuse is its marketing as a supplement [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Supplements are not approved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and are legal to buy, sell, and use. Phenibut is more than a mere supplement as it has pharmacologic properties that necessitate regulation. If phenibut had FDA approval, it could be used in clinical settings for treatment. However, it does not have FDA approval due to addiction potential. Phenibut is a controlled substance in Australia and banned in the countries of Hungary, Italy, and Lithuania, further highlighting the danger of this substance [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Although there is limited research on phenibut&#8217;s potential for addiction, cases have been reported where patients develop a tolerance in as little as a week, indicating the potential danger and risks of taking this supplement [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. While individuals may take this drug thinking they are using a supplement to help with their anxiety and depression, serious side effects may occur, especially when phenibut is combined with other substances, including coma and death [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Additional side effects that may occur when taking phenibut include relaxation, drowsiness, sedation, confusion, irritability, delirium, seizures, dilated pupils, high blood pressure, and increased heart rate [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].&#160;</p><p>Study aims</p><p>The primary aim of this study is to examine the reported cases of individuals presenting with phenibut dependence and to aid physicians in identifying patients to improve health outcomes. Additionally, this study seeks to educate physicians and raise awareness about substances marketed online as supplements that actually contain pharmacologic properties. Supplements contain vitamins, minerals, or other ingredients that an individual needs due to an insufficiency [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Phenibut falls outside of this scope. It is crucial for patients considering phenibut to understand the risks and potential for addiction, recognizing that they are not consuming a supplement.&#160;</p></sec><sec sec-type="review"><title>Review</title><p>Methods</p><p>Search Strategy</p><p>This systematic review was conducted with case reports found in the PubMed database with the keyword &#8220;Phenibut.&#8221;&#160;A total of 25 cases published from 2010 to October 2023 were identified and obtained. All case reports were screened for patients using phenibut. The authors then extracted data on the reasons for taking phenibut, withdrawal symptoms, and treatments associated with phenibut abuse.&#160;
<italic toggle="yes">Inclusion Criteria</italic></p><p>Inclusion criteria included patients presenting with withdrawal symptoms from phenibut ingestion. Various reports were excluded for the following reasons. One report was excluded because the subject was a canine, three were not in English, five were excluded because they focused on overdoses or irregular responses without detailing withdrawal symptoms, and one article could not be obtained. This selection process is illustrated in the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) diagram shown in Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) Diagram</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000068775-i01.jpg"/></fig><p>Data Extraction</p><p>The population analyzed in this systematic review consisted of patients presenting with phenibut withdrawals. Data collected included the reasons for taking phenibut, the clinical settings in which they presented, the withdrawal symptoms they exhibited, and the methods used for detoxification. This data was compared to understand the motivations behind phenibut use, best practices for tapering patients off of phenibut, and common withdrawal symptoms. Understanding these aspects is particularly important because phenibut does not appear on standard drug screenings or blood tests. The difficulty in making a formal diagnosis highlights the need for increased awareness and consideration of phenibut abuse in differential diagnoses along with a thorough history taking.</p><p>Statistical Analysis</p><p>Statistical analyses implemented in this systematic review include descriptive statistics. Descriptive statistics was used due to the small sample size of cases that have been reported. Data are presented using tables and bar graphs, which are the most suitable formats for this type of data.</p><p>Patients were first grouped for comparative analysis based on the reasons for phenibut use. Two primary groups were identified: First, patients using phenibut to overcome substance misuse (alcohol, opioids, methamphetamines, other drugs), and second, patients using phenibut for psychological conditions (depression, anxiety, insomnia, etc.).</p><p>Next, patients were grouped according to the type of clinic in which they presented. This was done to understand the most common settings for phenibut presentation, which is relevant because phenibut misuse is difficult to diagnose using standard drug tests. Identifying common presentation settings helps target education efforts for physicians. The groups were emergency settings (emergency department) and outpatient clinics (family medicine, internal medicine, psychiatry).</p><p>Finally, patients were grouped based on the withdrawal symptoms they presented with. This helps physicians recognize phenibut withdrawal when other drug and blood screenings are normal. The withdrawal symptoms were categorized into&#160;self-harm, psychomotor agitation, and hallucinations. These categories were selected because they are common withdrawal symptoms and were the common symptoms seen in the reported cases.&#160;</p><p>This systematic review aims to understand phenibut use by analyzing patient demographics, dosages, and durations, with a specific focus on withdrawal patterns. By examining reported cases of phenibut addiction, this review seeks to help physicians identify and manage phenibut use and raise awareness about the risks of substances like phenibut which are marketed as supplements but have pharmacologic properties.</p><p>Quality Assessment and Risk of Bias</p><p>The Joanna Briggs Institute for Case Reports (JBI) criteria were applied to case reports utilized in this review. This was essential to ensure that the case reports contained sufficient information to be accurate. The JBI criteria require&#160;that before using a case report the case report includes the patient&#8217;s demographic and characteristics, history, timeline, current clinical condition, and diagnostic tests and assessment, intervention/treatment is described, post-intervention clinical condition is described, adverse events/unanticipated events are identified and described, and the case report provides takeaway lessons. Potential bias in this review includes selection bias, in which the cases selected are not representative of all individuals using phenibut, and information bias, in which there are inaccuracies in the data reported. Information bias was prevented as best as possible by implementing the JBI criteria for case reports. Selection bias is possible due to the small sample size of case reports published on phenibut use.</p><p>Results</p><p>Of the 15 cases reported, 15 (100%) reported withdrawal symptoms and treatment. When looking at gender, 13 (87%) of the 15 cases were males and two (13%) were female. The average age of an individual with a phenibut addiction was 31.8 years (SD=12.66). Symptoms were categorized as either neurologic or physical. All 15 (100%) cases reported neurological symptoms and 11 (73%) reported both physical and neurological symptoms. The patients ingested an average of 13.6 g&#160;(SD=8 g) of phenibut each day for an average time period of 8.2 months. When looking at the location of the presentation, 9 (60%) of these cases were brought to the emergency department, whereas the remaining 6 (40%) were brought to psychiatric, general practice, or addiction medicine clinics. All individuals obtained phenibut either to help overcome other addictions (6, 40%), to help with anxiety (6, 40%), or to help with insomnia (3, 20%). When looking at tapering methods for withdrawal treatment, 9 (60%) were successfully treated with a Baclofen taper, with the majority of the remaining cases using benzodiazepine tapers (6, 40%). Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref> shows the demographics, symptoms, and treatment for patients presenting with phenibut abuse.&#160;</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Key Findings From Systematic Review</title><p>y/o,&#160;years old.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author (year)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reasons for taking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presenting symptoms</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Withdrawal symptoms</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dose (g/day)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time on phenibut</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment&#160;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Samokhvalov (2013) [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 y/o male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stop&#160; alcohol, anxiety, and stress</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anger</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insomnia, restlessness</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baclofen taper&#160;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hardman (2019) [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 y/o male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stop drugs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hallucinations, psychomotor agitation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hallucinations, tachycardia, myoclonus, hypertonic muscles</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baclofen taper</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vandreese (2022) [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 y/o male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stop opioids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agitation, sweating, hallucinations, confusion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hallucinations, encephalopathy, twitching</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baclofen taper</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zheng (2019) [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 y/o male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stop alcohol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suicidal ideation, seeking detoxification</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cold sweats, anxiety, insomnia, hallucinations</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 month</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benzodiazepine&#160;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mash (2020) [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 y/o male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Help relax</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertensive, found unconscious at home</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insomnia, restlessness, irritability, disorientation, heat flashes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benzodiazepine taper</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ahuja (2018) [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 y/o male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Help with anxiety and school</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insomnia, hallucinations, anxiety</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hallucinations, anxiety</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Few months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baclofen taper</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peterkin (2022) [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 y/o female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stop opioids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jumped out of three-story window - trauma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abdominal pain, headache, diaphoresis, lacrimation, restlessness, myalgia, anxiety, yawning, mydriasis, tachycardia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methadone and diazepam</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Esposito (2021) [<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 y/o female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Help with anxiety and insomnia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychomotor agitation, insomnia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abnormal motor behaviors, disorganized thinking, echolalia, visual hallucinations,&#160; insomnia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Several months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baclofen taper</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Joshi (2017) [<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 y/o male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suicide, insomnia, tachycardia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tremors, hallucinations, insomnia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baclofen taper</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Li (2017) [<xref rid="REF20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 y/o male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agitation, psychosis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agitation, psychosis, respiratory failure</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">McCabe (2019) [<xref rid="REF21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 y/o male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Help with anxiety</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-harm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agitation, tachycardia, hypertension, myoclonus, hallucinations</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baclofen and phenobarbital</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wainblat (2023) [<xref rid="REF22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 y/o male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insomnia and anxiety</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seeking detoxification</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Panic attack, insomnia, anxiety</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Several months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baclofen and phenobarbital</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brunner (2017) [<xref rid="REF23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 y/o male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stop opioids. Not tested in drug test</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased somnolence</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety, tremors, craving, muscle aches</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenobarbital</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coenen (2019) [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 y/o male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insomnia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brought for detoxification</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Changes in body temperature, depersonalization, hallucinations, insomnia, decreased appetite, sadness, irritability</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baclofen taper</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Magsalin (2010) [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 y/o male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Restless leg syndrome</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety, tremors, fatigue, psychomotor agitation, irritability, tachycardia, insomnia, decreased appetite</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 weeks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenibut taper</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The common presenting symptoms were isolated from the data. Self-harm (4, 27%) and psychomotor agitation (4, 27%) were listed as the most common withdrawal symptoms, followed by hallucinations (3, 20%), seeking detoxification (3, 20%), and insomnia (3, 20%). This can be seen in Table <xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Most Common Presenting Symptoms in Phenibut Patients</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presenting symptom</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number&#160; (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average dose of phenibut in grams (standard deviation)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychomotor agitation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (27%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6 (11.2)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-harm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (27%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8 (8.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hallucinations</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.3 (8.8)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seeking detoxification</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3 (16.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insomnia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5 (7.8)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tachycardia&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (13%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5 (0.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (13%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The most common withdrawal symptoms can be found in Table <xref rid="TAB3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, and were insomnia (8, 53%), hallucinations (8, 53%), and muscle abnormalities (8, 53%). Note that the percentages add up to more than 100% as many patients reported multiple symptoms.&#160;</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Most Common Withdrawal Symptoms in Phenibut Patients</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Withdrawal symptom&#160;&#160;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average dose of phenibut in grams (standard deviation)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insomnia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (53%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4 (10.5)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hallucinations</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (53%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8 (11.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Muscle abnormalities</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (53%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9 (9.6)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (40%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (5.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Restlessness</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3 (6.5)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tachycardia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7 (9.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Irritability</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7 (16.6)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disoriented</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (13%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (7.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agitation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (13%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5 (10.6)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Figure <xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> shows a side-by-side comparison of withdrawal and presenting symptoms. Note that the percentages shown in Figure <xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> are different from the percentages in Tables <xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, <xref rid="TAB3" ref-type="table">3</xref> because of Tables <xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, <xref rid="TAB3" ref-type="table">3</xref> factoring in several patients presenting with multiple symptoms. Figure <xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> looks at the total number of symptoms reported and calculates the percentage based on this number.</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Comparison of Withdrawal and Presenting Symptoms</title><p>A. Withdrawal Symptoms. B. Presenting Symptoms.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000068775-i02.jpg"/></fig><p>Next, an analysis was done on the dose of phenibut taken with each reported symptom. Figure <xref rid="FIG3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> compares the dosages for presenting and withdrawal symptoms.&#160;</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Comparison of Symptoms by Dose</title><p>A. Presenting Symptoms by Dose. B. Withdrawal Symptoms by Dose.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000068775-i03.jpg"/></fig><p>Finally, of the cases reported, 11 (73%) patients were taking phenibut to help overcome alcohol or drug misuse while 9 (60%) were taking phenibut as an anxiolytic and antidepressant. These add to over 100% because some patients listed multiple reasons for taking phenibut.&#160;</p><p>Discussion</p><p>Introduction and Relevance</p><p>Phenibut is a legally available substance with pharmacologic properties similar to prescription medications (GABA agonist). It is inexpensive and available online [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="REF24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="REF25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. It is important that awareness of this substance is increased, methods for withdrawal are evaluated, and the mechanism of phenibut is understood to increase the quality of care received by addicted patients or patients seeking medical care. As mentioned, phenibut does not appear on standard drug tests and there is no commercial test available, posing a diagnostic challenge for physicians. Proper history taking is essential, and physicians should specifically inquire about supplement use, as patients may not consider phenibut alongside prescription or OTC drugs. Physicians should keep phenibut on their differential when encountering patients with alcohol-like withdrawal symptoms and negative test results.</p><p>Physician Education and Raising Awareness</p><p>Educating physicians about supplements that carry a risk for harm, including their biological mechanisms, is crucial to determining methods of prevention and treatment. Phenibut should be considered in differential diagnoses for patients presenting with withdrawal symptoms like self-harm, psychomotor agitation, and hallucinations, even when standard tests are negative. Physicians are also key to raising awareness among patients and the community of what manufacturers often advertise as supplements but contain pharmacologic properties. Increased awareness of online supplements is vital, as these products have significant pharmacologic properties and addiction potential. Besides phenibut, other concerning supplements include kratom (stimulant) and tianeptine (NMDA agonist). Patients may quickly develop dependencies on these substances.</p><p>Tapering Strategies</p><p>Common strategies for tapering phenibut addiction include using baclofen and benzodiazepines. Baclofen, a GABA agonist and muscle relaxant, is effective in treating alcohol use disorder [<xref rid="REF26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="REF27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. It is used for tapering phenibut due to its ability to activate the same GABA receptors, eliciting similar responses. Gradual dose reduction helps mitigate withdrawal symptoms. While used less often in reported cases, benzodiazepines, methadone, diazepam, and phenobarbital were also successful in mitigating withdrawal symptoms.&#160;</p><p>Mechanism of Action</p><p>Phenibut functions as a GABA agonist due to its structural similarity to GABA, featuring an additional phenyl ring and carboxyl group [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. This structural modification enhances its lipophilicity, enabling it to cross the blood-brain barrier and exert potent effects [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Activation of GABA receptors increases the effects of the inhibitory neurotransmitter GABA, resulting in calming and anxiolytic effects [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p>Demographic Trends</p><p>Based on the results previously discussed, phenibut abuse shows to be more prevalent in younger males. This finding helps us identify the population that is most likely to be affected by this drug. Physicians should be aware of phenibut use as a possible diagnosis, especially when presented with a male patient between the ages of 20 and 35 years with withdrawal-like symptoms and negative drug screening. From cases reported, women may not be at as high of a risk as males as they accounted for a much smaller portion of the patient population reviewed.</p><p>Higher doses of phenibut were also seen in patients with addictive behavior and more associated symptoms. On average, patients consumed significantly more than recommended, which gives another factor to be aware of when taking a medical history. Because phenibut is a supplement and not a drug, there is no FDA-approved dosage of phenibut; however, guidelines generally recommend 500-1500 mg per day, which is significantly lower than the consumption of the patients who were reviewed [<xref rid="REF28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="REF29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. This underscores the importance of thorough history-taking, as patients may be unaware of their addiction. Physicians should inquire about all supplements to accurately assess intake as well as the amount of each supplement.&#160;</p><p>Limitations and Future Directions</p><p>This study's limitations include the small number of cases available, along with the limited age range and the gender of reporting patients. Another limitation of this study is that the study is based on cases that have been reported. The doses reported are based on the dosages reported by the patient. Further, we do not know exactly where the patients obtained their phenibut. Quality factors such as the purity of phenibut are not known and could contribute. These are all factors that we are unable to account for. This study focused on the limited data that are available to increase awareness and health outcomes. Increasing the reporting of phenibut cases will enhance the available data for review. As more information becomes available on phenibut addiction and withdrawal, our understanding of this drug will improve.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Phenibut is an easily accessible and legal substance with prescription-grade pharmacologic properties (GABA agonist) that does not show up on drug tests. Awareness of the drug adds differential diagnosis to physicians who see individuals with alcohol-like withdrawals, but all tests are negative. It is important to educate all physicians about potentially harmful supplements that are available to patients and their biological mechanisms. This review highlights the importance of collecting a thorough patient history, including supplements, to help prevent phenibut misuse and subsequent withdrawals. This review further educates physicians on how phenibut withdrawals can be treated, and to be wary of the facade many online retailers market as supplements.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#160; Christopher Stewart, Hunter Simonsen, Savitha K. Satyasi, Nauman Ashraf, Suporn Sukpraprut-Braaten</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#160; Christopher Stewart, Hunter Simonsen, Savitha K. Satyasi, Nauman Ashraf, Suporn Sukpraprut-Braaten</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#160; Christopher Stewart, Hunter Simonsen, Savitha K. Satyasi, Nauman Ashraf, Suporn Sukpraprut-Braaten</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#160; Christopher Stewart, Hunter Simonsen, Savitha K. Satyasi, Nauman Ashraf, Suporn Sukpraprut-Braaten</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold>&#160; Savitha K. Satyasi, Nauman Ashraf, Suporn Sukpraprut-Braaten</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Detoxification of a patient with comorbid dependence on phenibut and benzodiazepines by tapering with baclofen: Case report</article-title><source>J Clin Psychopharmacol</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Coenen</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dijkstra</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Batalla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schellekens</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>514</lpage><volume>39</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31433344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/JCP.0000000000001104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Phenibut (beta-phenyl-GABA): A tranquilizer and nootropic drug</article-title><source>CNS Drug Rev</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lapin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><volume>7</volume><year>2001</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11830761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1527-3458.2001.tb00211.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6494145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Acute behavioural disturbance associated with phenibut purchased via an internet supplier</article-title><source>Clin Toxicol (Phila)</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Downes</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berling</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mostafa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grice</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isbister</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>636</fpage><lpage>638</lpage><volume>53</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26114346</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3109/15563650.2015.1059945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>An unusual presentation of an uncommon drug: A case report on phenibut overdose</article-title><source>Cureus</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nedzlek</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michaelis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>14</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.23913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9078085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35530906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Withdrawal symptoms after Internet purchase of phenibut (&#946;-phenyl-&#947;-aminobutyric acid HCl)</article-title><source>J Clin Psychopharmacol</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Magsalin</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>648</fpage><lpage>649</lpage><volume>30</volume><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20841974</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/JCP.0b013e3181f057c8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Benzodiazepine pharmacology and central nervous system-mediated effects</article-title><source>Ochsner J</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffin CE</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bueno</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><volume>13</volume><year>2013</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3684331/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3684331/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23789008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3684331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>Barbiturates</article-title><source>StatPearls [Internet]</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Skibiski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdijadid</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-loc>Treasure Island, FL</publisher-loc><publisher-name>StatPearls Publishing</publisher-name><year>2024</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK539731/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK539731/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30969553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Notes from the field: Phenibut exposures reported to poison centers - United States, 2009-2019</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dilley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kubsad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liebelt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>1227</fpage><lpage>1228</lpage><volume>69</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32881852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.15585/mmwr.mm6935a5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7470459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Phenibut Addiction, Side Effects, Withdrawal, and Treatment</article-title><date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date-in-citation><year>2024</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://americanaddictioncenters.org/phenibut">https://americanaddictioncenters.org/phenibut</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Phenibut HCl</article-title><date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date-in-citation><year>2024</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://edengrows.org/products/phenibut-powder">https://edengrows.org/products/phenibut-powder</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Phenibut dependence</article-title><source>BMJ Case Rep</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Samokhvalov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paton-Gay</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balchand</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>2013</volume><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bcr-2012-008381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3604470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23391959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Acute phenibut withdrawal: A comprehensive literature review and illustrative case report</article-title><source>Bosn J Basic Med Sci</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardman</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sprung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weingarten</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><volume>19</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30501608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.17305/bjbms.2018.4008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6535394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Chronic phenibut use: Symptoms, severe withdrawal, and recovery</article-title><source>WMJ</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>VanDreese</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><volume>121</volume><year>2022</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35442585/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35442585/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35442585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Phenibut addiction in a patient with substance use disorder</article-title><source>Cureus</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Espiridion</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>11</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.5230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6758981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31565631</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Phenibut: A novel nootropic with abuse potential</article-title><source>Prim Care Companion CNS Disord</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mash</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leo</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>19</fpage><volume>22</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4088/PCC.19l02587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32791574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Phenibut (&#946;-phenyl-&#947;-aminobutyric acid) dependence and management of withdrawal: Emerging nootropics of abuse</article-title><source>Case Rep Psychiatry</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahuja</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mgbako</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katzman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>9864285</fpage><volume>2018</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29854531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2018/9864285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5952553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A case of phenibut directed detoxification leading to toxicity during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>J Addict Med</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterkin</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>602</fpage><lpage>605</lpage><volume>16</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35120058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/ADM.0000000000000966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9984204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Psychomotor agitation non-responsive to treatment: A case report of phenibut withdrawal syndrome</article-title><source>Front Psychiatry</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mandolini</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delvecchio</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiorentini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brambilla</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>688147</fpage><volume>12</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34262493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpsyt.2021.688147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8273510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Dissociative intoxication and prolonged withdrawal associated with phenibut: A case report</article-title><source>J Clin Psychopharmacol</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friend</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steiger</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>478</fpage><lpage>480</lpage><volume>37</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28614159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/JCP.0000000000000731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5662439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Phenibut (&#946;-phenyl-&#947;-aminobutyric acid) psychosis</article-title><source>Am J Ther</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madhira</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><volume>24</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MJT.0000000000000618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28723730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Phenibut exposures and clinical effects reported to a regional poison center</article-title><source>Am J Emerg Med</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bangh</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arens</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>2066</fpage><lpage>2071</lpage><volume>37</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30878413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajem.2019.02.044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Management of phenibut use disorder and withdrawal in a geriatric patient</article-title><source>Am J Geriatr Psychiatry</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wainblat</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weleff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><volume>31</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36266201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jagp.2022.09.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Case report of physiologic phenibut dependence treated with a phenobarbital taper in a patient being treated with buprenorphine</article-title><source>J Addict Med</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><volume>11</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28441273</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/ADM.0000000000000303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Phenibut Powder</article-title><date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date-in-citation><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hot Sale Phenibut Powder</surname><given-names>99</given-names></name></person-group><year>2024</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://keynovo.en.made-in-china.com/product/YFftMWkVbrAd/China-Hot-Sale-Phenibut-Powder-99-Phenibut-Phenibut-HCl-CAS-1078-21-3-Nootropics-Ingredients.html">https://keynovo.en.made-in-china.com/product/YFftMWkVbrAd/China-Hot-Sale-Phenibut-Powder-99-Phenibut-Phenibut-HCl-CAS-1078-21-3-Nootropics-Ingredients.html</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Phenibut</article-title><date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date-in-citation><year>2024</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cosmicnootropic.com/products/phenibut/">https://cosmicnootropic.com/products/phenibut/</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Efficacy and safety of baclofen for alcohol dependence: A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</article-title><source>Alcohol Clin Exp Res</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Garbutt</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kampov-Polevoy</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallop</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalka-Juhl</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flannery</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>1849</fpage><lpage>1857</lpage><volume>34</volume><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20662805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1530-0277.2010.01273.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2965272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The use of baclofen as a treatment for alcohol use disorder: A clinical practice perspective</article-title><source>Front Psychiatry</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>de Beaurepaire</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heydtmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>708</fpage><volume>9</volume><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Phenibut Dosage for Anxiety</article-title><date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date-in-citation><year>2023</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cosmicnootropic.com/shorts/phenibut-dosage-for-anxiety/">https://cosmicnootropic.com/shorts/phenibut-dosage-for-anxiety/</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>[Dietary supplements - a temporary trend or an effective help in the fight against obesity and increasing physical performance]</article-title><source>Pol Merkur Lekarski</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kostrzewska</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malinowski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zi&#243;&#322;kowska</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kijek</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><volume>50</volume><year>2022</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35801611/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35801611/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35801611</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>