<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2786</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">medicine</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MD</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12150925</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12150925.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12150925</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12150925</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40489815</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000042664</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MD-D-24-15919</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>5400</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Research Article</subject><subject>Observational Study</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Characteristics of patients showing dislocation after total hip arthroplasty in an acute care hospital: A retrospective cohort study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suenaga</surname><given-names initials="F">Fumihiko</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>hiko.0420.sue@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8121-1704</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names initials="T">Tokio</given-names></name><degrees>RPT, PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="c1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yasuoka</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yoshinori</given-names></name><degrees>RPT, MS</degrees><email>yasuoka@wakayama-med.ac.jp</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Minami</surname><given-names initials="K">Kohei</given-names></name><degrees>RPT, PhD</degrees><email>minamik@wakayama-med.ac.jp</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yukihide</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><email>ynishi@iwate-med.ac.jp</email><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishiyama</surname><given-names initials="D">Daisuke</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><email>dnishiya@wakayama-med.ac.jp</email><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names initials="H">Hiroshi</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><email>yamacha@wakayama-med.ac.jp</email><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kouda</surname><given-names initials="K">Ken</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><email>kenkouda@wakayama-med.ac.jp</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, Wakayama Medical University, Wakayama, Japan</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, Chuzan Hospital, Okinawa, Japan</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Division of Rehabilitation, Wakayama Medical University Hospital, Wakayama, Japan</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, Iwate Medical University, Iwate, Japan</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Department of Orthopedic Surgery, Wakayama Medical University, Wakayama, Japan.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>*</label>Correspondence: Tokio Kinoshita, Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, Wakayama Medical University, 811-1 Kimiidera, Wakayama 641-8509, Japan (e-mail: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="tokio@wakayama-med.ac.jp">tokio@wakayama-med.ac.jp</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>06</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>104</volume><issue>23</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">490304</issue-id><elocation-id>e42664</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>08</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>06</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-06-11 10:25:47.680"><day>11</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2025 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CCBY)</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="medi-104-e42664.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="medi-104-e42664.pdf"/><abstract><p>Most previous studies on dislocation after total hip arthroplasty (THA) have focused on patient- and surgery-related factors without detailing the specific circumstances of dislocation events. Therefore, this study aimed to analyze dislocation cases and compare these relevant factors between patients who experienced dislocation and those who did not to inform targeted prevention measures during acute care hospitalization. This retrospective study examined the electronic medical records of 420 patients (445 joints) who underwent THA and rehabilitation at our hospital between April 1, 2018, and August 31, 2023. A total of 9 cases of dislocation in 6 patients were reported. Dislocation occurred most frequently in bed within the patient&#8217;s room (5 cases; 55.6%), followed by in the rehabilitation room and the toilet (1 case each; 11.1%), and unknown locations (2 cases; 22.2%). Bed-related dislocations were associated with trunk rotation or external rotation of the hip joint; in 2 cases, the dislocation was already present when the patient awoke. The revision THA and THA indication rates, preoperative Functional Independence Measure scores, and locomotion status differed significantly between the patients who showed dislocation and those who did not. Revision THA, THA indications other than osteoarthritis, low Functional Independence Measure score at admission, and low locomotion status may increase the risk of dislocation. Furthermore, the findings suggest that dislocation prevention strategies during acute hospitalization should prioritize safe bed use and sleep positions.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>acute phase</kwd><kwd>complications</kwd><kwd>dislocation prevention</kwd><kwd>risk factor</kwd><kwd>total hip arthroplasty</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Dislocation is a serious adverse event following total hip arthroplasty (THA), and, along with mechanical loosening, is a leading cause for revision surgery.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> In addition to prolonging hospitalization in patients indicated for revision THA,<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> additional treatment costs associated with dislocation have increased over the years and represent a considerable financial burden on healthcare systems. Specifically, the average costs for treatment in the United States were $54,553 in 2009 and $77,851.24 in 2017.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> Dislocations occur frequently within weeks after surgery and 60% of dislocations occur within the first 5 weeks,<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> with the median time to dislocation being 24 (12&#8211;45) days<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup> and the time to readmission being 40.0 (15.3&#8211;92.8) days.<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> Therefore, given their frequency and impact, early dislocation prevention is essential not only to reduce patient morbidity but also to mitigate healthcare costs.</p><p>Previous studies on post-THA dislocation have focused on patient-related factors, such as age, sex, body mass index (BMI), THA indications, and history of spine fusion surgery, as well as surgery-related factors, including the approach method and cup-placement angle.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</sup> These investigations have made it possible to identify patients at high risk of dislocation. However, to develop effective dislocation prevention protocols and optimize the inpatient environment post-THA, it is necessary to clarify the specific circumstances under which dislocations occur. Yet to date, the locations and circumstances of dislocations occurring during hospitalization shortly after THA have not been investigated.</p><p>This study examined the characteristics of patients who experienced dislocation at our hospital and compared them between patients who experienced dislocation and those who did not to inform targeted prevention measures during acute care hospitalization.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>2. Materials and methods</title><sec><title>2.1. Study design and setting</title><p>This retrospective cohort study was conducted at Wakayama Medical University Hospital.</p></sec><sec><title>2.2. Participants</title><p>This study analyzed the electronic medical records of all patients who underwent THA and rehabilitation at our hospital between April 1, 2018, and August 31, 2023. Regarding the dislocation cases, reports submitted to the Medical Safety Promotion Department at our hospital were retrieved, and detailed information regarding each case was collected. The study period was defined as the acute period from the time of THA to the time of transfer from our hospital. We excluded patients who received a dual-mobility cup and those who underwent revision arthroplasty on only 1 side of the cup or the head.</p></sec><sec><title>2.3. Outcome measures</title><p>The survey items included the location of dislocation, dislocation status, direction of the dislocation, interval between surgery and dislocation, and treatment after dislocation. In addition, the Functional Independence Measure (FIM) score at admission,<sup>[<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</sup> preadmission locomotion status, preadmission Devane Activity score,<sup>[<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</sup> American Society of Anesthesiologists physical status classification system (ASA-PS) score at admission,<sup>[<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</sup> Charlson Comorbidity Index (CCI) at admission,<sup>[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</sup> approach method, cup inclination angle/anteversion angle,<sup>[<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</sup> cup size, head size, use of stem cement, history of spinal fusion surgery, number of days from surgery to discharge, and discharge destination were measured. The FIM consists of 18 items with a motor subscale (13 items) and a cognition subscale (5 items), each of which was assessed using a 7-point ordinal scale.<sup>[<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</sup> The Devane Activity Score uses a 5-point scale that indicates a patient&#8217;s activity level (1 indicates a sedentary/dependent status, whereas 5 indicates participation in contact sports).<sup>[<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</sup> The ASA-PS classifies the health status of patients before surgery into 6 classes (class I indicates a healthy person, whereas class VI indicates a brain-dead organ transplant donor).<sup>[<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</sup> The CCI evaluates comorbidities that contribute to death, with higher CCI values indicating a higher predicted mortality rate.<sup>[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</sup></p></sec><sec><title>2.4. Data analyses</title><p>Values of the variables are presented as number, mean&#8197;&#177;&#8197;standard deviation, and median (25th&#8211;75th percentiles), where applicable. Comparisons of age, weight, height, BMI, FIM score, CCI, days from surgery to discharge, cup and head size, cup inclination angle, and anteversion angle in patients who experienced dislocation and those who did not were performed using the Mann&#8211;Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> test. The chi-square test was used to evaluate the percentage of primary versus revision surgeries, THA indication, ASA-PS score, Devane Activity score, discharge destination, presence of spinal fusion, approach method, and use of stem cement. Differences were considered statistically significant at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.05, and statistical analyses were performed using GraphPad Prism 6 software (GraphPad Software Inc., San Diego, CA).</p></sec><sec><title>2.5. Ethical considerations</title><p>This study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki, and the protocol was approved by the relevant ethics review committee (number: 4100). This retrospective study posed no additional risks to patients during data collection and analysis, and all patient information was protected. Information concerning this study was posted on the university website, and patients or their families or relatives were given the opportunity to opt out of the study. The ethics review committee waived the requirement for written informed patient consent owing to the retrospective design of the study.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>3. Results</title><p>Fig. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows the flow diagram of patient selection. During the study period, THA was performed for 445 joints in 420 patients; among these, 7 patients experienced dislocation during hospitalization. After excluding 1 patient who experienced intraoperative dislocation, the dislocation group consisted of 6 patients. Four patients experienced dislocation once, one experienced it twice, and one experienced dislocation 3 times, yielding a total of 9 dislocations during hospitalization. The number of patients who did not experience dislocation was 413. After excluding 10 patients who underwent cup-only or head-only revision and 23 patients who received dual-mobility cups, the non-dislocation group consisted of 380 patients (401 joints).</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Patient flow diagram. (A, B) Unilateral revision was performed in all patients who underwent cup or head-only surgery.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medi-104-e42664-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>The incidences of dislocation during the study period were 1.55% in patients who underwent THA (6/386 patients) and 1.47% in the joints for which THA was performed (6/407 joints). The incidences of dislocation were 0.79% (3/381 joints) after primary THA and 11.5% (3/26 joints) after revision THA.</p><p>Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> presents the characteristics of patients in the dislocation and non-dislocation groups. Age, sex, height, weight, and BMI were not significantly different between the 2 groups. The rate of revision THA in the dislocation group (3 patients, 50%) was significantly higher than that in the non-dislocation group (23 patients, 5.7%). The most frequent indications for THA were osteoarthritis (2 patients, 33.3%) and fracture (2 patients, 33.3%; both fractures around THA) in the dislocation group, and osteoarthritis (300 patients, 74.8%) and osteonecrosis (53 patients, 13.2%) in the non-dislocation group, with the 2 groups showing significant differences in the proportions of patients with these THA indications. In the dislocation group, the total FIM score before surgery was 85.9 (49.8&#8211;115.0), and the scores for the motor and cognition subscales were 55.5 (30.5&#8211;81.3) and 32.5 (18.8&#8211;35.0), respectively; the corresponding values in the non-dislocation group were 124 (117.0&#8211;125.3), 89.0 (82.0&#8211;91.0), and 35 (35.0&#8211;35.0), respectively. The dislocation group showed significantly lower scores for all measured items than the non-dislocation group. In the dislocation group, 3 patients (50%) walked with a cane and 2 (33.3%) required a wheelchair before hospitalization, whereas in the non-dislocation group, 168 (44.2) patients could walk without assistive devices and 168 (44.2%) walked with a cane before hospitalization, with the percentages differing significantly between the 2 groups. The groups showed no significant differences in the Devane Activity score, ASA-PS, or CCI. However, the interval from surgery to discharge was significantly longer in the dislocation group than in the non-dislocation group (37.8&#8197;&#177;&#8197;16.2 days vs 18.1&#8197;&#177;&#8197;6.5 days). The discharge destination also differed significantly between the groups, with 83.3% of the patients who experienced dislocation being transferred to other facilities and 65.3% of those without dislocations being discharged home. However, the 2 groups showed no significant difference in the proportions of patients who showed spinal fusion and those who did not.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Patient characteristics.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with dislocation (n&#8197;=&#8197;6)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients without dislocation (n&#8197;=&#8197;380)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (yr)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.3&#8197;&#177;&#8197;12.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.2&#8197;&#177;&#8197;11.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.6095</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male/female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72/308</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.3744</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height (cm)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150.4&#8197;&#177;&#8197;10.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">153.9&#8197;&#177;&#8197;8.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.3450</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight (kg)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.4&#8197;&#177;&#8197;10.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.4&#8197;&#177;&#8197;11.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.1445</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0&#8197;&#177;&#8197;4.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.7&#8197;&#177;&#8197;4.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.4970</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary/revision<xref rid="tab1fn3" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/3 (50.0%/50.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">378/23 (94.3%/5.7%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">THA indication<xref rid="tab1fn3" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Osteoarthritis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (33.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300 (74.8%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Fracture</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (33.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (2.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Osteonecrosis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (16.7%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (13.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Post-THA infection</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (16.7%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;THA loosening</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (4.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Developmental dysplasia</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (2.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Rheumatoid arthritis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (1.7%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Tumor</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;THA dislocation</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.25%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total FIM score</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.9 (49.8&#8211;115.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124.0 (117.0&#8211;125.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Motor subscale score</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.5 (30.5&#8211;81.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.0 (82.0&#8211;91.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Cognition subscale score</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.5 (18.8&#8211;35.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.0 (35.0&#8211;35.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Locomotion status</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0042</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Possible without aids</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168 (44.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;With a cane</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (50.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168 (44.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;With walking frame</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (16.7%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (1.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Using wheelchair</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (33.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (10.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Devane Activity Score</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.2223</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (50%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (18.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (50%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">159 (41.8%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (18.7%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76 (20.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (1.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASA-PS</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.9286</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8544;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (50.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">194 (51.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8545;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (50.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162 (42.6%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8546;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (5.8%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8547;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8548;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8549;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCI</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.0&#8211;1.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0&#8211;1.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.4764</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Days from surgery to discharge</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.8&#8197;&#177;&#8197;16.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.1&#8197;&#177;&#8197;6.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0006</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discharge destination</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Home/other facilities</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/5 (16.7%/83.3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248/132 (65.3%/34.7%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0136</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spine fusion</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (16.7%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (4.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.1599</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>The FIM score and CCI are shown as median (25th&#8211;75th percentile).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>BMI = body mass index, THA = total hip arthroplasty, FIM = Functional Independence Measure, ASA-PS = American Society of Anesthesiologists physical status, CCI = Charlson Comorbidity Index.</p></fn><fn id="tab1fn3"><label>*</label><p>The results for the dislocation group were based on the data obtained for 6 dislocated joints, and those for the non-dislocation group were based on the data for 401 joints that were treated with THA. The Mann&#8211;Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> test was used to compare age, height, weight, BMI, FIM score, CCI, and days from surgery to discharge between patients who experienced dislocation and those who did not, and the chi-square test was used to evaluate the percentage of primary versus revision surgeries, locomotion status, Devane score, ASA-PS score, discharge destination, and the presence of spinal fixation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref> summarizes the dislocation scenarios. Six patients experienced 9 dislocations. The dislocations occurred on the bed in the patient&#8217;s own room in 5 cases (55.6%), the rehabilitation room and the toilet in 1 case each (11.1%), and at an unknown location in 2 cases (22.2%), with dislocation on the bed accounting for half of the cases. The dislocation direction was anterior in 6 cases (66.6%) and posterior in 3 cases (33.3%). The interval from surgery to dislocation ranged from 4 to 22 days (mean, 11.9&#8197;&#177;&#8197;5.7 days). Dislocation occurred during range of motion training in the hip extension direction by a physical therapist in 1 case; when standing up from a toilet seat with the hip in external rotation in 1 case; when the patient moved in an escape reaction on experiencing pain as a result of the balloon catheter getting stuck while the patient was on the bed in 1 case; when the patient tried to pick up an object from a sitting posture on the bed and rotated the trunk in 1 case; when the patient externally rotated the hip joint while changing a lower garment during 1 case; and in unknown circumstances in 4 cases, including 2 cases in which dislocation was identified on routine radiographic assessments and 2 cases in which dislocation was observed upon waking. Treatment after dislocation was closed reduction in 2 of the 4 patients who experienced a first dislocation, revision THA in the other 2 patients, and revision THA after the last dislocation in 2 patients who experienced multiple dislocations.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Summary of the cases showing dislocation.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">THA indication</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Approach</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary/revision</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location of dislocation</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Direction of dislocation</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interval from surgery to dislocation</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dislocated situation</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1<sup>st</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteoarthritis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rehabilitation room</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">During right hip extension range of motion training by therapist</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Closed reduction</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;2<sup>nd</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown (periodic radiographic evaluation revealed dislocation)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Revision THA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient B</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1<sup>st</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fracture</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Revision</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterior</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown (periodic radiographic evaluation revealed dislocation)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Revision THA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient C</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1<sup>st</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteoarthritis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Toilet</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">When standing up from a toilet seat with the hip in external rotation</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Revision THA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient D</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1<sup>st</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infection</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Revision</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">On the bed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterior</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown (dislocated upon awakening)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Closed reduction</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient E</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1<sup>st</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fracture</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Revision</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">On the bed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">During pain escape movement</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Closed reduction</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;2<sup>nd</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">On the bed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown (dislocated upon awakening)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Closed reduction</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;3<sup>rd</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">On the bed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterior</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">When the patient rotated the trunk to pick up an object in a sitting position</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Revision THA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;1<sup>st</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Necrosis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALS</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">On the bed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">When changing lower garments on the bed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Closed reduction</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>ALS&#8197;=&#8197;anterolateral supine, L&#8197;=&#8197;lateral, P&#8197;=&#8197;posterior, T&#8197;=&#8197;two-incision, THA&#8197;=&#8197;total hip arthroplasty.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref> shows the surgical information for both groups. The surgical approaches employed were the anterior lateral supine&#8197;+&#8197;Orthopadisehe Chirurgie Munchen approach in 287 cases, 2-incision approach in 98 cases, posterior and lateral approaches in 9 cases each, and anterior approach in 4 cases. The surgical approaches in the cases of dislocation were the posterior (22.2%), lateral (11.1%), 2-incision (2.0%), and anterior lateral supine&#8197;+&#8197;Orthopadisehe Chirurgie Munchen (0.3%) approaches, with the incidence of dislocation differing significantly depending on the approach. The cup sizes were 51.3&#8197;&#177;&#8197;4.1&#8197;mm in the dislocation group and 48.8&#8197;&#177;&#8197;3.3&#8197;mm in the non-dislocation group, and the femoral head sizes were 32.7&#8197;&#177;&#8197;3.0&#8197;mm in the dislocation group and 32.5&#8197;&#177;&#8197;2.0&#8197;mm in the non-dislocation group, with both sizes showing no significant intergroup differences. The dislocation rates of the stem were 0.85% when cement was not used and 5.8% when cement was used; the dislocation rate differed significantly in relation to cement usage. Cup inclination values were 47.3&#8197;&#177;&#8197;6.0&#176; in the dislocated group and 45.2&#8197;&#177;&#8197;28.8&#176; in the non-dislocated group, and cup anteversion values were 15.5&#8197;&#177;&#8197;4.7&#176; in the dislocated group and 17.9&#8197;&#177;&#8197;6.9&#176; in the non-dislocated group, with no significant differences between the 2 groups.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Surgical information.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (n&#8197;=&#8197;407)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases showing dislocation (n&#8197;=&#8197;6)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases without dislocation (n&#8197;=&#8197;401)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rate of dislocation (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Approach</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;ALS&#8197;+&#8197;OCM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">287 (70.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Two-incision</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98 (24.1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Posterior</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (2.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Lateral</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (2.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Anterior</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (1.0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cup size (mm)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.8&#8197;&#177;&#8197;3.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.3&#8197;&#177;&#8197;4.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.8&#8197;&#177;&#8197;3.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.1009</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Femoral head size (mm)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.5&#8197;&#177;&#8197;2.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.7&#8197;&#177;&#8197;3.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.5&#8197;&#177;&#8197;2.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.7033</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Femoral stem</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0059</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Cementless</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">355 (87.2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">352</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Cemented</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (12.8%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cup inclination (&#176;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.2&#8197;&#177;&#8197;28.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.3&#8197;&#177;&#8197;6.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.2&#8197;&#177;&#8197;28.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.1519</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cup anteversion (&#176;)<xref rid="tab3fn3" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9&#8197;&#177;&#8197;6.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5&#8197;&#177;&#8197;4.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9&#8197;&#177;&#8197;6.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.3519</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Chi-square test was used to evaluate the approach method, and use of stem cement between patients who experienced dislocation and those who did not, and the Mann&#8211;Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> test was used to compare cup and head size, cup inclination angle, and anteversion angle.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>ALS = anterolateral supine, OCM = Orthopadisehe Chirurgie Munchen, THA = total hip arthroplasty.</p></fn><fn id="tab3fn3"><label>*</label><p>Measurements were difficult to obtain in 20 joints, so the findings represent the data for 381 joints.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>4. Discussion</title><p>The results of this study showed that more than half of the early postoperative THA dislocations occurred while the patient was on the bed, and that revision THA, THA indications, FIM score on admission, and preoperative locomotion status were related to the occurrence of dislocation. In addition, more than half of the cases of dislocation required revision THA, which increased the duration of hospitalization by a factor of 2 and decreased the percentage of patients who were discharged. To our knowledge, this study is the first to report specific dislocation conditions in addition to the factors related to the occurrence of dislocation in patients early after THA.</p><p>A meta-analysis spanning nearly 60 years and encompassing 5,030,293 patients with follow-up data exceeding 1 year reported that the incidence of dislocation after primary THA was 1.7%, with a 1-year dislocation rate of 1.0%.<sup>[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</sup> In contrast, the incidences of dislocation in cases of revision THA were reported to be 5.1% at 1 year postoperatively,<sup>[<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</sup> 9.0% in broader reviews covering follow-ups from several months to years,<sup>[<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</sup> and 15.9% in a 15-year follow-up study.<sup>[<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</sup> The present results showed that the incidences of dislocation were 0.79% after primary THA and 11.5% after revision THA, but this study had a shorter study period than that of other previous studies and it evaluated the acute postoperative care period. Furthermore, the approach method, patient severity, indications, and other factors cannot be matched and compared to those used in previous studies; therefore, caution must be exercised when interpreting the results.</p><p>Anterior and 2-incision approaches are associated with a higher risk of dislocation in the direction of hip extension and external rotation, whereas lateral and posterior approaches show a higher risk of dislocation in the direction of flexion and internal rotation.<sup>[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</sup> Excluding 2 cases in which the occurrence status was unknown (patients A and B), most cases (71.4%) involved dislocations on the bed in the patient&#8217;s own hospital room. Surprisingly, 2 cases of dislocation occurred during sleep and did not involve large body movements. Although the circumstances of the dislocation are unknown, patient D showed posterior dislocation after undergoing a posterior approach, possibly because the hip joint involuntarily moved in the direction of flexion and internal rotation while sleeping. However, in patient E, anterior dislocation occurred despite a lateral approach. This patient had previously undergone rotational osteotomy, 2 rounds of plate fixation due to a fracture caused by a fall, 2 rounds of THA, and treatment for a fracture and wound infection before this surgery. Therefore, the anterior dislocation was thought to have occurred because the soft tissue was weak after surgery and treatment. Patient E also experienced 2 dislocations on bed, including a posterior dislocation. Therefore, in patients who have a history of multiple surgeries due to fractures, infections, or dislocations, care should be taken since the approach may not indicate the direction of dislocation. Patient F, who underwent an anterior approach, experienced dislocation during external rotation of the hip when putting on and taking off pants in bed, while patient C, who also underwent an anterior approach, experienced dislocation when standing up in the external rotation position of the hip during toileting. Patient C&#8217;s preoperative hip extension was &#8722;45&#176;, and her range of motion at the time of dislocation was about the same, indicating that impingement may have occurred due to extension and external rotation of the hip joint when she stood up. These findings indicate that in the acute stage, patient education on bed mobility and proper sleep positioning is essential. Moreover, in patients who have a complex medical history and functional impairment, as in patients C and E, standardized dislocation precautions based solely on the surgical approach may be inadequate, underscoring the need for individualized guidance.</p><p>Revision THA, THA indications other than osteoarthritis, obesity, small head size, abnormal cup-placement angle, and prior spinal fusion have been associated with the risk of dislocation.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</sup> The study period was defined as the acute period from the time of THA to the time of transfer from our hospital. Our results suggest that revision surgery and THA indications other than osteoarthritis indicate a high risk of dislocation during the early postoperative period. Fessy et al reported that low Devane Activity scores (low activity) indicate a higher risk of dislocation<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup>; however, the relationship between preoperative activity levels and dislocation remains unclear. The dislocation group in our study also had significantly lower preoperative FIM motor, cognition, and locomotion status scores than the non-dislocation group. Previous studies have shown that dementia is associated with dislocation<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> and that patients who have low preoperative activities of daily living, cognitive ability, and preoperative locomotion need special attention to prevent dislocation. The association between the approach and the occurrence of dislocation is controversial,<sup>[<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</sup> and there is no consensus regarding the association between the use of cement and dislocation.<sup>[<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</sup> However, this study showed significant differences related to the surgical approach and cement usage. Nevertheless, the influence of the surgical approach on dislocations is difficult to confirm because the approach differs depending on the patient&#8217;s condition, pathology, and surgeon.</p><p>More than half of the patients who experienced dislocations in this study underwent revision THA. Their hospital stay was approximately twice as long as that in than those without dislocations, and most patients were transferred to other hospitals, making dislocations a huge burden on patients. Therefore, more information is required to strengthen the measures to prevent dislocation. This study was a single-center retrospective cohort study with a sample size of only 6 patients who experienced dislocations. Therefore, large-scale, multicenter, joint research should be conducted in the future. However, this report provides useful information on measures to prevent dislocation during the acute hospital stay after THA.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>5. Conclusions</title><p>Over a period of 5 years and 4 months, 6 of the 386 patients who underwent THA at our acute care hospital experienced postoperative dislocation. Revision THA, THA indications other than osteoarthritis, low FIM motor and cognitive scores on admission, and low preoperative locomotion status may contribute to the increased risk of dislocation in the early postoperative period. The study findings highlight the need to reassess in-hospital dislocation prevention strategies, particularly with regard to bed mobility and sleep positioning, and emphasize necessity of personalized measures in patients who have a complex medical history and functional disability.</p></sec><sec><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors thank the rehabilitation staff for their support with this study.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> Fumihiko Suenaga, Tokio Kinoshita, Daisuke Nishiyama.</p><p><bold>Data curation:</bold> Yoshinori Yasuoka, Kohei Minami, Daisuke Nishiyama.</p><p><bold>Formal analysis:</bold> Yoshinori Yasuoka, Kohei Minami, Daisuke Nishiyama.</p><p><bold>Methodology:</bold> Fumihiko Suenaga.</p><p><bold>Project administration:</bold> Yukihide Nishimura, Hiroshi Yamada, Ken Kouda.</p><p><bold>Writing &#8211; original draft:</bold> Fumihiko Suenaga, Tokio Kinoshita, Yoshinori Yasuoka, Kohei Minami.</p><p><bold>Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing:</bold> Tokio Kinoshita, Yukihide Nishimura, Daisuke Nishiyama, Hiroshi Yamada, Ken Kouda.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="abbr"><p><def-list><title>Abbreviations:</title><def-item><term>ASA-PS</term><def><p>American Society of Anesthesiologists physical status classification system</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BMI</term><def><p>body mass index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CCI</term><def><p>Charlson Comorbidity Index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FIM</term><def><p>Functional Independence Measure</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OCM</term><def><p>Orthopadisehe Chirurgie Munchen</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>THA</term><def><p>total hip arthroplasty</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>The authors have no funding and conflicts of interest to disclose.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>How to cite this article: Suenaga F, Kinoshita T, Yasuoka Y, Minami K, Nishimura Y, Nishiyama D, Yamada H, Kouda K. Characteristics of patients showing dislocation after total hip arthroplasty in an acute care hospital: A retrospective cohort study. Medicine 2025;104:23(e42664).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gwam</surname><given-names>CU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mistry</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Current epidemiology of revision total hip arthroplasty in the United States: national inpatient sample 2009 to 2013.</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>2088</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28336249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2017.02.046</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castrodad</surname><given-names>IMD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Etcheson</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Inpatient dislocation after primary total hip arthroplasty: incidence and associated patient and hospital factors.</article-title><source>Hip Int</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>152</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32716660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1120700020940968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bozic</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurtz</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vail</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The epidemiology of revision total hip arthroplasty in the United States.</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>128</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19122087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2106/JBJS.H.00155</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourne</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The dislocating hip: what to do, what to do.</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15190564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2004.02.016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maloy</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kammien</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grauer</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Adverse events after total hip arthroplasty are not sufficiently characterized by 30-day follow-up: a database study.</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>525</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36272511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2022.10.020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gausden</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parhar</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Popper</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sculco</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rush</surname><given-names>BNM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for early dislocation following primary elective total hip arthroplasty.</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>1567</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71.e2</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29395718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2017.12.034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fessy</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Putman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Viste</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>What are the risk factors for dislocation in primary total hip arthroplasty? A multicenter case-control study of 128 unstable and 438 stable hips.</article-title><source>Orthop Traumatol Surg Res</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>663</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28629944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.otsr.2017.05.014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waddell</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitziger</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gladnick</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Is dislocation risk due to posterior pelvic tilt reduced with direct anterior approach total hip arthroplasty?</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>3692</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34330601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2021.07.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hopper</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parks</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Direct anterior approach for primary total hip arthroplasty lowers the risk of dislocation compared to the posterior approach: a single institution experience.</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>495</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>500</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34774686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2021.11.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Insufficient stem antetorsion and lower cup abduction is a combined risk factor for posterior hip dislocation in patients undergoing THA for femoral neck fractures: a retrospective analysis.</article-title><source>BMC Musculoskelet Disord</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>103</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38291445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12891-024-07199-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10826068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Umarov</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urazbaev</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Patient-related factors affecting the risk of complications after primary total hip arthroplasty.</article-title><source>Georgian Med News</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>344</volume>:<fpage>180</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38236120</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tarasawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Increased early complication rates following total hip arthroplasty in rheumatoid arthritis patients based on a Japanese nationwide medical claims database study.</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>9137</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40097592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-025-94342-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11914517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turkmani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gililland</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerlinger</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Della Valle</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Total hip arthroplasty performed by fellowship- and nonfellowship-trained surgeons: a comparison of indications, perioperative management, and complications [published online ahead of print March 8, 2025]</article-title> . <source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <comment>doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2025.03.003</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2025.03.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40058510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sterling</surname><given-names>ON</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Does femoral head size matter? A comparison of 32-, 36-, and 40-millimeter heads in primary total hip arthroplasty: an American joint replacement registry analysis [published online ahead of print February 25, 2025].</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <comment>doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2025.02.060</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2025.02.060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40015384</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Causes of reoperations after primary total hip arthroplasty: a retrospective cohort study over 20 years [published online ahead of print February 14, 2025].</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <comment>doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2025.02.032</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2025.02.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39956497</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambrechts</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Patients undergoing multilevel thoracolumbar fusions with prior total hip arthroplasty are at higher risk for prosthetic dislocations.</article-title><source>J Am Acad Orthop Surg</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5435</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5435/JAAOS-D-24-00606</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39928854</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tarasawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Does osteonecrosis of the femoral head increase early complication rates after total hip arthroplasty? A Japanese nationwide medical claims database study [published online ahead of print January 22, 2025].</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <comment>doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2025.01.029</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2025.01.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39855403</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palacios</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palacios</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palacios</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of bariatric surgery on postoperative outcomes of total hip arthroplasty: an updated systematic review and meta-analysis [published online ahead of print November 27, 2024].</article-title><source>Asian J Surg</source>. <comment>doi: 10.1016/j.asjsur.2024.11.003</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.asjsur.2024.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39609199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwasa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakahara</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Large cohort study on prevention strategies for dislocation in total hip arthroplasty [published online ahead of print November 12, 2024].</article-title><source>J Orthop Sci</source>. <comment>doi: 10.1016/j.jos.2024.10.001</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jos.2024.10.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39537524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keith</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Granger</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherwin</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The functional independence measure: a new tool for rehabilitation.</article-title><source>Adv Clin Rehabil</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3503663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Devane</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horne</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coldham</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Three-dimensional polyethylene wear of a press-fit titanium prosthesis: factors influencing generation of polyethylene debris.</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>256</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9113539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0883-5403(97)90021-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hendrix</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garmon</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>American society of anesthesiologists physical status classification system.</article-title> In: <source>StatPearls</source>. <publisher-name>StatPearls Publishing</publisher-name>; <year>2025</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28722969</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlson</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pompei</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ales</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacKenzie</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A new method of classifying prognostic comorbidity in longitudinal studies: development and validation.</article-title><source>J Chronic Dis</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>373</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>83</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3558716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0021-9681(87)90171-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Widmer</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A simplified method to determine acetabular cup anteversion from plain radiographs.</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>387</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15067657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2003.10.016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Erp</surname><given-names>JHJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#252;sken</surname><given-names>MFT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Filipe</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Did the dislocation risk after primary total hip arthroplasty decrease over time? A meta-analysis across six decades.</article-title><source>Arch Orthop Trauma Surg</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>143</volume>:<fpage>4491</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>500</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36357707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00402-022-04678-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10293125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khatod</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paxton</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Namba</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fithian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An analysis of the risk of hip dislocation with a contemporary total joint registry.</article-title><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>447</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16741469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/01.blo.0000218752.22613.78</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for dislocation after revision total hip arthroplasty: a systematic review and meta-analysis.</article-title><source>Int J Surg</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28043927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijsu.2016.12.122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>[28]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jimenez Almonte</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sierra</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The cumulative risk of re-dislocation after revision THA performed for instability increases close to 35% at 15 years.</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>1177</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25686783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2015.02.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>[29]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rowan</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pietrak</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevention of dislocation after total hip arthroplasty.</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>1316</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29525344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2018.01.047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>[30]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rastogi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kendoff</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dislocation after total hip arthroplasty.</article-title><source>Curr Rev Musculoskelet Med</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>350</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24170479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12178-013-9187-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4094102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>[31]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>SHL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Total hip arthroplasty has higher complication rates in stiff spine patients: a systematic review and network meta-analysis.</article-title><source>J Orthop Surg Res</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>353</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35842632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13018-022-03237-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9288065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>[32]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Masonis</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourne</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Surgical approach, abductor function, and total hip arthroplasty dislocation.</article-title><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>405</volume>:<fpage>46</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00003086-200212000-00006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12461355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>[33]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright-Chisem</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elbuluk</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jerabek</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sculco</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vigdorchik</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The journey to preventing dislocation after total hip arthroplasty: how did we get here?</article-title><source>Bone Joint J</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>104-B</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34969287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1302/0301-620X.104B1.BJJ-2021-0823.R1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>[34]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elbardesy</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anazor</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maatough</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cemented versus uncemented stems for revision total hip replacement: a systematic review and meta-analysis.</article-title><source>World J Orthop</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>630</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37662666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5312/wjo.v14.i8.630</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10473907</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>[35]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mon&#225;rrez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cemented versus cementless femoral fixation for total hip arthroplasty following osteoarthritis.</article-title><source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>1545</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38128624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.arth.2023.12.024</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>