<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">AJOG Glob Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">AJOG Glob Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4305</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ajoggr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>AJOG Global Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2666-5778</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11388400</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11388400.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11388400</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11388400</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39263682</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.xagr.2024.100384</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2666-5778(24)00078-9</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100384</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Implementation of universal screening for substance use in pregnancy in a public healthcare system</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names initials="A">Alesha</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>Alesha.white@utsouthwestern.edu</email><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">&#8270;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002"><name name-style="western"><surname>Afsari</surname><given-names initials="M">Macy</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0003"><name name-style="western"><surname>Balakrishnan</surname><given-names initials="H">Harini</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0004"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapa</surname><given-names initials="E">Emilia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="M">Meredith</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0006"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehra</surname><given-names initials="S">Shubhangi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0007"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faucher</surname><given-names initials="MA">Mary Ann</given-names></name><degrees>PhD, CNM, FACNM</degrees><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0008"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names initials="J">Joyce</given-names></name><degrees>DNP, APRN, WHNP-BC</degrees><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0009"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cordova</surname><given-names initials="P">Polly</given-names></name><degrees>DNP, APRN, CNM</degrees><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duryea</surname><given-names initials="EL">Elaine L.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0011"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names initials="DB">David B.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0012"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ambia</surname><given-names initials="AM">Anne M.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0013"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mcintire</surname><given-names initials="DD">Donald D.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0014"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names initials="EH">Emily H.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, TX (White, Afsari, Balakrishnan, Chapa, Kim, Mehra, Duryea, Nelson, Ambia, Mcintire, Adhikari)</aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology at Parkland Health, Dallas, TX (White, Duryea, Nelson, Ambia, Adhikari, Faucher, Miller, Cordova)</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor0001"><label>&#8270;</label>Corresponding author: Alesha White, MD <email>Alesha.white@utsouthwestern.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">465747</issue-id><elocation-id>100384</elocation-id><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>27</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-09-12 17:25:15.823"><day>12</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2024 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0001"><sec><title>Objective</title><p>Screening questionnaires are one option for identification of at-risk substance use and substance use disorder (SUD) during pregnancy. We report the experience of a single institution following universal implementation of a brief screening tool for self-reported substance use at the first prenatal encounter.</p></sec><sec><title>Study Design</title><p>This is a prospective implementation study evaluating screening for substance use in pregnancy in a large safety net healthcare system. Universal screening with the National Institute of Drug Abuse (NIDA) Quick Screen V1.0 was integrated into the electronic medical record (EMR) and administered at the first point of contact with the healthcare system. SUD was identified initially with diagnosis within the EMR by a healthcare provider and was confirmed with toxicology (maternal or neonatal) results corroborating a pattern of substance use and maternal and neonatal ICD-10 codes for SUD. Patients identified with SUD were then classified as moderate or severe SUD based on criteria established by the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 5th edition. We measured rates of NIDA implementation across different healthcare settings, evaluated NIDA concordance with ascertainment of SUD, and compared adverse pregnancy outcomes associated with moderate and severe SUD.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>From July 28, 2021, through June 25, 2022, 14,634 unique pregnant individuals accessed care at ambulatory and acute care sites. Universal implementation of the NIDA Quick Screen identified at-risk substance use in 2146 (14.7%) of those who accessed our system, or 17.1% of 12,550 screened across the system, with greater screen completion in ambulatory over acute care settings. SUD was identified in 256 (1.7%) of 14,634 individuals and moderate or severe SUD was identified in 184 (1.3%). Among those with moderate or severe SUD, 90 (48.9%) were NIDA positive, 22 (12.0%) NIDA negative, and 72 (39.1%) unscreened. Of 94 individuals with NIDA discordance or who were unscreened 76 (81%) accessed initial care through an acute care setting. Of 96 individuals with opioid use disorder, 68 (70.8%) were treated with medication-assisted therapy, and 56 (58.3%) were screened with the NIDA Quick Screen. Among delivered individuals with available outcomes, those with moderate or severe SUD were less likely to seek prenatal care (71 (76%) vs 9852 (98%), &lt;0.001)) and more likely to deliver before 37 weeks, (18 (20%) vs 909 (9%), RR (95% CI) 2.13 (1.40, 3.24)) compared to individuals without SUD. Neonates exposed to moderate or severe SUD were more likely to have birth weight &lt;10th centile for gestational age (20 (22%) vs 1147 (12%), RR (95% CI) 1.92 (1.29, 2.85)) and require admission to the neonatal intensive care unit (NICU) (19 (21%) vs 964 (10%), RR (95%) 1.95 (1.30, 2.93)).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Universal screening was implemented across a large public healthcare system at a high rate, with higher rates of implementation in ambulatory settings. NIDA successfully identified at-risk substance use in 17% of the SUD cohort but failed to identify more than 50% of patients with moderate or severe SUD. Patients with moderate and severe SUD accessed care primarily through the emergency department and experienced higher rates of adverse obstetric and neonatal outcomes. Future efforts to identify, engage, and retain this highest-risk group are needed.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="keys0001"><title>Key words</title><kwd>methamphetamines</kwd><kwd>NIDA</kwd><kwd>opioid use</kwd><kwd>prescription drugs</kwd><kwd>screening</kwd><kwd>substance use disorder</kwd><kwd>substance use in pregnancy</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="para9001">
<boxed-text id="mcf5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>AJOG Global Reports at a Glance</title></caption><sec id="sec0001"><title>Why was this study conducted?</title><p id="para0007">We report a single-center experience implementing a universal 4-question NIDA Quick Screen tool for self-reported substance use at the first prenatal encounter across a large public healthcare system. Objectives were to (1) evaluate rates of implementation across different clinical sites, (2) characterize success in identifying substance use disorder (SUD) in pregnancy, and (3) compare pregnancy outcomes among those with and without moderate and severe SUD in pregnancy.</p></sec><sec id="sec0002"><title>Key findings</title><p id="para0011">Universal implementation of a 4-question NIDA Quick Screen identified at-risk substance use in 17.1% screened individuals across the system, with greater screen completion in ambulatory over acute care settings.</p><p id="para0012">NIDA Quick Screen identified about half of individuals with moderate or severe SUD in pregnancy ascertained by medical record review, with others screening negative or unscreened. Most unscreened individuals accessed care through acute or emergent care settings.</p><p id="para0013">Of individuals who delivered in our system, those with moderate or severe SUD were less likely to access early prenatal care and had higher preterm birth, low birth weight, and neonatal intensive care unit admission compared to those without moderate or severe SUD.</p></sec><sec id="sec0003"><title>What does this add to what is known?</title><p id="para0014">Universal screening for self-reported substance use facilitates identification of at-risk substance use for early intervention but may fail to identify patients with moderate or severe SUD who are less likely to access traditional prenatal care.</p><p id="para0015">Our results support findings in other studies that pregnant individuals with moderate or severe SUD are less likely to seek or maintain prenatal care and have increased maternal and neonatal morbidity. Future efforts to engage and retain this highest-risk group outside the traditional prenatal care system may be needed.</p></sec></boxed-text>
</p><sec id="sec0004"><title>Introduction</title><p id="para0016">According to the 2022 National Survey on Drug Use and Health (NSDUH), rates of substance use among pregnant women include 9.6% illicit drugs, 8.4% tobacco and 11% alcohol.<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Although opioid use disorder (OUD) has been a recent major focus, rates of overall illicit drug use have also risen. According to NSDUH, between the years of 2021 and 2022, illicit drug use rose from 7.9% to 9.6% among U.S. pregnant female adults between the ages of 15 and 44.<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> One possible contributor to the rise of substance use disorder (SUD) in pregnancy in this time period is the COVID-19 pandemic given its association with higher rates of financial hardship, isolation and anxiety.<xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Among contributors to preventable pregnancy-related deaths in the U.S., mental health conditions, including deaths due to overdose or poisoning-related to SUD, made up the largest percentage at 23% in the 2017&#8211;2019 Maternal Mortality Review Committee findings, surpassing previously more common causes to include hemorrhage and infection.<xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> SUD in pregnancy is associated with poorer maternal and neonatal outcomes to include neonatal abstinence syndrome, low birth weight and increased rates of neonatal and maternal mortality.<xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></p><p id="para0017">Globally, drug use is one of the most common causes of preventable death, injuries and disabilities.<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> The United States Preventative Services Task Force, a task force made up of a panel of experts in primary care and prevention that make recommendations for clinical preventative services, recommends screening for substance use via patient interview for all adults over the age of 18.<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> Given the rise in SUD and its effects on pregnancy outcomes, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists and the World Health Organization recommend screening for substance use at the first prenatal visit for all patients as a part of comprehensive and universal obstetric care.<xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Validated screening questionnaires such has 4Ps,<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA) Quick Screen<xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> and CRAFFT<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> among others have been recommended for detection of at-risk substance use during pregnancy in order to link patients to appropriate care given their ability to detect substance use and misuse.<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> The purpose of these screening questionnaires is to detect at risk substance use and SUD early on but does not formally provide a diagnosis.<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> Coleman-Cowger et al demonstrated 80% to 90% sensitivity with adaptations of the 4Ps and NIDA Quick Screen administered by providers when validated with urine and hair drug testing.<xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> Generalizability of studies may be limited by self-selection bias, or because participants may be inherently more likely to admit use and seek treatment services as well as prenatal care. Alternatively, identification of substance use through self-report may underestimate true prevalence given the stigma associated with substance use in pregnancy.<xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> Extrapolation of findings from studies of screening in ambulatory settings likely do not apply to individuals with SUD who inherently have other barriers to prenatal care.<xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Limited real-world evidence exists to measure success in implementing a universal brief screening tool across all healthcare settings to identify substance use, and whether this practice also identifies SUD in a medically underserved pregnant population.</p><p id="para0018">We report the experience of a single institution following universal implementation of a brief screening tool (NIDA Quick Screen) for self-reported substance use at the first prenatal encounter. Our objectives were to measure rate of implementation across different healthcare settings, characterize NIDA success in identification of SUD, and compare adverse pregnancy outcomes associated with moderate and severe SUD in pregnancy.</p></sec><sec id="sec0005"><title>Materials and methods</title><p id="para0019">This is a prospective implementation study evaluating screening for substance use among pregnant individuals who accessed care in a large safety net healthcare system. Universal screening with the NIDA Quick Screen V1.0 for frequency of past-year use of tobacco, alcohol, illicit drugs, and prescription drugs for nonmedical reasons was integrated into the electronic medical record (EMR) and administered at the first point of contact with the healthcare system beginning July 28, 2021 (<xref rid="sec0015" ref-type="fn">Supplemental Figure</xref>). Although other screening questionnaires have been found to have higher sensitivity and negative predictive values when compared to NIDA,<xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> we chose to use the NIDA screen in our population because we felt it was the most succinct of the screening questionnaires and thus would allow for higher compliance with screening at all of our prenatal care sites. Sites for screening included 10 community-based prenatal clinics known as women's health centers (WHC), a centralized referral Maternal-Fetal Medicine (MFM) clinic with colocated SUD treatment services, and acute care settings including the emergency department (ED) for pregnancies &lt;20 weeks of gestation, and Labor and Delivery Triage (L&amp;D) for pregnancies 20 weeks of gestation or greater.</p><p id="para0020">NIDA was administered by a healthcare educator or provider, with any response other than &#8220;Never&#8221; considered positive for at-risk substance use and followed by a targeted brief intervention and education on risks in pregnancy.<xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> Individuals reporting use of prescription drugs for nonmedical reasons or illegal drugs were either referred to a specialized MFM clinic for individuals with SUD or evaluated immediately in an emergency care setting by a specialized multidisciplinary team known as the Perinatal Intervention Program (PIP). This team functioned throughout the acute care hospital and centralized MFM clinic to provide comprehensive treatment and recovery services during pregnancy and coordinate referrals to SUD programs postpartum. For eligible patients with OUD electing MAT, buprenorphine was prescribed to eligible candidates by the PIP team in both inpatient and ambulatory settings or methadone therapy was initiated inpatient with referral to one of several local methadone clinics for maintenance MAT.</p><p id="para0021">We first measured rate of NIDA implementation at the first pregnancy encounter across our different healthcare sites. Next, we evaluated concordance of NIDA screening positivity with ascertainment of SUD across the healthcare system. SUD was initially identified via documentation of SUD in the EMR by a healthcare provider with formal assessment by our PIP team when available. Toxicology (maternal or neonatal) results corroborating a clinical diagnosis of substance use during pregnancy, and maternal and neonatal ICD-10 codes for SUD (F11.XX for maternal codes, and P96.1, P04.49, or P04.14 for neonates) were used as supplementary sources to identify maternal SUD. Urine toxicology was performed as a diagnostic tool to confirm reported substance use before initiation of MAT, or in workup of suspected intoxication, but was not used as a screening method. Behaviors excluded from the SUD group included medically indicated chronic opioid use, tobacco use (as this is difficult to ascertain retrospectively), intermittent (less than 3 times weekly) cannabis use, and alcohol use that stopped with recognition of pregnancy.</p><p id="para0022">After identification of documented SUD, diagnosis of moderate or severe SUD was identified using criteria established by the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 5th edition (DSM-V).<xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> Moderate SUD was diagnosed when 4 to 5 criteria of the 11 criteria outlined by the DSM-V were met and severe SUD was diagnosed when 6 or more criteria were met. Cannabis use was excluded from this cohort as diagnosis of SUD using the DSM-V criteria retrospectively was difficult. Ultimately, demographic characteristics (including the mean Area Deprivation Index<xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref>), prenatal care, and pregnancy and neonatal outcomes of those patients with moderate and severe SUD were compared to all other patients without SUD that delivered at our institution during this time period. This study was approved by the institutional review board at UT Southwestern in Dallas, Texas.</p><sec id="sec0006"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="para0023">Categorical variables were summarized with frequencies and percentages. Means and standard deviations were reported for normally distributed variables, and median with interquartile ranges were reported for data not normally distributed. Data was analyzed using chi-square for categorical data, Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test for normally distributed continuous data, and Wilcoxon rank-sum test for continuous data not normally distributed. Effect sizes are presented as relative risk (95% confidence interval) for categorical responses, mean difference &#177; standard deviation for normally distributed continuous responses, and Hodges&#8211;Lehmann (95% confidence interval) for continuous responses not assumed as normally distributed. Calculations were performed using SAS version 9.4, SAS Institute (Cary, NC). Statistical significance was indicated by <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;.05. If multiple pregnancies for one patient were identified, the delivery data for the first pregnancy was included in data analysis if all pregnancies were affected by maternal SUD. If only one pregnancy was affected by maternal SUD this was the pregnancy that was included in data analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0007"><title>Results</title><p id="para0024">From July 28, 2021, through June 25, 2022, 14,829 pregnancies occurred among 14,634 unique individuals. Among these, a first encounter occurred in a community-based prenatal clinic for 9221 (63.01%). Across the healthcare system, 12,550 (85.8%) of 14,634 individuals were screened with NIDA. The majority (70.5%) of NIDA screens were completed in the community-based prenatal clinics, where NIDA was completed for 96.2% of individuals attending a first prenatal visit. Rates of implementation of universal screening were less if first access to care occurred in acute care settings, where NIDA screening occurred for 67.8% in the ED and 57.1% for L&amp;D Triage.</p><p id="para0025">Of 14,634 individuals, NIDA was positive for any past-year substance in 2146 (14.7%) (<xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Positive screens included at-risk alcohol use (4 or more drinks per day) in 59%, illegal drugs in 44%, tobacco use in 35%, and prescription drugs for nonmedical reasons in 5%. Of 1269 screens positive for alcohol use, 1043 (82.2%) were positive for infrequent use, defined as monthly or less. Of 950 screens positive for illegal drugs 336 (35.3%) were positive only for cannabis, with 188 of 336 (56%) of these patients with infrequent use (less than 3 times weekly). Most positive screens after further chart review were not found to meet criteria for SUD given frequency of use or use outside of pregnancy that stopped when pregnancy was recognized.<fig id="fig0001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flow diagram of NIDA Screening during first encounter in pregnancy, identification of substance use disorder, and pregnancy outcomes available among individuals accessing care at Parkland Health, July 28, 2021, through June 25, 2022.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0001">Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="celink0001" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/><attrib>White. Implementation of universal screening for substance use in pregnancy. AJOG Glob Rep 2024.</attrib></fig></p><p id="para0026">SUD was identified in 256 (1.7%) of the total cohort. Based on review of DSM-V criteria, 184 (1.3%) patients met criteria for moderate or severe SUD. NIDA screening completion and results varied within this group, with 90 (48.9%) NIDA positive, 22 (12%) NIDA negative, and 72 (39.1%) unscreened (<xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Of the 2108 individuals with positive NIDA screens, 128 (6%) of 2108 were noted to have SUD for reasons alluded to above. Of individuals with moderate and severe SUD who were screened, the majority were screened in the WHC. Discordance in screening was identified for 22 of the 112 (19.6%) NIDA-screened patients identified to have moderate and severe SUD; that is, 22 individuals who screened negative for past-year substance use were identified to have SUD through the other methods described. Of these, 9 (40.9%) had first contact with the health system through an acute or emergent care setting (ED or L&amp;D Triage). Of the 72 unscreened individuals with moderate and severe SUD, 67 (93.1%) had their first and sometimes only contact with our healthcare system in an emergent care setting. Within the moderate and severe SUD population, the most common primarily used drugs were nonprescription opioids (45.1%) followed by methamphetamines (22.8%) and alcohol (13%) (<xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). Of 96 individuals with OUD, 68 (70.8%) were treated with MAT with either buprenorphine or methadone. Of these 96, 56 (58.3%) were screened with NIDA. A total of 43 (76.8%) of 56 NIDA-screened patients with OUD were initiated on MAT during the included index pregnancy.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>NIDA Quick Screen results for any past-year substance use compared with documented moderate to severe SUD in pregnancy</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0003">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1">NIDA screen positive<hr/></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not screened</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate to severe SUD identified<xref rid="tb1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90 (48.9)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (12.0)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72 (39.1)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">184</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2018 (14)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,369 (72.1)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1991 (13.8)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,378</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2108</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,391</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2063</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,562</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="spara004"><p><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> in each column represents total pregnancies per subgroup. Data reported as <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%).</p></fn><fn id="spara005"><p><italic toggle="yes">NIDA</italic>, National Institute on Drug Abuse; <italic toggle="yes">SUD</italic>, substance use disorder.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tb1fn1"><label>a</label><p id="notep0009">SUD identified through medical record review, toxicology results, maternal and neonatal diagnostic codes, and referrals to a specialized addiction medicine team, moderate and severe SUD identified via chart review using DSM-V criteria. Numbers reported here represent moderate and severe SUD.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><attrib>White. Implementation of universal screening for substance use in pregnancy. AJOG Glob Rep 2024.</attrib></table-wrap><fig id="fig0002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Primary drug identified among individuals with illicit moderate and severe SUD in pregnancy (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=184), (regardless of NIDA Quick Screen results), Parkland Health, July 28, 2021, through June 25, 2022.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0002">Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="celink0002" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/><attrib>White. Implementation of universal screening for substance use in pregnancy. AJOG Glob Rep 2024.</attrib></fig></p><p id="para0027">Among 14,634 individuals in the cohort, 10,201 delivered at our institution with available pregnancy outcomes including 94 (51.1%) of 184 with moderate and severe SUD and 10,066 (69.5%) of 14,378 without SUD. Maternal characteristics, delivery, and neonatal outcomes differed for patients with moderate and severe SUD (<xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Compared to those without SUD, individuals with moderate and severe SUD were more likely to be Black, non-Hispanic (16% vs 14%) or White, non-Hispanic (21% vs 3%) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;.001). The mean ADI was higher in the group without SUD although both groups had ADIs in the range of 50 to 60. Individuals with moderate and severe SUD were less likely to have prenatal care (71 (76%) vs 9852 (98%), &lt;0.001) with a lower mean (&#177;SD) number of prenatal visits (5.7 &#177; 4.7 vs 9.8 &#177; 3.7, mean difference 3.9 (3.1, 4.7), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;.001) (<xref rid="tbl0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). After adjusting for race, those with moderate and severe SUD were more likely to experience prelabor rupture of membranes (29 (32%) vs 2208 (22%), RR (95% CI) 1.43 (1.05, 1.93)) and preterm delivery less than 37 weeks (18 (20%) vs 909 (9%), RR (95% CI) 2.09 (1.37, 3.19)). Neonates born to mothers with moderate or severe SUD were more likely to have birth weight less than the 10th percentile (20 (22%) vs 1147 (12%), RR 1.92 (1.29, 2.85)), were twice as likely to be admitted to the NICU (19 (21%) vs 964 (10%), RR 1.95 (1.30, 2.93)) and were more likely to require extended hospitalization (10 days [4, 21] vs 3 days [3, 4], mean difference (Q1, Q3) in days 9 (7, 11)) (<xref rid="tbl0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0002" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Characteristics of delivered individuals with and without identified moderate to severe SUD</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0004">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristic</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate to severe SUD</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No moderate to severe SUD</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Delivered (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,066</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age, y</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.4 &#177; 5.1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.7 &#177; 6.4</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Race and ethnicity</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Black, non-Hispanic</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (16)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1395 (14)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;White, non-Hispanic</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (21)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">306 (3)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hispanic</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58 (62)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8123 (81)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Other</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">242 (2)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nulliparous</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (28)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3046 (30)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.58</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Early pregnancy loss</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (2)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">125 (1)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.44</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stillbirth</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44 (0)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.52</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ADI</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.6&#177;18.9</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.6&#177;16.9</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prenatal care<xref rid="tb2fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71 (76)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9852 (98)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="spara007"><p><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> in each column represents total deliveries per subgroup. Data reported as <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%) and mean +/&#8211; SD as appropriate.</p></fn><fn id="spara008"><p><italic toggle="yes">ADI</italic>, area deprivation index; <italic toggle="yes">SUD</italic>, substance use disorder.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tb2fn1"><label>a</label><p id="notep0013">Prenatal care represents that the patient attended at least one prenatal care visit.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><attrib>White. Implementation of universal screening for substance use in pregnancy. AJOG Glob Rep 2024.</attrib></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0003" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Delivery outcomes among individuals with and <italic toggle="yes">without</italic> identified moderate to severe SUD who delivered live-born infants</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0005">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Outcome</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate to severe SUD <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>=92</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No moderate to severe SUD <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>=9897</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RR (95% CI) or mean difference &#177; SD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nulliparous</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (26)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3007 (30)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.37</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.84 (0.59, 1.18)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prenatal care</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Enrolled in 3rd trimester</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (22)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1102 (11)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.13 (1.47, 3.09)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Number of PNC visits</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.7 &#177; 4.7</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.8 &#177; 3.7</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.9 &#177; 3.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;GA at enrollment</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.3 &#177; 9.1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.7 &#177; 7.9</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.0 &#177; 6.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pregestational diabetes</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">227 (2)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.44</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.50 (0.07, 3.57)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chronic hypertension</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (9)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">548 (6)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.19</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.50 (0.77, 2.92)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prelabor rupture of membranes</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (32)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2208 (22)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.03</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.43 (1.05, 1.93)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chorioamnionitis</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (10)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1039 (10)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.82</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95 (0.51, 1.77)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cesarean delivery</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 (38)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2922 (30)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.07</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.26 (0.97, 1.64)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gestational age at delivery &lt;37 wk</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (20)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">909 (9)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.09 (1.37, 3.19)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PPH (EBL &gt;1000 mL)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (8)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">981 (10)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.46</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.75 (0.35, 1.58)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Transfusion after delivery</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (5)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">523 (5)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.95</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.01 (0.40, 2.41)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="spara010"><p><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> in each column represents total liveborn infants excluding stillbirths and early pregnancy losses. Data reported <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%) or mean &#177; standard deviation (SD) with effect size of mean difference &#177; SD. RR adjusted for difference in race.</p></fn><fn id="spara011"><p><italic toggle="yes">PPH</italic>, postpartum hemorrhage; <italic toggle="yes">SUD</italic>, substance use disorder.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><attrib>White. Implementation of universal screening for substance use in pregnancy. AJOG Glob Rep 2024.</attrib></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0004" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Neonatal outcomes of live-born infants of individuals with and without identified moderate to severe SUD</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0006">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Outcome</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate to severe SUD <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>=132</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No moderate to severe SUD <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>=9897</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RR (95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 min Apgar &lt;4</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (2)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64 (0.6)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.07</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.85 (0.69, 11.75)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Umbilical artery pH &lt;7.0</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (1)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (0.4)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.31</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.84 (0.39, 20.77)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Infant birth weight &lt;10th percentile</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (22)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1147 (12)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.003</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.92 (1.29, 2.85)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Infant ventilator or CPAP, first 24 h</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (3)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">343 (3)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.91</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.90 (0.30, 2.88)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NICU admission</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (21)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">964 (10)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.95 (1.30, 2.93)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Exclusive breastfeeding</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (22)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3844 (42)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.01</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.64 (0.44, 0.94)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Length of stay, d</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 [4, 21]</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 [3, 4]</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.4 (7.4, 11.3)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="spara013"><p><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> in each column represents total liveborn infants, excluding stillbirths and early pregnancy losses. Data reported <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%) or median [interquartile range] with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value from Wilcoxon rank-sum test and effect size as Hodges&#8211;Lehmann mean shift (95% CI). RR adjusted for difference in race.</p></fn><fn id="spara014"><p><italic toggle="yes">CPAP</italic>, continuous positive airway pressure; <italic toggle="yes">NICU</italic>, neonatal intensive care unit; <italic toggle="yes">SUD,</italic> substance use disorder.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><attrib>White. Implementation of universal screening for substance use in pregnancy. AJOG Glob Rep 2024.</attrib></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0008"><title>Comment</title><sec id="sec0009"><title>Principle findings</title><p id="para0028">There were three principal findings. First, universal implementation of the NIDA screen for at-risk substance use had higher rates of implementation in ambulatory prenatal clinics, and less successful in acute or emergent care settings. Second, while NIDA screening identified at-risk substance use in approximately 15% of our prenatal cohort, SUD was identified in 1.7%, with more than half of those with moderate and severe SUD either screening negative or going unscreened, and the majority accessing care through acute or emergent care settings. Finally, neonatal outcomes associated with moderate and severe SUD include prematurity, small for gestational age, NICU admission, and extended hospital stay.</p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><title>Results in the context of what is known</title><p id="para0029">Our prevalence estimates of at-risk substance use based on the NIDA screen are similar to those published by other recent National Surveys.<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> This contrasts to our rate of SUD which is lower than the national rate.<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> This can be explained by differences in the racial and ethnic makeup of our population compared to other areas, differences in methods of diagnosis including use of biologic tests, not used at our institution and underreporting. Our population is primarily Hispanic but SUD has been reported to be more prevalent in White, non-Hispanic, and Black populations.<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref></p><p id="para0030">Underreporting of SUD of up to 60% has been reported when comparing screening tools to documented urine drug screens, especially in cases of cannabis and opioid use.<xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> Stigma associated with SUD in pregnancy, compounded by fear of being reported, likely contributes to underreporting of SUD and lack of prenatal care in this population.<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> For our population specifically, legal ramifications associated with use of recreational cannabis in our state likely also contributed to underreporting. Individuals with SUD and no prenatal care were found in one study to be 12 times more likely to deliver preterm and 14 times more likely to have an infant with low birth weight when compared to individuals without SUD.<xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref></p><p id="para0031">With high rates of street opioid use measured among those with SUD, we are not immune to the recently documented rises in the prevalence of fentanyl in the United States,<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> which demands allocation of considerable resources to fully augment needed treatment and recovery resources, with education of the public and healthcare systems alike. We demonstrated that individuals who were identified to have OUD and were screened with NIDA had a high rate of MAT. This demonstrates, as supported by screening and treatment literature, that screening can identify patients with SUD and thus can aid in connecting them to appropriate treatment.<xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></p></sec><sec id="sec0011"><title>Clinical implications</title><p id="para0032">We demonstrate overall high rates of implementation of a universal screening tool to identify at-risk substance use behaviors, primarily in the ambulatory clinic setting. Our study highlights challenges in implementing universal screening for SUD in a high-volume ED setting, as it is more designed for diagnosis and management of acute intoxication or withdrawal. Just as screening did not take place equally in all healthcare settings, not all healthcare settings were equally accessed by patients with SUD. Lack of prenatal care and thus lack of screening due to different patterns of health care utilization may be contributors to lack of treatment. Although most individuals with SUD went unscreened in the ED, a proportion underwent screening which was negative. Thus, successful implementation of screening and patient comfort with responding honestly about substance use are separate challenges.</p><p id="para0033">Our study was not designed to measure sensitivity and specificity of NIDA screening compared to an objective test, and we continue to avoid universal screening with urine toxicology to reduce fear of punitive reporting and increase attendance to prenatal care. Screening questionnaires such as the NIDA screen reduce bias of providers as it is used universally with all patients and relies on patient self report.<xref rid="bib0034" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> Following implementation across a large safety-net healthcare system, we found that universal screening with brief intervention and targeted referral functions best for ambulatory prenatal settings, and that identification and engagement of pregnant individuals with SUD with treatment and recovery services may require creative solutions in the ED and even outside the traditional healthcare system.</p></sec><sec id="sec0012"><title>Research implications</title><p id="para0034">Further evidence regarding the effect of substance use screening and brief intervention on pregnancy outcomes is needed. The optimal method for engagement of pregnant individuals with SUD in treatment and recovery services as well as prenatal care is unknown and may differ across different communities. While evidence supporting initiation of MAT for OUD in the ED setting is building,<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> additional research is needed to determine whether MAT initiation in the ED in pregnant individuals with OUD is acceptable to providers and improves pregnancy outcomes. Finally, we recognize the need for evidence-based programs focused on measuring impact and interventions aimed at not only those that use substances in pregnancy but also at those who are secondarily affected by substance use (ie surrounding family and friends), which requires social support networks and community-based organizations outside the scope of this work.</p></sec><sec id="sec0013"><title>Strengths and limitations</title><p id="para0035">Strengths of this study include data collection across a large public hospital system with integrated EMR throughout multiple settings. Our study involved review of over 14,000 medical records, most of whom delivered at our hospital and for whom delivery and neonatal outcomes were available. Standardized screening and referral practices across 10 community-based clinics to a centralized MFM clinic with colocated treatment and recovery services by a specialized team will facilitate long-term measurement of outcomes associated with these practices. Finally, gestational age-specific criteria for triage to ED and L&amp;D facilitate pregnancy-specific protocols for future program development.</p><p id="para0036">Limitations of this study include its observational design and lack of a comparative analysis to test a performance of a specific intervention or practice. We did not use a biologic test to validate our diagnosis of SUD. Additionally, we used maternal ICD-10 codes for opioid use for confirmation of SUD diagnosis but did not include ICD-10 codes for other substances. However, we did use neonatal ICD-10 codes that were for exposure to all substances for diagnosis confirmation. Findings may not be generalizable to other healthcare systems and this study may not be reflective of other regions of the country as rates of SUD and population demographics differ. Additionally, screening questionnaires alone may be limited in their ability to identify SUD across all healthcare settings.<xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> We did not compare individuals who were and were not screened in the current study. Brief intervention at the time of screening for patients identified to have at-risk substance use is shown to have a favorable impact on drug abstinence and pregnancy outcomes,<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> but we did not measure the impact of the initial brief intervention in the current study. As well, our study was not designed to measure the effect of MAT on pregnancy outcomes among individuals with OUD nor was it designed to compare outcomes between those with treated and untreated SUD. This study took place during the COVID-19 pandemic which may have contributed to limited or no prenatal care but the effects of the pandemic were not assessed in this study.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0014"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="para0037">Universal implementation of the NIDA Quick Screen successfully identified at-risk substance use in a large urban prenatal system in ambulatory settings but failed to identify 50% of patients with moderate and severe SUD, who were identified primarily through the ED and lacked prenatal care. Significant adverse obstetric and neonatal outcomes are associated with moderate and severe SUD. Future efforts to engage and retain this highest-risk group in treatment and recovery services and prenatal care to improve adverse outcomes are needed.</p></sec><sec id="sec0003a"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="para0015a"><bold>Alesha White:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Writing &#8211; original draft, Visualization, Supervision, Methodology, Investigation, Formal analysis, Data curation, Conceptualization. <bold>Macy Afsari:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Data curation, Conceptualization. <bold>Harini Balakrishnan:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Data curation. <bold>Emilia Chapa:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. <bold>Meredith Kim:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Data curation. <bold>Shubhangi Mehra:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Data curation. <bold>Mary Ann Faucher:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. <bold>Joyce Miller:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. <bold>Polly Cordova:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. <bold>Elaine L. Duryea:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Conceptualization. <bold>David B. Nelson:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Conceptualization. <bold>Anne M. Ambia:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Conceptualization. <bold>Donald D. Mcintire:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Formal analysis, Data curation. <bold>Emily H. Adhikari:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Writing &#8211; original draft, Validation, Supervision, Methodology, Investigation, Formal analysis, Conceptualization.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebibl1"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0001">National Survey on Drug Use and Health&#8212;detailed tables; Table 8.27B, types of illicit drug, tobacco product, and alcohol use in past month: among females aged 15 to 44; by pregnancy status. 2022. Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration. Nov 13, 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0002"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Preeti</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomofohr-Madsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giesbrecht</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagshawe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lebel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol and substance use in pregnancy during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source><volume>225</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">108760</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2021.108760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9758579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34102507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0003"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0003"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trost</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beauregard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><part-title>Pregnancy related deaths: data from maternal mortality review committees in 36 US states, 2017-2019</part-title><year>2022</year><publisher-name>National Center for Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Atlanta, Georgia</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0004"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0004"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Polak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelpin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Terplan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening for substance use in pregnancy and the newborn</article-title><source>Semin Fetal Neonat Med</source><volume>24</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.siny.2019.01.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30770326</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0005"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schempf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strobino</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug use and limited prenatal care: an examination of responsible barriers</article-title><source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source><volume>200</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2009</year><comment>412.e1&#8211;10</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajog.2008.10.055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19217591</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0006"><article-title>American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists' Committee on Obstetric Practice and American Society of Addiction Medicine. Committee opinion 711: opioid use and opiod use disorder in pregnancy</article-title><source>American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists. Obstet Gynecol</source><volume>130</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>e81</fpage><lpage>e94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/AOG.0000000000002235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28742676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0007"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0007"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benneywor</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krans</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McAllister</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neonatal abstinence syndrome and associated health care expenditures</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>307</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>1934</fpage><lpage>1940</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22546608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2012.3951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0008"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0008"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>GBD 2016 Alcohol and Drug Use Collaborators</collab></person-group><article-title>The global burden of disease attributable to alcohol and drug use in 195 countries and territories, 1990-2016: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016</article-title><source>Lancet Psychiatry</source><volume>5</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>987</fpage><lpage>1012</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30392731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2215-0366(18)30337-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6251968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0009"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0009"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>United States Preventive Services Task Force</collab></person-group><part-title>Unhealth drug use: screening</part-title><year>2020</year><publisher-name>USPSTF</publisher-name><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.uspreventiveservicestaskforce.org/uspstf/recommendation/drug-use-illicit-screening#citation2" id="interref0002">https://www.uspreventiveservicestaskforce.org/uspstf/recommendation/drug-use-illicit-screening#citation2</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsakiridis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Substance use during pregnancy: a comparative review of major guidelines</article-title><source>Obstet Gynecol Surv</source><volume>76</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>634</fpage><lpage>643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34724075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/OGX.0000000000000943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0011"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0011"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ewing</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>A practical guide to intervention in health and social services with pregnant and postpartum addicts and alcoholics: theoretical framework, brief screening tool, key interview questions, and strategies for referral to recovery resources</part-title><source>Martinez: the born free project</source><year>1990</year><publisher-name>Contra Costa County Department of Health Services</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0012">National Institute on Drug Abuse. Resource guide: screening for drug use in general medical settings &#8211; NIDA quick screen, Jan 2023. Gaithersburg, Maryland: National Institute on Drug Abuse. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nida.nih.gov/nidamed-medical-health-professionals/screening-tools-resources/chart-screening-tools" id="interref0003">https://nida.nih.gov/nidamed-medical-health-professionals/screening-tools-resources/chart-screening-tools</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0013"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0013"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orav</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buynitsky</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkins-Haug</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-Reported alcohol and drug use in pregnant young women: a pilot study of prevalence and associated factors</article-title><source>J Addict Med</source><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21844837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/ADM.0b013e318214360b</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3157047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0014"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0014"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abuhamad</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Substance use disorders in pregnancy: clinical, ethical, and research imperatives of the opioid epidemic: a report of a joint workshop of the Society for Maternal-Fetal Medicine, American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, and American Society of Addiction Medicine</article-title><source>Am J Obstet Gynecol &#8211; SMFM Spec Rep</source><volume>221</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>B5</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajog.2019.03.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30928567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krist</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mangione</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening for unhealthy drug use: US Preventive Services Task Force recommendation statement</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>323</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>2301</fpage><lpage>2309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32515821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2020.8020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0016"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0016"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman-Cowger</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oga</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trocin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koszowski</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accuracy of three screening tools for prenatal substance use</article-title><source>Obstet Gynecol</source><volume>133</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>952</fpage><lpage>961</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30969217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/AOG.0000000000003230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6485306</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0017"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0017"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gopman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leeman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patient centered care to address barriers for pregnant women with opioid dependence</article-title><source>Obstet Gynecol Clin North Am</source><volume>44</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28160896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ogc.2016.11.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0018"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0018"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>York</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tulman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chalk</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perlman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of personal problems on accessing prenatal care in low-income urban African American Women</article-title><source>J Perinatol</source><volume>19</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10685203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.jp.7200052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0019"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0019"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Funkhouser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Butz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCaul</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prenatal care and drug use in pregnant women</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source><volume>33</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1993</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8396528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0376-8716(93)90027-n</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0020"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourdreaux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A study of antenatal cocaine use-Chaos in action</article-title><source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source><volume>180</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>1427</fpage><lpage>1431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10368482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0002-9378(99)70030-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0021">SBIRT: Screening, Brief intervention &amp; referral to treatment. New York: New York State Office of Addiction Services and Supports. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://oasas.ny.gov/sbirt" id="interref0004">https://oasas.ny.gov/sbirt</ext-link>. Accessed 13 October 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0022"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0022"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>American Psychiatric Association</collab></person-group><part-title>Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders</part-title><edition>5th ed</edition><year>2013</year><publisher-name>American Psychiatric Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0023"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0023"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kind</surname><given-names>AJH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buckingham</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Making neighborhood disadvantage metrics accessible: the neighborhood atlas</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>378</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>2456</fpage><lpage>2458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29949490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMp1802313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6051533</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0024">University of Wisconsin School of Medicine and Public Health. 2021 area deprivation index v4.01. Downloaded from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.neighborhoodatlas.medicine.wisc.edu/" id="interref0005">https://www.neighborhoodatlas.medicine.wisc.edu/</ext-link> 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0025"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wendell</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overview and epidemiology of substance abuse in pregnancy</article-title><source>Clin Obstetric Gynecol</source><volume>56</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.neighborhoodatlas.medicine.wisc.edu/" id="interref0006ar">https://www.neighborhoodatlas.medicine.wisc.edu/</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/GRF.0b013e31827feeb9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23314721</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0026">National Survey on Drug Use and Health-detailed tables; Table 5.4B-drug use disorder in past year: among people aged 12 or older; by age group and demographic characteristics, percentages 2021 and 2022. Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration. Nov 13, 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0027"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0027"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ondersma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Svikis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>LeBreton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development and preliminary validation of an indirect screener for drug use in the perinatal period</article-title><source>Addiction</source><volume>107</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>2099</fpage><lpage>2106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22882721</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1360-0443.2012.03982.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3499681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0028"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0028"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrison</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leeman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Validity of self-reported drug use information among pregnant women</article-title><source>Matern Child Health J</source><volume>20</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10995-015-1799-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4713294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26175273</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0029"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0029"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Mohandes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Khorazaty</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grylack</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prenatal care reduces the impact of illicit drug use on perinatal outcomes</article-title><source>J Perinatol</source><volume>23</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>354</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12847528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.jp.7210933</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0030"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glicksberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dempsey</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heroin and fentanyl in Dallas County: a 5-year retrospective review of toxicological, seized drug, and demographical data</article-title><source>J Forensic Sci</source><volume>68</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36303261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/1556-4029.15155</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0031"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0031"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Terplan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ondersma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of screening, brief intervention, and referral to treatment in the perinatal period</article-title><source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source><volume>215</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27373599</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajog.2016.06.038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11362984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0032"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0032"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McNamara</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orav</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Brief intervention for prenatal alcohol use: a randomized trial</article-title><source>Obstet Gynecol</source><volume>105</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>991</fpage><lpage>998</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15863535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/01.AOG.0000157109.05453.84</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1380262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0033"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0033"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Montag</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brodine</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alcaraz</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Preventing alcohol-exposed pregnancy among an American Indian/Alaska Native population: effect of a screening, brief intervention, and referral to treatment intervention</article-title><source>Alcohol Clin Exp Res</source><volume>39</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25623412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/acer.12607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0034"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0034"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olaniyan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jarlenski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Racial inequities in drug tests ordered by clinicians for pregnant people who disclose prenatal substance use</article-title><source>Obstet Gynecol</source><volume>142</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>1169</fpage><lpage>1178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37769307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/AOG.0000000000005385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0035">Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration: Use of Medication-Assisted Treatment in Emergency Departments. HHS Publication No. PEP21-PL-Guide-5 Rockville, MD: National Mental Health and Substance Use Policy Laboratory. Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://store.samhsa.gov/sites/default/files/pep21-pl-guide-5.pdf" id="interref0006">https://store.samhsa.gov/sites/default/files/pep21-pl-guide-5.pdf</ext-link> 2021.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="sec0016" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix</label><title>Supplementary materials</title><p id="para0038a">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ecom0001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Image, application 1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="d36e586"><p id="notep0001">Patient consent is not required because no personal information or details are included.</p></fn><fn id="d36e589"><p id="notep0002">Paper Presentation Information: Presented as a poster at the 43rd Annual Pregnancy Meeting, SMFM, San Francisco, California, February 6 to 11, 2023.</p></fn><fn id="d36e592"><p id="notep0003">Condensation/Tweetable Statement: Universal screening for self-reported substance use identified at-risk substance use in approximately half of individuals with substance use disorders in ambulatory over acute care settings.</p></fn><fn id="d36e595"><p id="notep0004">Funding: None.</p></fn><fn id="d36e598"><p id="notep0005">The authors report no conflict of interest.</p></fn><fn id="sec0015" fn-type="supplementary-material"><p id="para0010a">Supplementary material associated with this article can be found in the online version at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.xagr.2024.100384" id="interref0001">doi:10.1016/j.xagr.2024.100384</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>