<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol X</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol X</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3702</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">eurox</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>European Journal of Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology and Reproductive Biology: X</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2590-1613</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11872443</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11872443.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11872443</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11872443</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40027876</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eurox.2025.100374</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2590-1613(25)00010-9</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100374</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Obstetrics and Maternal Fetal Medicine</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Decreasing trend of gastroschisis prevalence in the United States from 2014 through 2022: Is attributed to declining birth rates in young, high-risk gravidae</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mustafa</surname><given-names initials="HJ">Hiba J.</given-names></name><email>hmustafa@iu.edu</email><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#8270;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zargarzadeh</surname><given-names initials="N">Nikan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0015"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moss</surname><given-names initials="KL">Kevin L.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0020"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abiad</surname><given-names initials="M">May</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0025"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names initials="B">Brian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0020" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0030"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aagaard</surname><given-names initials="KM">Kjersti M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff0025" ref-type="aff">e</xref><xref rid="aff0040" ref-type="aff">h</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0035"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchmiller</surname><given-names initials="TL">Terry L.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0030" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0040"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perrone</surname><given-names initials="EE">Erin E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0035" ref-type="aff">g</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0045"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shamshirsaz</surname><given-names initials="AA">Alireza A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0005"><label>a</label>Riley Children&#8217;s and Indiana University Health Fetal Center, Division of Maternal-Fetal Medicine, Riley Children&#8217;s Hospital, Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, IN, USA</aff><aff id="aff0010"><label>b</label>Fetal Care &amp; Surgery Center (FCSC), Division of Fetal Medicine and Surgery, Boston Children's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA</aff><aff id="aff0015"><label>c</label>Department of Biostatistics and Health Data Science, Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, IN, USA</aff><aff id="aff0020"><label>d</label>Department of Pediatric Surgery, Riley Children&#8217;s Hospital, Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, IN, USA</aff><aff id="aff0025"><label>e</label>HCA Healthcare and HCA Healthcare Research Institute, Nashville, TN, USA</aff><aff id="aff0030"><label>f</label>Department of Pediatric Surgery, Boston Children's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA</aff><aff id="aff0035"><label>g</label>Department of Surgery, Section of Pediatric Surgery, University of Michigan, C.S Mott&#8217;s Children&#8217;s Hospital, Ann Arbor, MI, USA</aff><aff id="aff0040"><label>h</label>HCA Texas Maternal Fetal Medicine, Houston, TX, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#8270;</label>Correspondence to: Riley Children&#8217;s and Indiana University Health Fetal Center, Division of Maternal-Fetal Medicine, Riley Children&#8217;s Hospital, Indiana University School of Medicine, 570 Riley Hospital Dr., Indianapolis, IN 46202, USA. <email>hmustafa@iu.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">479577</issue-id><elocation-id>100374</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>12</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>02</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-03-05 16:25:32.100"><day>05</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2025 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="ab0010"><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>To investigate the prevalence trend of gastroschisis in the United States between 2014 and 2022.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>A cross-sectional retrospective analysis of the Centers for the United States live births between 2014 and 2022. Pregnancies and neonatal singleton live births with documented isolated gastroschisis were included. Neonates with other major congenital anomalies and known chromosomal abnormalities were excluded. Prevalence per 10,000 live births along with 95&#8239;% confidence intervals was estimated.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Among 32,088,301 singleton live births, 6804 cases of isolated gastroschisis were identified (Point prevalence: 2 in 10,000 live births). A significant decline in gastroschisis prevalence was observed, decreasing from 2.86 per 10,000 live births in 2014&#8211;1.55 per 10,000 live births in 2022 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.001). The risk of gastroschisis was significantly higher in teen and nulliparous gravidae, with prepregnancy tobacco use, and among socially vulnerable populations (underweight, &lt; 12th-grade education, Medicaid, non-Hispanic Indigenous Americans). The drop in gastroschisis births from 2014 to 2022, compared to non-gastroschisis births, is more significant in maternal age &lt;&#8239;20 years, nulliparous, BMI &lt;&#8239;18.5, and in smokers prior to pregnancy than in the overall population (P&#8239;=&#8239;0.02, 0.0008, &lt;0.0001, &lt;0.0001, and 0.01 respectively). All of the associated maternal factors had a significant decline in prevalence (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.001), which may influence the decreasing trend of gastroschisis. There was no perceived considerable impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on gastroschisis trends.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>The study highlights a notable decline in gastroschisis prevalence mostly attributable to a declining birth rate in the highest at-risk strata, suggesting recent increases in birth rates among these at-risk gravidae may reverse the trend of declining gastroschisis disease prevalence. These findings support the need for ongoing further research to understand effective means of sustaining this decreasing trend.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="ab0015"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="li0005"><list-item id="u0005"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0005">While past studies showed rising gastroschisis trends, this US study (2014&#8211;2022) found a significant decline in prevalence.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0010"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0010">The declining trend was not due to COVID-19&#8217;s impact on gastroschisis but correlated with pregnancy rates among high-risk groups.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0015">Recalibrating risk factors and identifying trends can help develop targeted prevention, especially for vulnerable and young gravidae.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0020"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0020">The findings can help physicians address the modifiable risk factors for gastroschisis, such as nutrition, smoking, and healthcare access.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0025"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0025">This study supports public health research on gastroschisis etiology and prevention, guiding future research and trials.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><kwd-group id="keys0005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Gastroschisis</kwd><kwd>Birth prevalence</kwd><kwd>Abdominal wall defect</kwd><kwd>Trends</kwd><kwd>Cross-sectional study</kwd><kwd>CDC</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec0005"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0030">During the 1990s and 2000s, there was a notable rise in the point prevalence of gastroschisis, which underscored the urgent need for research into the underlying causes, and effective treatment and management strategies <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Specifically, based on Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) data, from 1995 to 2012, the prevalence of gastroschisis increased based on, rising from 3.6 to 4.9 per 10,000 live births, with similar trends observed in data from 15 states showing an increase from 2.32 to 4.42 per 10,000 live births during 1995&#8211;2005 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>.</p><p id="p0035">The association between young maternal age (e.g., under age 20, or &#8220;teen pregnancy&#8221;) and gastroschisis, first described in 1977 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, has been consistently documented <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Epidemiologic patterns suggest that health care disparities disproportionately experienced by teen gravidae (incomplete education, Medicaid insurance, poor nutrition, underweight BMI, tobacco and alcohol exposures, and race) may play a role <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Additionally, several studies suggested an association between genitourinary infections and fetal gastroschisis <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>.</p><p id="p0040">Historically, identifying potential risk factors for gastroschisis has been a critical public health objective to devise effective prevention strategies and mitigate its prevalence and health impacts <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. Moreover, understanding the factors contributing to change in its prevalence is crucial and could establish a predictive framework for managing this condition proactively. Our study aimed to identify factors associated with recently declining trends in the prevalence of gastroschisis using CDC data, to identify attributable factors and persistently at-risk populations with the overarching goal of recalibrating the algorithm of risk factors influencing prevalence patterns, understanding gastroschisis etiology, and informing prevention strategies.</p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><title>Methods and materials</title><sec id="sec0015"><title>Study design</title><p id="p0045">We performed a cross-sectional population study utilizing the natality dataset of the National Center for Health Statistics and Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) from January 1st, 2014 to December 31st, 2022. The natality dataset includes paternal, maternal, prenatal, labor, and obstetric characteristics. The information is derived from the national birth registry and uses the US Standard Certificate for live birth. This certificate is completed for every newborn upon delivery. This study was considered exempt from oversight by the IRB given that data were de-identified.</p></sec><sec id="sec0020"><title>Definition of variables</title><p id="p0050">The following prenatal characteristics around the time of conception were included from the CDC dataset: year of birth, maternal age, nativity (born in/outside of the U.S.), race (Non-Hispanic (NH) White, NH Black, NH Asian, Hispanic, and others)<italic toggle="yes"><bold>,</bold></italic> education, insurance, cigarette smoking before pregnancy and during the first trimester, parity, interval since last pregnancy, pre-pregnancy body mass index (BMI), pre-pregnancy diabetes mellitus (DM), and pre-pregnancy hypertension (HTN). The CDC-Natality datasets record weight at two intervals: once before pregnancy and once before delivery. Height is also recorded for each mother before pregnancy. Hence, pre-pregnancy BMI was calculated for each record. A detailed guide on the definition of each variable for all the included years can be seen in the vital statistics online data portal (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data_access/vitalstatsonline.htm" id="ir0005">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data_access/vitalstatsonline.htm</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="sec0025"><title>Inclusion and exclusion</title><p id="p0055">We included singleton live births with confirmed isolated fetal and/or neonatal gastroschisis. We excluded pregnancies with twins or higher-order multiple gestations, other major structural anomalies or chromosomal abnormalities, if gastroschisis status was unknown or not stated, and if there were missing data for one of the above-stated prenatal characteristics. Furthermore, the cohort was divided into cases to include patients with gastroschisis and controls to include those without gastroschisis.</p></sec><sec id="sec0030"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0060">Frequency distributions, prevalence per 10,000 live births along with 95&#8239;% confidence intervals were estimated. Logistic regression and multivariate logistic regression models were to calculate relative risk and 95&#8239;% confidence intervals in two models i)a minimally adjusted model to covariates known through previous studies to be associated with gastroschisis including age, smoking, BMI, and parity, and ii) a fully adjusted model to all the covariates in the univariate analysis. To explore the effect of COVID on the declining rate of gastroschisis we chose the 34 months before and after February 2020. We performed a linear regression model using the monthly rate of gastroschisis as the outcome and time, and indicator for pre and post-COVID and interaction of time and pre/post-COVID. The interaction tested the slope of decline in gastroschisis pre and post-COVID. Slope interaction was also tested between gastroschisis and non-gastroschisis in the high-risk groups. Statistical analysis was performed using SAS (Version 9.4; SAS Institute).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0035"><title>Results</title><p id="p0065">Following exclusion, we identified 32,088,301 singleton live births, among which 6804 (0.02&#8239;%) were pregnancies with isolated gastroschisis during the study period from 2014 to 2022 (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). The overall prevalence of gastroschisis in the population during this eight-year study period was 2.19 per 10,000 live births. A declining trend in the prevalence of gastroschisis was observed over the study period with the year-by-year analysis showing a significant decline from 2.86 per 10,000 births in 2014 to 1.55 per 10,000 in 2022 (<xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<fig id="fig0005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Population flowchart.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0005">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk0005" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0005" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Prevalence (95&#8239;% Confidence Interval) of Gastroschisis per 10,000 by Selected Demographics for 2014&#8211;2022.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0025">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Total</bold></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>N / Total N</bold><break/><bold>6804 / 31,088,301</bold></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Prevalence</bold><break/><bold>(95&#8239;% Confidence</bold><break/><bold>Interval)</bold><break/><bold>2.19 (2.14&#8211;2.24)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Race/Ethnicity</bold><break/>Non-Hispanic White<break/>Non-Hispanic Black<break/>Non-Hispanic AIAN<break/>Non-Hispanic Asian<break/>Non-Hispanic NHOPI<break/>Non-Hispanic more than one race<break/>Hispanic<break/>Origin unknown or not stated</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3835 / 16,214,961<break/>631 / 4374,234<break/>144 / 239,124<break/>122 / 1928,315<break/>12 / 71,934<break/>243 / 677,614<break/>1790 / 7466,387<break/>27 / 115,732</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.37 (2.29&#8211;2.44)<break/>1.44 (1.33&#8211;1.56)<break/>6.02 (5.08&#8211;7.09)<break/>0.63 (0.53&#8211;0.76)<break/>1.67 (0.86&#8211;2.92)<break/>3.59 (3.15&#8211;4.07)<break/>2.40 (2.29&#8211;2.51)<break/>2.33 (1.54&#8211;3.39)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Maternal Nativity</bold><break/>Born in U.S. (50 US States)<break/>Born outside U.S.</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6120 / 24,175,402<break/>684 / 6912,899</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.53 (2.47&#8211;2.60)<break/>0.99 (0.92&#8211;1.07)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Maternal Age</bold><break/>15-&lt;&#8239;20<break/>20-&lt;&#8239;25<break/>25-&lt;&#8239;30<break/>30-&lt;&#8239;35<break/>35-&lt;&#8239;40<break/>40&#8239;+</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1356 / 1568,959<break/>2870 / 6141,227<break/>1647 / 8957,063<break/>667 / 8917,239<break/>233 / 4499,441<break/>31 / 1004,372</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.64 (8.19&#8211;9.12)<break/>4.67 (4.50&#8211;4.85)<break/>1.84 (1.75&#8211;1.93)<break/>0.75 (0.69&#8211;0.81)<break/>0.52 (0.45&#8211;0.59)<break/>0.31 (0.21&#8211;0.44)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>BMI Category</bold><break/>Underweight (BMI &lt; 18.5)<break/>Normal weight (BMI 18.5-&lt;25)<break/>Overweight (BMI 25-&lt;30)<break/>Obese Class I (BMI 30-&lt;35)<break/>Obese Class II (BMI 35-&lt;40)<break/>Obese Class III (BMI &gt;=40)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">419 / 998,253<break/>3812 / 13,144,532<break/>1724 / 8265,407<break/>600 / 4702,518<break/>163 / 2321,044<break/>86 / 1656,547</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.20 (3.81&#8211;4.62)<break/>2.90 (2.81&#8211;2.99)<break/>2.09 (1.99&#8211;2.19)<break/>1.28 (1.18&#8211;1.38)<break/>0.70 (0.60&#8211;0.82)<break/>0.52 (0.42&#8211;0.64)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Pre-Pregnancy Hypertension</bold>, Yes<break/>No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">75 / 650,868<break/>6729 / 30,437,433</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.15 (0.91&#8211;1.44)<break/>2.21 (2.16&#8211;2.26)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Pre-Pregnancy Diabetes</bold>, Yes<break/>No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">38 / 293,268<break/>6766 / 30,795,033</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.30 (0.92&#8211;1.78)<break/>2.20 (2.15&#8211;2.25)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Pre-Pregnancy Cigarette Smoking</bold>, Yes<break/>No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1346 / 2543,971<break/>5458 / 28,544,330</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.29 (5.01&#8211;5.58)<break/>1.91 (1.86&#8211;1.96)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1</bold><sup><bold>st</bold></sup><bold>Trimester Cigarette Smoking,</bold> Yes<break/>No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1025 / 1913,963<break/>5779 / 29,174,963</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.36 (5.03&#8211;5.69)<break/>1.98 (1.93&#8211;2.03)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Insurance</bold><break/>Medicaid<break/>Private Insurance<break/>Self-Pay<break/>Other</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4275 / 13,119,764<break/>2103 / 15,504,333<break/>167 / 1291,770<break/>259 / 1172,434</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3<break/>.26 (3.16&#8211;3.36)<break/>1.36 (1.30&#8211;1.42)<break/>1.29 (1.10&#8211;1.50)<break/>2.21 (1.95&#8211;2.50)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Education</bold><break/>&lt;&#8239;High School Grad<break/>&gt;&#8239;=High School Grad</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1311 / 3972,751<break/>5493 / 27,115,550</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.30 (3.12&#8211;3.48)<break/>2.03 (1.97&#8211;2.08)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Interpregnancy Interval for multiparous</bold><break/>&lt;&#8239;18&#8239;m<break/>18&#8211;23&#8239;m<break/>24&#8239;m+<break/>Unknown</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">758 / 3392,656<break/>385 / 2535,302<break/>1606 / 11,837,817<break/>775 / 3396,690</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.23 (2.08&#8211;2.40)<break/>1.52 (1.37&#8211;1.68)<break/>1.36 (1.29&#8211;1.42)<break/>2.28 (2.12&#8211;2.45)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Parity</bold><break/>Nulliparous<break/>Multiparous</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3280 / 9925,836<break/>3524 / 21,162,465</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.30 (3.19&#8211;3.42)<break/>1.67 (1.61&#8211;1.72)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Season of Conception</bold><break/>Spring<break/>Summer<break/>Fall<break/>Winter</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2027 / 8345,177<break/>1699 / 7641,814<break/>1402 / 7319,781<break/>1675 / 7770,437</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.43 (2.32&#8211;2.54)<break/>2.22 (2.12&#8211;2.33)<break/>1.91 (1.82&#8211;2.02)<break/>2.16 (2.05&#8211;2.26)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Year of Birth</bold><break/>2014<break/>2015<break/>2016<break/>2017<break/>2018<break/>2019<break/>2020<break/>2021<break/>2022</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">975 / 3403,656<break/>955 / 3539,061<break/>823 / 3601,595<break/>818 / 3538,414<break/>715 / 3490,951<break/>738 / 3443,495<break/>647 / 3335,518<break/>612 / 3372,689<break/>521 / 3362,922</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.86 (2.69&#8211;3.05)<break/>2.70 (2.53&#8211;2.88)<break/>2.29 (2.13&#8211;2.45)<break/>2.31 (2.16&#8211;2.48)<break/>2.05 (1.90&#8211;2.20)<break/>2.14 (1.99&#8211;2.30)<break/>1.94 (1.79&#8211;2.10)<break/>1.81 (1.67&#8211;1.96)<break/>1.55 (1.42&#8211;1.69)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>AIAN: American Indiana Alaska Native, NHOPI: Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander, BMI: body mass index</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0070">The prevalence of gastroschisis was highest among non-Hispanic American Indigenous populations (6.02 per 10,000), those born in the US (2.53 per 10,000), maternal age &lt;&#8201;20 years (8.64 per 10,000), pre-pregnancy underweight BMI group (4.20 per 10,000), pre-pregnancy cigarette smoking (5.29 per 10,000), Medicaid recipients (3.26 per 10,000), and among nulliparous as compared to multiparous gravidae (3.30 per 10,000 vs. 1.67 per 10,000), among gravidae with a short interpregnancy interval &lt;&#8201;18 months (2.23 per 10,000), less than high school education (3.3 per 10,000), and more common among pregnancies conceived in the North American spring (2.43 per 10,000) (<xref rid="tbl0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0010" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Relative Risk (95&#8201;% Confidence Interval) for Gastroschisis.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0030">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Crude</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Minimally Adjusted</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fully Adjusted</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Year of Birth</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.93 (0.93&#8211;0.94)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.98 (0.97&#8211;0.99)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97 (0.96&#8211;0.98)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.84 (0.84&#8211;0.85)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86 (0.85&#8211;0.86)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86 (0.86&#8211;0.87)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Nulliparous</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.98 (1.89&#8211;2.08)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.07 (1.02&#8211;1.13)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.11 (1.05&#8211;1.17)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>BMI</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.92 (0.92&#8211;0.93)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94 (0.94&#8211;0.94)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94 (0.93&#8211;0.94)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Smoke Before Pregnancy</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.76 (2.61&#8211;2.94)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.02 (1.80&#8211;2.26)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.73 (1.55&#8211;1.94)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Smoke 1</bold><sup><bold>st</bold></sup><bold>Trimester</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.70 (2.53&#8211;2.89)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.11 (0.98&#8211;1.26)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.07 (0.94&#8211;1.21)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Non-Hispanic White (only)</bold><break/><bold>Non-Hispanic Black (only)</bold><break/><bold>Non-Hispanic AIAN (only)</bold><break/><bold>Non-Hispanic Asian (only)</bold><break/><bold>Non-Hispanic NHOPI (only)</bold><break/><bold>Non-Hispanic more than one race</bold><break/><bold>Hispanic</bold><break/><bold>Origin unknown or not stated</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref<break/>0.61 (0.56&#8211;0.66)<break/>2.55 (2.16&#8211;3.01)<break/>0.27 (0.22&#8211;0.32)<break/>0.71 (0.40&#8211;1.24)<break/>1.52 (1.33&#8211;1.73)<break/>1.01 (0.96&#8211;1.07)<break/>0.99 (0.68&#8211;1.44)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref<break/>0.50 (0.46&#8211;0.55)<break/>1.76 (1.49&#8211;2.08)<break/>0.61 (0.50&#8211;0.74)<break/>0.97 (0.55&#8211;1.71)<break/>1.13 (0.99&#8211;1.28)<break/>1.04 (0.97&#8211;1.10)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Born Outside U.S.</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.39 (0.36&#8211;0.42)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.57 (0.52&#8211;0.62)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Less than High School Education</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.63 (1.53&#8211;1.73)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.80 (0.75&#8211;0.85)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Private Insurance</bold><break/><bold>Medicaid</bold><break/><bold>Self-Pay</bold><break/><bold>Other</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref<break/>2.40 (2.28&#8211;2.53)<break/>0.95 (0.81&#8211;1.12)<break/>1.63 (1.43&#8211;1.85)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref<break/>1.43 (1.35&#8211;1.52)<break/>0.89 (0.75&#8211;1.04)<break/>1.10 (0.97&#8211;1.26)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Pre-pregnancy hypertension</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.52 (0.42&#8211;0.65)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.13 (0.90&#8211;1.42)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Pre-pregnancy diabetes</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.59 (0.43&#8211;0.81)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.07 (0.77&#8211;1.47)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>AIAN: American Indiana Alaska Native, NHOPI: Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander, BMI: body mass index</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0075">When adjusting for all the previously mentioned factors in the minimally and the fully adjusted models described in the methods, the risk of gastroschisis still exhibited a significant decreasing trend across all models, with RR of 0.97 in the fully adjusted model (<xref rid="tbl0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> shows the annual prevalence of gastroschisis per 10,000 live births over the study period (2014&#8211;2022), respectively.<fig id="fig0010" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Annual Prevalence per 10,000 births of Gastroschisis from 2014 to 2022.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0010">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk0010" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0080">To understand the etiology behind the decreasing trend of gastroschisis, we investigated the temporal trends by year in demographic characteristics in patients with pregnancies complicated by gastroschisis. There was a significant decrease in the proportion of pregnancies occurring among gravidae &lt;&#8201;20 years of age, underweight, and with pre-pregnancy cigarette smoking over the study period (<xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). <xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> shows the graphical demonstration of the annual prevalence of gastroschisis per 10,000 births by maternal age, BMI, parity, and pre-pregnancy smoking.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0015" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Rates of Selected Demographics by Year.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0035">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2014&#8211;2016</bold></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2017&#8211;2019</bold></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2020&#8211;2022</bold></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>P-value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Race/Ethnicity</bold><break/>Non-Hispanic White (only)<break/>Non-Hispanic Black (only)<break/>Non-Hispanic AIAN (only)<break/>Non-Hispanic Asian (only)<break/>Non-Hispanic NHOPI (only)<break/>Non-Hispanic more than one race<break/>Hispanic<break/>Origin unknown or not stated</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.1<break/>13.8<break/>0.8<break/>6.1<break/>0.2<break/>2.0<break/>23.6<break/>0.4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.9<break/>14.3<break/>0.8<break/>6.5<break/>0.2<break/>2.2<break/>23.8<break/>0.4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.4<break/>14.1<break/>0.7<break/>6.0<break/>0.3<break/>2.4<break/>24.8<break/>0.4</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Maternal Nativity</bold><break/>Born in U.S.<break/>Born outside U.S.</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.8<break/>22.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.3<break/>22.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">78.2<break/>21.8</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Maternal Age</bold><break/>15-&lt;&#8201;20<break/>20-&lt;&#8201;25<break/>25-&lt;&#8201;30<break/>30-&lt;&#8201;35<break/>35-&lt;&#8201;40<break/>40&#8201;+</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.0<break/>21.7<break/>29.2<break/>27.3<break/>12.9<break/>2.9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.9<break/>19.5<break/>29.1<break/>28.6<break/>14.6<break/>3.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.2<break/>18.0<break/>28.1<break/>30.1<break/>15.9<break/>3.6</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Mean(SD) Age, Years</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.3</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>BMI Category</bold><break/>Underweight (BMI &lt; 18.5)<break/>Normal weight (BMI 18.5-&lt;25)<break/>Overweight (BMI 25-&lt;30)<break/>Obese Class I (BMI 30-&lt;35)<break/>Obese Class II (BMI 35-&lt;40)<break/>Obese Class III (BMI &gt;=40)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.7<break/>45.2<break/>25.8<break/>13.9<break/>6.7<break/>4.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.2<break/>42.3<break/>26.6<break/>15.1<break/>7.5<break/>5.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.7<break/>39.2<break/>27.4<break/>16.4<break/>8.3<break/>6.0</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Mean(SD), BMI</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.6</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Pre-Pregnancy Hypertension,</bold> Yes<break/>No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6<break/>98.4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0<break/>98.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.7<break/>97.3</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Pre-Pregnancy Diabetes,</bold> Yes<break/>No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8<break/>99.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9<break/>99.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.1<break/>98.9</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Pre-Pregnancy Smoker,</bold> Yes<break/>No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.2<break/>89.8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.4<break/>91.6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.8<break/>94.2</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1</bold><sup><bold>st</bold></sup><bold>Trimester Smoker,</bold> Yes<break/>No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.6<break/>92.4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.3<break/>93.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.5<break/>95.5</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Insurance</bold><break/>Medicaid<break/>Private Insurance<break/>Self-Pay<break/>Other</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.1<break/>48.6<break/>4.2<break/>4.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.3<break/>49.7<break/>4.3<break/>3.8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.2<break/>51.4<break/>4.0<break/>3.4</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Education</bold><break/>&lt;&#8201;High School Grad<break/>&gt;&#8201;=High School Grad</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.4<break/>85.6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.6<break/>87.4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.2<break/>88.8</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Interpregnancy Interval</bold><break/>&lt;&#8201;18&#8201;m<break/>18&#8211;23&#8201;m<break/>24&#8201;m+<break/>Unknown</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.5<break/>8.0<break/>37.8<break/>11.4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.9<break/>8.1<break/>38.3<break/>11.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.5<break/>8.4<break/>38.1<break/>10.1</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Parity</bold><break/>Nulliparous<break/>Multiparous</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.3<break/>67.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.5<break/>68.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.0<break/>68.0</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>AIAN: American Indiana Alaska Native, NHOPI: Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander, BMI: body mass index</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig0015" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Graphical demonstration of the annual Prevalence per 10,000 Births of Gastroschisis from 2014 to 2022 by (a) Maternal Age Group, (b) Body Mass Index Category, (c) Parity, and (d) Smoking Status Before Pregnancy.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0015">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk0015" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0085">The decline in gastroschisis births from 2014 to 2022, compared to non-gastroschisis births, was significantly more common in nulliparous, underweight (BMI&lt;18.5), young gravidae (&lt;age 20), relative to the overall gravid population (<xref rid="fig0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>a-d). These trends are further confirmed by a significant interaction between the slopes of the two trends, suggesting that the observed reduction in gastroschisis cases is not simply a reflection of a general decrease in birth rates but is associated with a specific, significant, and unique decline in births among these higher-risk groups. Finally, the rate and trend of gastroschisis did not significantly change between pre-and post-COVID-19 cohorts; notably, in the interval since COVID-19, legislative actions which have resulted in access to reproductive care have also occurred and may lend to the trend in recent increases in gastroschisis previously attributed by others to COVID-19 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>.<fig id="fig0020" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Numbers of births trend of gastroschisis and non-gastroschisis births for (a) Nulliparity, (b) Maternal Age &lt;&#8201;20, (c) BMI &lt;&#8201;18.5, and (d) Smoking Prior to Pregnancy.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0020">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="lk0020" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec0040"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="sec0045"><title>Principal findings</title><p id="p0090">Our study identified a significant decline in gastroschisis prevalence in a nationwide cohort including over 32 million singleton live births in the US from 2014 to 2022. Notably, this decline correlates with decreases in pregnancy rates among high-risk groups such as individuals under 20 years, those classified as underweight, nulliparous, and smokers.</p></sec><sec id="sec0050"><title>Result in the context of what is known</title><p id="p0095">Several studies have established a link between gastroschisis and several risk factors including white and Hispanic race <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, low maternal age <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, abnormal BMI <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> (mostly low BMI <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>), cigarette smoking history <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, nulliparity<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, low interpregnancy interval <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, and conception in the spring <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Our findings align with this literature, adding a temporal dimension that suggests an effective reduction in these risk factors over time. The declining rate of gastroschisis can be paralleled by the nationwide decline in the maternal age under 25 years <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. However, the significant decline in gastroschisis cases among higher-risk individuals compared to the general population suggests that targeted improvements in reducing risk factors specific to these groups may be effective <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. Additionally, similar to our findings, Medicaid recipients, representing low socioeconomic groups, have been shown to have a higher rate of gastroschisis and worse infant&#8217; outcomes <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. Individuals on Medicaid may have limited access to high-quality prenatal care, which can impact early pregnancy health and the management of risk factors known to be associated with gastroschisis, such as nutritional deficiencies and exposure to harmful substances. Lifestyle patterns and environmental habits affecting the teenage population have also been shown to play a role in the association of young age with gastroschisis <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. It has been suggested that state cigarette taxes are an influential intervention in reducing the rate of cigarette use and therefore, the risk of gastroschisis <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. Prepregnancy diet and nutrient stores suggested an influence on the etiology of gastroschisis <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, potentially explaining the effects related to interpregnancy interval and BMI. National data supported our findings on the trend of decreasing major risk factors for gastroschisis; the maternal age has increased in recent years <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, prepregnancy obesity has risen <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, leading to a decrease in low BMI at pregnancy, and the rate of cigarette smoking during pregnancy has declined in the US <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. In addition, other studies reinforced the lack of relevance of COVID-19 to this decreasing trend in gastroschisis <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec0055"><title>Clinical and research implications</title><p id="p0100">One interpretation of our findings may be to lessen the urgency for public health research to address the high incidence of gastroschisis, which peaked prior to 2010 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. However, our data also notes that the population at highest risk includes young and vulnerable individuals, and occurs in parallel to birth rates within this population <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. Given that these same young and vulnerable populations may rely on public resources for contraception care and availability of reproductive health care, any state, local, or federal laws that limit that access would be anticipated to lead to increased occurrence of gastroschisis. Ongoing surveillance is essential to identify these factors, inform public health interventions, and mitigate prevalence.</p></sec><sec id="sec0060"><title>Strengths and limitations</title><p id="p0105">Utilizing national data allowed us to conduct the prevalence trend analysis over a long period. Our subgroup analysis enhances understanding of the associated factors. Limitations are related to utilizing birth certificates to detect gastroschisis occurrences in the United States, which could be subject to collection inaccuracies. The natality dataset includes only live births which could affect true prevalence due to lack of data on pregnancy losses, terminations, and fetal demises. However, that is unanimous over the included years, and the study aimed to track trends rather than period prevalence. Additionally, causality could not be determined from the CDC database due to its cross-sectional design. It is also important to consider variations at more localized levels, which necessitates prospective studies. Furthermore, state-level healthcare policies and variations in data collection practices could influence the reported trends, but these factors could not be analyzed due to the lack of state-specific and policy-related data in the CDC dataset.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0065"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0110">Up through 2010, there was an exponential increase in the prevalence of gastroschisis. Our current study is the first to provide an in-depth characterization of a significant decline in gastroschisis prevalence among singleton live births in the US from 2014 through 2022. This decline is attributable to overall birth rate declines in the at-risk population of young/teen gravidae, those who are underweight, and among gravidae who smoke prior to pregnancy. Given recent legislative actions that limit or eliminate reproductive health care access disproportionately, we anticipate the absolute need for continued public health efforts focused on remediating reproductive health care disparities among this population. Future studies should focus on identifying and monitoring potential unidentified risk factors to prevent future peaks in gastroschisis prevalence.</p></sec><sec id="sec0070"><title>Funding</title><p id="p0115">No external funding has been received for this study.</p></sec><sec id="sec0075"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0120"><bold>Perrone Erin E.:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Validation, Supervision. <bold>Buchmiller Terry L.:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Validation, Supervision. <bold>Aagaard Kjersti M.:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Supervision, Resources, Methodology. <bold>Gray Brian:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Visualization, Validation, Supervision. <bold>Abiad May:</bold> Writing &#8211; original draft, Validation, Supervision. <bold>Moss Kevin L.:</bold> Software, Methodology, Formal analysis, Data curation. <bold>Zargarzadeh Nikan:</bold> Writing &#8211; original draft, Visualization, Validation. <bold>Mustafa Hiba J.:</bold> Writing &#8211; original draft, Supervision, Project administration, Methodology, Investigation, Data curation, Conceptualization. <bold>Shamshirsaz Alireza A.:</bold> Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Visualization, Validation, Supervision, Resources, Methodology, Conceptualization.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0005"><title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title><p id="p0125">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bibliog0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krishnapura</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McNeer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dupont</surname><given-names>W.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>County-level atrazine use and gastroschisis</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><volume>7</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2410056</object-id><comment>(-e)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.10056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11074809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38709530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Tanna</surname><given-names>G.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosano</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mastroiacovo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of gastroschisis at birth: retrospective study</article-title><source>BMJ Br Med J</source><volume>325</volume><issue>7377</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>1389</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12480852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.325.7377.1389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC138514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mastroiacovo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lisi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castilla</surname><given-names>E.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The incidence of gastroschisis: research urgently needs resources</article-title><source>Bmj</source><volume>332</volume><issue>7538</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.332.7538.423-a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1371009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16484273</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kilby</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The incidence of gastroschisis</article-title><source>Bmj</source><volume>332</volume><issue>7536</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>250</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.332.7536.250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16455699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1360382</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keys</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drewett</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burge</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gastroschisis: the cost of an epidemic</article-title><source>J Pediatr Surg</source><volume>43</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>654</fpage><lpage>657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpedsurg.2007.12.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18405711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanner</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salemi</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feldkamp</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marengo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and correlates of gastroschisis in 15 states, 1995 to 2005</article-title><source>Obstet Gynecol</source><volume>122</volume><issue>2 Pt 1</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/AOG.0b013e31829cbbb4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23969795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4605404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increasing prevalence of gastroschisis&#8212;14 states, 1995&#8211;2012</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><volume>65</volume><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.15585/mmwr.mm6502a2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26796490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colombani</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perinatal aspects of omphalocele and gastroschisis</article-title><source>Am J Dis Child</source><volume>131</volume><issue>12</issue><year>1977</year><fpage>1386</fpage><lpage>1388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">930890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/archpedi.1977.02120250068011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skarsgard</surname><given-names>E.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meaney</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bassil</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brindle</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arbour</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moineddin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Maternal risk factors for gastroschisis in Canada</article-title><source>Birth Defects Res Part A Clin Mol Teratol</source><volume>103</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/bdra.23349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25684659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dewberry</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalia</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vazquez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilton</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaretsky</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Behrendt</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Determining maternal risk factors for gastroschisis using Colorado's birth registry database</article-title><source>J Pediatr Surg</source><volume>55</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>1002</fpage><lpage>1005</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32173119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jpedsurg.2020.02.030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haddow</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palomaki</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Young maternal age and smoking during pregnancy as risk factors for gastroschisis</article-title><source>Teratology</source><volume>47</volume><issue>3</issue><year>1993</year><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8475465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/tera.1420470306</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vo</surname><given-names>L.U.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langlois</surname><given-names>P.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Time trends in prevalence of gastroschisis in Texas, 1999 to 2011: subgroup analyses by maternal and infant characteristics</article-title><source>Birth Defects Res Part A Clin Mol Teratol</source><volume>103</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>928</fpage><lpage>940</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/bdra.23438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26408207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galganski</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saadai</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephenson</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of gastroschisis: a population-based study in California from 1995 to 2012</article-title><source>J Pedia Surg</source><volume>53</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>2399</fpage><lpage>2403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpedsurg.2018.08.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6327946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30266482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neo</surname><given-names>D.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desrosiers</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carmichael</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gucsavas-Calikoglu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neighborhood-level socioeconomic position during early pregnancy and risk of gastroschisis</article-title><source>Epidemiology</source><volume>34</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/EDE.0000000000001621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10291502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36976718</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldacci</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mezzasalma</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medication use during pregnancy and the risk of gastroschisis: a systematic review and meta-analysis of observational studies</article-title><source>Orphanet J Rare Dis</source><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>31</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38287353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13023-023-02992-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10826191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fr&#237;as</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Non-genetic risk factors for gastroschisis</article-title><source>Am J Med Genet Part C: Semin Med Genet Wiley Online Libr</source><year>2008</year><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ajmg.c.30175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18655102</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="othref0005">Nash E., State policy trends 2021: the worst year for abortion rights in almost half a century. Guttmacher Institute. 2021;12.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isenburg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salemi</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mai</surname><given-names>C.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increasing Prevalence of Gastroschisis--14 States, 1995-2012</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><volume>65</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6502a2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26796490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dewberry</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalia</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vazquez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilton</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaretsky</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Behrendt</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Determining maternal risk factors for gastroschisis using colorado's birth registry database</article-title><source>J Pedia Surg</source><volume>55</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>1002</fpage><lpage>1005</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpedsurg.2020.02.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32173119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ethen</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Canfield</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Change in prepregnancy body mass index and gastroschisis</article-title><source>Ann Epidemiol</source><volume>41</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annepidem.2019.12.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31928895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>P.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torfs</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A low pregnancy body mass index is a risk factor for an offspring with gastroschisis</article-title><source>Epidemiology</source><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><year>1999</year><fpage>717</fpage><lpage>721</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10535786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Block</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salemi</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rutkowski</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanner</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Correia</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Maternal pre-pregnancy body mass index and risk of selected birth defects: evidence of a dose-response relationship</article-title><source>Paediatr Perinat Epidemiol</source><volume>27</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>531</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ppe.12084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24117964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raitio</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tauriainen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leinonen</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Syv&#228;nen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kemppainen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#246;yttyniemi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Maternal risk factors for gastroschisis: a population-based case-control study</article-title><source>Birth Defects Res</source><volume>112</volume><issue>13</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>989</fpage><lpage>995</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bdr2.1703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32406607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waller</surname><given-names>D.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hobbs</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Canfield</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siega-Riz</surname><given-names>A.-M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prepregnancy obesity as a risk factor for structural birth defects</article-title><source>Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med</source><volume>161</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>745</fpage><lpage>750</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archpedi.161.8.745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17679655</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Getz</surname><given-names>K.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderka</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Werler</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Case</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Short interpregnancy interval and gastroschisis risk in the National Birth Defects Prevention Study</article-title><source>Birth Defects Res A Clin Mol Teratol</source><volume>94</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>714</fpage><lpage>720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bdra.23061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22903973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4856468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waller</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hitti</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Agricultural-related chemical exposures, season of conception, and risk of gastroschisis in Washington State</article-title><comment>241.e1-.e6</comment><source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source><volume>202</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajog.2010.01.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20207240</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="othref0010">Births: Final Data for 2022. Hyattsville, MD: https://dx.doi.org/10.15620/cdc:145588; 2024.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="othref0015">Births: Final Data for 2021. Hyattsville, MD: https://dx.doi.org/10.15620/cdc:122047; 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neo</surname><given-names>D.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carmichael</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gucsavas-Calikoglu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Are individual-level risk factors for gastroschisis modified by neighborhood-level socioeconomic factors?</article-title><source>Birth Defects Res</source><volume>115</volume><issue>15</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>1438</fpage><lpage>1449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bdr2.2224</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37439400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10527855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatt</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poku</surname><given-names>F.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Umscheid</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayensu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parmar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasudeva</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Trends in prevalence and mortality of gastroschisis and omphalocele in the United States from 2010 to 2018</article-title><source>World J Pedia</source><volume>18</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>514</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12519-022-00544-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35294711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunez Lopez</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>H.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohanon</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rojas-Khalil</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowen-Jallow</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Race and outcomes in gastroschisis repair: a nationwide analysis</article-title><source>J Pedia Surg</source><volume>52</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1755</fpage><lpage>1759</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpedsurg.2017.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7772778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28365103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of state tobacco control policies on birth defects</article-title><source>Prev Med</source><volume>127</volume><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">105791</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ypmed.2019.105791</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31398414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paranjothy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Broughton</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huddart</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drayton</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jefferson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of maternal nutrition in the aetiology of gastroschisis: an incident case-control study</article-title><source>Int J Epidemiol</source><volume>41</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>1141</fpage><lpage>1152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dys092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22798661</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torfs</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>P.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between mothers' nutrient intake and their offspring's risk of gastroschisis</article-title><source>Teratology</source><volume>58</volume><issue>6</issue><year>1998</year><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1002/(sici)1096-9926(199812)58:6&lt;&#8201;241::Aid-tera5&gt;&#8201;3.0.Co;2-r</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9894673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/(SICI)1096-9926(199812)58:6&lt;241::AID-TERA5&gt;3.0.CO;2-R</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Osterman</surname><given-names>M.J.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Driscoll</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valenzuela</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Births: final Data for 2022</article-title><source>Natl Vital- Stat Rep</source><volume>73</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38625869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Driscoll</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>E.C.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increases in prepregnancy obesity: United States, 2016-2019</article-title><source>NCHS Data Brief</source><issue>392</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33270551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osterman</surname><given-names>M.J.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Driscoll</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Declines in cigarette smoking during pregnancy in the United States, 2016-2021</article-title><source>NCHS Data Brief</source><issue>458</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36723453</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meza</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>D.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trends in US adult smoking prevalence, 2011 to 2022</article-title><source>JAMA Health Forum</source><volume>4</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e234213</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamahealthforum.2023.4213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10692849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38038988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reppucci</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaizer</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prendergast</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acker</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mandell</surname><given-names>E.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Euser</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Incidence of congenital complications related to COVID-19 infection during pregnancy</article-title><source>J Neonatal Perinat Med</source><volume>16</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/npm-221122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37092239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haddock</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skarsgard</surname><given-names>E.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding gastroschisis and its clinical management: where are we?</article-title><source>Expert Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29419329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/17474124.2018.1438890</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0005"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="p0130">We want to acknowledge the CDC personnel and staff who have worked on building this database and making it publicly available.</p></ack></back></article></pmc-articleset>