<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1609</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmjo</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMJ Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2044-6055</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10335474</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10335474.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10335474</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10335474</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37419645</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2023-072404</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen-2023-072404</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Health Services Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1506</subject><subject>1704</subject></subj-group><series-title>Protocol</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Examining service utilisation and impact among consumers of a national mental health stepped care programme in Australia: a protocol using linked administrative data</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-57594351" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2069-0948</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names initials="R">Rachel</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-105154927" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kynn</surname><given-names initials="M">Mary</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-105154956" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carberry</surname><given-names initials="A">Angela</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-105154983" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names initials="R">Rhian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-105155036" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parekh</surname><given-names initials="S">Sanjoti</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-105155008" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names initials="E">Emma</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-105155097" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names initials="J">Jane</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-105155125" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Merollini</surname><given-names initials="K">Katharina</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">School of Health</institution>, <institution>University of the Sunshine Coast</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Sippy Downs</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Queensland</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Sunshine Coast Health Network</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Maroochydore</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Queensland</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="department">School of Electrical Engineering, Computing and Mathematical Sciences</institution>, <institution specific-use="Ringgold_1649">Curtin University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Perth</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Western Australia</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution>Abt Associates</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Milton</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">New South Wales</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff><author-notes><corresp><label>Correspondence to</label> Dr Rachel Cole; <email>rcole@usc.edu.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>7</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">440494</issue-id><elocation-id>e072404</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>07</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>12</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-07-12 10:25:10.323"><day>12</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2023. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense" start_date="2023-07-07">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See:&#160;<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-072404.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-072404.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="reviewers-comments-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-072404.reviewer_comments.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="draft-revisions-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-072404.draft_revisions.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Mental well-being is a global public health priority with increasing mental health conditions having substantial burden on individuals, health systems and society. &#8216;Stepped care&#8217;, where services are provided at an intensity to meet the changing needs of the consumer, is the chosen approach to mental health service delivery in primary healthcare in Australia for its efficiencies and patient outcomes; yet limited evidence exists on how the programme is being rolled out and its impact in practice. This protocol outlines a data linkage project to characterise and quantify healthcare service utilisation and impacts among a cohort of consumers of a national mental health stepped care programme in one region of Australia.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods and analysis</title><p>Data linkage will be used to establish a retrospective cohort of consumers of mental health stepped care services between 1 July 2020 and 31 December 2021 in one primary healthcare region in Australia (n=approx. 12 710). These data will be linked with records from other healthcare service data sets (eg, hospitalisations, emergency department presentations, community-based state government-delivered mental healthcare, hospital costs). Four areas for analysis will include: (1) characterising the nature of mental health stepped care service use; (2) describing the cohort&#8217;s sociodemographic and health characteristics; (3) quantifying broader service utilisation and associated economic costs; and (4) assessing the impact of mental health stepped care service utilisation on health and service outcomes.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethics and dissemination</title><p>Approval from the Darling Downs Health Human Research Ethics Committee (HREA/2020/QTDD/65518) has been granted. All data will be non-identifiable, and research findings will be disseminated through peer-reviewed journals, conference presentations and industry meetings.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>health policy</kwd><kwd>primary health care</kwd><kwd>organisation of health services</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group specific-use="FundRef"><award-group id="funding-1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100004463</institution-id><institution>Bupa Health Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>n/a</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>special-feature</meta-name><meta-value>unlocked</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>STRENGTHS AND LIMITATIONS OF THIS STUDY</title></caption><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>This study is one of the first to characterise the implementation and impact of a national stepped care programme at the level of administration.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The study uses system-wide data linkage to understand health resourcing among consumers of mental health services within an integrated healthcare system.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Having a rich linked database enables tracking of resourcing and outcomes across the healthcare system for a more comprehensive understanding of the characteristics and resource needs of consumers.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The study is being undertaken by a Primary Health Network responsible for health system planning and management with a focus on translation and targeted service improvement.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Study limitations include the omission of data on mental healthcare provided by general practitioners, broader medical prescriptions and private care data, and data being limited to one primary healthcare region within Australia; however, there is opportunity to build on this preliminary study in future projects.</p></list-item></list></boxed-text><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Mental well-being is a global public health priority recognised in United Nations Sustainable Development Goals impacting individuals, health systems and society.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Almost half of Australians (43.7%) will experience a mental disorder in their lifetime.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2 3</xref> People living with mental illness are more likely to also have comorbid physical illness and die earlier than the general population.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4 5</xref> In Australia, mental and substance use disorders are responsible for an estimated 13% of the total burden of disease and 24% of non-fatal burden, representing the fourth and second highest disease group, respectively.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></p><p>About 46% of people predicted to have a mental condition in Australia are estimated to access care.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> In 2020&#8211;2021, approximately 11.2% of the Australian population received government-subsidised mental health-specific services, which was almost double that of the previous decade,<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> and this has increased further since the COVID-19 pandemic.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Mental health services were estimated to comprise 7.6% of combined Australian government recurrent health spending, amounting to a total of $A11.0 billion or $A431 per person in 2019&#8211;2020,<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> with a further estimated $A90.6 million going towards mental health carer service costs.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></p><p>Mental health services in Australia are provided by various professionals such as general practitioners, psychologists, psychiatrists, nurses, occupational therapists, social workers and peer workers in different care settings including, public and private psychiatric hospitals, psychiatric units/wards in public acute hospitals, community mental healthcare services, and government or non-government-operated residential mental health services, and hospital emergency departments.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> In 2018, in response to a national review of mental health services in Australia, a &#8216;stepped care&#8217; approach to mental health service delivery in primary healthcare was adopted by the Australian Government and rolled out by Primary Health Networks (PHN) as a national programme across Australia.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> The PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care model was described as,</p><disp-quote><p>&#8230;an evidence-based, staged system comprising a hierarchy of interventions, from the least to the most intensive, matched to the individual&#8217;s needs. While there are multiple levels within a stepped care approach, they do not operate in silos or as one-directional steps, but rather offer a spectrum of service interventions.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p></disp-quote><p>The stepped care concept in the national programme is built on similar models in the UK with the purpose of better rationalising resources and utilising prevention and low intensity &#8216;coaching&#8217; services for people with lesser needs.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> A range of services at different need levels or &#8216;steps&#8217; are offered which consumers can move up or down pending need, improving service access and efficiency by not over or underservicing the consumer.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></p><p>While many public policies globally endorse and/or have mandated stepped care approaches to healthcare provision for its efficiencies and consumer health outcomes<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, recent reviews report insufficient evidence on whether stepped care achieves better consumer health outcomes against lower costs<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13&#8211;17</xref> with combining evidence difficult given the variety of definitions and programme models used (ie, varying in treatment type, step number and duration, delivering professionals and criteria used).<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> In addition, from an administration perspective, little is currently known about the systems levers that could be applied to achieve the intent of stepped care in rolling out of national programmes at the local level.<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13&#8211;17</xref></p><p>International literature on stepped care programmes is predominantly limited to consumers with depression and anxiety. These studies have found: moderate effects on depression;<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> reductions in anxiety and/or depressive disorders using stepped care as a treatment but no change when used for prevention;<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> mixed findings when used prior to outpatient psychotherapy such as active waiting, self-help, guided self-help, brief single-strand interventions and low-intensity psychotherapy;<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> and, overall better clinical outcomes and cost-effectiveness when used with older people with depression and anxiety symptoms.<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Further, stepped care approaches have also shown potential in reducing stigma and structural barriers to accessing mental health services, particularly among priority populations.<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></p><p>Australian stepped care research is in its infancy, with stepped care still being developed and fully implemented and integrated into primary care.<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> The few Australian studies that do exist are in the early phases of evaluation, with many being pilot or feasibility studies. Among young people with anxiety or depression, studies have found general practitioner web-based screening tools to be feasible,<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> and online school-based mental health services to have high student satisfaction with stable or improvement in help-seeking, depression and anxiety.<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22 23</xref> Three-step models have also shown comparable outcomes and total health sector costs to other validated face-to-face programmes but at less cost to deliver from a societal perspective,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> and hybrid in-person/telehealth models having less therapy time compared with a control group, with comparable clinical outcomes, wait times and quality adjusted life years.<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Among adults, screening and feedback mobile tablets in general practice were found to be acceptable and feasible in early detection of undiagnosed anxiety and depression<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> and informing mental health treatment plans, with reduced symptoms and potential cost saving.<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> A low intensity cognitive&#8211;behavioural therapy early intervention pilot for mild to moderate depression and anxiety also found initial recovery rates and projected economic viability as promising.<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></p><p>Beyond the feasibility, effectiveness and cost efficiency of stepped care as a model of mental health service delivery, little is also known about how mandated national programmes in Australia are being administered and fit within the broader healthcare system. Data linkage studies used at the macrolevel have been shown to provide useful information to inform large-scale programmes from a system level such as Better Access,<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> birthing outcomes for those with substance use or mental health issues<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> and even as a predictive tool for self harm.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> However, to the authors&#8217; knowledge, there are no Australian mental health stepped care studies using data linkage research. Some studies do exist in the UK and Scotland at the programme level. One UK study, using a single case evaluation follow-up with over 25 000 consumers with severe depression and anxiety disorders, found improvements in conditions and functioning, with between 18% and 34% recovery rate.<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> A second UK study of a single service using different types of stepped care with over 16 000 consumers found consumers were 1.5 times more likely to recover in a progression delivery model where patients were treated with a lower intensity intervention.<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> A third UK study found people who used early psychosis intervention services had substantially lower rates of all-cause mortality and emergency department presentations, higher rates of hospitalisation and no difference in self-harm and suicide after 2 years, and mortality rates four times lower than those not using these services.<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> A Scottish study found disparate patterns of psychiatric hospitalisations across disorder types by socioeconomic group, with some ethnic groups having under and late utilisation of mental health services.<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></p><p>With the limited research and understanding of the national mental health stepped care programme roll out within the Australian context, this study aims to describe and quantify healthcare service utilisation and impacts of consumers of PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care services in one PHN region in Australia. Study objectives are to:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Characterise the nature of PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care service delivery among consumers and the extent to which &#8216;stepped care&#8217; was used.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Examine the sociodemographic and health characteristics of consumers of PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care services and their use of PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care services.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Describe and quantify the utilisation of healthcare services and associated economic costs across the broader health system between consumers using different intensities and forms of stepped care, and assess predictors of utilisation frequency such as consumers&#8217; sociodemographic and health characteristics.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Assess the impact of PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care service utilisation across different forms of care on changes to consumers&#8217; mental health outcomes, by intensity of care.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods and analysis</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Study setting</title><p>Data from one PHN, the Central Queensland Wide Bay Sunshine Coast PHN (CQWBSC-PHN), in Queensland, Australia will be used in the study. The CQWBSC-PHN region comprises approximately 899 707 people growing at 1.6% per annum, with a higher proportion of people aged 65 years or older than the national average (21.9% vs 16.6%, respectively).<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Communities vary from rural centres through to metropolitan cities; with 11% of the population residing in outer regional or remote areas.<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> The region has a lower socioeconomic status than national averages,<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> similar overall self-rated health status ratings (82.4% vs 84.4%, rating as excellent, very good or good, respectively), but higher rates of self-reported mental and physical unhealthy days in the past 30 days (4.9 vs 4.8 and 4.8 vs 4.2, respectively),<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> and people in need of assistance with a profound or severe disability (7.3 vs 6.0, respectively).<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Slightly higher reported high or very high psychological distress (13.5 per 100 vs 12.9, respectively)<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> and mental health service utilisation (17.0% vs 10.7%, respectively) were also recorded across the region compared with national averages, with higher mental health-related overnight hospitalisations (98 vs 68 per 10 000 people, respectively) and emergency care presentations (143 vs 122 per 10 000 people, respectively).<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care programme</title><p>The national PHN-commissioned mental health programme commenced in the CQWBSC-PHN region in 2018. The programme offers a continuum of service interventions, matched to the spectrum of mental illness across five levels of care (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>).<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Alignment of a consumer to a service intervention begins at the initial assessment by assessing eight &#8216;domains&#8217;.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Some streams/services in the programme provide a single level of care, many provide multiple levels. For example, general practice mental healthcare provides lower levels of care when it is provided in isolation, or higher levels when delivered in combination with other services or interventions (eg, psychiatrist or a multidisciplinary team). The assigned levels of care often form &#8216;packages&#8217; for people requiring that level of care, with the levels differentiated by the amount and scope of resources available. A given consumer may use some or all interventions described at that level and move between levels of care as required. PHNs commission the PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care programme using six specific streams shown in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Levels of stepped care and alignment with assessment relative to severity of assess mental illness and need for services (adapted from &#8216;PHN Primary Mental Healthcare Flexible Funding Pool Programme Guidance: Stepped Care 2019&#8217;<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level of care</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Level of severity</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description of clinical services</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workforce requirements</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acute and specialist community mental health services</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe and persistent often with complex multiagency needs; other severe conditions that include high level of risk, disability or complexity</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intensive team-based specialist assessment and intervention (typically state-delivered mental health services).</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Involvement from a range of different mental health professionals including case managers, psychiatrists, allied health workers and GPs.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High intensity services</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe mental illness (may be persistent or episodic) where there is not a high level of risk, complexity or disability</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High intensity services including periods of intensive intervention that may involve multidisciplinary support.</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Central role of private psychiatrists, paediatricians and GPs in assessment and management.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Psychological therapy provided by psychologists and other allied health professionals.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Mental health nurses involved in coordinating clinical care.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Appropriately trained, supervised and mentored peer workforce can be part of primary care team to offer peer support and advocacy.</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate intensity services</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild to moderate to mental illness</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Structured, reasonably frequent and intensive interventions.</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Central role of GPs in management and assessment.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Psychological therapy provided by psychologists and other allied health professionals.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Private psychiatrists and paediatricians involved for some, particularly for clinical assessment and review.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Peer workforce can complement clinical services from primary care team through provision of peer support where appropriate.</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low intensity services</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild to moderate mental illness</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Services designed to be accessed quickly, without need for formal referral, easily through a range of modalities and involve few short sessions.</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>GP psychoeducation/care planning, (though formal referral not required).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Interventions may be delivered by mental health professionals or other workforce with appropriate skills, training and qualifications to deliver evidence based mental health services.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Appropriately trained, supervised and mentored peer workforce are well placed to deliver low intensity services.</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self management</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subsyndromal or mild mental illness; or no mental illness relapse prevention</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Services designed to prevent the onset of illness, or prevent further escalation, and focused on supporting symptom self-management.</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T1_FN1"><p>GPs, general practitioners; PHN, primary health network.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care programme streams</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stream</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low intensity</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early intervention and mental healthcare services for those at risk of mental illness, mild mental illness, or as a transition out of care.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child and young people</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Services across the spectrum of mental health severity needs (excluding acute services) for consumers 0&#8211;24 years of age.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychological therapies</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychological therapies with a focus on rural/remote consumers and underserviced groups.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe and complex</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical care coordination activities for consumers with severe and/or complex requirements.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suicide prevention aftercare</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment and care coordination to consumers exiting acute services following a suicide attempt.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indigenous-specific</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Social and emotional well-being services for Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islander consumers.</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T2_FN1"><p>PHN, primary health network.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Mental health services within the national stepped care programme may be provided by state governments or private providers, delivering government-subsidised services, or services commissioned by PHNs designed to better integrate local services, address service gaps across the stepped care spectrum and support equitable access. The CQWBSC-PHN model includes a centralised intake and triage service to field queries, and process and allocate incoming consumers to a service stream/service that suits their needs at that time. Referrals to the programme are primarily by primary healthcare general practitioners.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Study design</title><p>Data linkage will underpin the study design, linking six routinely collected administrative data sets from Queensland, Australia, for a retrospective observational cohort of consumers of PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care services. Once identified, consumers&#8217; data from other Queensland Government routinely collected health administrative data sets will be extracted and linked, providing information on admitted and non-admitted hospital separations, emergency department presentations, Queensland government-delivered community and residential mental health and alcohol and drug service utilisation, and hospital cost data. Identified data will be linked by the Statistical Service Branch, Queensland Health (SSB-QH) under the Public Health Act 2005 governing the use of public health data in Queensland.<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Study cohort</title><p>The study cohort will comprise all persons who were triaged and attended at least one PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care service appointment as registered in the Primary Mental Healthcare-Minimum Data Set (PMHC-MDS), a reporting requirement of the programme by the Australian Government Department of Health, between 1 July 2020 and 31 December 2021 (N=approx. 12 710). A flow chart of how the study cohort will be established, and administrative data sets to be linked, is presented in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Study cohort and data linkage structure. PHN, Primary Health Network; PMHC-MDS, Primary Mental Health Care-Minimum Data Set.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-072404f01.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Data sets and linkage</title><p>After identifying the study cohort, PMHC-MDS data custodians will transfer the data through a secure platform (eg, Kiteworks) using a unique, time-limited link to the SSB-QH for linkage. The SBB-QH will assign an encryption key to identify individuals to the identifiable data set (eg, using individuals&#8217; last name, given names, date of birth, usual residential address) and will extract linked data for these individuals from the routinely collected administrative health data sets using deterministic and probabilistic linkage, depending on the data set.<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> Once linked, the data set will be deidentified and transferred using a secured site (eg, Kiteworks) to researchers in preparation for analysis.</p><p>The data sets to be linked include the Queensland Hospital Admitted Patient Data Collection (QHAPDC), Queensland Hospital Non-Admitted Patient Data Collection (QHNAPDC), Emergency Department Minimum Data Collection (EDIS), Consumer Integrated Mental Health Application (CIMHA) and National Hospital Cost Data Collection (NHCDC). Descriptions of the data contained in each data set are provided in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Outcome variables</title><p>The primary outcomes of the study are healthcare service utilisation and costs, and impacts and are summarised in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Outcome variable definitions</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome variable</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Administrative data set source</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome variable definition</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mental health-related hospitalisations<break/>Non-mental health-related hospitalisations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Queensland Hospital Admitted Patient Data Collection (QHAPDC)<break/>Queensland Hospital Non-Admitted Patient Data Collection (QHNAPDC)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient and outpatient hospital admissions to designated mental health beds and other mental health-related admissions per year will be ascertained as a count variable of episodes of care and continuous variable of length of stay in the 12-month period of interest, as identified in QHAPDC and QHNAPDC.<break/>Inpatient and outpatient admissions for other medical conditions or surgical procedures per year will be ascertained as a count variable of episodes of care and continuous variable of length of stay in the 12-month period of interest, as identified in QHAPDC and QHNAPDC.<break/>Type of care will be determined by the &#8216;care type&#8217;, which is a descriptor of the overall nature of clinical care provided to non-admitted and admitted patients during a service event (Rehabilitation care, Palliative care, Geriatric evaluation and management, Psychogeriatric care, Mental healthcare and Other care) in QHAPDC and QHNAPDC. &#8216;Principal diagnosis&#8217; and &#8216;other diagnoses&#8217; will also be used in QHAPDC (according to the International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems, Tenth Revision, Australian Modification (ICD-10-AM code)).</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mental health-related emergency department presentations<break/><break/><break/>Non-mental health-related emergency department presentations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emergency Department Minimum Data Collection (EDIS)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mental health-related and non-mental health-related emergency department presentations per year will be ascertained as a count variable of episodes of care and continuous variable of length of stay in the 12 month period of interest will be ascertained as a count variable, as identified in the EDIS.<break/>Type of care will be determined by &#8216;principal diagnosis&#8217; established at the conclusion of the presentation and &#8216;other diagnoses&#8217; or coexisting complaint during the presentation (ICD-10-AM code).</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public community and residential mental health, and alcohol and drug service attendances</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Consumer Integrated Mental Health Application (CIMHA)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public community and residential mental health and alcohol and drug service attendances per year will be ascertained as a count variable of episodes of care and continuous variable of length of stay in the 12-month period of interest, as identified in the CIMHA.<break/>Type of care will be determined by &#8216;primary diagnosis&#8217;, a disease or condition experienced by a consumer chiefly responsible for causing the interaction with a health service and &#8216;secondary diagnosis&#8217;, which is a disease or condition experienced by a consumer either coexisting with a primary diagnosis or occurring due to a disease or condition process or due to the treatment given for a disease or condition.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total hospital costs per person</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National Hospital Cost Data Collection</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total costs of admitted and non-admitted hospitalisations, and emergency department presentations per person will be ascertained as continuous variables linked with episodes of care associated with related healthcare services (QHAPDC, QHNAPDC, EDIS) in the 12-month period of interest.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total consumer mental health outcome<break/>Change in consumer mental health outcomes</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary Mental Healthcare Minimum Data set</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall consumer mental health outcomes will be the change in mental health outcome scores from first to last attendance in the PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care programme.<break/>Incremental change in consumer mental health outcomes will be the change in mental health outcome scores after individual PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care service sessions.<break/>Clinical-rated mental health outcomes scores include:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Kessler Psychological Distress Scale</p></list-item><list-item><p>Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire</p></list-item></list><break/>Scores may include individual items, subscales and/or total scores.</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T3_FN1"><p>PHN, primary health network.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Healthcare service utilisation measures will include the difference in the number of healthcare encounters (admissions, presentations and attendances) and healthcare costs associated with those encounters per person for the 12 months prior to the first PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care programme service attendance, and 12 months following that date, identified in Queensland Government health administrative data sets separated as admitted and non-admitted hospitalisations, emergency department presentations, and Queensland Health community and residential mental health and alcohol and drug service attendances. The number of healthcare service encounters will be estimated as a count of episodes of care and length of stay and treated as continuous variables for the purposes of analyses.<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41 42</xref> A length of stay will be defined as the complete period of care from admission to hospital until separation. Hospitalisations will be categorised for mental health-related and non-mental health-related care determined by recorded principal and other diagnoses in relevant databases.</p><p>Total costs per person will be estimated directly using an individual-level microcosting approach by linking the NHCDC administrative data records with other linked hospital-based administrative data sets (QHAPDC, QHNAPDC and EDIS). Average and overall patient costs will be estimated per costing period for the 12 months prior to the first PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care programme service attendance and 12 months after.</p><p>Change in overall mental health outcomes will be identified in the PMHC-MDS and include total, subscale or individual item scores from clinician-derived Kessler Psychological Distress Scale (K10 or K5) and Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire scores, which are routinely collected during attendances as part of the national programme. The differences in each score will be described over the total attendance in the PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care programme, and over time after individual sessions.</p></sec><sec id="s2-7"><title>Exposure variables</title><p>Exposure variables of interest for the study include the sociodemographic characteristics of the study cohort, such as consumer age at first programme appointment, gender, Indigenous status, homelessness, ethnicity and identification as lesbian, gay, bisexual, trans/transgender, intersex, queer and other sexuality (LGBTIQ+). The health status of the study cohort, including clinical mental health diagnoses, comorbidities and suicide risk, and healthcare support such as general practitioner treatment plan, drug assessment and care team arrangement will also be used. In addition, the nature of utilisation of PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care programme services will be assessed, including presence of stepped care, severity level, clinical diagnosis and level/s and frequency of services used. The nature of the utilisation of other health services will also be explored as exposure variables for some outcomes. Presence of stepped care for this study will be defined as a consumer experiencing at least one variation in their intensity of service during programme participation. Further definitions or categories of stepped care may be developed in line with findings in the data during analyses consistent with the nature of consumer service utilisation. Finally, transition points of care, care coordination and system interactions (eg, case coordination, referrals) will be mapped over time. <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> describes the list of exposure variables related data sources and definitions that will be explored in analyses.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Exposure variable definitions</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exposure variable</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Administrative data set source</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exposure variable definition</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nature of mental health-related hospitalisations<break/><break/><break/>Nature of non-mental health-related hospitalisations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Queensland Hospital Admitted Patient Data Collection<break/>Queensland Hospital Non-Admitted Patient Data Collection (QHNAPDC)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source of referral/transfer<break/>Care type<break/>Service delivery mode<break/>Mode of separation<break/>Length of stay<break/>Diagnosis<break/>Hospital district</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nature of mental health-related emergency department presentations<break/><break/><break/>Nature of non-mental health-related emergency department presentations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emergency Department Minimum Data Collection</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triage category<break/>Diagnosis<break/>Episode end status<break/>Hospital district</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nature of Queensland Health community and residential mental health, and alcohol and drug service attendances</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Consumer Integrated Mental Health Application</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Referral source<break/>Diagnosis<break/>Service delivery mode<break/>Intervention type<break/>Session type<break/>Session duration<break/>Service type<break/>Hospital district</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Consumer sociodemographic characteristics<break/>Consumer health status<break/>Existing care arrangements<break/>Nature of PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care utilisation</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary Mental Healthcare Minimum Data set</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age<break/>Gender identity<break/>Ethnic identity<break/>Indigenous status<break/>Rurality of place of residence (based on the Australian Statistical Geography Standard)<break/>Low socioeconomic status marker<break/>Homeless marker<break/>Employment status<break/>Domestic violence marker<break/>Government disability support<break/>Suicide referral marker<break/>Condition severity level<break/>Principal and additional clinical diagnoses<break/>Comorbidity status<break/>Mental health-related medication utilisation<break/>Existing healthcare support<break/>Level of service<break/>Treatment type<break/>Service type<break/>Service delivery mode<break/>Session type<break/>Session duration<break/>Stepped up or down<break/>Servicing practitioner organisation<break/>Servicing practitioner type<break/>Referral time<break/>Episodes of care in programme<break/>Length of time in programme<break/>Servicing practitioner location<break/>Mode of separation</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T4_FN1"><p>PHN, primary health network.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2-8"><title>Analysis plan</title><p>Primary analyses for study objectives are outlined below. Regression modelling appropriate for variables will be used in all analyses, adjusted for confounding variables of relevance.</p><sec id="s2-8-1"><title>Objective 1: to characterise the nature of PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care service delivery among consumers and the extent to which &#8216;stepped care&#8217; was used</title><p>Within each episode of care in the PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care programme, consumers experiences of &#8216;stepped care&#8217; will be described for transitioning between care intensities. This will include describing and, where possible depending on the nature of the data, quantifying (and possibly categorising) their service utilisation characteristics such as intensity/ies of care, transitioning between intensities of care, frequency of service use and levels of condition severity.</p></sec><sec id="s2-8-2"><title>Objective 2: to examine the sociodemographic and health characteristics of consumers of PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care services and their use of PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care services</title><p>Sociodemographic characteristics of consumers of PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care services will be described along with the nature of their utilisation of programme services. This description will include consumers&#8217; individual characteristics (eg, age, gender, health status and socioeconomic status), and their situational and service utilisation characteristics (eg, service stream and intensity/ies of care, transitioning between intensities of care, and frequency of service use). Comparisons of consumer characteristics will also be made with broader population and/or service usage data as reference points.</p></sec><sec id="s2-8-3"><title>Objective 3: to describe and quantify the utilisation of healthcare services and associated economic costs across the broader system between consumers using different intensities and forms of stepped care and assess predictors of utilisation frequency such as consumers&#8217; sociodemographic and health characteristics</title><p>To understand healthcare resourcing used by different types of PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care programme consumers, and the influence different consumer characteristics has on that use, healthcare utilisation, the sequencing of service utilisation across service types and transition points in care will be mapped and described over time for each programme stream, in the 12 months prior to their first appointment in the programme to 12 months after.</p><p>Changes in levels of healthcare service utilisation and associated economic costs, using the outcome variables described above, from the 12-month period prior to consumers&#8217; first attendance with the PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care programme and the 12-month period after for each programme stream will be examined using &#967;<sup>2</sup> tests or analysis of variance. Bivariate and multivariable count and linear models will identify factors associated with higher levels of change in measures.</p></sec><sec id="s2-8-4"><title>Objective 4: to assess the impact of PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care service utilisation across different forms of care on changes to consumers&#8217; mental health outcomes, by intensity of care</title><p>Routinely collected psychological assessment scores will be described over time in relation to consumers&#8217; journey through the PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care programme and for service programme streams attended and changes in stepping up and down in the programme, with individual consumers being their own control. To ensure adequate exposure to the programme when assessing outcomes, criteria relating to, and/or categories of, the number of PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care sessions will be determined using average/median of session numbers across the cohort. Changes will be examined using dependent t-tests or repeated measures of analysis of variance. Bivariate and multivariable regression models will assess change over time and identify associated factors including other healthcare service utilisation and consumer characteristics, and health status will be included as exposure variables.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2-9"><title>Statistical power</title><p>This study will describe and quantify healthcare service utilisation and the mental health outcomes of consumers of the PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care programme assessing whether the programme is associated with outcomes of interest. The primary exposures of interest include programme service factors, consumer clinical factors and sociodemographic factors. The number of study participants needed to detect a significant difference in outcomes of interest preprogramme and postprogramme will be calculated using OpenEpi<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> and set to 0.05, with two-sided tests and power of 0.8 based on the findings of previous studies. Only studies comparing stepped care programmes with usual care were available for estimating study sample sizes for healthcare encounters and costs, with studies limited to hospitalisations and emergency department presentations. Hospital encounters were found to be greater among consumers of stepped care services (hazard ratio (HR) of 1.42) and lower for emergency department presentations (HR of 0.71).<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Recovery of consumers assessed using standardised scores defined as at least a 50% reduction in mental health scores have found recovery rates of consumers to be 30% for severe levels of anxiety and 34% for severe levels of depression,<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> and 40%&#8211;60% overall.<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Using these figures, the estimated number of participants needed to detect a difference in each exposure category to conservatively be approximately at least 90.</p></sec><sec id="s2-10"><title>Patient and public involvement</title><p>This study involves the secondary analysis of data from routinely collected health administrative data sets. The public will not be involved in the design, conduct, reporting or dissemination of the study. Findings will be shared in peer-reviewed publications and conferences, reports and at industry meetings attended by researchers, policy-makers and service providers.</p></sec><sec id="s2-11"><title>Ethics and dissemination</title><p>To protect privacy and confidentiality, approval for the linkage of health data in Queensland is provided under strict conditions for the storage, retention and use of the data under the Public Health Act 2005.<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39 40</xref> Ethics approval has been obtained from the Darling Downs Health Human Research Ethics Committee (HREA/2020/QTDD/65518), as well as a waiver of participant consent for the use of privately owned PMHC-MDS data for the study under the Privacy Act 1988,<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> on the grounds of consent outlined in the National Statement on Ethical Conduct in Human Research<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> were met. Approvals from data custodians for the use of data have also been obtained for all data sets in the study.</p><p>Findings of the study will be disseminated through publication in peer-reviewed journals, and presentations at conferences with researchers, healthcare professionals and consumers. Findings will also be shared in routine correspondence (eg, newsletters) and meetings with healthcare providers and government partners and on public platforms to reach the general public by researcher organisations.</p></sec><sec id="s2-12"><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study will provide an understanding of the nature and impact of the implementation of a national stepped care mental health programme at a regional level and may provide insight to its feasibility, effectiveness and efficiency as a programme allowing for a better understanding of the support strategies that may be required in rolling out the intent of such programmes in Australia and potentially national programmes elsewhere. In examining the burden of mental health on consumers of the PHN-commissioned mental health stepped care programme and health system more broadly, the study will extend knowledge of the consumer and healthcare service factors that influence service utilisation and mental health-related outcomes, with the capacity to predict health service utilisation of consumers of mental health stepped care services to inform future planning for the resourcing of mental health services and supports. The patterns of healthcare utilisation will also improve knowledge about consumers&#8217; needs to enhance healthcare delivery for priority populations. The linkage of data sets across the healthcare system in this study will assist in better understanding consumers use of mental health services and the impact this has on their health and well-being.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="d64e174" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Reviewer comments</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-072404.reviewer_comments.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="d64e175" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Author's
manuscript</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjopen-2023-072404.draft_revisions.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Contributors:</bold> SP and EW designed and planned the initial study concept and secured funding as co-principal investigators. RC, KM and MK further developed the study protocol. RC provided project administration and coordination to obtain ethics and other approvals and drafted the manuscript; SP and EW provided input to the process. AC supported organisational approvals and data custodian access to the Primary Health Network data. RJ updated the literature for the manuscript. JT edited and proofed the manuscript ready for submission and provided final conceptual checks of the project. All authors provided editing and feedback throughout the writing processes.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This research received a grant from the Bupa Foundation for the foundation work in preparing and obtaining the approvals for the research project.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> None declared.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient and public involvement:</bold> Patients and/or the public were not involved in the design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="ethics-statement"><title>Ethics statements</title><sec><title>Patient consent for publication</title><p content-type="ethics-consent-to-publish">Not applicable.</p></sec></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>United Nations Department of Economic and Social Affairs</collab></person-group>. <source>United National Sustainable Development: Goal 3. Ensure healthy lives and promote well-being for all at all ages. Goal 3</source>. <year>2022</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Australian Bureau of Statistics</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Health conditions prevalence 2020-21</article-title>. <comment>n.d.</comment><comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.abs.gov.au/statistics/health/health-conditions-and-risks/health-conditions-prevalence/2020-21">https://www.abs.gov.au/statistics/health/health-conditions-and-risks/health-conditions-prevalence/2020-21</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organisation</collab></person-group>. <article-title>World mental health report: transforming mental health for all 2022</article-title>. <comment>n.d.</comment><comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240049338">https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240049338</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bartlem</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Freund</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Care provision to prevent chronic disease by community mental health Clinicians</article-title>. <source>Am J Prev Med</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>762</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2014.08.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25455118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Australian Bureau of Statistics</collab></person-group>. <article-title>National survey of mental health and wellbeing: summary of results 2008</article-title>. <comment>n.d.</comment><comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.abs.gov.au/statistics/health/mental-health/national-study-mental-health-and-wellbeing/2007">https://www.abs.gov.au/statistics/health/mental-health/national-study-mental-health-and-wellbeing/2007</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Australian Institute of Health and Welfare</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Australian burden of disease study: impact and causes of illness and death in Australia 2018</article-title>. <year>2021</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.aihw.gov.au/reports/burden-of-disease/abds-impact-and-causes-of-illness-and-death-in-aus/summary">https://www.aihw.gov.au/reports/burden-of-disease/abds-impact-and-causes-of-illness-and-death-in-aus/summary</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Australian Bureau of Statistics</collab></person-group>. <article-title>National study of mental health and wellbeing [Internet] 2020-21</article-title>. <comment>n.d.</comment><comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.abs.gov.au/statistics/health/mental-health/national-study-mental-health-and-wellbeing/latest-release">https://www.abs.gov.au/statistics/health/mental-health/national-study-mental-health-and-wellbeing/latest-release</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aknin</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>De Neve</surname><given-names>J-E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Mental health during the first year of the COVID-19 pandemic: A review and recommendations for moving forward</article-title>. <source>Perspect Psychol Sci</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>915</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/17456916211029964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35044275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9274782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schess</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Diminic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hielscher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Investment in Australian mental health Carer services: how much and does it reflect evidence of effectiveness</article-title><source>Aust Health Rev</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>104</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/AH18065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30558709</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Australian Government Department of Health</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Contributing lives, thriving communities. report of the National review of mental health programmes and services</article-title>. <year>2015</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.health.gov.au/resources/publications/australian-government-response-to-contributing-lives-thriving-communities-review-of-mental-health-programmes-and-services">https://www.health.gov.au/resources/publications/australian-government-response-to-contributing-lives-thriving-communities-review-of-mental-health-programmes-and-services</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hickie</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Transdiagnostic stepped care in mental health</article-title>. <source>Public Health Res Pract</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<elocation-id>2721712</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17061/phrp2721712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28474049</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Australian Government Department of Health</collab></person-group>. <article-title>PHN mental health flexible funding pool programme guidance: stepped care 2019</article-title>. <comment>n.d.</comment><comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.health.gov.au/sites/default/files/documents/2021/04/primary-health-networks-phn-primary-mental-health-care-guidance-stepped-care.pdf">https://www.health.gov.au/sites/default/files/documents/2021/04/primary-health-networks-phn-primary-mental-health-care-guidance-stepped-care.pdf</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Szewczyk</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Proudfoot</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Economic evaluations of stepped models of care for depression and anxiety and associated implementation strategies: A review of Empiric studies</article-title>. <source>Int J Integr Care</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<elocation-id>8</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5334/ijic.4157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6588024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31244562</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>van Straten</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Stepped care treatment delivery for depression: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>231</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291714000701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25065653</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gr&#252;nzig</surname><given-names>S-D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bengel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>G&#246;hner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Low-intensity interventions to reduce depressive symptoms before outpatient psychotherapy: A systematic literature review</article-title>. <source>Psychother Psychosom Med Psychol</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>212</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/a-0630-2397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30045413</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Firth</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barkham</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kellett</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The clinical effectiveness of stepped care systems for depression in working age adults: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>170</volume>:<fpage>119</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2014.08.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25240141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Stepped care, system architecture and mental health services in Australia</article-title>. <source>Int J Integr Care</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<elocation-id>16</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5334/ijic.2505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5351042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28435424</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>FY-Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>W-F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>TH-Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The efficacy and cost-effectiveness of stepped care prevention and treatment for depressive and/or anxiety disorders: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<elocation-id>29281</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep29281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27377429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4932532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Meuldijk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wuthrich</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Stepped-care treatment of anxiety and depression in older adults: A narrative review</article-title>. <source>Aust J Rural Health</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>275</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ajr.12524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31429140</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fuessel-Hermann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pazdera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Preventative care in first Responder mental health: focusing on access and utilization via stepped Telehealth care</article-title>. <source>Front Health Serv</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<elocation-id>848138</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/frhs.2022.848138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36925868</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10012773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Achilles</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Subotic-Kerry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Youth Stepcare: A pilot study of an online screening and recommendations service for depression and anxiety among youth patients in general practice</article-title>. <source>BMC Fam Pract</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<elocation-id>2</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12875-019-1071-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31910811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6945483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Dea</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Subotic-Kerry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Smooth sailing: a pilot study of an online, school-based, mental health service for depression and anxiety</article-title>. <source>Front Psychiatry</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<elocation-id>574</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2019.00574</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31481904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6710361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Dea</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Subotic-Kerry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>A cluster randomised controlled trial of a web-based youth mental health service in Australian schools</article-title>. <source>Lancet Reg Health West Pac</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<elocation-id>100178</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lanwpc.2021.100178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34527971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8356132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterton</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rapee</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Catchpool</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Economic evaluation of stepped care for the management of childhood anxiety disorders: results from a randomised trial</article-title>. <source>Aust N Z J Psychiatry</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>673</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0004867418823272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30658546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wuthrich</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rapee</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McLellan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Psychological stepped care for anxious adolescents in community mental health services: A pilot effectiveness trial</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Res</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>303</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2021.114066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34175714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Proudfoot</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Implementation and cost effectiveness evaluation of an integrated mental health stepped care service for adults in primary care</article-title>. <source>Int J Integr Care</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>446</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5334/ijic.s3446</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>O Moore</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Faraj</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Stepped care mental health service in Australian primary care: Codesign and feasibility study</article-title>. <source>Aust Health Rev</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>873</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/AH19078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31662177</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cromarty</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Newaccess for depression and anxiety: adapting the UK improving access to psychological therapies program across Australia</article-title>. <source>Australas Psychiatry</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>489</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1039856216641310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27034440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McCauley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sheeran</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The interaction of pregnancy, substance use and mental illness on birthing outcomes in Australia</article-title>. <source>Midwifery</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.midw.2017.08.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28886465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Spittal</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pirkis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The repeated episodes of self-harm (RESH) score: A tool for predicting risk of future episodes of self-harm by hospital patients</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>161</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2014.02.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24751305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Recovery and reliable change rates for patients scoring severe on depression, anxiety or impaired functioning in a psychological therapies service: IAPT</article-title>. <source>Mental Health Rev J</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>28</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/MHRJ-06-2014-0022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reilly</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of a progressive stepped care approach in an improving access to psychological therapies service: an observational study</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<elocation-id>e0214715</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0214715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30964883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6456251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>MacDougall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness of early psychosis intervention: comparison of service users and nonusers in population-based health administrative data</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>175</volume>:<fpage>443</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2017.17050480</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29495897</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bhopal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Netto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Disparate patterns of Hospitalisation reflect unmet needs and persistent ethnic inequalities in mental health care: the Scottish health and Ethnicity linkage study</article-title>. <source>Ethn Health</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>217</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>39</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13557858.2013.814764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23844602</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Queensland Government Statistician&#8217;s Office</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Queensland regional profiles</article-title>. <year>2021</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.qgso.qld.gov.au">www.qgso.qld.gov.au</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Queensland Government Department of Health</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Queensland survey analytic system: regional headline indicators 2020</article-title>. <comment>n.d.</comment><comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.health.qld.gov.au/research-reports/population-health/preventive-health-surveys/data-trends">https://www.health.qld.gov.au/research-reports/population-health/preventive-health-surveys/data-trends</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Australian Bureau of Statistics</collab></person-group>. <article-title>National health survey 2017-18</article-title>. <comment>n.d.</comment><comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.abs.gov.au/statistics/health/health-conditions-and-risks/national-health-survey-first-results/latest-release">https://www.abs.gov.au/statistics/health/health-conditions-and-risks/national-health-survey-first-results/latest-release</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Public Health Information Development Unit</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Social health Atlas of Australia</article-title>. <year>2022</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://phidu.torrens.edu.au/social-health-atlases/">https://phidu.torrens.edu.au/social-health-atlases/</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>State of Queensland</collab></person-group>. <source>Public health act 2005</source>. <publisher-loc>Brisbane</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>State of Queensland</publisher-name>, <year>2022</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Queensland Government Department of Health</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Queensland data linkage framework</article-title>. <year>2021</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.health.qld.gov.au/__data/assets/pdf_file/0030/150798/qlddatalinkframework.pdf">https://www.health.qld.gov.au/__data/assets/pdf_file/0030/150798/qlddatalinkframework.pdf</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Protocol for the data-linkage alcohol cohort study (DACS): investigating mortality, morbidity and offending among people with an alcohol-related problem using linked administrative data</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<elocation-id>e030605</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2019-030605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6687018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31383711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Australian Institute of Health and Welfare</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Australia&#8217;s hospitals at a glance</article-title>. <year>2022</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.aihw.gov.au/reports/hospitals/australias-hospitals-at-a-glance">https://www.aihw.gov.au/reports/hospitals/australias-hospitals-at-a-glance</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soe</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Open source epidemiologic statistics for public health (open Epi)</article-title>. <year>2013</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.openepi.com/SampleSize/SSCohort.htm">https://www.openepi.com/SampleSize/SSCohort.htm</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Austalian Government</collab></person-group>. <source>Privacy act 1998</source>. <publisher-loc>Canberra</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Office of Parliamentary Counsel</publisher-name>, <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Health and Medical Research Council</collab></person-group>. <article-title>National statement on ethical conduct in human research</article-title>. <year>2018</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.nhmrc.gov.au/about-us/publications/national-statement-ethical-conduct-human-research-2007-updated-2018">https://www.nhmrc.gov.au/about-us/publications/national-statement-ethical-conduct-human-research-2007-updated-2018</uri></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>