<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">216</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcmedicine</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1741-7015</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10740225</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10740225.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10740225</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10740225</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38129845</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12916-023-03229-3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3229</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Risk of newly developed atrial fibrillation by alcohol consumption differs according to genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism: a large-scale cohort study with UK Biobank</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names initials="CS">Chan Soon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names initials="J">Jaewon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names initials="J">JungMin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names initials="KY">Kyung-Yeon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names initials="HJ">Hyo-Jeong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names initials="S">Soonil</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names initials="SR">So-Ryoung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names initials="EK">Eue-Keun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names initials="SH">Soo Heon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2504-9615</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names initials="S">Seil</given-names></name><address><email>seil@snu.ac.kr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01z4nnt86</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412484.f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0302 820X</institution-id><institution>Cardiovascular Center, </institution><institution>Seoul National University Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Seoul, Republic of Korea </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01z4nnt86</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412484.f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0302 820X</institution-id><institution>Division of Data Science Research, </institution><institution>Innovative Biomedical Technology Research Institute, Seoul National University Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Seoul, Republic of Korea </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04h9pn542</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.31501.36</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0470 5905</institution-id><institution>Department of Internal Medicine, </institution><institution>Seoul National University College of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>Seoul, Republic of Korea </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>21</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">425426</issue-id><elocation-id>509</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-01-29 13:25:10.193"><day>29</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12916_2023_Article_3229.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">The predictive relationship between mild-to-moderate alcohol consumption and the risk of incident atrial fibrillation (AF) remains controversial.</p></sec><sec><title>Objective</title><p id="Par2">We investigated whether the relationship between alcohol consumption and the risk of incident AF could be associated with the genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par3">A total of 399,329 subjects with genetic data from the UK Biobank database, enrolled between 2006 and 2010, were identified and followed for incident AF until 2021. Genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism was stratified according to the polygenic risk score (PRS) tertiles. Alcohol consumption was categorized as non-drinkers, mild-to-moderate drinkers (&lt; 30 g/day), and heavy drinkers (&#8805; 30 g/day).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par4">During the follow-up (median 12.2 years), 19,237 cases of AF occurred. When stratified by PRS tertiles, there was a significant relationship between genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism and actual alcohol consumption habits (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Mild-to-moderate drinkers showed a decreased risk of AF (HR 0.96, 95% CI 0.92&#8211;0.99), and heavy drinkers showed an increased risk of AF (HR 1.06, 95% CI 1.02&#8211;1.10) compared to non-drinkers. When stratified according to PRS tertiles for genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism, mild-to-moderate drinkers had equivalent AF risks, and heavy drinkers showed increased AF risk in the low PRS tertile group. However, mild-to-moderate drinkers had decreased AF risks and heavy drinkers showed similar risks of AF in the middle/high PRS tertile groups.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par5">Differential associations between alcohol consumption habits and incident AF across genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism were observed; individuals with genetic predisposition to low alcohol metabolism were more susceptible to AF.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12916-023-03229-3.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Atrial fibrillation</kwd><kwd>Alcohol consumption</kwd><kwd>Genetic predisposition to disease</kwd><kwd>Prognosis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100004332</institution-id><institution>Seoul National University Hospital</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>04-2022-2260</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>Seil</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2023</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par12">Atrial fibrillation (AF) is one of the most common clinical arrhythmias and a major cause of stroke, dementia, heart failure, and mortality worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. For this reason, many attempts have been made to improve the clinical prognosis of AF patients, including refining clinical risk stratification for predicting stroke and thromboembolism, such as CHA<sub>2</sub>DS<sub>2</sub>-VASc scores [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. In addition, interventional treatment of AF with catheter ablation has become the cornerstone of AF management [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Despite these advances, recent studies have shown unacceptably high prevalence and incidence of AF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], indicating the need for tailored prevention strategies to improve clinical outcomes further.</p><p id="Par13">Various studies have demonstrated that unhealthy lifestyle behaviors such as smoking, obesity, and a lack of regular physical activity are associated with a significantly increased risk of AF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Moreover, the risk of cardiovascular diseases such as coronary artery disease and heart failure had a J-shaped association with alcohol consumption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. However, reports are contradictory as to whether mild or moderate alcohol consumption are associated with a decreased risk of incident AF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. This may be due to unmeasured contributing factors that may influence the association between alcohol consumption and the risk of AF. It has been reported that heterogeneity of genetic traits for alcohol metabolism could play a pivotal role in the genetic liability to alcohol consumption habits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Polymorphisms of genes related to alcohol metabolism, such as alcohol dehydrogenase and aldehyde dehydrogenase, could affect differential response after alcohol consumption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] as well as differential alcohol consumption habits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Therefore, it could be speculated that the genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism may alter the association between alcohol consumption habits and the risk of incident AF; if an individual has low levels of alcohol metabolic capacity, they might experience more side effects than beneficial effects from alcohol consumption and become less likely to drink alcohol. Unfortunately, there is little data exploring the association between genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism, alcohol consumption habits, and the risk of AF.</p><p id="Par14">This study aimed to verify whether the association between alcohol consumption habits and incident AF risk differs according to genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism, using a large prospective cohort from the UK Biobank.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Ethical statement and data availability</title><p id="Par15">This study was conducted in accordance with the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki and approved by the Institutional Review Board (IRB No. E-2203-005-1302). The need for informed consent was waived as anonymized data were used. For reasonable requests, data are available through approval and oversight by the UK Biobank. The UK Biobank has approval from the North West Multi-centre Research Ethics Committee as a Research Tissue Bank approval.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Data source and study population</title><p id="Par16">The UK Biobank is a large-scale prospective cohort study of approximately 500,000 volunteers enrolled from 2006 to 2010 in the UK. The detailed design and preliminary results have been published elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. In brief, the UK Biobank database includes individual demographic information, diagnostic history, and genomic data. All participants signed a written informed consent form, and the UK Biobank received ethical approval from the National Health Service Research Ethics Service (reference 11/NW/0382).</p><p id="Par17">The study design is illustrated in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. In total, 502,392 individuals enrolled between 2006 and 2010 were identified. Subjects with a history of AF before enrollment (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3650) were excluded. Moreover, individuals without valid genetic data (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 22,187) and those without valid answers to alcohol consumption questionnaires (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1061) were also excluded. Among these, we conducted this study among individuals in the white British population who self-reported as white British and were verified through principal component analysis of genetic ancestry. A final total of 399,329 individuals were included in this study and followed up until 2021. The index date was the baseline visit to the UK Biobank.<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Study population. Study design using data from UK Biobank</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12916_2023_3229_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Definitions of alcohol consumption habit and genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism</title><p id="Par18">Using the UK Biobank database, the average alcohol intake per day (g/day) was calculated to evaluate alcohol consumption, and the participants were subsequently categorized into non-drinkers, mild-to-moderate drinkers (&lt;30 g/day), and heavy drinkers (&#8805;30 g/day).</p><p id="Par19">Participants in the UK Biobank were genotyped using the Affymetrix UK Biobank Lung Exome Evaluation (UK BiLEVE) Axiom array or the Affymetrix UK Biobank Axiom array. As previously reported, the UK Biobank team performed central quality control and imputation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. To define genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism, we calculated polygenic risk score (PRS) as the sum of the single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP)&#8217;s allele dosages of risk-increasing alleles weighted by their reported log odds ratios. SNPs associated with alcohol metabolism were identified from an existing large genome-wide association study from European ancestry (Supplemental Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], which has been explored in other studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. To compare effect sizes corresponding to the continuous PRS, we transformed each PRS of the corresponding analytical data set to the standard normal distribution (Supplemental Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). According to the PRS, we stratified subjects into three groups based on tertiles: the low PRS tertile group implies a genetic predisposition of slower alcohol metabolism, while the high PRS tertile group implies a genetic predisposition of faster alcohol metabolism.
</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Definitions of covariates and the study endpoint</title><p id="Par20">Demographic data, anthropometric data, and medical history of hypertension, diabetes mellitus, myocardial infarction, dyslipidemia, chronic kidney disease, heart failure, and stroke were obtained. In addition, data on smoking history were collected. Smoking history was assessed using standardized questionnaires. Detailed definitions of comorbidities are provided in Supplemental Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>.
</p><p id="Par21">Newly diagnosed AF was defined as the study endpoint. The endpoint was defined based on ICD-10 codes (I48). The follow-up duration was defined as the interval between the index date and the occurrence of incident AF.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par22">Data are presented as numbers and frequencies for categorical variables and mean &#177; standard deviation or median with interquartile range for continuous variables. For categorical variables, the chi-square test or Fisher&#8217;s exact test was used as appropriate. One-way analysis of variance was used to analyze continuous variables between two or more groups. The annual event incidence rate (aIR) was calculated as the number of events per 1000 person-years (PY). Multivariate Cox proportional hazard regression models were used to estimate hazard ratios (HRs) and corresponding 95% confidence intervals (CIs) for the associations between genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism, real alcohol consumption habits, and the risk of incident AF. Variables that initially achieved <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.2 in the univariate Cox regression analysis or those with clinical relevance in terms of AF risks were included in a multivariable model (Supplemental Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>). The multivariable models were adjusted for covariates, including age, sex, previous history of hypertension, diabetes mellitus, myocardial infarction, dyslipidemia, chronic kidney disease, heart failure, stroke, and PRS tertile for alcohol metabolism or alcohol consumption habit, respectively. Subgroup analyses were conducted according to the PRS tertiles for alcohol metabolism and alcohol consumption habits using Cox models. The joint association was demonstrated, with individuals who had heavy drinking habits and low PRS tertile serving as the reference group. We further investigated whether the effects of genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism could be associated with the risks of incident AF across varying levels of alcohol consumption, using structural equation model (SEM) analysis. With SEM, we aimed to explore the complex association between genetic predisposition, alcohol consumption, and risks of incident AF. A two-sided <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value of &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. Statistical analyses were performed using R programming version 4.2.1 (The R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria). We manipulated the imputed genotype data and calculated the individual-level polygenic risk score using PLINK version 1.90 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cog-genomics.org/plink/">https://www.cog-genomics.org/plink/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Baseline characteristics of the study population</title><p id="Par23">In total, 399,329 individuals without previous history of AF (mean age 56.8 &#177; 8.0 years; men, 181,981 [45.6%]) were analyzed in this study. Hypertension was diagnosed in 104,879 individuals (26.3%), diabetes mellitus in 16,148 individuals (4.0%), myocardial infarction in 21,369 individuals (5.4%), dyslipidemia in 47,650 individuals (11.9%), chronic kidney disease in 16,695 individuals (4.2%), heart failure in 12,550 individuals (3.1%), and stroke in 8455 individuals (2.1%). More than half of the included participants were never smokers (54.7%), and approximately one-third were ex-smokers (35.0%).</p><p id="Par24">Based on alcohol consumption habits, individuals were classified into three groups: non-drinkers, mild-to-moderate drinkers, and heavy drinkers. The baseline characteristics of each group are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Heavy drinkers showed male preponderance, had a more frequent history of hypertension and dyslipidemia and substantially higher rates of smoking than non-drinkers and mild-to-moderate drinkers. They also showed a genetic predisposition to higher alcohol metabolism, as calculated by the PRS. In contrast, non-drinkers seemed to have a greater history of diabetes mellitus than other groups. The baseline characteristics classified by a genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism according to PRS are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Individuals with a higher PRS for alcohol metabolism tended to consume more alcohol.
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics according to alcohol consumption habit</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Non-drinkers (</bold><bold><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></bold><bold> = 114,528)</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Mild-to-moderate drinkers (</bold><bold><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></bold><bold> = 207,254)</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Heavy drinkers (</bold><bold><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></bold><bold> = 77,547)</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold><bold>-value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Demographic data</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Age, years</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.0&#177;8.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.9&#177;8.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.4&#177;79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Sex, %</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36,978 (32.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83,621 (40.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61,382 (79.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.2&#177;5.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.7&#177;4.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.8&#177;4.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Past medical history, %</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Hypertension</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32,398 (28.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48,433 (23.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24,048 (31.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Diabetes mellitus</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7014 (6.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5998 (2.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3336 (4.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Myocardial infarction</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6993 (6.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9237 (4.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5139 (6.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Dyslipidemia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,528 (12.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21,954 (10.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1168 (14.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Chronic kidney disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6791 (5.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7182 (3.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2722 (3.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Heart failure</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4528 (4.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5134 (2.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2888 (3.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Stroke</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2689 (2.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3823 (1.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1943 (2.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Physical examination</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;SBP, mmHg</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">137.0&#177;18.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">137.4&#177;18.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">142.8&#177;18.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;DBP, mmHg</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81.3&#177;10.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81.8&#177;9.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85.3&#177;10.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking, %</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Never smoker</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69,351 (60.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">120,481 (58.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28,467 (37.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Ex-smoker</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32,184 (28.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71,657 (34.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35,468 (46.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Current smoker</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12,514 (11.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,508 (7.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,056 (17.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PRS for alcohol use</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.011&#177;0.021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.012&#177;0.020</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.013&#177;0.019</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">BMI</italic> Body mass index, <italic toggle="yes">PRS</italic> Polygenic risk score, <italic toggle="yes">S(D)BP</italic> Systolic (diastolic) blood pressure</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics classified by genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism according to PRS</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Low tertile (</bold><bold><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></bold><bold> = 133,054)</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Middle tertile (</bold><bold><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></bold><bold> = 132,363)</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>High tertile (</bold><bold><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></bold><bold> = 133,912)</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold><bold>-value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Demographic data</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Age, years</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.9&#177;8.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.8&#177;8.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.8&#177;8.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.015</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Sex, %</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60,811(45.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60,469 (45.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60,701 (45.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.091</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.3&#177;4.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.4&#177;4.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.4&#177;4.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Past medical history, %</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Hypertension</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34,487 (25.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34,950 (26.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35,442 (26.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Diabetes mellitus</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5273 (4.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5340 (4.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5535 (4.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.081</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Myocardial infarction</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7010 (5.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6993 (5.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7366 (5.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Dyslipidemia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,740 (11.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,971 (12.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,939 (11.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.157</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Chronic kidney disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5644 (4.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5505 (4.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5546 (4.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.384</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Heart failure</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4132 (3.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4183 (3.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4235 (#.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.634</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Stroke</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2744 (2.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2836 (2.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2875 (2.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.233</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Physical examination</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;SBP, mmHg</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">138.2&#177;18.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">138.4&#177;18.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">138.4&#177;18.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;DBP, mmHg</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.2&#177;10.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.3&#177;10.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.4&#177;10.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking, %</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.169</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Never smoker</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72,788 (54.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72,298 (54.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73,213 (54.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Ex-smoker</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46,598 (35.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46,241 (35.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46,770 (35.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Current smoker</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,182 (9.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,388 (10.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,508 (10.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alcohol consumption, unit/day</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.1&#177;2.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.2&#177;2.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.3&#177;2.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">BMI</italic> Body mass index, <italic toggle="yes">PRS</italic> Polygenic risk score, <italic toggle="yes">S(D)BP</italic> Systolic (diastolic) blood pressure</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Predictive implication of a genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism and real alcohol consumption habit for incident AF</title><p id="Par25">During a median follow-up of 12.2 years (interquartile range, 11.5&#8211;12.8), there were 19,237 new cases of AF (4.0%). As shown in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, the aIRs of AF were 5.50, 4.73, and 6.90 per 1000 PY for non-drinkers, mild-to-moderate drinkers, and heavy drinkers, respectively. In the univariate analysis, mild-to-moderate drinkers were associated with a lower risk of AF (HR 0.89, 95% CI 0.86&#8211;0.92), but heavy drinkers were associated with an increased risk of AF (HR 1.12, 95% CI 1.08&#8211;1.16). After adjusting for covariates, mild-to-moderate drinkers showed a decreased risk of AF (HR 0.96, 95% CI 0.92&#8211;0.99), while heavy drinkers consistently showed a higher risk of AF (HR 1.06, 95% CI 1.02&#8211;1.10). When analyzed as a continuous variable, one alcohol unit increment per day was significantly related to an increased risk of AF (HR 1.01, 95% CI 1.01&#8211;1.02).
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Associations of alcohol consumption habit and PRS for alcohol metabolism with atrial fibrillation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Variables</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Total number</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Atrial fibrillation</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Incidence rates</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Unadjusted HR (95% CI)</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold><bold>-value</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Adjusted HR</bold><sup>a</sup><bold> (95% CI)</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold><bold>-value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Alcohol consumption habit</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Non-drinkers</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">114,528</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5640</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (reference)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (reference)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Mild-to-moderate drinkers</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">207,254</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8781</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.89 (0.86&#8211;0.92)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.96 (0.92&#8211;0.99)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Heavy drinkers</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77,547</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4816</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.90</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12 (1.08&#8211;1.16)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.06 (1.02&#8211;1.10)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Per 1 alcohol unit/day increment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02 (1.02&#8211;1.03)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.01 (1.01&#8211;1.02)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Low tertile</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">133,054</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6259</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (reference)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.837</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (reference)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.388</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Middle tertile</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">132,363</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6465</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.01 (0.98&#8211;1.05)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.01 (0.97&#8211;1.04)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;High tertile</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">133,912</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6513</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.42</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (0.97&#8211;1.04)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.99 (0.96&#8211;1.03)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Per 1 SD increment in PRS</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.01 (1.00&#8211;1.02)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.221</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 (0.99&#8211;1.02)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.551</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Follow-up duration was presented as person-years. Incidence rates were presented as per 1000 person-years</p><p><italic toggle="yes">CI</italic> Confidence interval, <italic toggle="yes">HR</italic> Hazard ratio, <italic toggle="yes">PRS</italic> Polygenic risk score, <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> Standard deviation</p><p><sup>a</sup>Adjusted for age, sex, previous history of hypertension, diabetes mellitus, myocardial infarction, dyslipidemia, chronic kidney disease, heart failure, stroke, and PRS tertile for alcohol metabolism or alcohol consumption habit, respectively</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par26">When individuals were stratified according to PRS tertiles, the aIRs of AF were 5.26, 5.45, and 5.42 per 1000 PY for the low, middle, and high tertiles, respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). In the univariate analysis, the middle tertile group (HR 1.01, 95% CI 0.98&#8211;1.05) and high tertile group (HR 1.00, 95% CI 0.97&#8211;1.04) had similar risks of incident AF compared to the low tertile group. Similarly, the risk of incident AF was consistently equivalent in the middle tertile group (HR 1.01, 95% CI 0.97&#8211;1.04) and high tertile group (HR 0.99, 95% CI 0.96&#8211;1.03) compared to the low tertile group in the multivariate analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Subgroup analyses for AF</title><p id="Par27">To determine whether the predicted risks of incident AF, based on real alcohol consumption habits, could be modified by a genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism, we performed a subgroup analysis according to PRS for alcohol metabolism (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). In the low PRS tertile group, mild-to-moderate drinkers showed similar risks of AF (HR 0.97, 95% CI 0.92&#8211;1.03), whereas heavy drinkers showed a higher AF (HR 1.10, 95% CI 1.02&#8211;1.18) than non-drinkers. In contrast, in the middle PRS tertile group, mild-to-moderate drinkers and heavy drinkers showed equivalent risks of AF (HR 0.95, 95% CI 0.90&#8211;1.01 and HR 1.06, 95% CI 0.99&#8211;1.14), compared to non-drinkers. Similar findings were observed in the high PRS tertile group; mild-to-moderate drinkers and heavy drinkers showed a similar risk of AF (HR 0.94, 95% CI 0.89&#8211;1.00 and HR 1.02, 95% CI 0.95&#8211;1.10) compared to non-drinkers. The subgroup analysis according to alcohol consumption habits is presented in Supplemental Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>. When we analyzed joint association across genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism and alcohol consumption habits, individuals in the low PRS tertile group appeared to be more susceptible to incident AF among drinkers (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). In SEM analysis, we found associations between genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism, alcohol consumption habits, and the risk of AF (Supplemental Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>) after assessment of the goodness-of-fit parameters indicated an adequate fir for this model (Supplemental Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>).<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Association between alcohol consumption habit and risks of incident AF according to genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism. Subgroup analysis according to PRS tertiles for alcohol metabolism was performed to determine whether the prognostic effect of alcohol consumption habits could be modified by genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism. AF, atrial fibrillation; CI, confidence interval; HR, hazard ratio; PRS, polygenic risk score. *Adjusted for age, sex, previous history of hypertension, diabetes mellitus, myocardial infarction, dyslipidemia, chronic kidney disease, heart failure, and stroke</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12916_2023_3229_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig><fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Joint association of alcohol consumption habits and tertiles of genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism with risks of incident AF. Individuals with heavy drinking habits and low PRS tertile served as the reference group for analysis. Hazard ratios with 95% confidence intervals are displayed as dot and whisker plots, adjusted for covariates. Covariates include age, sex, previous history of hypertension, diabetes mellitus, myocardial infarction, dyslipidemia, chronic kidney disease, heart failure, and stroke</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12916_2023_3229_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par28">This study investigated the differential association between actual alcohol consumption habits and incident AF based on genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism. The major findings are summarized as follows (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>): First, when the PRS for alcohol metabolism was calculated, there was a significant correlation between genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism and real alcohol consumption habits. Second, there was significant association between risks of alcohol consumption habits and risks of incident AF. Third, there was no difference in risks of incident AF across PRS tertiles (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.221). Fourth, there was a significant interaction between alcohol consumption habits and genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism for incident AF (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction &lt;0.001).<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Summarizing illustration. Schematic diagram depicting the association between genetic and acquired traits for alcohol consumption and risks of AF. AF, atrial fibrillation</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO4" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12916_2023_3229_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par29">As the number of elderly people increases, the prevalence of AF, the most common clinical arrhythmia, is increasing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Since AF is not only a debilitating disease but also could cause comorbidities such as stroke, dementia, and heart failure, there is a demand for effective prevention strategies to mitigate the disease burden. There have been numerous efforts to unveil the association between unhealthy lifestyle behaviors and risks of incident AF, enabling the identification of correctable AF risk factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Alcohol consumption is prevalent worldwide and is an important issue in lifestyle behavior modification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. A previous study reported that approximately 5% of deaths worldwide could be attributable to alcohol consumption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Due to the detrimental relationship between alcohol consumption and health problems, the association between alcohol consumption and cardiovascular diseases has been studied over the past several decades.</p><p id="Par30">Interestingly, the association between alcohol consumption and cardiovascular diseases is complex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. There are reports that mild alcohol consumption might be beneficial to coronary artery disease and heart failure while excessive alcohol consumption could cause grave prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. An anti-inflammatory effect and improved insulin sensitivity from small quantities of alcohol consumption were provided as plausible explanations for the aforementioned J-shaped associations between alcohol consumption and cardiovascular diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Our study, based on the UK biobank database, also showed nonlinear associations between alcohol consumption and risks of incident AF, as presented in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. Indeed, the association between alcohol consumption and the risk of incident AF remains controversial. Notably, previous studies have reported either a J-shaped association or linear association between alcohol consumption and the risk of AF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Several studies utilizing Mendelian Randomization have demonstrated that even mild-to-moderate alcohol consumption could increase the risk of cardiovascular diseases, including AF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. However, a nonlinear Mendelian Randomization study has also shown that the increase in risk within the range of mild-to-moderate drinking is minimal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Taken together, the complex association between alcohol consumption and cardiovascular diseases still remains inconclusive and demands further investigation. Meanwhile, we attempted to explore whether the genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism might influence the association between alcohol consumption and AF risks; we found that there could be individuals who are more susceptible to AF from the same level of alcohol consumption.</p><p id="Par31">Alcohol, especially ethanol, is a substance in alcoholic beverages and is mainly metabolized in the liver [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Alcohol metabolism is known to be significantly influenced by genetic factors, including genetic polymorphisms of alcohol dehydrogenase and aldehyde dehydrogenase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Previous studies have reported that genetic polymorphisms in alcohol metabolism are associated with altered levels of acetaldehyde and differential responses to unpleasant experiences after alcohol consumption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], resulting in increased or decreased susceptibility to habitual alcohol consumption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. This suggests genetically decreased alcohol metabolism may result in higher acetaldehyde levels, even after drinking small amounts of alcohol, and could cause flushing syndrome increasing the risk of incident AF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. In our data, individuals in the low PRS tertile group showed the lowest alcohol consumption. In contrast, the high PRS tertile group showed the highest alcohol consumption (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Considering the importance of genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism and actual alcohol consumption habits, we designed this study to explore the differential predictive relationship of alcohol metabolism according to genetic background. The authors hypothesized that the genetic predisposition to metabolize alcohol could differentiate an individual&#8217;s susceptibility to complications and benefits associated with alcohol consumption. If someone has low levels of alcohol metabolic capacity, they might experience relatively more side effects and fewer beneficial effects from alcohol consumption compared to those with high levels of alcohol metabolic capacity. Using the UK Biobank database, we found that the predicted risk of incident AF according to of alcohol consumption differed based on genetic background stratified by PRS tertiles (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), which was in line with our hypothesis. Although the genetic ability to metabolize alcohol and/or alcohol metabolites itself was not associated with risks of increased AF as in our report as well as a previous study,<sup>22</sup> genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism could alter the relationship between alcohol consumption habits and risks of AF.</p><p id="Par32">To the best of our knowledge, this study is the first to show comprehensive relationships between genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism, alcohol consumption habits, and risk of incident AF in a sizable cohort with long-term follow-up. This study had two strengths. The UK Biobank is a large population-based prospective cohort study with genotype data. The authors acknowledge that a randomized controlled trial is the best to verify the hypothesis, and an ethical issue could not be avoided in a trial demanding alcohol metabolism. Therefore, a well-designed and well-controlled observational study could be an optimal alternative and provide valuable information. Second, as results of quality control regarding genotype data in the UK Biobank have been reported elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], we could explore comprehensive association between genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism, alcohol consumption habits, and risks of AF with reliable genetic databases.</p><p id="Par33">This study has several limitations. First, alcohol consumption habits might have been altered from baseline during follow-up, for which information was not available. Second, since the study included only individuals in the UK, it is uncertain whether this study could be extrapolated to other ethnicities and countries. However, this large population-based study enabled use of a notably large number of subjects with long-term follow-up, effectively reflecting the phenomenon observed in real-world practice. Additionally, we employed stepwise selections to identify significant confounders, a method that could not exclude the possibility of collider bias during the analysis. Finally, in this study, newly diagnosed AF was defined as the study endpoint based on ICD-10 codes. While continuous ECG monitoring for each individual could potentially detect more cases of AF, it was not feasible in this retrospective cohort study due to its observational nature.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par34">In this large nationwide study using a prospective registry, we found associations between alcohol consumption habits and incident AF differed according to the genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism; authors found that PRS might help identify individuals who are more susceptible to developing incident AF than others. Alcohol consumption of more than 30 g/day was associated with increased risks of incident AF in the low PRS tertile group, but the significance was attenuated in the middle/high PRS tertile group. Therefore, alcohol consumption might be more harmful among those with a genetic predisposition to low alcohol metabolism. These findings highlight the importance of assessing genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism for risk prediction and emphasize the significance of tailored preventive strategies for AF.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><sec id="Sec14"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12916_2023_3229_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1:</bold>&#160;<bold>Supplemental Figure 1.</bold> Distribution of Polygenic risk score for alcohol metabolism PRS, polygenic risk score. <bold>Supplemental Table 1.</bold> A list of 10 SNPs known to be associated with alcohol metabolism. <bold>Supplemental Table 2.</bold> Definitions of comorbidities and outcomes. <bold>Supplemental Table 3.</bold> Univariable Cox-proportional hazard regression analysis for overall subjects and for white British subjects. <bold>Supplemental Table 4.</bold> Associations of PRS for alcohol metabolism and atrial fibrillation across alcohol consumption habits. <bold>Supplemental Table 5.</bold> Structural equation models for alcohol consumption, genetic predisposition to alcohol metabolism, and atrial fibrillation. <bold>Supplemental Table 6.</bold> The statistical fit of structural equation models.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AF</term><def><p id="Par6">Atrial fibrillation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>aIR</term><def><p id="Par7">Annual incidence rate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p id="Par8">Confidence interval</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HR</term><def><p id="Par9">Hazard ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PRS</term><def><p id="Par10">Polygenic risk score</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SNP</term><def><p id="Par11">Single nucleotide polymorphism</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>None.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>CSP contributed to the conception and design of the work, data interpretation, data analysis, and drafting of the manuscript. SO contributed to the conception, design, data acquisition, data interpretation, and critical revision of the manuscript. JC and SHK contributed to the data acquisition, data interpretation, data analysis, and critical revision of the manuscript. JMC, K-YL, H-JA, SK, S-RL, and E-KC contributed to the conception and design of the work and critically revised the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by grant no. 04-2022-2260 from the SNUH Research Fund.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>UKB data are available in a public, open access repository. This research has been conducted using the UK Biobank Resource under Application Number 91312. The UK Biobank data are available on application to the UK Biobank (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ukbiobank.ac.uk/">www.ukbiobank.ac.uk/</ext-link>). For reasonable requests, data are available through approval and oversight by the UK Biobank.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par35">The UK Biobank has approval from the North West Multi-centre Research Ethics Committee as a Research Tissue Bank approval. All participants signed informed consent. This study was conducted in accordance with the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki and approved by the Institutional Review Board of the Seoul National University Hospital (IRB No. E-2203-005-1302). The need for informed consent was waived as anonymized data were used.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par36">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par37">EKC received research grants from Bayer, BMS/Pfizer, Biosense Webster, Chong Kun Dang, Daiichi-Sankyo, Samjinpharm, Sanofi-Aventis, Seers Technology, Skylabs, and Yuhan.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chugh</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Havmoeller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Narayanan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Worldwide epidemiology of atrial fibrillation: a Global Burden of Disease 2010 Study</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2014</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>837</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.113.005119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24345399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4151302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adderley</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nirantharakumar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and treatment of atrial fibrillation in UK general practice from 2000 to 2016</article-title><source>Heart</source><year>2019</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/heartjnl-2018-312977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29991504</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsao</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aday</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Almarzooq</surname><given-names>ZI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Heart disease and stroke statistics-2022 update: a report from the American Heart Association</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2022</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>e153</fpage><lpage>e639</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIR.0000000000001052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35078371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lip</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nieuwlaat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pisters</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crijns</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Refining clinical risk stratification for predicting stroke and thromboembolism in atrial fibrillation using a novel risk factor-based approach: the euro heart survey on atrial fibrillation</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>2010</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.09-1584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19762550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hindricks</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Potpara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dagres</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>2020 ESC Guidelines for the diagnosis and management of atrial fibrillation developed in collaboration with the European Association for Cardio-Thoracic Surgery (EACTS): The Task Force for the diagnosis and management of atrial fibrillation of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) Developed with the special contribution of the European Heart Rhythm Association (EHRA) of the ESC</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><year>2021</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehaa612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32860505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colilla</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petkun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimates of current and future incidence and prevalence of atrial fibrillation in the U.S. adult population</article-title><source>Am J Cardiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>1142</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjcard.2013.05.063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23831166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krijthe</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Projections on the number of individuals with atrial fibrillation in the European Union, from 2000 to 2060</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><year>2013</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>2746</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/eht280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23900699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3858024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asad</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Javed</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Korantzopoulos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stavrakis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Obesity is associated with incident atrial fibrillation independent of gender: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jce.13458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29443438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aune</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schlesinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norat</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riboli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tobacco smoking and the risk of atrial fibrillation: a systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective studies</article-title><source>Eur J Prev Cardiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1437</fpage><lpage>1451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2047487318780435</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29996680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qureshi</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alirhayim</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blaha</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardiorespiratory fitness and risk of incident atrial fibrillation: results from the Henry Ford Exercise Testing (FIT) Project</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2015</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>1827</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.114.014833</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25904645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kyung</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Physical activity changes and the risk of incident atrial fibrillation in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus: a nationwide longitudinal follow-up cohort study of 1.8 million subjects</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2023</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>434</fpage><lpage>440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc22-1655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36469745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lifestyle is associated with atrial fibrillation development in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>4676</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-84307-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33633333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7907194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitman</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nah</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alcohol abuse and cardiac disease</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2016.10.048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28057245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5226115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goncalves</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Claggett</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jhund</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alcohol consumption and risk of heart failure: the atherosclerosis risk in communities study</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><year>2015</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>939</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehu514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25602025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4481602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Voskoboinik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prabhu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kistler</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol and atrial fibrillation: a sobering review</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>2567</fpage><lpage>2576</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2016.08.074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27931615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Csengeri</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sprunker</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Castelnuovo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alcohol consumption, cardiac biomarkers, and risk of atrial fibrillation and adverse outcomes</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><year>2021</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>1170</fpage><lpage>1177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehaa953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33438022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7982286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Castelnuovo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costanzo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonaccio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Moderate alcohol consumption is associated with lower risk for heart failure but not atrial fibrillation</article-title><source>JACC Heart Fail</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>837</fpage><lpage>844</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jchf.2017.08.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29032141</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hendriks</surname><given-names>JML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alcohol and incident atrial fibrillation - A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Int J Cardiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>246</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijcard.2017.05.133</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28867013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polimanti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transancestral GWAS of alcohol dependence reveals common genetic underpinnings with psychiatric disorders</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2018</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1656</fpage><lpage>1669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41593-018-0275-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30482948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6430207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goedde</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aldehyde dehydrogenase deficiency as cause of facial flushing reaction to alcohol in Japanese</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1981</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>982</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(81)91172-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6117742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yukawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Combination of ADH1B*2/ALDH2*2 polymorphisms alters acetaldehyde-derived DNA damage in the blood of Japanese alcoholics</article-title><source>Cancer Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>1651</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1349-7006.2012.02360.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22703580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7659228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoshiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of the ALDH2 variant on the prevalence of atrial fibrillation in habitual drinkers</article-title><source>JACC Asia</source><year>2022</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacasi.2021.10.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36340257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9627901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sudlow</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallacher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>UK biobank: an open access resource for identifying the causes of a wide range of complex diseases of middle and old age</article-title><source>PLoS Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e1001779</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25826379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4380465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bycroft</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petkova</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The UK Biobank resource with deep phenotyping and genomic data</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2018</year><volume>562</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-018-0579-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30305743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6786975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>KX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rijsdijk</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagenaars</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Studying individual risk factors for self-harm in the UK Biobank: a polygenic scoring and Mendelian randomisation study</article-title><source>PLoS Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>e1003137</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32479557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7263593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tellier</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vattikuti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Second-generation PLINK: rising to the challenge of larger and richer datasets</article-title><source>Gigascience.</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13742-015-0047-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25722852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4342193</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in alcohol consumption: United States, 2001&#8211;2002 to 2012&#8211;2013</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source><year>2015</year><volume>148</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2014.12.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25620731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4330106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noh</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The prevalence of and factors associated with high-risk alcohol consumption in Korean adults: the 2009&#8211;2011 Korea National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e0175299</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0175299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28384270</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5383276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization. Management of Substance Abuse Team</collab></person-group><source>Global status report on alcohol and health</source><year>2014</year><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">O&#8217;Keefe JH, Bybee KA, Lavie CJ. Alcohol and cardiovascular health: the razor-sharp double-edged sword. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2007;50:1009&#8211;14.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jacc.2007.04.089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17825708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glynn</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ridker</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol consumption and plasma concentration of C-reactive protein</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2003</year><volume>107</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.0000045669.16499.EC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12551869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenfield</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samaras</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chisholm</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beneficial postprandial effect of a small amount of alcohol on diabetes and cardiovascular risk factors: modification by insulin resistance</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2005</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.2004-1511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15522927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Millwood</surname><given-names>IY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Conventional and genetic evidence on alcohol and vascular disease aetiology: a prospective study of 500 000 men and women in China</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2019</year><volume>393</volume><fpage>1831</fpage><lpage>1842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)31772-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30955975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6497989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michaelsson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol consumption and cardiovascular disease: a Mendelian Randomization study</article-title><source>Circ Genom Precis Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e002814</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCGEN.119.002814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32367730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7299220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Biddinger</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emdin</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of habitual alcohol intake with risk of cardiovascular disease</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2022</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e223849</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.3849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35333364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8956974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edenberg</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foroud</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics of alcoholism</article-title><source>Handb Clin Neurol</source><year>2014</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>561</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-444-62619-6.00032-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25307596</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalayasiri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide meta-analysis of alcohol use disorder in East Asians</article-title><source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source><year>2022</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1791</fpage><lpage>1797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41386-022-01265-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35094024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9372033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of acetaldehyde dehydrogenase 2 rs671 polymorphism with the occurrence and progression of atrial fibrillation</article-title><source>Front Cardiovasc Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1027000</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcvm.2022.1027000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36426220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9679000</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>