<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Drugs Aging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Drugs Aging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">365</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">springeropen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Drugs &amp; Aging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1170-229X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1969</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Springer</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10769917</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10769917.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10769917</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10769917</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38114724</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40266-023-01085-7</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1085</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Do Proton Pump Inhibitors Reduce Upper Gastrointestinal Bleeding in Older Patients with Atrial Fibrillation Treated with Oral Anticoagulants? A Nationwide Cohort Study in France</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6758-1901</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Drusch</surname><given-names initials="S">Solene</given-names></name><address><email>solene.drusch@outlook.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names initials="A">Anke</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Michelon</surname><given-names initials="H">Hugues</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>P&#233;pin</surname><given-names initials="M">Marion</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zureik</surname><given-names initials="M">Mahmoud</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herr</surname><given-names initials="M">Marie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02nt00p03</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.512012.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0005 0375 6417</institution-id><institution>EPI-PHARE, Epidemiology of Health Products (French National Agency for Medicines and Health Products Safety, and French National Health Insurance), </institution></institution-wrap>Saint-Denis, France </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Anti-Infective Evasion and Pharmacoepidemiology, University of Paris-Saclay, UVSQ, Inserm, Montigny-le-Bretonneux, France </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.460789.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 4910 6535</institution-id><institution>Pharmacy Department, Sainte-P&#233;rine Hospital, GHU AP-HP, </institution><institution>University of Paris-Saclay, </institution></institution-wrap>Paris, France </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.460789.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 4910 6535</institution-id><institution>Geriatrics Department, Ambroise Par&#233; Hospital, GHU AP-HP, </institution><institution>University of Paris-Saclay, </institution></institution-wrap>Boulogne-Billancourt, France </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Clinical Epidemiology, University of Paris-Saclay, UVSQ, Inserm, Villejuif, France </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.460789.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 4910 6535</institution-id><institution>Epidemiology and Public Health department, Raymond Poincar&#233; Hospital, GHU AP-HP, </institution><institution>University of Paris-Saclay, </institution></institution-wrap>Garches, France </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>41</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">452691</issue-id><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>07</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-01-29 23:25:10.630"><day>29</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="40266_2023_Article_1085.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Proton pump inhibitors (PPIs) are largely used in older adults and data are needed in off-label indications, such as the prevention of upper gastrointestinal bleeding (UGIB) in patients receiving oral anticoagulants (OACs). This study aimed to assess whether PPIs reduce the risk of UGIB in patients initiating oral anticoagulation.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">We conducted a longitudinal study based on the French national health database. The study population included 109,693 patients aged 75&#8211;110 years with a diagnosis of atrial fibrillation who initiated OACs [vitamin K antagonist (VKA) or direct OAC&#160;(DOAC)] between 2012 and 2016. We used multivariable Cox models weighted by inverse of probability of treatment to estimate the adjusted hazard ratio (aHR) of UGIB between PPI users and nonusers over a 6- and 12-month follow-up.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">PPI users represented 23% of the study population (28% among VKA initiators and 17% among DOAC initiators). The mean age (83 &#177; 5.3 years) and proportion of women (near 60%) were similar between groups. The risk of UGIB in the first 6 months after initiation of OAC decreased by 20% in PPI users compared with PPI nonusers [aHR<sub>6 months</sub> = 0.80, 95% confidence interval (CI) 0.65&#8211;0.98], but was not significantly modified when the follow-up was extended to 12 months (aHR<sub>12 months</sub> = 0.90, 95% CI 0.76&#8211;1.07), with a stronger effect among patients treated with vitamin K antagonists (aHR<sub>6 months</sub> = 0.73, 95% CI 0.58&#8211;0.93; aHR<sub>12 months</sub> = 0.81, 95% CI 0.67&#8211;0.99).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">This study suggests that PPIs were associated with reduced risk of gastrointestinal bleeding after initiation of oral anticoagulation in older patients with atrial fibrillation, particularly within 6 months after initiation of an antivitamin K antagonist.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1007/s40266-023-01085-7.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100007543</institution-id><institution>Agence Nationale de S&#233;curit&#233; du m&#233;dicament et des produits de sant&#233;</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2019S008</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Drusch</surname><given-names>Solene</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="d32e258"><title>Key Points</title><p id="Par5">
<table-wrap id="Taba" position="float" orientation="portrait"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Observational studies show that proton pump inhibitors (PPIs) are often used off-label, particularly for preventing upper gastrointestinal bleeding (UGIB) in older patients treated with oral anticoagulants (OACs). Evidence is needed to support their use in this indication, as it could help reduce drug adverse events and health care costs.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">We compare the risk of UGIB between PPI users and nonusers among more than 100,000 French older adults with atrial fibrillation who initiated an OAC treatment between 2012 and 2016.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The risk of UGIB decreased by 20% in the first 6 months after initiation of OAC in PPI users compared with PPI nonusers. The risk reduction was no longer significant when the follow-up was extended to 12 months.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">In subgroup analyses by type of OAC, the protective effects of PPIs persisted in vitamin k antagonist initiators but not in direct OAC initiators.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par6">Proton pump inhibitors (PPIs, such as pantoprazole, esomeprazole, omeprazole, lansoprazole, and rabeprazole) are drugs indicated for the treatment and prevention of peptic ulcer and gastroesophageal reflux diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The efficacy and safety of short-term use of PPIs, as well as the introduction of generics drugs, have contributed to the increase in PPI use over the past 2&#160;decades [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. However, misuse (inappropriate duration of use) and overuse of PPIs (prescription in the absence of validated indication) have been reported in many countries. In the UK, a quarter of PPI users were still treated 12 months after initiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In Ireland, long-term PPI use (&#8805; 8 weeks) in older adults increased from 4.1 to 35.5% between 1997 and 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. In France, a study based on the French national health database showed that among more than 1.5 million adults aged 65 years or older who initiated a PPI in 2015, indication was off-label for 22.2% of them [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. In addition to avoidable health care costs, PPIs misuse raises a safety issue, as adverse drug reactions have been reported for long-term use such as <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium difficile</italic> infection, community acquired pneumonia, hypomagnesia, vitamin B12 deficiency, fracture, and sarcopenia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. As a consequence, the prescription of PPIs for more than 8 weeks without justification was added to the criteria of potentially inappropriate prescriptions of the Beers and STOPP lists in 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], hence reinforcing the need to rationalize PPI prescriptions in older adults.</p><p id="Par7">Atrial fibrillation is the most common arrhythmia with 37.6 million people affected worldwide in 2017, with age being the main risk factor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. OAC treatment for atrial fibrillation is a lifelong therapy with a high risk of bleeding, particularly in case of peptic ulcer disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Coprescription of PPIs with an oral anticoagulant (OAC) treatment for the prevention of upper gastrointestinal bleeding (UGIB) is a frequent off-label indication for PPI use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. In France, data from the national health database indicated that 15% of PPI dispensing was related to the initiation of OAC or antiplatelet treatment in people aged over 65 years in 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Another French study conducted in a geriatrics ward in 2016&#8211;2017 also reported this indication as the main reason for off-label prescribing of PPIs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Furthermore, an Irish study found that OAC or antiplatelet treatment was the main factor associated with long-term use and high dosage of PPI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">Although the prevention of UGIB in patients treated with OAC treatment is not a validated indication of PPIs, previous observational studies have suggested the added value of PPIs to prevent UGIB in this indication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. However, the Cardiovascular Outcomes for People Using Anticoagulant Strategies (COMPASS) clinical trial did not confirm that pantoprazole could reduce the risk of UGIB in patients taking rivaroxaban and/or aspirin (HR = 0.88, 95% CI 0.67&#8211;1.15; mean age of study population: 67.6 &#177; 8.1 years) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">In 2020, the French National Health Authority (HAS) reviewed the indications of PPIs and considered that there may be a benefit to prescribe the PPIs with OACs to prevent UGIB in patients at risk of digestive complications, but further data were needed to support this indication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. In the context of massive utilization of PPIs in older adults and uncertainty of their benefit in coprescription with OACs, we aimed to conduct a large-scale study based on the data from the French national health database to assess whether prescribing a PPI in patients initiating an OAC for atrial fibrillation effectively decreased the risk of UGIB.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec4"><title>Data Sources</title><p id="Par10">This study is based on the French national health database [<italic toggle="yes">Syst&#232;me National des Donn&#233;es de Sant&#233;</italic> (SNDS)], which has been widely used for epidemiological studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], including for studies involving patients with atrial fibrillation initiating OACs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. A complete description of the database is available in previous publications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Briefly, a unique anonymous individual identifier links information from the outpatient care database [DCIR (<italic toggle="yes">Donn&#233;es de Consommation Inter-R&#233;gime</italic>)] and hospital care database [PMSI (<italic toggle="yes">Programme de M&#233;dicalisation des Syst&#232;mes d&#8217;information</italic>)]. The DCIR database includes outpatient medical care reimbursement, including drugs coded according to the Anatomic Therapeutic Chemical (ATC) classification, status with respect to full reimbursement of care for a severe long-term disease, coded using the International Classification of Disease, tenth revision (ICD-10), as well as demographic information (age, sex, and date of death). The PMSI database includes all hospital diagnosis discharges, recorded using the ICD-10 classification, and medical procedures.</p><p id="Par11">The data access permission policy prohibits making the data set publicly available.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Study Population</title><p id="Par12">We conducted a longitudinal study on patients aged 75&#8211;110 years old, diagnosed with atrial fibrillation, and initiating an OAC treatment (no dispensing in the previous 2 years), either vitamin-K antagonist (VKA) or direct oral anticoagulant (DOAC), between April 2012 and 2016 (inclusion date). The 75-year threshold used to define our study population was defined in line with previous studies and recommendations concerning medication use in older people in France [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].&#160;We restricted the study population to people affiliated with the French general health insurance scheme for at least 5 years at inclusion so that we could assess medical history. Atrial fibrillation was defined according to previous studies conducted on the SNDS (see Supplementary Methods for definition) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Patients with contraindications to the use of OACs were excluded (see Supplementary Methods for exclusion criteria). In addition, patients who had received a PPI within 3 months prior to OAC initiation were excluded.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Exposure and Outcome Definitions</title><p id="Par13">The exposure to PPI was defined as the reimbursement of at least one of the following ATC codes within the 14 days following inclusion: A02BC05, A02BC03, A02BC01, A02BC02, or A02BC04.</p><p id="Par14">The outcome event was the occurrence of hospitalization for UGIB according to the following ICD-10 codes during the follow-up period (any diagnostic position in the hospital record): K250, K52, K254, K256, K260, K262, K264, K266, K270, K272, K274, K276, K280, K282, K284, K286, K290, K920, K921, or I850 (see Supplementary Table 1 for details about the codes). Melena has an upper gastrointestinal predominant origin, but it can also have a lower origin. To reduce the risk of identifying cases of lower gastrointestinal origin, we considered the diagnosis code K921 in the outcome definition unless the diagnosis code K625 (anus or rectum bleeding) was also recorded for the same hospitalization.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Covariates</title><p id="Par15">Covariates assessed at baseline included sociodemographic characteristics (age, sex, and quintile of deprivation index&#8212;a combination of four socioeconomic variables at the smallest administrative unit in France), 5-year medical history (cardiovascular, neurodegenerative, epilepsy or psychiatric diseases, diabetes, chronic kidney disease, liver disease, cancer, coagulation abnormalities, and hemorrhage), and drug exposure in the 4 months before inclusion (antihypertensive drugs, lipid-lowering agents, oral corticosteroids, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, antiplatelet agents, anxiolytics and hypnotics, and analgesics). Concomitant dispensing of drugs that increase the risk of bleeding, namely nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, heparin and antiplatelet agent, and the total number of different ATC codes (0&#8211;4/5 to 9/10 drugs or more) at OAC initiation were also considered. The individual risk of bleeding was assessed using a version of the HAS-BLED score adapted for use in the French national health database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Follow-Up</title><p id="Par16">In PPI users, the follow-up started on the first date of PPI dispensing within the 14-day period following OAC initiation (index date). This time window was chosen to include patients who had been prescribed a PPI by another physician in the days following OAC initiation. In PPI nonusers, the index date was randomly defined over this 14-day period so that the distribution of time between OAC initiation and index date was similar between PPI users and nonusers.</p><p id="Par17">Patients were followed for 12 months or until the occurrence of UGIB, death, discontinuation of OAC treatment (defined as at least 3 months without OAC dispensing), or switch from a VKA to a DOAC and vice-versa (only for analyses by type of OAC), whichever came first. The time scale was time since start of follow-up (in days).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Analyses</title><p id="Par18">Cox proportional hazard models were used to estimate hazard ratios (HR) of UGIB between PPI users and nonusers. Different models have been implemented to progressively control for confounding and indication bias: a first model without adjustment to assess the crude association, a second model adjusted for confounders by multivariable Cox regression, and a final and main model controlling for indication bias by inverse probability of treatment weighting (IPTW) adjustment, including weight stabilization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. All above mentioned covariates were used for adjustment. The distribution of stabilized weights was analyzed to test the positivity assumption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The balance of covariates between the PPI users and nonusers before and after weighting was assessed by measuring the standardized mean difference. We conducted two parallel analyses, the first with an end of follow-up at 6 months, at the latest, and the second at 12 months. We explored two end-of-follow-up periods, as the risk of bleeding is higher at OAC treatment initiation, especially for VKA, which may require dosage adjustment. In addition, the HR estimate is a weighted average of all instantaneous risks over the study period. Estimating the HR over a shorter period allow us to test for potential variation of the effect over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>].</p><p id="Par19">In addition to the semiparametric approach of the Cox model, Kaplan&#8211;Meier cumulative incidence curves of UGIB adjusted for IPTW were also estimated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Bootstraping based on the standard deviation method was used to calculate the 95% confidence interval (200 replications).</p><p id="Par20">To assess the effect of PPIs by sociodemographic variables and risk of UGIB, we repeated the 6-month analysis in the following subgroups: sex, age categories (75&#8211;89 years and &#8805; 90 years), HAS-BLED score (score 1 to 2 and score &#8805; 3), year of inclusion, and exposition to an antiplatelet agent at baseline.</p><p id="Par21">Several sensitivity analyses were performed. First, we introduced an additional censoring event at PPI discontinuation in the exposed group and at PPI initiation in the unexposed group. In this analysis, we additionally weighted by the inverse of the probability of censoring for PPI discontinuation or initiation, respectively (IPTCW), using all baseline covariates and spline terms for modeling time trends in censuring [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Second, to assess the specificity of the effect of PPIs on UGIB, analyses were repeated with nongastrointestinal bleeding as the outcome. The ICD-10 codes used to define nongastrointestinal bleeding are detailed in Supplementary Table 1. Other sensitivity analyses included: (1) defining PPI use based on the drugs dispensed on the same day as OAC initiation (versus within 14 days in the main analysis), (2) excluding patients with at least one PPI dispensation within 6 months before inclusion (versus 3 months in the main analysis), and (3) considering death as a competing risk to estimate the cumulative incidence curves and the risk for UGIB.</p><p id="Par22">Analyses were performed using SAS, version 9.4 software (SAS Institute, Inc).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Results</title><p id="Par23">The selection of the study population is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Between April 2012 and December 2016, 196,275 individuals aged 75&#8211;110 years affiliated with the general schemes and with a diagnosis of atrial fibrillation initiated an OAC treatment. Among them, we excluded 18,824 individuals who had a contraindication to OAC use and an additional 67,585 individuals who received at least one PPI dispensation in the 3 months before OAC initiation. In the end, the study population included 109,693 subjects. Of these, 53.6% initiated a VKA (mostly fluindione) and 46.4% a DOAC (mostly rivaroxaban; see Supplementary Table 2 for the details of the OACs).<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Study population selection, patients with atrial fibrillation initiating an oral anticoagulant (OAC) treatment between April 2012 and December 2016 [French national health database (SNDS), France]</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40266_2023_1085_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par24">As described in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, PPI users represented 23% of the study population (28% among VKA initiators and 17% among DOAC initiators). The mean age (83 &#177; 5.3 years) and proportion of women (near 60%) were similar between PPI users and nonusers. Overall, PPI users had chronic diseases, including cardiovascular diseases, more frequently than PPI nonusers, particularly among VKA initiators. PPI users had a higher risk of bleeding according to the HAS-BLED score and were more exposed to antiplatelet agents (28% of PPI users and 10% of PPI nonusers) at OAC initiation (see Supplementary Table 3 for information on prior treatments). The mean duration of follow-up for PPI users was 266 &#177; 123 days and 284 &#177; 117 days for PPI nonusers (see Supplementary Table 4 for information on follow-up duration and censoring events).<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of patients with atrial fibrillation initiating an oral anticoagulant treatment between April 2012 and December 2016, according to proton pump inhibitor (PPI) exposure [French national health database (SNDS), France]</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Vitamin K antagonist<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 58,824)</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Direct oral anticoagulant<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 50,869)</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">All oral anticoagulants<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 109,693)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PPI nonusers</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PPI users<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PPI nonusers</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PPI users<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PPI nonusers</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PPI users<sup>a</sup></th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 42,197) (72%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 16,627) (28%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 42,042) (83%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 8827) (17%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 84,239) (77%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 25,454) (23%)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sociodemographic characteristics</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Year of inclusion</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;2012</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;2013</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;2014</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;2015</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (years, mean &#177; sd)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.1 &#177; 5.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83.5 &#177; 5.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.4 &#177; 5.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.8 &#177; 5.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83.2 &#177; 5.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83.3 &#177; 5.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;75&#8211;79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;80&#8211;84</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;85&#8211;89</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;90&#8211;94</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#8805; 95</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Women</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Quintile of social deprivation index</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;1 (less deprived)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;5 (most deprived)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Unknown</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chronic diseases</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Heart failure</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Myocardial infarction</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Ischemic heart disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Arrhythmia (other than atrial fibrillation)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Vascular disease, stroke</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Epilepsy or mental illness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Diabetes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Dementia or Parkinson&#8217;s disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Chronic kidney disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Cancer (within the last year)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Hepatic diseases</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Anemia, purpura, coagulopathy or other bleeding conditions (within the last year)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Bleeding (within the last 5 years)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HAS-BLED score</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Low risk (1&#8211;2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Medium risk (3&#8211;4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;High risk (&#8805; 5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Treatments at initiation of OAC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of medications</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#8805; 5 drugs</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#8805; 10 drugs</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs or antirheumatic agents</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Antiplatelet agents</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Anticoagulants, injectable</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;Serotonin and noradrenaline reuptake inhibitors</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>PPI users if at least one dispensation of PPI within 14 days of OAC initiation</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par25">Cumulative incidence curves adjusted for IPTW show that the incidence of UGIB was slightly lower in PPI users compared with PPI nonusers (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), with a greater difference in VKA initiators than in DOAC initiators. Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> presents the number of events, crude incidence of UGIB, and its association with PPI exposure. During the 12-month follow-up 1141 UGIB events occurred, of which two-thirds occurred during the first 6 months. The unadjusted Cox model showed an increased risk of UGIB in PPI users compared with PPI nonusers, regardless of the duration of follow-up and type of OAC. After adjustment for the covariates, the association was reversed: PPI use was associated with a significantly lower risk of UGIB in the 6 months after OAC initiation (aHR<sub>6 months</sub> = 0.82, 95% CI 0.69&#8211;0.98), with no significant effect when follow-up ended at 12 months. Weighting on IPTW enabled to balance the covariates frequency between PPI users and nonusers (see Supplementary Fig. 1). In the Cox model with IPTW, PPI use remained associated with a lower risk of UGIB in the 6-month follow-up analysis (aHR<sub>6 months</sub> = 0.80, 95% CI 0.65&#8211;0.98), without significant effect in the 12-month follow-up analysis (aHR<sub>12 months</sub> = 0.90, 95% CI 0.76&#8211;1.07). The risk of UGIB was significantly decreased in VKA initiators (aHR<sub>6 months</sub> = 0.73, 95% CI 0.58&#8211;0.93; aHR<sub>12 months</sub> = 0.81, 95% CI 0.67&#8211;0.99) but not in DOAC initiators (aHR<sub>6 months</sub> = 0.89, 95% CI 0.59&#8211;1.33; aHR<sub>12 months</sub> = 0.93, 95% CI 0.67&#8211;1.30). No association was found between PPI use and other bleeding events.<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Adjusted cumulative incidence of upper gastrointestinal bleeding (UGIB) over 12 months by proton pump inhibitor (PPI) exposure group in patients with atrial fibrillation initiating an oral anticoagulant, either vitamin K antagonist or direct oral anticoagulant; results adjusted for the inverse of probability of treatment weighting [French national health database (SNDS), France]</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40266_2023_1085_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Association between proton pump inhibitor (PPI) use and risk of upper gastrointestinal bleeding and other bleeding in patients with atrial fibrillation initiating an oral anticoagulant (OAC) treatment, either vitamin K antagonist (VKA) or direct oral anticoagulant (DOAC) between April 2012 and December 2016 [French national health database (SNDS), France]</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">PPI nonusers</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">PPI users<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Cox model</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cox model with IPTW</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Events</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Incidence/1,000 PY</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Events</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Incidence/1,000 PY</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Crude HR [95% CI]</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aHR [95% CI]</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aHR [95% CI]</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Upper gastrointestinal bleeding</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;6-month follow-up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;All OACs</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">580</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.6 [14.4&#8211;17.0]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">206</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.0 [16.6&#8211;21.8]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.21 [1.03</bold>&#8211;<bold>1.41]</bold></td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.82 [0.69</bold>&#8211;<bold>0.98]</bold></td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.80 [0.65</bold>&#8211;<bold>0.98]</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;VKA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">319</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.4 [16.5&#8211;20.5]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">142</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.1 [17.9&#8211;24.8]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14 [0.94&#8211;1.39]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.80 [0.65</bold>&#8211;<bold>0.99]</bold></td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.73 [0.58</bold>&#8211;<bold>0.93]</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;DOAC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">244</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.4 [11.8&#8211;15.2]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.3 [11.8&#8211;19.8]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.13 [0.85&#8211;1.51]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.83 [0.61&#8211;1.13]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.89 [0.59&#8211;1.33]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12-month follow-up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;All OACs</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">837</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.8 [11.9&#8211;13.7]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">304</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.4 [14.6&#8211;18.3]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.26 [1.11</bold>&#8211;<bold>1.44]</bold></td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.91 [0.79&#8211;1.05]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.90 [0.76&#8211;1.07]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;VKA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">454</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.8 [14.4&#8211;17.3]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">205</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.7 [16.3&#8211;21.5]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.18 [1.00</bold>&#8211;<bold>1.39]</bold></td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.88 [0.73&#8211;1.05]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.81 [0.67</bold>&#8211;<bold>0.99]</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;DOAC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">344</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.5 [9.4&#8211;11.6]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.2 [9.8&#8211;15.2]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.16 [0.91&#8211;1.47]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.88 [0.68&#8211;1.14]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.93 [0.67&#8211;1.30]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other bleeding</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;6-month follow-up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;All OACs</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,425</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.6 [26.7&#8211;40.7]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">511</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.4 [43.4&#8211;51.7]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.22 [1.10</bold>&#8211;<bold>1.35]</bold></td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.98 [0.88&#8211;1.10]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03 [0.90&#8211;1.18]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;VKA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">806</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.7 [43.6&#8211;50.0]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">357</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.3 [48.0&#8211;59.1]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.14 [1.00</bold>&#8211;<bold>1.29]</bold></td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95 [0.83&#8211;1.09]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.96 [0.82&#8211;1.13]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;DOAC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">548</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.2 [27.8&#8211;32.8]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">135</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.3 [30.6&#8211;42.9]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.20 [0.99&#8211;1.45]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02 [0.83&#8211;1.25]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14 [0.90&#8211;1.46]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12-month follow-up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;All OACs</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,068</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.8 [30.5&#8211;33.2]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">730</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.7 [36.9&#8211;42.7]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.23 [1.13</bold>&#8211;<bold>1.34]</bold></td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.99 [0.90&#8211;1.08]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00 [0.89&#8211;1.12]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;VKA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,112</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.1 [36.8&#8211;41.4]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">495</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.6 [41.8&#8211;49.8]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.16 1.04</bold>&#8211;<bold>1.29]</bold></td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97 [0.86&#8211;1.09]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.96 [0.84&#8211;1.10]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#160;&#160;DOAC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">823</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.2 [23.5&#8211;26.9]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.3 [26.4&#8211;34.8]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.20 1.02</bold>&#8211;<bold>1.40]</bold></td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.01 [0.85&#8211;1.19]</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03 [0.84&#8211;1.26]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">PY</italic> Person-year, <italic toggle="yes">HR</italic> hazard ratio, <italic toggle="yes">aHR</italic> adjusted hazard ratio, <italic toggle="yes">IPTW</italic> inverse probability of treatment weighting Significant results are in bold</p><p><sup>a</sup>PPI users if at least one dispensation of PPI within 14 days of OAC initiation</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par26">Subgroup analyses are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. Of note, there was no difference in the risk of UGIB according to age category (75&#8211;89 years versus 90 years and over), bleeding risk assessed with the HAS-BLED score, and use of APT.<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Association between proton pomp inhibitor (PPI) use and risk of upper gastrointestinal bleeding (UGIB) over 6 months in patients with atrial fibrillation initiating an oral anticoagulant treatment, subgroup analyses [French national health database (SNDS), France]. <italic toggle="yes">NSAIDs</italic> nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs. NSAIDs and antiplatelet agent exposure is considered at inclusion and four months before</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40266_2023_1085_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par27">The results of the sensitivity analyses are described in Supplementary Table 5 and Supplementary Fig. 2. Briefly, estimations resulting from IPTCW were consistent with the main analysis, although slightly attenuated. The decrease in the risk of UGIB was greater when exposure was defined as PPI dispensing on the same date of the first OAC dispensing, except for DOAC initiators. Conversely, the exclusion of PPI users within the 6 months before the initiation of OAC lessened the associations. Finally, the calculated associations were significant when death was considered as a competing risk to estimate the cumulative incidence curves.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par28">This longitudinal study based on the French national health database investigated the added value of PPIs to prevent UGIB in 109,693 patients aged 75&#8211;110 years with a diagnosis of atrial fibrillation who initiated oral anticoagulation between 2012 and 2016. We report a 20% relative risk reduction of UGIB among PPI users compared with PPI nonusers in the first 6 months after OAC initiation, which did not persist when the follow-up was extended to 12 months. When the type of anticoagulation was differentiated, the risk reduction was more important in patients treated with VKA (53.6% of the study population) than in patients receiving DOAC.</p><p id="Par29">The lower risk of UGIB among PPI users initiating an OAC reported in our study is consistent with results of previous observational studies, although greater effects have been previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Indeed, two recent meta-analyses, including seven and ten studies, reported a 32&#8211;33% decrease in the risk of gastrointestinal bleeding associated with PPI in OAC users [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The study by Ray et al. contributed the most to these results as it was the largest study; based on the Medicare database, they estimated that PPI use decreased the risk of UGIB by 32% (aIRR = 0.66, 95% CI 0.62&#8211;0.69) in patients treated with OAC for atrial fibrillation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Furthermore, the specificity of our results is supported by the lack of association with nongastrointestinal bleeding events.</p><p id="Par30">Although our study reports a reduced risk of gastrointestinal bleeding associated with PPI use in VKA initiators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], it did not confirm the risk reduction observed in previous studies among DOAC initiators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. This result is surprising, as the meta-analysis by Anh et al. reported little difference in the risk of UGIB according to the type of OAC; OR = 0.65 (95% CI 0.62&#8211;0.69) for warfarin, OR = 0.67 (95% CI 0.56&#8211;0.81) for apixaban, OR = 0.56 (95% CI 0.45&#8211;0.69) for dabigatran, and OR = 0.76 (95% CI 0.62&#8211;0.91) for rivaroxaban [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. In addition, using pooled data from Sweden, Denmark, and the Netherlands, Komen et al. estimated that the risk of UGIB was 25% lower (IRRa = 0.75, 95% CI 0.59&#8211;0.95) when DOAC were prescribed with PPIs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. In our study, power issues could have contributed to the absence of significant results in the subgroup analyses. In the study by Komen et al., the risk of UGIB became nonsignificant in Sweden and in the Netherlands when the analysis was stratified by country [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The hypothesis of a higher risk of bleeding with VKAs compared with DOACs could also explain why the protective effect of PPIs was observed in VKA users only. However, this difference in bleeding risk between VKAs and DOACs remains debated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Difference in the characteristics of patients treated with VKAs and DOACs may also explain part of the difference in the results between the types of OAC in our study. Indeed, VKA initiators were older and more at risk of bleeding according to HAS-BLED score. They also had more cardiovascular disease and heavier medication than DOAC initiators. As the study period corresponded to the beginning of commercialization of DOACs in France, VKAs may have been preferred to DOACs for patients with poorer health status because they were better known to prescribers.</p><p id="Par31">In its 2020 reevaluation of PPIs, the HAS mentioned the potential benefit of PPIs in combination with oral anticoagulation in patients at risk of digestive complications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Indeed, Ray et al. reported a protective association between PPI use and the risk of UGIB, the magnitude of which increased with the bleeding risk score [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. However, we did not observe significant difference in the risk of UGIB according to age, APT use, and HAS-BLED score in our study. The lack of association with this usual risk factor may be due to the selection of relatively older people (of mean age 83 years versus 76 years in the study by Ray et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]) with no history of gastrointestinal bleeding in the last 12 months. In addition, the HAS-BLED score may be underestimated in our study, as there is no information on the measurement of the International Normalized Ratio in administrative databases.</p><p id="Par32">Our study focused on the risk of UGIB during the first 12 months after the initiation of the ACO. The fact that PPI prescribing was associated with a risk reduction of UGIB in the first 6 months of follow-up and not after could indicate a mitigation of the effect of PPIs with time. However, it could also be explained by possible discontinuation of PPI treatment over time, but the sensitivity analysis with censoring at PPI discontinuation provided similar results. Finally, it could also be due to the depletion of susceptible over time, where the proportion of patients who are likely to develop UGIB decreases faster in PPI nonusers than in PPI users [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].</p><p id="Par33">The use of the SNDS allowed us to include over 100,000 patients with atrial fibrillation starting an OAC treatment over nearly 5 years and to observe the occurrence of UGIB, which is a rare but severe event. However, our study has several limitations. First, the use of claims data only accounts for drugs that are reimbursed; therefore, self-medication of PPIs could not be considered, although they have been available without prescription since 2010 in France. However, this probably had a limited effect on our results, since 97% of PPIs were prescribed in 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Second, some information was unknown, such as indication of treatments, compliance or the exact dose received. Finally, the use of healthcare administrative data may lead to potential residual confounding as information on some potential confounders, such as smoking, alcohol use, and ulcers, was not available in this study.</p><p id="Par34">In conclusion, this study suggests that PPIs were associated with reduced risk of gastrointestinal bleeding after initiation of oral anticoagulation in older patients with atrial fibrillation, particularly within 6 months after initiation of antivitamin K antagonist. The greater effect with VKAs and the optimal duration of PPI treatment need further study. And, as the potentially inappropriate medication criteria remind us, caution is still required regarding the long-term use of PPIs.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><sec id="Sec12"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="40266_2023_1085_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary file1 (PDF 538 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors are grateful to G&#233;ric Maura, C&#233;cile Billionnet, and J&#233;r&#244;me Drouin for their previous work, in particular, for the elaboration of numerous definitions used to identify the study population and to calculate the covariates, and for providing part of the data used in our analyses.</p></ack><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par35">SD, AN, HM, MP, MZ, and MH have no competing interests to declare that are relevant to the content of this article.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2" notes-type="funding"><title>Funding sources</title><p id="Par36">This work was conducted at EPI-PHARE and University of Paris-Saclay, UVSQ and supported by the French National Agency for Medicines and Health Products Safety [Grant no. 2019S008] within the scope of Ph.D. funding to S.D.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Sponsor&#8217;s role</title><p id="Par37">The French National Agency for Medicines and Health Products Safety had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; or decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p></notes><notes id="FPar4"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par38">In accordance with data protection legislation and French regulations, the authors cannot publicly release data from the French National Health Data System (SNDS). However, any person or structure, public or private, for-profit or nonprofit, is entitled to access SNDS data upon authorization from the French Data Protection Office (CNIL), for the purposes of carrying out a study, research, or an evaluation in the public interest (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.snds.gouv.fr/SNDS/Processus-d-acces-aux-donnees">https://www.snds.gouv.fr/SNDS/Processus-d-acces-aux-donnees</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.indsante.fr/">https://www.indsante.fr/</ext-link>). EPI-PHARE has permanent regulatory access to data from the French National Health Data System (SNDS) via its constitutive bodies ANSM and CNAM. This permanent access is given in accordance with French Decree no. 2016-1871 of 26 December 2016 relating to personal data processing under the French National Health Data System (SNDS) and French law articles Art. R. 1461-13 and 14. All requests in the database were made by duly authorized people. In accordance with the permanent regulatory access granted to EPI-PHARE via ANSM and CNAM, this work did not require the approval of the French Data Protection Authority (CNIL). The study was registered on the study register of EPI-PHARE for studies based on SNDS data (T-2021-10-340).</p></notes><notes id="FPar5"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par39">This study has been authorized and conducted according to decree 2016&#8211;1871 of 26 December 2016 relating to personal data processing under the French National Health Data System (SNDS) and French law articles Art. R. 1461&#8211;1323 and 1424(5). As permanent users of the SNDS, the author&#8217;s team is exempted from institutional review board approval. Given that data are anonymous, informed consent to participate was not required.</p></notes><notes id="FPar6"><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p id="Par40">This study is a part of the PhD thesis of S.D. and supervised by M.H. and M.Z. M.H. and M.Z. conceptualized the study. M.H., M.Z., H.M., M.P., and S.D. designed the methodology, S.D. and A.N. extracted and managed the data, S.D. performed the analyses under the supervision of A.N. and M.H. S.D. wrote the manuscript and M.H., H.M., A.N., M.P., and M.Z. reviewed and edited the manuscript. M.Z., S.D.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sachs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacology of proton pump inhibitors</article-title><source>Curr Gastroenterol Rep</source><year>2008</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>528</fpage><lpage>534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11894-008-0098-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19006606</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2855237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>We are using too many ppis, and we need to stop: a European perspective</article-title><source>Off J Am Coll Gastroenterol ACG</source><year>2016</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>1085</fpage><lpage>1086</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ajg.2016.166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27166129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Othman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Card</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crooks</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proton pump inhibitor prescribing patterns in the UK: a primary care database study</article-title><source>Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</source><year>2016</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1079</fpage><lpage>1087</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pds.4043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27255671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moriarty</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cahir</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterizing potentially inappropriate prescribing of proton pump inhibitors in older people in primary care in Ireland from 1997 to 2012</article-title><source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source><year>2016</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>e291</fpage><lpage>e296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgs.14528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27996115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lassalle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Tri</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bardou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of proton pump inhibitors in adults in France: a nationwide drug utilization study</article-title><source>Eur J Clin Pharmacol</source><year>2020</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00228-019-02810-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31838548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salvo</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferko</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cash</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Umbrella review of 42 systematic reviews with meta-analyses: the safety of proton pump inhibitors</article-title><source>Aliment Pharmacol Ther</source><year>2021</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/apt.16407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34114655</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaynes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The risks of long-term use of proton pump inhibitors: a critical review</article-title><source>Ther Adv Drug Saf</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2042098618809927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31019676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6463334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forgacs</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loganayagam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overprescribing proton pump inhibitors</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2008</year><volume>336</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.39406.449456.BE</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18174564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2174763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maes</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fixen</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linnebur</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adverse effects of proton-pump inhibitor use in older adults: a review of the evidence</article-title><source>Ther Adv Drug Saf.</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2042098617715381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28861211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5557164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>The 2015 American Geriatrics Society Beers Criteria&#174; update expert panel. American Geriatrics Society</collab></person-group><article-title>updated Beers criteria for potentially inappropriate medication use in older adults</article-title><source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source><year>2015</year><volume>2015</volume><issue>63</issue><fpage>2227</fpage><lpage>2246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jgs.13702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26446832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Mahony</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Sullivan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>STOPP/START criteria for potentially inappropriate prescribing in older people: version 2</article-title><source>Age Ageing</source><year>2015</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ageing/afu145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25324330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4339726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ze</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Trends of global burden of atrial fibrillation/flutter from Global Burden of Disease Study 2017</article-title><source>Heart</source><year>2021</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>881</fpage><lpage>887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/heartjnl-2020-317656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33148545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kornej</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#246;rschel</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of atrial fibrillation in the 21st century</article-title><source>Circ Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.120.316340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32716709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7577553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoeb</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing bleeding risk in patients taking anticoagulants</article-title><source>J Thromb Thrombolysis</source><year>2013</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>312</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11239-013-0899-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23479259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3888359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Michelon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delahaye</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fellous</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proton pump inhibitors: why this gap between guidelines and prescribing practices in geriatrics?</article-title><source>Eur J Clin Pharmacol</source><year>2019</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>1327</fpage><lpage>1329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00228-019-02692-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31129732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Komen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Potteg&#229;rd</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hjemdahl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Non-vitamin K antagonist oral anticoagulants, proton pump inhibitors and gastrointestinal bleeds</article-title><source>Heart</source><year>2022</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/heartjnl-2021-319332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34340993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8961762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of oral anticoagulants and proton pump inhibitor cotherapy with hospitalization for upper gastrointestinal tract bleeding</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2018</year><volume>320</volume><fpage>2221</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2018.17242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30512099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6404233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>E-K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proton pump inhibitor co-therapy in patients with atrial fibrillation treated with oral anticoagulants and a prior history of upper gastrointestinal tract bleeding</article-title><source>Cardiovasc Drugs Ther</source><year>2022</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10557-021-07170-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33730289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moayyedi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eikelboom</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pantoprazole to prevent gastroduodenal events in patients receiving rivaroxaban and/or aspirin in a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2019</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>412.e5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2019.04.041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31054846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Commission de la Transparence. Rapport d&#8217;&#233;valuation Des Inhibiteurs de La Pompe &#224; Protons (Sp&#233;cialit&#233;s et G&#233;n&#233;riques). <italic toggle="yes">Haute Autorit&#233; de Sant&#233;</italic>. 2020:163.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Semenzato</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drouin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antihypertensive drugs and COVID-19 risk</article-title><source>Hypertension</source><year>2021</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>833</fpage><lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.120.16314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33423528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7884243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Penso</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dray-Spira</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weill</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association between biologics use and risk of serious infection in patients with psoriasis</article-title><source>JAMA Dermatol</source><year>2021</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>1056</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamadermatol.2021.2599</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34287624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8295892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Billionnet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alla</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#233;rigaud</surname><given-names>&#201;</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identifying atrial fibrillation in outpatients initiating oral anticoagulants based on medico-administrative data: results from the French national healthcare databases</article-title><source>Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</source><year>2017</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pds.4192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28295882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maura</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bloti&#232;re</surname><given-names>P-O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouillon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the short-term risk of bleeding and arterial thromboembolic events in nonvalvular atrial fibrillation patients newly treated with dabigatran or rivaroxaban versus vitamin K antagonists: a French nationwide propensity-matched cohort study</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2015</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>1252</fpage><lpage>1260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.115.015710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26199338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4885525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maura</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pariente</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alla</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adherence with direct oral anticoagulants in nonvalvular atrial fibrillation new users and associated factors: a French nationwide cohort study</article-title><source>Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</source><year>2017</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1367</fpage><lpage>1377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pds.4268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28752560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5697683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maura</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Billionnet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alla</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of treatment persistence with dabigatran or rivaroxaban versus vitamin k antagonist oral anticoagulants in atrial fibrillation patients: a competing risk analysis in the french national health care databases</article-title><source>Pharmacotherapy</source><year>2018</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/phar.2046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29028119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jabagi</surname><given-names>M-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zureik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vitamin K antagonists did not increase the risk of myelodysplastic syndrome in a large-scale cohort study</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2021</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood.2021010848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33876243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maura</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bardou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Billionnet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oral anticoagulants and risk of acute liver injury in patients with nonvalvular atrial fibrillation: a propensity-weighted nationwide cohort study</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>11624</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-68304-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32669591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7363898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maura</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Billionnet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drouin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oral anticoagulation therapy use in patients with atrial fibrillation after the introduction of non-vitamin K antagonist oral anticoagulants: findings from the French healthcare databases, 2011&#8211;2016</article-title><source>BMJ Open</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e026645</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2018-026645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31005934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6500377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bezin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lassalle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The national healthcare system claims databases in France, SNIIRAM and EGB: Powerful tools for pharmacoepidemiology</article-title><source>Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</source><year>2017</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>954</fpage><lpage>962</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pds.4233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28544284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuppin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Constantinou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Value of a national administrative database to guide public decisions: from the syst&#232;me national d&#8217;information interr&#233;gimes de l&#8217;Assurance Maladie (SNIIRAM) to the syst&#232;me national des donn&#233;es de sant&#233; (SNDS) in France</article-title><source>Rev Epidemiol Sante Publique</source><year>2017</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>S149</fpage><lpage>S167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.respe.2017.05.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28756037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laroche</surname><given-names>M-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charmes</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potentially inappropriate medications in the elderly: a French consensus panel list</article-title><source>Eur J Clin Pharmacol</source><year>2007</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>731</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00228-007-0324-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17554532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bongue</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laroche</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gutton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Potentially inappropriate drug prescription in the elderly in France: a population-based study from the French National Insurance Healthcare system</article-title><source>Eur J Clin Pharmacol</source><year>2011</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>1291</fpage><lpage>1299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00228-011-1077-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21691806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berthou-Contreras</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beuscart</surname><given-names>J-B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>REview of potentially inappropriate MEDIcation pr[e]scribing in Seniors (REMEDI[e]S): French implicit and explicit criteria</article-title><source>Eur J Clin Pharmacol</source><year>2021</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>1713</fpage><lpage>1724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00228-021-03145-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34115158</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moving towards best practice when using inverse probability of treatment weighting (IPTW) using the propensity score to estimate causal treatment effects in observational studies</article-title><source>Stat Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>3661</fpage><lpage>3679</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/sim.6607</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26238958</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4626409</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#225;n</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Constructing inverse probability weights for marginal structural models</article-title><source>Am J Epidemiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>656</fpage><lpage>664</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwn164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18682488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2732954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#225;n</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The hazards of hazard ratios</article-title><source>Epidemiology</source><year>2010</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/EDE.0b013e3181c1ea43</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20010207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3653612</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#225;n</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adjusted survival curves with inverse probability weights</article-title><source>Comput Methods Programs Biomed</source><year>2004</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmpb.2003.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15158046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Billionnet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Covariate adjustment of cumulative incidence functions for competing risks data using inverse probability of treatment weighting</article-title><source>Comput Methods Programs Biomed</source><year>2016</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmpb.2016.03.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27084321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robins</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finkelstein</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correcting for noncompliance and dependent censoring in an AIDS Clinical Trial with inverse probability of censoring weighted (IPCW) log-rank tests</article-title><source>Biometrics</source><year>2000</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0006-341X.2000.00779.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10985216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><source>The elements of statistical learning: data mining, inference, and prediction</source><year>2009</year><edition>2</edition><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurlander</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of antisecretory drugs with upper gastrointestinal bleeding in patients using oral anticoagulants: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Am J Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>1231</fpage><lpage>1243.e8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjmed.2022.05.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35679879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10031639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Protective effect of proton-pump inhibitor against gastrointestinal bleeding in patients receiving oral anticoagulants: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source><year>2022</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>4676</fpage><lpage>4687</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bcp.15478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35921204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bang</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joo</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>B-W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of acid suppressants in the prevention of anticoagulant-related gastrointestinal bleeding: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Gut Liver</source><year>2020</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5009/gnl19009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30974930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6974330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevention of non-vitamin k oral anticoagulants-related gastrointestinal bleeding with acid suppressants: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Clin Appl Thromb</source><year>2022</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>10760296211064897</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/10760296211064897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8777378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35037779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burr</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lummis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sood</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk of gastrointestinal bleeding with direct oral anticoagulants: a systematic review and network meta-analysis</article-title><source>Lancet Gastroenterol Hepatol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2468-1253(16)30162-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28403994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>ICK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The association between non-vitamin K antagonist oral anticoagulants and gastrointestinal bleeding: a meta-analysis of observational studies</article-title><source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source><year>2016</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bcp.12911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26889922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4917795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lip</surname><given-names>GYH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keshishian</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oral anticoagulants for nonvalvular atrial fibrillation in patients with high risk of gastrointestinal bleeding</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2021</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e2120064</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.20064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34398204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8369361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Renoux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dell&#8217;Aniello</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bias from depletion of susceptibles: the example of hormone replacement therapy and the risk of venous thromboembolism</article-title><source>Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</source><year>2017</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>554</fpage><lpage>560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pds.4197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28326633</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>