<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2120</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">inthealth</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">inthealth</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1876-3413</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1876-3405</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10318961</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10318961.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10318961</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10318961</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36331288</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/inthealth/ihac067</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ihac067</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00390</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Preceding birth interval, timing and number of antenatal contacts in Africa, 2010&#8211;2020</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6877-7826</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuoyire</surname><given-names initials="DA">Derek Anamaale</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Community Medicine, School of Medical Sciences, University of Cape Coast</institution>, Cape Coast, <country country="GH">Ghana</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8394-1874</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Amo-Adjei</surname><given-names initials="J">Joshua</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Population and Health, Faculty of Social Sciences, University of Cape Coast</institution>, Cape Coast, <country country="GH">Ghana</country></aff><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author: Tel: +233244092814; E-mail: <email>Joshua.amo-adjei@ucc.edu.gh</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>7</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2022-11-04"><day>04</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">439868</issue-id><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>452</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>31</day><month>8</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>04</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>05</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-07-05 10:25:15.960"><day>05</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2022. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Royal Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact <email>journals.permissions@oup.com</email></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="ihac067.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ihac067.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="abs1"><title>Background</title><p>Utilization of adequate and quality prenatal healthcare services confers critical benefits to women and their unborn children. However, utilization rates remain low in many countries in Africa. Several studies have attempted to understand the primary drivers behind these low statistics. This article contributes to this discourse by examining the associations between birth interval and timing and number/frequency of antenatal care visits in Africa.</p></sec><sec id="abs2"><title>Methods</title><p>We pooled data from the publicly available Demographic and Health Surveys conducted in the last decade (2010&#8211;2020) for 32 African countries. Data were analysed using descriptive proportions and mixed effect binary logistic regression.</p></sec><sec id="abs3"><title>Results</title><p>The results illustrate moderate significant associations between spacing on the most recent birth by &#8805;36&#160;months and early (first trimester) first antenatal care contact in both our bivariate (odds ratio [OR] 1.18, p&lt;0.001) and multivariate (OR 1.106, p&lt;0.001) analyses. The benefits on optimal antenatal contacts predicted on spacing are also noticed with birth intervals of 24&#8211;35&#160;months (OR 1.08, p&lt;0.001) and &#8805;36&#160;months (OR 1.48, p&lt;0.001).</p></sec><sec id="abs4"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Optimal birth spacing is beneficial for ANC utilization in terms of timing and total number of contacts. Post-partum family planning/contraceptive use can be an effective pathway to prolonging birth intervals. We argue that maternal and child health programmes strengthen prioritizing contraceptive use between births.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="keywords"><kwd>adequate</kwd><kwd>ANC visits/contacts</kwd><kwd>birth interval</kwd><kwd>prenatal</kwd><kwd>SSA</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Antenatal care (ANC) is one of the key proven healthcare interventions for the prevention and management of pregnancy or birth-related complications, which account for most poor maternal and child health outcomes. ANC offers a critical platform within the continuum of reproductive healthcare for pregnant women to receive preventive and supportive care and information during the prenatal period. ANC also allows for early screening and identification of potential risks associated with pregnancy and, in turn, implementation of timely interventions to avert fatal outcomes.<sup><xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> With a few exceptions,<sup><xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> there is general concurrence<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3&#8211;5</sup></xref> that adequate ANC utilization has a consequential association/impact on reduced adverse pregnancy outcomes. Focused ANC (FANC), which until 2016 was the model around the world, recommended four ANC contacts as optimal for improved maternity outcomes. Relying on current knowledge, in 2016 the World Health Organization (WHO) recommended eight contacts for enhanced outcomes, but maintaining the first contact within the first trimester of pregnancy.<sup><xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup></p><p>Despite the known benefits of timely and optimal coverage of ANC on maternal and child health, progress in improving ANC coverage among pregnant women has been slow, particularly in low- and middle-income countries (LMICs). According to the United Nations Children's Fund (2021)<sup><xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>, the proportion of pregnant women 15&#8211;49&#160;years of age who received ANC at least four times increased by only 10% between 2007 (58%) and 2020 (68%). Wide disparities in ANC coverage continue to exist, with lower ANC coverage in southern Asia (49%) and sub-Saharan Africa (SSA; 53%). With the persisting commitment to improve maternal and child health through the Sustainable Development Goals, there is the need for concerted effort in understanding factors that affect ANC utilization to help tackle the unacceptably high pregnancy-related preventable adverse outcomes for mothers and their children.</p><p>Birth interval is one factor that can impact maternal and child health outcomes. Whereas there is no consensus on the optimal birth interval, many experts or consultative groups, including a WHO technical consultative group, agree that a 24-month interval between births provides significant benefits to women and their children.<sup><xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Indeed, studies have found an increased risk of poor pregnancy outcomes, including preterm birth, low birthweight and small for gestational age, associated with shorter birth intervals.<sup><xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> Existing literature seems to draw more on the biological mechanisms in explaining the link between birth intervals and pregnancy outcomes, including maternal nutritional depletion, folate depletion, cervical insufficiency, vertical transmission of infections, suboptimal lactation related to breastfeeding and pregnancy overlap, among others, while less research effort has been invested towards understanding some behavioural dimensions of the problem.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9&#8211;13</sup></xref></p><p>One such important but much less explored behavioural hypothesis is the effect of birth interval on women's pregnancy-related health services utilization. Yet the preceding interval between the last birth and the next pregnancy could influence a pregnant woman's decisions and behaviours regarding ANC service utilization and subsequent pregnancy outcomes. For instance, women with shorter preceding intervals may entertain some sense of protection against potential risks of non-utilization of ANC based on recent pregnancy experiences. On the other hand, in contexts such as SSA, where abuse and disrespect during maternity care is pervasive,<sup><xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> women with shorter birth intervals may be reluctant to access ANC for fear of being abused by health providers for not practicing adequate birth spacing.</p><p>Notwithstanding the rich and large volume of scholarship on determinants of ANC utilization,<sup><xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> little is known about the relationship between the preceding birth interval and ANC utilisation. The evidence on the relationship between birth interval and ANC utilization is scarce. Indeed, previous attempts<sup><xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> have only examined this relationship partially or indirectly, with birth interval often merely treated as a covariate rather than a key variable of interest. While alluding to the lack of previous studies on the relationship between birth interval and ANC attendance, Heaman et al.<sup><xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> considered their findings linking shorter birth interval with inadequate ANC as new knowledge for improving ANC service utilization in Manitoba. Our aim in this article is to further analyse the relationship between the preceding birth interval and ANC attendance using analogous datasets from 32 African countries.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec2"><title>Methods</title><p>Data for this article were culled from Demographic and Health Surveys (DHS) conducted in 32 African countries between 2010 and 2020. The DHS adopts a comparable methodology in data collection, cleaning and coding that easily facilities cross-country/regional analysis. The first phase of sampling involves demarcating regions/counties/provinces into urban and rural zones. From the urban and rural areas, enumeration areas (EAs)/clusters are chosen and from each cluster/EA, a predetermined number of households are selected through a simple random technique. Eligible women 15&#8211;49&#160;y of age (in the majority of countries) who voluntarily consent are recruited and interviewed; response rates usually average 95% (range 87&#8211;99.3).<sup><xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> The surveys conform to in-country protocols for granting ethical approval for research involving humans.</p><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Variables</title><p>The main independent variable for this paper is the interval preceding recent births and the outcome variables were timing of the first ANC and the number of ANC visits. These variables were based on the most recent birth (before survey) and the intention was to avoid potential recall biases associated with births occurring &gt;5&#160;years prior to the surveys. Birth interval is measured in months for the purposes of this analysis and was divided into four groups:<sup><xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> &#8804;17, 18&#8211;23, 24&#8211;35 and &#8805;36&#160;months. Timing of the first ANC was categorised into first trimester or otherwise, while the number of ANC visits was grouped into three or less and four or more. Although in 2016 the WHO revised the focused ANC model from four to eight visits, the recent surveys from all but six countries in this analysis were conducted before the implementation of the new 2016 WHO ANC model. It is unlikely that these countries had started full implementation of the new recommendations. This is particularly important in light of the retrospective nature of the DHS methodology. Our analysis was therefore based on the old recommendations of a minimum of four visits. Other explanatory/independent variables included in the multivariable models were household wealth, maternal education, area of residence (urban, rural), marital status, pregnancy intentions (wanted, mistimed and unplanned) and parity (nulliparity, low parity [1&#8211;4] and grand multiparity [&#8805;5]).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Data analysis</title><p>A two-step approach was employed in analysing the data. The first involved descriptive statistics reporting proportions for the timing of ANC and the number of ANC visits. Next, mixed effects binary logistic regression was used to estimate the effect of birth interval on the two outcomes (timing and number of ANC visits) separately. Mixed effects binary logistic regression was used because the DHS datasets are based on a complex survey design with unequal weighting at the country and cross-country levels.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21&#8211;23</sup></xref> The mixed effects regression belongs to the generalized linear mixed models that allow us to account for the complex sampling processes.<sup><xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> In each case, two models were estimated. Model 1, in Tables&#160;<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and&#160;<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, focused on the bivariate relationship birth interval (&#8804;17, 18&#8211;23, 24&#8211;35 and &#8805;36&#160;months) and timing of the first ANC and optimal visits. Model 2 (Tables&#160;<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>) were multivariable models aimed at clarifying the net effect of birth interval on the outcomes, while controlling for other documented predictors of ANC. Random effects are reported at the country level.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3-1"><title>Descriptive results</title><sec id="sec3-1-1"><title>Preceding birth intervals</title><p>Of the total of 290 816 involved in the surveys, 226 337 and 251 141 had usable records on the timing of their first ANC contact and the number of ANC visits, respectively. As shown in Table&#160;<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, more than 8 in 10 women across all 32 countries spaced their most recent birth by at least 24&#160;months (24&#8211;35&#160;months, 32%; &#8805;36&#160;months, 51%) compared with about 16% of women who spaced their most recent birth by &lt;24&#160;months. The proportion of women who spaced their recent birth by &#8805;36&#160;months ranged from 35% in Chad to 74% in Zambia.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Proportion of women reporting first trimester ANC and at least four visits, by background characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">First trimester</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&gt;4 visits</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Preceding birth interval (months)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8804;17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9512</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#160;319</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;18&#8211;23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19&#160;048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22&#160;485</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;24&#8211;35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57&#160;927</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66&#160;411</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8805;36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90&#160;522</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98&#160;624</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country, year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Angola, 2015/16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13&#160;980</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#160;678</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Benin, 2017/18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7889</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8766</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Burkina Faso, 2017/18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8588</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8655</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;DR Congo, 2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9825</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#160;214</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Congo, 2011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5834</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6429</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Cote d&#8217;Ivoire, 2011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4914</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5392</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Cameroon, 2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5633</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6395</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Egypt, 2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#160;371</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#160;447</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Gabon, 2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3805</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4093</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Ghana, 2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4161</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4272</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Gambia, 2019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5741</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5747</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Guinea, 2018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4705</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5383</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Kenya, 2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13&#160;996</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#160;898</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Comoros, 2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1830</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1730</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Liberia, 2019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4167</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4185</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Lesotho, 2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2468</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2576</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Mali, 2019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4869</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6246</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Malawi, 2015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13&#160;194</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13&#160;389</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Mozambique, 2011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7038</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7516</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Nigeria, 2018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16&#160;398</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#160;465</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Niger, 2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#160;938</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#160;290</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Namibia, 2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3790</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3126</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Rwanda, 2019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6036</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6166</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Sierra Leone, 2019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7249</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6540</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Senegal, 2019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4306</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Chad, 2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6506</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#160;928</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Togo, 2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4650</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Tanzania, 2015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6914</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7019</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Uganda, 2016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#160;061</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#160;219</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;South Africa, 2016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2858</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2942</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Zambia, 2018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7269</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7305</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Zimbabwe, 2015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4564</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4823</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Wealth quintile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Poorest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49&#160;020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59&#160;915</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Poorer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47&#160;101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54&#160;005</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Middle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#160;920</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#160;046</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Richer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43&#160;423</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#160;866</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Richest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#160;873</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41&#160;309</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Highest education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71&#160;301</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90&#160;046</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Primary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77&#160;686</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82&#160;531</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Secondary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67&#160;272</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68&#160;577</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Higher</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#160;046</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9953</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age cohort (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;15&#8211;19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#160;145</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19&#160;321</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;20&#8211;24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51&#160;226</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56&#160;207</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;25&#8211;29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58&#160;290</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64&#160;237</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;30&#8211;34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#160;680</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#160;424</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;35&#8211;39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32&#160;972</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36&#160;642</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;40&#8211;44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#160;890</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#160;193</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;45&#8211;49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6117</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Residence</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Urban</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81&#160;132</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84&#160;167</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Rural</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">145&#160;205</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">166&#160;974</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Marital status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never in union</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19&#160;209</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#160;207</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150&#160;947</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">169&#160;465</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Living with partner</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#160;217</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42&#160;952</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Formerly in union/living with a man</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16&#160;964</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#160;517</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Pregnancy intentions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Wanted then</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">156&#160;325</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176&#160;243</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Wanted later</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48&#160;149</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#160;970</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No more</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#160;553</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16&#160;036</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Nulliparous</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1561</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1772</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Low multiparous</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135&#160;159</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146&#160;032</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Grand multiparous</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89&#160;617</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103&#160;337</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">226&#160;337</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">251&#160;141</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-1-2"><title>ANC outcomes and background characteristics of women</title><p>The results (Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) on ANC attendance show that 4 in 10 women attended their first ANC within the first trimester of pregnancy, ranging from 18% in Kenya to
85% in Egypt. The mean number of ANC visits was 4.2, with the highest (8.9) and lowest (2.1) mean number of ANC visits observed in Egypt and Chad, respectively.</p><p>The results generally suggest improvements in ANC outcomes (ANC in the first trimester and &#8805;4 ANC visits) with increasing preceding birth intervals. Regarding the timing of ANC contact, women who attended their first ANC within the first trimester of the index pregnancy increased from 37% among those with a preceding interval of &#8804;17&#160;months to about 42% among those with a preceding birth interval of &#8805;36&#160;months. A similar pattern was observed regarding the recommended minimum number of four ANC visits by women during their pregnancy. The proportion of women who reported to have had at least four ANC contacts during their most recent pregnancy increased from about 50% among those with a preceding birth interval of &#8804;17&#160;months to 60% among those with a preceding interval of &#8805;36&#160;months.</p><p>Variations in the two ANC outcomes were observed across background characteristics of women considered in the analysis. For instance, attendance of the first ANC within the first trimester increased from 36% among the poorest women to 50% among the richest women. Similarly, the proportion of women with four or more ANC visits increased from about 46% among the poorest women to about 73% in the richest group. The differences by education on both first trimester ANC contact as well as the number attained favoured better educated women (61% and 88%, respectively). Except for those 25&#8211;29 and 30&#8211;34&#160;y of age, both the first ANC visit and number of ANC visits varied across all other age cohorts.</p><p>More urban (46%) than rural (37%) women attended their first ANC within the first trimester. The same was the case for the number of ANC visits (69% vs 51%). While the proportion of women who attained four or more ANC visits varied considerably by marital status, the proportion of women who attended their first ANC visit in the first trimester was similar across the marital categories apart from those formerly in unions. Regarding pregnancy intentions, most women who attended ANC in their first trimester of pregnancy wanted their most recent pregnancy at the time it occurred (42%), whereas those attending four or more ANC visits were mostly women who wanted their most recent pregnancy later (58%). Both the first ANC visit and the number of ANC visits were dominated by low multiparous women (43% and 61%, respectively).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>Multivariate results</title><sec id="sec3-2-1"><title>Birth spacing and first ANC contact</title><p>Our bivariate model in Table <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows some beneficial relationship between the preceding birth interval and the first ANC visit in the first trimester, and this is more significant with a birth interval of &#8805;36&#160;months; women who spaced births by this duration were about 1.18 times (p&lt;0.001) more likely to initiate the first ANC contact in the first trimester compared with those who spaced for &lt;18&#160;months. Adjusting for socio-economic factors, the benefits of long birth intervals decrease slightly (OR 1.106, p&lt;0.001), but remain statistically significant.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Mixed effects binary logistic regression on early (first trimester) ANC visits</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Model 1</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Model 2</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preceding birth interval (months)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8804;17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;18&#8211;23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.921**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.875 to 0.970</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.929**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.882 to 0.980</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;24&#8211;35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.943*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.901 to 0.987</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.959</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.915 to 1.004</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&gt;36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.182***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.131 to 1.236</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.106***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.056 to 1.158</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wealth quintile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Poorest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Poorer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.980</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.951 to 1.010</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Middle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.930***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.902 to 0.960</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Richer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.952**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.921 to 0.985</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Richest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.142***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.098 to 1.187</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Highest education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Primary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.979</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.955 to 1.003</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Secondary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.444***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.405 to 1.485</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Higher</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.132***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.009 to 2.262</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age cohort (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;15&#8211;19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;20&#8211;24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.050</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.966 to 1.140</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;25&#8211;29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.219***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.122 to 1.323</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;30&#8211;34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.388***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.277 to 1.509</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;35&#8211;39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.436***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.318 to 1.565</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;40&#8211;44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.429***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.306 to 1.563</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;45&#8211;49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.337***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.207 to 1.481</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Residence</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Urban</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Rural</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.882***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.860 to 0.906</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never in union</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.948*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.899 to 1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Living with partner</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.990</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.937 to 1.047</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Formerly in union/living with a man</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.874***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.821 to 0.930</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pregnancy intentions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Wanted then</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Wanted later</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.879***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.856 to 0.902</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No more</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.900***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.866 to 0.935</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Nulliparous</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Low multiparous</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.959</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.729 to 1.260</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Grand multiparous</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.695**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.529 to 0.914</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">_cons</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.519***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.494 to 0.544</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.571***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.427 to 0.763</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">var(_cons[v021])</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.113***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.093 to 1.134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.088***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.071 to 1.104</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">var(_cons[v012])</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">177&#160;009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">171&#160;329</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tb2fn1"><p>Exponentiated coefficients.</p></fn><fn id="tb2fn2"><p>*p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001.</p></fn><fn id="tb2fn3"><p>Model 1, bivariate model; model 2, multivariate model.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Mixed effects binary logistic regression on optimal (&#8805;4 visits) ANC visits</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Model 1</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Model 2</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preceding birth interval (months)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8804;17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;18&#8211;23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.971</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.928 to 1.016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.961 to 1.058</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;24&#8211;35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.079***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.037 to 1.123</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.162***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.114 to 1.213</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&gt;36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.480***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.423 to 1.540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.420***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.361 to 1.482</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wealth quintile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Poorest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Poorer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.117***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.087 to 1.148</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Middle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.198***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.164 to 1.233</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Richer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.211***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.173 to 1.249</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Richest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.244***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.197 to 1.293</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Highest education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Primary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.700***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.662 to 1.738</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Secondary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.175***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.087 to 3.265</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Higher</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.334***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.843 to 6.867</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age cohort (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;15&#8211;19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;20&#8211;24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.244***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.155 to 1.340</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;25&#8211;29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.476***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.370 to 1.589</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;30&#8211;34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.688***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.565 to 1.820</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;35&#8211;39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.813***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.678 to 1.960</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;40&#8211;44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.746***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.610 to 1.894</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;45&#8211;49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.732***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.579 to 1.899</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Residence</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Urban</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Rural</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.690***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.673 to 0.708</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never in union</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.930**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.882 to 0.982</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Living with partner</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.999</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.944 to 1.057</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Formerly in union/living with a man</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.867***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.815 to 0.923</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pregnancy intentions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Wanted then</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Wanted later</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.938***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.915 to 0.963</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No more</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.865***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.834 to 0.897</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Nulliparous</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Low multiparous</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.123</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.875 to 1.441</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Grand multiparous</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.903</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.704 to 1.160</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">_cons</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.940</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.878 to 1.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.497***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.382 to 0.648</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">var(_cons[v021])</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.053***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.044 to 1.062</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">var(_cons[v012])</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.029***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.013 to 1.044</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">198&#160;839</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">192&#160;652</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tb3fn1"><p>Exponentiated coefficients.</p></fn><fn id="tb3fn2"><p>*p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001.</p></fn><fn id="tb3fn3"><p>Model 1, bivariate model; model 2, multivariate model.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Our analyses on other socio-economic predictors reveal their already known effects on ANC initiation. For instance, there is an upward improvement in early ANC initiation/contact with increasing household wealth. The likelihood of first trimester ANC initiation increases to approximately 14% for the fifth quintile women with reference to the first quintile. Similar effects are observed for formal education, where women with higher education are &gt;100% (OR 2.13, p&lt;0.001) inclined to seek ANC services in their first trimester compared with those without formal education. Age also has significant positive consequences on early ANC visits. In contrast, we observed significant negative effects of residence, marital status, pregnancy intentions and parity on early first ANC visits.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-2-2"><title>Birth spacing and optimal ANC utilization</title><p>Table&#160;<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref> presents the models on preceding birth interval and optimal use of ANC services. We show that spacing births by &#8805;24&#160;months has significant positive effects on the optimal number of ANC contacts. For example, women who reported an interval of 24&#8211;35&#160;months (OR 1.08, p&lt;0.001) and &#8805;36&#160;months (OR 1.48, p&lt;0.001) were more likely to comply with four or more visits. Controlling for model confounders, the magnitude of odds reduced slightly, but the statistical significance remains unchanged (Table&#160;<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><p>Our estimation of the effect of other factors (socio-economic) on the optimal number of ANC visits follows the earlier pattern observed for timing of initiating the first contact. However, the magnitudes of the relationships are larger in these estimates. For example, a higher household wealth quintile increased the chances of optimal contacts by about twofold compared with the model on initiating the first visit. The effects of education are even stronger&#8212;women with more education are three times more likely to record optimal FANC compared with uneducated women.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this article we pooled DHS data from 32 African countries to examine how the preceding birth interval of women may affect their initiation of ANC visits within their first trimester of pregnancy and their attainment of an optimal number of ANC visits over the period of pregnancy. Our findings support earlier reports<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25&#8211;27</sup></xref> that longer preceding birth intervals increase the probability of women both initiating ANC visits within their first trimester of pregnancy and obtaining an optimal number of ANC visits. Despite controlling for the impacts of other possible confounders, our study showed that women with preceding birth intervals &gt;35&#160;months were more likely to initiate ANC early (within the first trimester). These positive associations were even more pronounced when considering the WHO-recommended optimal number of four ANC visits for pregnant women. Here, our findings suggest that preceding birth intervals of at least 24&#160;months are beneficial for attainment of at least four ANC visits.</p><p>One plausible interpretation for the overall positive consequence is that longer intervals allow women to better prepare for the next child/pregnancy and thus they are more motivated to utilize ANC services. In other words, any concerns about sibling competition, which characterizes shorter birth intervals, is reduced such that there is no younger child to care for, which has the potential of hindering the general personal management of women, including making time for ANC. Again, the findings could reflect some sociocultural connotations that may surround the length of preceding birth intervals of women; while delayed return to pregnancy/childbirth is often more acceptable, a rapid return to pregnancy following a preceding birth may be socially undesirable and embarrassing in some societies.<sup><xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> As such, women with longer preceding birth intervals may be more comfortable with any form of social and health interactions, including the use of prenatal interventions. Women with shorter birth intervals, particularly those not on post-partum contraception, may feet-drag in returning to the same provider for ANC. Also, with a long time lag between pregnancies, women may feel the need to attend ANC clinics to learn new trends in maternal and newborn care practices for improved outcomes. This is more plausible if the long interval was unintended, occasioned by prolonged resumption of conception or experiences of spontaneous abortion. Women in this category are likely to prioritise prenatal services with early initiation and subsequent increased use of services.</p><p>Regarding other factors, our findings reiterate the persistent weight of socio-economic factors on maternal and child health.<sup><xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> On the one hand, the benefits of timeliness and adequacy of prenatal visits are better understood and complied with as women become more educated.<sup><xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> On the other hand, wealth provides greater access to prenatal health services, especially continuity of ANC visits. The influence of financial resources on frequent ANC utilization<sup><xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> could explain why we found larger wealth effects on the optimal number of ANC visits. As previously established, we found pregnancy intentions (unwanted and mistimed) to have negative effects on both early initiation and adequacy of ANC. This could be due to several factors, including late detection, negative or low vulnerability perception and abortion contemplation by women who experience unintended pregnancies. We are presently unable to pinpoint any plausible explanation, but we know that pregnancy intentions do not remain fixed throughout the duration of a pregnancy. Intentions for these women probably changed based on emerging or new reproductive circumstances, triggering enhanced use of ANC services.</p><p>We acknowledge some limitations in this study, beginning with the usual disclaimer of non-causality in the use of cross-sectional surveys. Also, we did not account for the complex nature of the survey data. While it is an appropriate approach for single-country data analysis, some logistical and data constraints make this difficult in multicountry analysis. In multicountry analysis, weights must be de-normalized and new weights computed as a function of the total population of the sampled women at the time of the survey. Unfortunately, we could not obtain reliable national estimates of the population of women 15&#8211;49&#160;y of age at the time of the survey for each country. Nonetheless, by designating a country as a random intercept in our models, we feel confident that the results closely reflect the composite picture as regards our variables of interests. Another limitation that we should state is that the dataset did not have questions on women's reasons for the duration of intervals. This constrains us from isolating the actual pathways through which birth spacing/intervals affects prenatal services utilization. That notwithstanding, we have attempted to offer some plausible trajectories through which the observed findings may be unfolding. Qualitative studies/mixed methods studies will be useful in unmasking the &#8216;black box&#8217; fully.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This article highlights strong associations between birth spacing/interval and the timing and number of ANC visits. We conclude that encouraging long birth intervals (a minimum of 24&#160;months) through increased use of contraceptives may contribute to efforts at improving the utilization of ANC services, which in turn may advance women and children's health.</p></sec></body><back><sec id="sec6"><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>JAA and DAT were responsible for conceptualization. JAA performed the analysis and interpretated the results. DAT drafted the introduction and discussion. All authors approved the version submitted for peer review and publication.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors are grateful to Measure DHS for granting access to use the data.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Funding</title><p>None.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec9"><title>Competing interests</title><p>None declared.</p></sec><sec id="sec10"><title>Ethical approval</title><p>We relied on publicly available secondary datasets. However, all the respective surveys received approval from relevant in-country ethics review bodies.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec11"><title>Data availability</title><p>Data used for this paper are publicly available and can be accessed here: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://dhsprogram.com/data/available-datasets.cfm" ext-link-type="uri">https://dhsprogram.com/data/available-datasets.cfm</ext-link>.</p></sec><ref-list id="ref1"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>. <source>WHO recommendations on antenatal care for a positive pregnancy experience</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>; <year>2016</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28079998</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hollowell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kurinczuk</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>The effectiveness of antenatal care programmes to reduce infant mortality and preterm birth in socially disadvantaged and vulnerable women in high-income countries: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21314944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2393-11-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3050773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Linard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Blondel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Estellat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Association between inadequate antenatal care utilisation and severe perinatal and maternal morbidity: an analysis in the PreCARE cohort</article-title>. <source>BJOG</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>125</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>587</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28631308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/1471-0528.14794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pallikadavath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ram</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Do antenatal care interventions improve neonatal survival in India?</article-title><source>Health Policy Plan</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>842</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24038077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/heapol/czt066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4471439</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Doku</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Neupane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Survival analysis of the association between antenatal care attendance and neonatal mortality in 57 low-and middle-income countries</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1668</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>77</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29040531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ije/dyx125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5837573</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>UNICEF</collab></person-group>. (<year>2022</year>). <comment>Global Annual Results Report 2021: Every child survives and thrives. New York, UNICEF</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>. <source>Report of a WHO technical consultation on birth spacing: Geneva, Switzerland 13&#8211;15 June 2005</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva:</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rutstein</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Further evidence of the effects of preceding birth intervals on neonatal infant and under-five-years mortality and nutritional status in developing countries: evidence from the Demographic and Health Surveys</article-title>. <source>Int J Gynecol Obstet.</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>S7</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijgo.2004.11.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15820369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Conde-Agudelo</surname><given-names>A&#173;N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rosas-Bermudez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Casta&#241;o</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Effects of birth spacing on maternal, perinatal, infant, and child health: a systematic review of causal mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Stud Fam Plann</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>93</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>114</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23175949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1728-4465.2012.00308.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bauserman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nolen</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>The relationship between birth intervals and adverse maternal and neonatal outcomes in six low and lower-middle income countries</article-title>. <source>Reprod Health</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>Suppl 2</issue>):<fpage>157</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33256784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12978-020-01008-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7708104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yee</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Truong</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Caughey</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>The association between interdelivery interval and adverse perinatal outcomes in a diverse US population</article-title>. <source>J Perinatol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>593</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27031319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/jp.2016.54</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Conde-Agudelo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rosas-Berm&#250;dez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kafury-Goeta</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of birth spacing on maternal health: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>196</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>297</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>308</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17403398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajog.2006.05.055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>DaVanzo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hale</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Razzaque</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Effects of interpregnancy interval and outcome of the preceding pregnancy on pregnancy outcomes in Matlab, Bangladesh</article-title>. <source>BJOG</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>114</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1079</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>87</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17617195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1471-0528.2007.01338.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2366022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kassa</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tsegaye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abeje</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Disrespect and abuse of women during the process of childbirth at health facilities in sub-Saharan Africa: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>BMC Int Health Hum Rights</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32894127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12914-020-00242-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7487593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lippeveld</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wypij</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Does antenatal care make a difference to safe delivery? A study in urban Uttar Pradesh, India</article-title>. <source>Health Policy Plan</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>38</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>48</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10351468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/heapol/14.1.38</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Belay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Astatkie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abebaw</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and factors affecting the utilization of antenatal care in rural areas of southwestern Ethiopia</article-title>. <source>BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35031008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12884-021-04362-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8759251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adewuyi</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Auta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khanal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and factors associated with underutilization of antenatal care services in Nigeria: a comparative study of rural and urban residences based on the 2013 Nigeria demographic and health survey</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e0197324</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29782511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0197324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5962076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heaman</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brownell</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Inequities in utilization of prenatal care: a population-based study in the Canadian province of Manitoba</article-title>. <source>BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>4308</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12884-018-2061-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6211437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30382911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>United Nations</collab></person-group>. <source>Household sample surveys in developing and transition countries</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UN Statistics Division</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fotso</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mberu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Birth spacing and child mortality: an analysis of prospective data from the Nairobi urban health and demographic surveillance system</article-title>. <source>J Biosoc Sci</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>779</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>98</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22958417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/S0021932012000570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3785173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heeringa</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Berglund</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Applied survey data analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>JNK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The analysis of categorical data from complex sample surveys: chi-squared tests for goodness of fit and independence in two-way tables</article-title>. <source>J Am Stat Assoc</source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>76</volume>(<issue>374</issue>):<fpage>221</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rozi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Multilevel modeling of binary outcomes with three-level complex health survey data</article-title>. <source>Open J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>27</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McCullagh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nelder</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Generalized linear models</source>. <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>; <year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hajizadeh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tehrani</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Simbar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Factors influencing the use of prenatal care: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Midwifery Reprod Health</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>544</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Magadi</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Madise</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Frequency and timing of antenatal care in Kenya: explaining the variations between women of different communities</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>551</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10868670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0277-9536(99)00495-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Melo</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>De Oliveira</surname><given-names>R R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>de Freitas Mathias</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. [<article-title>Factors associated with the quality of prenatal care: an approach to premature birth]</article-title>. <source>Rev Esc Enferm USP</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>540</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26353089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/S0080-623420150000400002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boerma</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bicego</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Preceding birth intervals and child survival: searching for pathways of influence</article-title>. <source>Stud Fam Plann</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>243</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>56</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1412597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Din&#231;er</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kaushal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Women's education: harbinger of another spring? Evidence from a natural experiment in Turkey</article-title>. <source>World Dev</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>243</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>