<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Respir Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Respir Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">80</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">rr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Respiratory Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1465-9921</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1465-993X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11059669</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11059669.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11059669</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11059669</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38685071</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-024-02819-w</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2819</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Smoking status and clinical outcome in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: a nationwide study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names initials="HY">Hee-Young</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="H">Hoseob</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yoonjong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names initials="JW">Jin Woo</given-names></name><address><email>jwsongasan@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412678.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0634 1623</institution-id><institution>Division of Allergy and Respiratory Diseases, </institution><institution>Soonchunhyang University Seoul Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Seoul, Republic of Korea </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.488317.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0626 1869</institution-id><institution>Department of Data Science, </institution><institution>Hanmi Pharm. Co., Ltd, </institution></institution-wrap>Seoul, Republic of Korea </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.267370.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0533 4667</institution-id><institution>Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, Asan Medical Center, </institution><institution>University of Ulsan College of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>88, Olympic-Ro 43-Gil, Songpa-Gu, Seoul, 05505 Republic of Korea </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">452476</issue-id><elocation-id>191</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>29</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>30</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-01 10:25:34.103"><day>01</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12931_2024_Article_2819.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Smoking status has been linked to the development of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF). However, the effect of smoking on the prognosis of patients with IPF is unclear. We aimed to investigate the association between smoking status and all-cause mortality or hospitalisation by using national health claims data.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">IPF cases were defined as people who visited medical institutions between January 2002 and December 2018 with IPF and rare incurable disease exempted calculation codes from the National Health Insurance Database. Total 10,182 patients with available data on smoking status were included in this study. Ever-smoking status was assigned to individuals with a history of smoking&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;6 pack-years. The multivariable Cox proportional hazard model was used to evaluate the association between smoking status and prognosis.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">In the entire cohort, the mean age was 69.4 years, 73.9% were males, and 45.2% were ever smokers (current smokers: 14.2%; former smokers: 31.0%). Current smokers (hazard ratio [HR]: 0.709; 95% confidence interval [CI]: 0.643&#8211;0.782) and former smokers (HR: 0.926; 95% CI: 0.862&#8211;0.996) were independently associated with all-cause mortality compared with non-smokers. Current smokers (HR: 0.884; 95% CI: 0.827&#8211;0.945) and former smokers (HR: 0.909; 95% CI: 0.862&#8211;0.959) were also associated with a reduced risk of all-cause hospitalisation compared with non-smokers. A non-linear association between smoking amount and prognosis was found in a spline HR curve and showed increasing risk below 6 pack-years.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Ever-smoking status may be associated with favourable clinical outcomes in patients with IPF.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12931-024-02819-w.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</kwd><kwd>Smoking</kwd><kwd>Mortality</kwd><kwd>Hospitalization</kwd><kwd>Prognosis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100003725</institution-id><institution>National Research Foundation of Korea</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NRF-2022R1A2B5B02001602</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par7">Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF) is a chronic progressive fibrosing interstitial pneumonia of unknown aetiology predominantly affecting older male smokers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Recent studies suggest that recurrent injuries to the alveolar epithelium stimulate the fibrogenic pathway, thus leading to the activation of fibroblasts and the production of excessive extracellular matrix in genetically susceptible individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Risk factors for the IPF include older age, male sex, genetic mutation, environmental and occupational exposures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], and cigarette smoking [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">Previous studies have highlighted the association between cigarette smoking and IPF development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], with 60&#8211;80% of IPF having a history of smoking [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Recent studies showed a dose-dependent relationship between smoking amount and IPF incidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. However, the effect of smoking on IPF prognosis is controversial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Some research indicates smokers with IPF have better outcomes than non-smokers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], whereas others find no difference when considering disease severity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. A recent study on patients with interstitial lung disease (ILD) (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;377, IPF&#8201;=&#8201;59) showed that heavy smokers (&#8805;&#8201;20 pack-years) had worse survival than never or mild smokers (0.1&#8211;19.9 pack-years) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Smoking may also affect poor survival because it increases the risk of lung cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. However, many of these findings come from single-center studies with limited number of patients (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;98&#8211;461) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Thus, we aimed to investigate the association between smoking status and prognosis in a large number of patients with IPF by using a nationwide claims database.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Data sources</title><p id="Par9">Data were obtained from the National Health Insurance Sharing Service (NHISS) database, which includes all claims data, such as qualification, insurance premiums, registration status for rare and incurable diseases, clinic visits, and treatment status, of Korean citizens. All South Korean residents aged&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;20 years are provided with a biennial health check-up, including smoking status [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], and this information is also stored in the NHISS database. Survival data were obtained from the Korean Statistical Information Service. The Institutional Review Board of Asan Medical Center approved this study (no. S2021-1136-0011) and did not require informed consent due to its retrospective nature and the use of de-identified data.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study population</title><p id="Par10">IPF cases were identified using both the IPF diagnostic code of the Korean Standard Classification of Disease (KCD) (7<sup>th</sup> edition), a modified version of the International Classification of Disease and Related Health Problems (10<sup>th</sup> revision), and a rare intractable diseases (RID) program code. To be eligible for the RID program, patients must meet the National Health Insurance (NHI) criteria, which require the (1) exclusion of other conditions that could cause ILD, (2) presence of a usual interstitial pneumonia pattern on chest computed tomography (CT) or on surgical lung biopsy along with corresponding chest CT findings. Owing to the strictness of the final registration process reviewed by the NHI, the RID code has been used for identification of other rare diseases in previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p><p id="Par11">We screened 22,301 patients who visited secondary and tertiary medical institutions with both IPF (J84.1) and RID registration (V236) diagnostic codes and underwent chest CT within 3 months from the index date (the first date of identification of J84.1 and V236 codes) (Additional file 1: Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). From these, we excluded those diagnosed in 2018 due to insufficient follow-up (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;2,407), those under 50 years (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;767) considering the lower possibility of IPF diagnosis, and those without a recorded smoking status as they didn&#8217;t undergo health check-ups (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8,948). A total of 10,182 patients were included in this study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Definition</title><p id="Par12">The participants were classified into never, former, and current smokers on the basis of their smoking status. Ever smokers (current and former smokers) were defined as individuals with &#8805;&#8201;6 pack-years of smoking by using spline hazard ratio (HR) curve analysis. Former smokers were defined as individuals who smoked at least 6 pack-years in their lifetime but had quit smoking at survey time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The follow-up periods were calculated from the index date to the occurrence of the events or censoring (December 2018). The primary outcome was the occurrence of all-cause death or the first hospitalisation for all-cause or respiratory cause. Respiratory hospitalisations were identified using codes for diseases of the respiratory system (KCD J00-J99). Comorbidities were identified when patients had&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;two visits to medical institutions with the same comorbidity codes within 1 year from the index date. Medication history included the use of antifibrotics (pirfenidone) or corticosteroids (oral or injectable form) for &#8805;&#8201;1 month. The analysis also used socioeconomic variables as covariates, including insurance types (NHI vs. medical aid), household income (high vs. low [defined as the lowest 30% of NHI premium]), and residence type (urban vs. rural areas).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par13">All variables were presented as mean&#8201;&#177;&#8201;standard deviation or numbers (percentage). Differences between groups were assessed using paired t-tests or chi-square tests. Kaplan&#8211;Meier survival curve analysis and a log-rank test evaluated survival differences among groups. Cox proportional hazards analysis was performed to identify the risk factors for mortality or hospitalisation. A multivariable analysis was adjusted for preselected covariates, including clinical (age, sex, diagnosis year, Charlson comorbidity index [CCI], prescribed medication, and home oxygen use) and socioeconomic (type of insurance, income, region) covariates. To evaluate the association between smoking amount and prognosis, smoking amount was examined as a continuous variable or by using quartiles: Q1 (1&#8211;17 pack-years), Q2 (18&#8211;29 pack-years), Q3 (30&#8211;39 pack-years), and Q4 (40&#8211;200 pack-years). We performed subgroup analyses based on sex (male vs. female) and age (&lt;&#8201;65 years vs.&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;65 years). We also performed analyses using three different approaches: stratification by quartiles of year of diagnosis (Q1: 2009&#8211;2010, Q2: 2011&#8211;2012, Q3: 2013&#8211;2014, Q4: 2015&#8211;2017), antifibrotics availability (before vs. after October 2015), and treatment status (none, antifibrotics only, steroids only, antifibrotics and steroids). A cubic spline HR curve analysis was used to identify the non-linear dose-dependent relationships after adjusting for clinical and socioeconomic covariates. The adjusted HR used 6 pack-years (the lowest HR value observed in the spline curve analysis) as a reference. Analyses were conducted using SAS version 9.4 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA), and a two-tailed <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value of &lt;&#8201;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Baseline characteristics and outcomes</title><p id="Par14">Among the patients (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;10,182), the mean age was 69.4 years, 73.9% were male, and 45.3%&#160;were ever smokers (current: 14.2%; former: 31.0%) (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The mean smoking amount was 10.6&#8201;&#177;&#8201;12.8 pack years, and Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> in Additional file 1 shows participant distribution of smoking amounts. The most common comorbidity was dyslipidaemia (69.6%), followed by hypertension (59.4%).</p><p id="Par15">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of baseline characteristics of patients with IPF according to smoking status</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Total</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Never</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Ever smokers</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Former</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of patients</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,182</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,574</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,608</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,159</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,449</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69.4&#8201;&#177;&#8201;8.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.4&#8201;&#177;&#8201;8.3*<sup>&#8224;&#8225;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.4&#8201;&#177;&#8201;7.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69&#8201;&#177;&#8201;7.7<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.7&#8201;&#177;&#8201;7.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7,528 (73.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,011 (54.0)*<sup>&#8224;&#8225;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4,517 (98.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,129 (99.1)<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,388 (95.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Body mass index, kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup>&#8225;</sup>24.0&#8201;&#177;&#8201;3.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.9&#8201;&#177;&#8201;3.1<sup>&#8224;&#8225;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.0&#8201;&#177;&#8201;3.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.2&#8201;&#177;&#8201;2.9<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.7&#8201;&#177;&#8201;3.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking amount, pack years</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.6&#8201;&#177;&#8201;12.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.0*<sup>&#8224;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.5&#8201;&#177;&#8201;7.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.3&#8201;&#177;&#8201;7.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.8&#8201;&#177;&#8201;7.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low household income</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,528 (15.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">835 (15.0)<sup>&#8225;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">693 (15.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">451 (14.3)<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">242 (16.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medical aid</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">119 (1.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56 (1.0)<sup>&#8225;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63 (1.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (0.9)<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 (2.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Comorbidity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Lung cancer</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,134 (11.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">551 (9.9)*<sup>&#8224;&#8225;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">583 (12.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">383 (12.1)<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200 (13.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Diabetes mellitus</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,285 (51.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,865 (51.4)<sup>&#8224;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,420 (52.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,702 (53.9)<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">718 (49.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Dyslipidaemia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7,084 (69.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,931 (70.5)*<sup>&#8225;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,153 (68.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,209 (69.9)<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">944 (65.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Hypertension</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,047 (59.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,346 (60.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,701 (58.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,906 (60.3)<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">795 (54.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Ischaemic heart disease</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,174 (31.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,730 (31.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,444 (31.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,031 (32.6)<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">413 (28.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Arrhythmias</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,198 (11.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">650 (11.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">548 (11.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">409 (12.9)<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">139 (9.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Infection</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,849 (18.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,076 (19.3)*<sup>&#8224;&#8225;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">773 (16.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">556 (17.6)<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">217 (15.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Tuberculosis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,743 (17.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,020 (18.3)*<sup>&#8224;&#8225;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">723 (15.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">520 (16.5)<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">203 (14.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;NTM<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94 (0.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60 (1.1)<sup>&#8225;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (0.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (0.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (0.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Fungal infection</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80 (0.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (0.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38 (0.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (1.0)<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (0.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Invasive pulmonary aspergillosis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98 (1.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51 (0.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 (1.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36 (1.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (0.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;COPD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,241 (12.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">590 (10.6)*<sup>&#8224;&#8225;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">651 (14.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">457 (14.5)<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">194 (13.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Renal failure</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">810 (8.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">441 (7.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">369 (8.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">273 (8.6)<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96 (6.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;CCI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.9<sup>&#8224;&#8225;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.9<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Treatment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Pirfendone</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,937 (28.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,327 (23.8)*<sup>&#8224;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,610 (34.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,211 (38.3)<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">399 (27.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Median duration, month (IQR)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.2 (4.2&#8211;22.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.7 (4&#8211;22)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.8 (4.4&#8211;23.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.5 (4.9&#8211;24)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.4 (3.7&#8211;22)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Corticosteroid</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6,207 (61.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,510 (63.0)*<sup>&#8224;&#8225;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,697 (58.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,878 (59.4)<sup>&#167;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">819 (56.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Home oxygen supply<sup>&#8225;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98 (1.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46 (0.8)<sup>&#8224;</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52 (1.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 (1.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (1.2)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data were expressed as mean&#8201;&#177;&#8201;standard deviation or number (%). IPF, idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis; BMI, body mass index; NTM, nontuberculous mycobacterial; COPD, chronic obstructive lung disease; CCI, Charlson comorbidity index; IQR, interquartile range</p><p>*The <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value was &lt;&#8201;0.05 when comparing never and ever smokers. &#8224;The p-value was &lt;&#8201;0.05 when comparing between never and former smokers. &#8225;The <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value was &lt;&#8201;0.05 when comparing between never and current smokers. &#167;The <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value was &lt;&#8201;0.05 when comparing former and current smokers</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par16">Never smokers were older, more frequently female, and less likely to use pirfenidone than ever smokers. Never smokers exhibited higher mortality rates than ever, former, and current smokers (Additional file 1: Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Never smokers also showed higher rates of all-cause or respiratory hospitalisation than ever and former smokers. Current smokers were younger, more frequently male, more likely to require medical aid, and less likely to be prescribed pirfenidone than former smokers (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Current smokers had lower mortality, longer hospitalisation-free survival time than former smokers (Additional file 1: Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Association with all-cause mortality</title><p id="Par17">During the follow-up (median: 3.1 years; interquartile range: 0.0&#8211;10.0 years), 4,576 (44.9%) patients died. Median survival was 5.4 years (95% confidence interval [CI]: 5.3&#8211;5.6 years). Never smokers had worse survival (median survival period: 5.1 vs. 5.8 years; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001) than ever smokers (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). Current smokers showed better survival (6.8 years) than never smokers (5.1 years, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001) and former smokers (5.3 years, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001). However, former smokers showed no difference from never (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.125) (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b).</p><p id="Par18">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Association between smoking and mortality according to smoking status in patients with IPF. (<bold>a</bold>) Comparison of the survival curves between never and ever smokers in patients with IPF. (<bold>b</bold>) Comparison of the survival curves among never, former, and current smokers in patients with IPF. (<bold>c</bold>) Spline curve analysis of smoking amount for the prognosis</p><p> The Kaplan&#8211;Meier method was used for overall survival estimates, and the log-rank test was used for survival differences by subgroups. The spline curve hazard ratio was computed by adjusting covariates including age, sex, diagnosis year, Charlson comorbidity index, medication (use of steroid and pirfenidone), medical aid, residential address, and low household income. The reference point (6 pack-years) was indicated by a vertical dashed line</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e886" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12931_2024_2819_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par19">Cox proportional analysis found that ever smokers were associated with decreased mortality risk in unadjusted and adjusted (HR: 0.853; 95% CI: 0.798&#8211;0.912) models compared with never smokers (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Current smokers were associated with a decreased risk of mortality compared with never smokers in the unadjusted model; however, in the multivariable analysis, both former smokers (HR: 0.926; 95% CI: 0.862&#8211;0.996) and current smokers (HR: 0.709; 95% CI: 0.643&#8211;0.782) were independently associated with a decreased risk of mortality. The increased number of pack-years showed a marginal association with mortality in unadjusted and adjusted models (HR: 0.998; 95% CI: 0.997&#8211;1.000) (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). When smoking amounts were categorised into quartiles, all quartiles showed a decreased risk of mortality compared to never smokers (reference: 0 pack-years) in the unadjusted and multivariable analyses.</p><p id="Par20">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Cox proportional hazards analysis for risk factors of mortality in patients with IPF</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Unadjusted</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Multivariable</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HR</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HR</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Two groups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Never (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;5,574)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Ever (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;4,608)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.877</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.827&#8211;0.930</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.853</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.798&#8211;0.912</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Three groups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Never (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;5,574)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Former (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;3,159)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.963</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.902&#8211;1.027</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.249</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.926</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.862&#8211;0.996</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.038</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Current (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1,449)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.716</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.653&#8211;0.785</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.709</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.643&#8211;0.782</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking amount*</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.998</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.997&#8211;1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.033</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.998</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.997&#8211;1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.037</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Never (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;5,574)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Q1 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1,145)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.870</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.789&#8211;0.960</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.005</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.818</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.739&#8211;0.906</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Q2 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1,077)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.880</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.795&#8211;0.973</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.013</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.840</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.755&#8211;0.934</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Q3 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;956)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.822</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.738&#8211;0.915</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.875</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.782&#8211;0.979</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.020</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Q4 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1,430)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.917</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.842&#8211;0.999</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.048</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.878</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.802&#8211;0.962</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.005</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>IPF, idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis; HR, hazard ratio; CI, confidence interval; pyrs, pack-years</p><p>*Smoking amount (pack-years) was treated as a continuous variable for the analysis. Smoking amount was divided into Q1 (1&#8211;17 pack-years), Q2 (18&#8211;29 pack-years), Q3 (30&#8211;39 pack-years), and Q4 (40&#8211;200 pack-years). The multivariable Cox model was adjusted for age, sex, diagnosis year, Charlson comorbidity index, medication (use of steroid and pirfenidone), medical aid, residential address, and low household income</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par21">After adjusting for all covariates (age, sex, diagnosis year, CCI, medication, medical aid, regional types, and low household income), spline HR curve analysis showed a non-linear association between smoking amount and all-cause mortality, with a nadir of mortality risk at 6 pack-years (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c). A significant increase in mortality risk was observed below 6 pack-years (highest mortality at 0 pack-years [HR: 1.218; 95% CI: 1.077&#8211;1.377]), whereas no increases in mortality risk were found above 6 pack-years when 6 pack-years were used as a reference.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Association with hospitalisation</title><p id="Par22">The median hospitalisation-free survival time for all-cause and respiratory-cause hospitalisation was 0.7 years (95% CI: 0.6&#8211;0.7 years) and 2.0 years (95% CI: 1.9&#8211;2.1 years), respectively. In the Kaplan&#8211;Meier survival analysis, never smokers had worse all-cause hospitalisation-free survival (median survival period: 0.6 vs. 0.8 years, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.001) than ever smokers (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). When classified into three groups, never smokers had worse hospitalisation-free survival (0.6 vs. 0.8 years [former] vs. 0.8 years [current], <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001) than the other groups; however, there were no differences between former and current smokers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.747) (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). Regarding respiratory hospitalisation, never smokers showed worse hospitalisation-free survival (median survival period: 1.6 vs. 2.5 years, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001) than ever smokers (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). Never smokers also had worse hospitalisation-free survival (1.6 vs. 2.1 years [former] vs. 3.6 years [current], <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001) than former and current smokers (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). Additionally, former smokers had shorter hospitalisation-free survival than current smokers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.001).</p><p id="Par23">
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Association between smoking and all-cause hospitalisation according to smoking status in patients with IPF. (<bold>a</bold>) Comparison of the all-cause hospitalisation-free survival curves between never and ever smokers in patients with IPF. (<bold>b</bold>) Comparison of the all-cause hospitalisation-free survival curves among never, former, and current smokers in patients with IPF. (<bold>c</bold>) Spline curve analysis of smoking amount for the all-cause hospitalisation</p><p>The Kaplan&#8211;Meier method was used for all-cause hospitalisation estimates, and the log-rank test was used for all-cause hospitalisation differences by subgroups. The spline curve hazard ratio was computed by adjusting covariates including age, sex, diagnosis year, Charlson comorbidity index, medication (use of steroid and pirfenidone), medical aid, residential address, and low household income. The reference point (6 pack-years) was indicated by a vertical dashed line</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1222" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12931_2024_2819_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par24">
<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Association between smoking and respiratory hospitalisation according to smoking status in patients with IPF. (<bold>a</bold>) Comparison of the respiratory hospitalisation-free survival curves between never and ever smokers in patients with IPF. (<bold>b</bold>) Comparison of the respiratory hospitalisation-free survival curves among never, former, and current smokers in patients with IPF. (<bold>c</bold>) Spline curve analysis of smoking amount for the respiratory hospitalisation</p><p>The Kaplan&#8211;Meier method was used for respiratory hospitalisation estimates, and the log-rank test was used for respiratory hospitalisation differences by subgroups. Spline curve hazard ratio was computed by adjusting covariates including age, sex, diagnosis year, Charlson comorbidity index, medication (use of steroid, pirfenidone), medical aid, residential address, and low household income. The reference point (6 pack-years) was indicated by a vertical dashed line</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1243" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12931_2024_2819_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par25">In terms of all-cause hospitalisation, ever smokers had a decreased risk of hospitalisation compared with never smokers in the unadjusted and multivariable analysis (HR: 0.901; 95% CI: 0.857&#8211;0.974) (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Former smokers (HR: 0.909; 95% CI: 0.862&#8211;0.959) and current smokers (HR: 0.884; 95% CI: 0.827&#8211;0.945) were associated with a decreased risk of hospitalisation on the multivariable analysis. In terms of respiratory hospitalisation, ever smokers had a reduced risk of hospitalisation compared with the never smokers in both the unadjusted analysis and adjusted analysis (HR: 0.860; 95% CI: 0.813&#8211;0.910) (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Former smokers (HR: 0.939; 95% CI: 0.883&#8211;0.997) and current smokers (HR: 0.746; 95% CI: 0.688&#8211;0.808) were independently associated with a reduced risk of respiratory hospitalisation in the multivariable analysis.</p><p id="Par26">
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The Cox proportional hazards analysis for the risk factors of hospitalisation in patients with IPF</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">All-cause</th><th align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Respiratory</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Unadjusted</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Multivariable</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Unadjusted</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Multivariable</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HR</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HR</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HR</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HR</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Two groups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Never (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;5,574)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Ever (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;4,608)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.854</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.810&#8211;0.890</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.901</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.857&#8211;0.947</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.809</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.771&#8211;0.848</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.860</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.813&#8211;0.910</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Three groups</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Never (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;5,574)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Former (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;3,159)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.864</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.825&#8211;0.905</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.909</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.862&#8211;0.959</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.885</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.839&#8211;0.992</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.939</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.883&#8211;0.997</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.040</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Current (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1,449)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.833</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.783&#8211;0.885</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.884</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.827&#8211;0.945</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.695</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.644&#8211;0.749</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.746</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.688&#8211;0.808</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Smoking amount*</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.998</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.997&#8211;1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.005</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.999&#8211;1.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.989</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.994</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.992&#8211;0.995</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.996</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.994&#8211;0.998</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Never (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;5,574)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Q1 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1,145)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.862</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.805&#8211;0.924</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.904</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.840&#8211;0.972</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.007</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.790</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.728&#8211;0.856</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.197</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.957&#8211;1.497</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.115</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Q2 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1,077)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.818</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.761&#8211;0.879</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.874</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.809&#8211;0.943</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.796</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.733&#8211;0.865</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.830</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.762&#8211;0.903</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Q3 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;956)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.862</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.800&#8211;0.929</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.941</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.869&#8211;1.108</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.131</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.851</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.781&#8211;0.927</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.853</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.782&#8211;0.931</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Q4 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1,430)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.937</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.881&#8211;0.997</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.041</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.988</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.924&#8211;1.057</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.730</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.843</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.785&#8211;0.906</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.925</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.845&#8211;1.103</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.092</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>IPF, idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis; HR, hazard ratio; CI, confidence interval; pyrs, pack-years</p><p>*Smoking amount (pack-years) was treated as a continuous variable for the analysis. Smoking amount was divided into Q1 (1&#8211;17 pack-years), Q2 (18&#8211;29 pack-years), Q3 (30&#8211;39 pack-years), and Q4 (40&#8211;200 pack-years). An multivariable model was adjusted for age, sex, diagnosis year, Charlson comorbidity index, medication (use of steroid and pirfenidone), medical aid, residential address, and low household income</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par27">In the multivariable analysis, smoking amount was insignificantly associated with all-cause hospitalisation but significantly associated with respiratory hospitalisation (HR: 0.996; 95% CI: 0.994&#8211;0.998). When smoking amounts were categorised into quartiles, Q1 (HR: 0.904; 95% CI: 0.840&#8211;0.972) and Q2 (HR: 0.874; 95% CI: 0.809&#8211;0.943) showed a decreased risk of all-cause hospitalisation compared with never smokers (zero pack-years) (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). A decreased risk of respiratory hospitalisation was also observed in Q2 (HR: 0.835; 95% CI: 0.782&#8211;0.892) and Q3 (HR: 0.887; 95% CI: 0.830&#8211;0.949) in the multivariable analysis (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><p id="Par28">The spline HR curve analysis, after adjusting all clinical and socioeconomic covariates, showed a non-linear association between smoking amounts and all-cause hospitalisation. Below 6 pack-years, the risk of all-cause hospitalisation significantly increased with the highest risk at zero pack-years (HR: 1.163; 95% CI: 1.065&#8211;1.270); however, there was no significant association beyond 6 pack-years (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c). Similar trends were exhibited in the spline HR curve analysis for respiratory hospitalisation, with an increased risk below 6 pack-years (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Subgroup analysis stratified by sex and age</title><p id="Par29">We performed stratified analyses by sex. In men, similar to the main analysis, ever smoker or former and current smokers were independently associated with a lower risk of mortality and all-cause or respiratory hospitalisation in the multivariable analysis (Additional file 1: Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). In the analysis of smoking amount, high smoking levels were also independently associated with a decreased risk of mortality and respiratory hospitalisation in the multivariable analysis (Additional file 1: Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). In women, ever smokers and smoking amount showed a numerical trend towards lower risk of death and hospitalisation, but were only significantly associated with respiratory hospitalisation (Additional file 1: Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> and Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). Current smokers also showed a reduced risk of all-cause and respiratory hospitalisation in the multivariable analysis (Additional file 1: Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>).</p><p id="Par30">In the analysis stratified by age group (&lt;&#8201;65 years and &#8805;&#8201;65 years), associations between smoking status and clinical outcomes were consistently observed in the multivariable analysis (Additional file 1: Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). In younger age group, ever and current smokers were independently associated with a lower risk of mortality and all-cause or respiratory hospitalisation in the multivariable analysis (Additional file 1: Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). In older age group, ever and current smokers were also independently associated with a lower risk of mortality and respiratory hospitalisation in the multivariable analysis (Additional file 1: Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). Smoking amount showed a numerical trend towards lower risk of death and hospitalisation, but did not reach statistical significance in either age group (Additional file 1: Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Subgroup analysis stratified by years of diagnosis and treatment status</title><p id="Par31">When we performed stratified analyses by quartiles of the year of diagnosis, the results were similar to the main findings (Additional file 1: Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>). Both ever smokers and current smokers showed a significant association with reduced mortality in the multivariate analysis, with the exception of the third quartile (2013&#8211;2014). Respiratory admissions also showed similar results in both groups. However, for former smokers, the results were not significant in most periods except Q4.</p><p id="Par32">In an analysis stratifying patients based on antifibrotis availability (before vs. after October 2015), consistent results were observed, indicating a favourable prognosis for ever smokers compared with never smokers in both time periods (Additional file 1: Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>). In the analysis stratified by treatment status, the results were also consistent with the main analysis (Additional file 1: Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S8</xref>). In the untreated patient group, both ever and current smokers had a significantly lower risk of respiratory hospitalisation. In the group treated with steroids alone, both ever and current smokers also had a reduced risk of mortality, and respiratory hospitalisation. Among patients treated with both steroid and pirfenidone, current smokers had a significant reduction in mortality and respiratory hospitalisation. In the group treated with pirfenidone alone, there was also a trend towards a reduced risk of death in both current and former smokers, although this was not statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par33">In this large-scale population-based study using a claim database, we demonstrated an association between smoking status and clinical outcomes in patients with IPF. Current and former smokers had better prognoses, including lower mortality and fewer hospitalisations, than never smokers. We also found a non-linear association between smoking amount and prognosis in IPF.</p><p id="Par34">In our study, smoking was associated with IPF mortality, consistent with previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Kishaba et al. in a retrospective IPF cohort (n&#8201;=&#8201;98) showed that never smokers had worse median survival (18.5 vs. 26.3 months) than ever smokers after adjusting for composite physiologic index (CPI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. King et al. reported that current smokers, being generally younger (54.7 years [current] vs. 62.3 years [never] vs. 62.6 years [former], <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) had better survival (median survival period: 116.4 months) than other groups (former smokers: 25.3 months; never smokers: 27.2 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001) in a prospective IPF cohort (n&#8201;=&#8201;238) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Better survival for current smokers may result from earlier diagnoses due to smoking-related symptoms, leading to lead-time bias (healthy smoker&#8217; effect) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. This effect can be taken into account in our study because the average age of never-smokers is higher than that of smokers (ever, current and former). However, in our study, both age-adjusted multivariable results and analyses stratified by age showed better prognosis in smokers.</p><p id="Par35">However, Antonious et al. in a retrospective IPF cohort (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;249), reported that current smokers had a lower risk of mortality in an unadjusted analysis than the other groups, but did not show a difference (HR: 0.75; 95% CI: 0.40&#8211;1.43) in mortality risk compared with former smokers after adjusting for CPI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. In addition, never smokers showed a lower mortality rate in both the unadjusted and CPI-adjusted analyses (HR: 0.48; 95% CI: 0.32&#8211;0.71) compared with former smokers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. K&#228;rkk&#228;inen et al. in a retrospective IPF cohort (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;128) also demonstrated that current smokers (HR: 0.52; 95% CI: 0.29&#8211;0.95) and never smokers (HR: 0.64; 95% CI: 0.42&#8211;0.97) had a decreased risk of mortality compared with former smokers in the unadjusted analysis; but this effect disappeared when adjusting for disease severity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Therefore, previous studies have demonstrated that the beneficial effects of smoking on IPF outcomes disappeared when controlling for lung function or disease severity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. However, in our study, current smokers had a better prognosis than never or former smokers even after adjusting for individual and socioeconomic variables.</p><p id="Par36">We observed an association between ever smokers and a decreased risk of hospitalisation. Acute exacerbation (AE) is one of the leading causes of hospitalisation in patients with IPF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. The effect of smoking on AE occurrence in IPF varies across studies, with some studies showing a positive association [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], whereas others show a negative one [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Cao et al., in 107 patients with IPF, demonstrated that ever-smoking was a risk factor for AE occurrence (HR: 1.974; 95% CI: 1.140&#8211;3.419) in those with a UIP pattern on high-resolution CT but not in those with a possible UIP pattern [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Similarly, the phase 3 trial of nintedanib for patients with IPF (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1,062) suggested that ever-smoking was associated with increased risk of AE (adjusted HR: 2.13; 95% CI: 0.89&#8211;5.13; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.09) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. However, Song et al., in 461 patients with IPF, reported that ever-smoking was associated with a decreased risk of AE (HR: 0.585; 95% CI: 0.342&#8211;1.001, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.050) when adjusted by age and lung function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Kishaba et al. also showed that never smokers had a higher AE incidence (50% vs. 18%). than ever smokers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. These findings were in line with our results.</p><p id="Par37">This finding of better outcomes in smokers may be partly explained by smoking-induced upregulation of heat shock proteins (HSPs), particularly HSP70 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. HSP70, known for its protective effects, including inhibition of transforming growth factor-beta-&#946; (TGF-&#946;)-dependent epithelial-mesenchymal transition and anti-inflammatory properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], may delay IPF progression. In addition, smoking has been reported to upregulate autophagy markers, such as microtubule-associated protein 1&#160;A/1B light chain 3B (LC3B) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Increased LC3B activity, known for its antifibrotic effects in alveolar epithelial cells, may also contribute to slower IPF progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. This is supported by an in vitro study showing that inhibition of autophagy by LC3B knockdown in human lung fibroblasts increased &#945;-smooth muscle actin and type I collagen expression, which was further enhanced by TGF-&#946; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. In addition, lower levels of LC3B in IPF lung compared to the normal lung [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] highlight its potential role in IPF progression.</p><p id="Par38">Our study showed that a significant association between smoking and favourable prognosis was more frequently observed in men. This may be due to several factors, including physiological differences between the sexes, such as women having anatomically narrower airways and lower lung function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. In addition, the potential of smoking to increase oestrogen levels in women may increase the risk of mortality by increasing the likelihood of cancer and thrombosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Moreover, genetic factors may affect the effects of smoking differently in men and women. A study by Paul showed more smoking-induced genetic changes in female smokers than in males, suggesting a greater susceptibility of women to tobacco carcinogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. However, it is also possible that the relatively smaller sample size of female IPF patients in our study may have resulted in less statistical significance in the observed results.</p><p id="Par39">Our study has some limitations. First, our reliance on medical check-up data may introduce selection bias owing to the inclusion of patients with high health concerns or socioeconomic status. However, the wide coverage of the national health examination in Korea ensures that the characteristics of our study population are representative of the broader IPF population in South Korea. Second, IPF diagnoses may be overestimated owing to the use of diagnostic codes to define IPF cases. Therefore, we utilised both IPF and RID registration codes to define cases. Finally, our analysis was based on a claims database, which limits the inclusion of lung function in the analysis. However, we included clinical variables known to be associated with IPF prognosis, including home oxygen use, medications, and CCI, in our multivariable analysis.</p><p id="Par40">In conclusion, our results suggest that smoking may be associated with clinical outcomes in IPF, with a non-linear association with smoking amount. These findings highlight the complex relationship between smoking and IPF prognosis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><sec id="Sec14"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12931_2024_2819_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Additional file 1. Fig. S1 Flow diagram of the study population; Fig. S2 Distribution of smoking pack-years in the IPF cohort; Table S1. Comparison of clinical outcome in patients with IPF according to smoking status; Table S2. The multivariable Cox proportional hazards analysis for the risk factors of prognosis in patients with IPF according to the smoking status stratified by sex; Table S3. The multivariable Cox proportional hazards analysis for the risk factors of prognosis in patients with IPF according to the smoking amount stratified by sex; Table S4. The multivariable Cox proportional hazards analysis for the risk factors of prognosis in patients with IPF stratified by age; Table S5. The multivariable Cox proportional hazards analysis for the risk factors of prognosis in patients with IPF according to the smoking amount stratified by age.; Table S6. The multivariable Cox proportional hazards analysis for the risk factors of prognosis in patients with IPF stratified by year of diagnosis; Table S7. The multivariable Cox proportional hazards analysis for the risk factors of prognosis in patients with IPF stratified by antifibrotics availability; Table S8. The multivariable Cox proportional hazards analysis for the risk factors of prognosis in patients with IPF stratified by the treatment status</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#8217;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>None.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>J.W.S. performed data acquisition and was responsible for study conception and design and manuscript content such as data analysis. H.K. and Y.B. performed statistical analysis and data interpretation. H-Y.Y. and J.W.S. were responsible for writing the first draft. All authors reviewed and have approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was supported by grants from the Basic Science Research Program (NRF-2022R1A2B5B02001602) and the Bio &amp; Medical Technology Development Program (NRF-2022M3A9E4082647) of the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) funded by the Ministry of Science &amp; ICT, Republic of Korea. This study was also supported by the National Institute of Health research project (2021ER120701) and the Korea Environment Industry &amp; Technology Institute via the Core Technology Development Project for Environmental Diseases Prevention and Management Program funded by the Korea Ministry of Environment (RS-2022-<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="KE002197">KE002197</ext-link>), Republic of Korea.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par44">The Institutional Review Board of Asan Medical Center approved this study (no. S2021-1136-0011). Written informed consent was waived because of the retrospective design and the use of de-identified data. This study was conducted in accordance with the ethical standards of the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></notes><notes id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par45">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar5" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par42">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>IPF</term><def><p id="Par46">Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CT</term><def><p id="Par471">Computed tomography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ILD</term><def><p id="Par481">Intestinal lung disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NHISS</term><def><p id="Par49">National Health Insurance Sharing Service</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NHI</term><def><p id="Par50">National Health Insurance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RID</term><def><p id="Par51">Rare intractable diseases</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KCD</term><def><p id="Par52">Korean Standard Classification of Disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HR</term><def><p id="Par53">Hazard ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p id="Par54">Confidence interval</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AE</term><def><p id="Par55">Acute exacerbation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UIP</term><def><p id="Par56">Usual interstitial pneumonia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CPI</term><def><p id="Par57">Composite physiologic index</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raghu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Remy-Jardin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richeldi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryerson</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lederer</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. An Official ATS/ERS/JRS/ALAT Clinical Practice Guideline</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>198</volume><fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201807-1255ST</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30168753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wynn</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrating mechanisms of pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>208</volume><fpage>7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20110551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3136685</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21727191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kropski</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loyd</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genetic basis of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2015</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>6</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.00163814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4849867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25837031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bendstrup</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dron</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalid</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global incidence and prevalence of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-021-01791-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34233665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8261998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T-H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Occupational and environmental risk factors of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: a systematic review and meta-analyses</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33654111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-021-81591-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7925580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Korean guidelines for diagnosis and management of interstitial Lung diseases: part 2. Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Tuberc Respir Dis (Seoul)</source><year>2019</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>2</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4046/trd.2018.0091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6435928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30841014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of smoking on the development of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: results from a nationwide population-based cohort study</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2022</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2020-215386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34593614</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baumgartner</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samet</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stidley</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colby</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waldron</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cigarette smoking: a risk factor for idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>1997</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/ajrccm.155.1.9001319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9001319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taskar</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coultas</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis an environmental disease?</article-title><source>Proc Am Thorac Soc</source><year>2006</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1513/pats.200512-131TK</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16738192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellou</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belbasis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evangelou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tobacco Smoking and Risk for Pulmonary Fibrosis: a prospective cohort study from the UK Biobank</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>2021</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>3</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chest.2021.04.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33905677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Speer</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loyd</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herron</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slifer</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical and pathologic features of familial interstitial pneumonia</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>9</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.200408-1104OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2718398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16109978</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Longitudinal changes in clinical features, management, and outcomes of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. A Nationwide Cohort Study</article-title><source>Ann Am Thorac Soc</source><year>2021</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1513/AnnalsATS.202005-451OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33270528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoyer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bendstrup</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilcke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaker</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for diagnostic delay in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-019-1076-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31126287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6534848</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wuyts</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dahlqvist</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slabbynck</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schlesser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gusbin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Compere</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Longitudinal clinical outcomes in a real-world population of patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: the PROOF registry</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-019-1182-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31651324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6813978</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kishaba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamashiro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical characteristics of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis patients according to their smoking status</article-title><source>J Thorac Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>6</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jtd.2016.03.89</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27293827</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4886024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>TE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tooze</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cherniack</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predicting survival in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: scoring system and survival model</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/ajrccm.164.7.2003140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11673205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Antoniou</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansell</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubens</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marten</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siafakas</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: outcome in relation to smoking status</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>2</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.200612-1759OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17962635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>K&#228;rkk&#228;inen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kettunen</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nurmi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selander</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Purokivi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaarteenaho</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of smoking and comorbidities on survival in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Respir Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-017-0642-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28830514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5567897</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zubairi</surname><given-names>ABS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarwar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahzad</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Irfan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical characteristics and factors associated with mortality in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: an experience from a tertiary care center in Pakistan</article-title><source>Clin Respir J</source><year>2018</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>3</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/crj.12650</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28508572</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute exacerbation of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: incidence, risk factors and outcome</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2011</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>2</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.00159709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20595144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Platenburg M, van der Vis JJ, Kazemier KM, Grutters JC, van Moorsel CHM. The detrimental effect of quantity of smoking on survival in progressive fibrosing ILD. Respir Med 2022;194.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.rmed.2022.106760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35149406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karampitsakos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spagnolo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mogulkoc</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wuyts</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomassetti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bendstrup</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lung cancer in patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: a retrospective multicentre study in Europe</article-title><source>Respirology</source><year>2023</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/resp.14363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36117239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tzouvelekis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antoniou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreuter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poletti</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The DIAMORFOSIS (DIAgnosis and management of lung canceR and FibrOSIS) survey: international survey and call for consensus</article-title><source>ERJ Open Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/23120541.00529-2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7837280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33532484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guallar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Korean National Health Insurance Database</article-title><source>JAMA Intern Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2015.7110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26747667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kim HK, Song SO, Noh J, Jeong I-K, Lee B-W. Data Configuration and Publication Trends for the Korean National Health Insurance and Health Insurance Review &amp; Assessment Database. Diabetes &amp; metabolism journal 2020;44:5.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4093/dmj.2020.0207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7643590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33115211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>S-S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y-K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cumulative incidence and trends of rare diseases in South Korea: a nationwide study of the administrative data from the National Health Insurance Service database from 2011&#8211;2015</article-title><source>Orphanet J Rare Dis</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13023-019-1032-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30777110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6379926</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Na KH, Kim HJ, Kim KH, Han S, Kim P, Hann HJ, Ahn HS. Prevalence, age at diagnosis, mortality, and cause of death in Retinitis Pigmentosa in Korea-A Nationwide Population-based study. Am J Ophthalmol 2017;176.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajo.2017.01.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28130043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kramarow EA. Health of former cigarette smokers aged 65 and over: United States, 2018. 2020.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32730739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Becklake MR, Lalloo U. The &#8216;healthy smoker&#8217;: a phenomenon of health selection? Respiration 1990;57:3.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000195837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2274712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patterns and Economic Burden of Hospitalizations and exacerbations among patients diagnosed with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>J Manag Care Spec Pharm</source><year>2016</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18553/jmcp.2016.22.4.414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10398274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27023695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acute exacerbation of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: usual interstitial pneumonitis vs. possible usual interstitial pneumonitis pattern</article-title><source>Chin Med J (Engl)</source><year>2019</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>18</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/CM9.0000000000000422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6797146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31490258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collard</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richeldi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tschoepe</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luisetti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acute exacerbations in the INPULSIS trials of nintedanib in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2017</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.01339-2016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28526798</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Volm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattern</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stammler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Up-regulation of heat shock protein 70 in adenocarcinomas of the lung in smokers</article-title><source>Anticancer Res</source><year>1995</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>6b</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8669833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roque</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heat shock proteins in pulmonary fibrosis: pawns of cell homeostasis</article-title><source>Am J Physiology-Cell Physiol</source><year>2022</year><volume>322</volume><fpage>6</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpcell.00073.2022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35508189</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kono</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colley</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>To</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Papaioannou</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mercado</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cigarette smoke-induced impairment of autophagy in macrophages increases galectin-8 and inflammation</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-79848-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33432024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7801483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kesireddy</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chillappagari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahuja</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henneke</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graumann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Susceptibility of microtubule-associated protein 1 light chain 3&#946; (MAP1LC3B/LC3B) knockout mice to lung injury and fibrosis</article-title><source>Faseb j</source><year>2019</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>11</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.201900854R</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6902724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31431059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Araya</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takasaka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insufficient autophagy in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>304</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajplung.00213.2012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23087019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of ANXA2 (annexin A2) as a specific bleomycin target to induce pulmonary fibrosis by impeding TFEB-mediated autophagic flux</article-title><source>Autophagy</source><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15548627.2017.1409405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5902212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29172997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sathish V, Prakash YS. Sex differences in pulmonary anatomy and physiology. Implications for Health and Disease. In.; 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sieminska A, Jassem E. The many faces of tobacco use among women. Med Sci Monit 2014;20.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.12659/MSM.889796</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3915001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24487778</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Paul S, Amundson SA. Differential Effect of active smoking on Gene expression in male and female smokers. J Carcinog Mutagen 2014;5.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4172/2157-2518.1000198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4303254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25621181</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>