<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1609</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmjo</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMJ Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2044-6055</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10008325</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10008325.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10008325</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10008325</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36898743</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2022-071172</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bmjopen-2022-071172</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Dermatology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1506</subject><subject>1687</subject></subj-group><series-title>Original research</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Rates of malignancies among patients with moderate to severe atopic dermatitis: a retrospective cohort study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-37391504" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1768-0412</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedderson</surname><given-names initials="MM">Monique M</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-64547694" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asgari</surname><given-names initials="MM">Maryam M</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-96160463" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="F">Fei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-57659740" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quesenberry</surname><given-names initials="CP">Charles P</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-56113276" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sridhar</surname><given-names initials="S">Sneha</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-96160467" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Geier</surname><given-names initials="J">Jamie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-96160469" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemeshow</surname><given-names initials="AR">Adina R</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<institution content-type="department">Division of Research</institution>, <institution>Kaiser Permanente Northern California</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Oakland</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">California</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<institution content-type="department">Massachusetts General Hospital</institution>, <institution>Harvard Medical School</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Boston</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Massachusetts</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<institution>Pfizer Inc</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">New York</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">New York</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp><label>Correspondence to</label> Dr Monique M Hedderson; <email>monique.m.hedderson@kp.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">430261</issue-id><elocation-id>e071172</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>10</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>13</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-03-13 10:10:11.987"><day>13</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2023. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense" start_date="2023-03-10">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See:&#160;<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-071172.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-071172.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="reviewers-comments-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-071172.reviewer_comments.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="draft-revisions-pdf" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-071172.draft_revisions.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>Patients with atopic dermatitis (AD), also known as eczema, may be at an increased risk for malignancies compared with patients without AD; however, incidence rates (IRs) of malignancies in patients with moderate to severe AD are largely unknown. The objective of this study was to evaluate and compare IRs of malignancies in adults with moderate to severe AD (aged &#8805;18 years).</p></sec><sec><title>Design</title><p>Retrospective cohort study using data from a Kaiser Permanente Northern California (KPNC) cohort. AD severity classification was adjudicated with medical chart review. Covariates and stratification variables included age, sex and smoking status.</p></sec><sec><title>Setting</title><p>Data were obtained from the KPNC healthcare delivery system in northern California, USA. Cases of AD were defined by outpatient dermatologist-rendered codes and prescriptions of topical therapy or phototherapy (moderate) or systemic treatment (severe).</p></sec><sec><title>Participants</title><p>KPNC health plan members with moderate or severe AD (2007&#8211;2018).</p></sec><sec><title>Primary and secondary outcome measures</title><p>Malignancy IRs and 95% CIs per 1000 person-years were calculated.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>7050 KPNC health plan members with moderate and severe AD met eligibility criteria for inclusion. IRs (95% CI) were highest for non-melanoma skin cancer (NMSC) in patients with moderate and severe AD (4.6 (95% CI 3.9 to 5.5) and 5.9 (95% CI 3.8 to 9.2), respectively) and breast cancer (2.2 (95% CI 1.6 to 3.0) and 0.5 (95% CI 0.1 to 3.9), respectively). Except for breast cancer, which was only evaluated in women, malignancies were higher (with non-overlapping CIs) in patients with moderate and moderate to severe AD in men versus women for basal cell carcinoma and NMSC and in former versus never smokers for NMSC and squamous cell carcinoma.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>This study estimated IRs of malignancies in patients with moderate and severe AD and provides valuable information for dermatology clinicians and ongoing clinical trials in these populations.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Dermatological epidemiology</kwd><kwd>DERMATOLOGY</kwd><kwd>Eczema</kwd><kwd>EPIDEMIOLOGY</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group specific-use="FundRef"><award-group id="funding-1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100009032</institution-id><institution>Pfizer UK</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>special-feature</meta-name><meta-value>unlocked</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>STRENGTHS AND LIMITATIONS OF THIS STUDY</title></caption><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>This study assessed a large number of participants (N=7050) with moderate or severe atopic dermatitis (AD).</p></list-item><list-item><p>The Kaiser Permanente Northern California (KPNC) cohort is racially and ethnically diverse.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The sociodemographic and health characteristics of KPNC members are very similar to the general population of northern California, and study findings are therefore likely generalisable to the broader insured population of northern California.</p></list-item><list-item><p>No control group without AD was assessed.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Causation between AD and malignancies cannot be inferred.</p></list-item></list></boxed-text><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Atopic dermatitis (AD) is a chronic and relapsing inflammatory skin condition with considerable symptom burden and disability attributed to severe itching and pain and adverse effects on sleep, anxiety and depression that increase with AD severity.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1&#8211;4</xref> The prevalence of AD has been estimated to be as high as 20% in children and almost 23% in adults, and recent data show that the prevalence is increasing.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5 6</xref> The global burden and patient-level disability associated with skin conditions such as AD are significant.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> AD has complex and multifactorial pathophysiology involving barrier dysfunction, cell-mediated immune response alterations, immunoglobulin E-mediated hypersensitivity and environmental triggers.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1 8 9</xref>
</p><p>A growing body of evidence suggests an increased risk of malignancies with chronic inflammatory conditions, including AD.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10&#8211;13</xref> Significant associations were found between AD and non-melanoma skin cancer (NMSC), lymphoma, pancreatic cancer, keratinocyte carcinoma and kidney cancer but not for most other cancers.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14&#8211;16</xref> To better inform clinical and health system decision-making for patients with AD, there is a need for robust epidemiological data that substantiate potential associations between disease severity and malignancy risk. In addition, understanding background incidence rates (IRs) of these events in the general population of patients with moderate to severe AD is important for clinicians caring for patients with moderate to severe AD and for ongoing clinical trials. A recent study from our group estimated the incidence of cardiovascular events in patients with moderate to severe AD by using epidemiological data from a racially and ethnically diverse cohort of Kaiser Permanente Northern California (KPNC) health plan members.<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> The objective of this retrospective cohort study was to estimate IRs of malignancies in moderate and severe adult AD populations using data from the same KPNC cohort.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Study design</title><p>Details of this cohort study have been described elsewhere.<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Data from adult KPNC health plan members (18 years or older) with moderate and severe AD were analysed from the KPNC database. This database constitutes approximately 30% of residents in a northern California community, who receive comprehensive healthcare and pharmaceutical benefits as members of the KPNC healthcare delivery system. KPNC health plan members are racially and ethnically diverse, with sociodemographic and health characteristics similar to the greater northern California population. Therefore, findings from this population are likely generalisable to the broader insured population of northern California.<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Electronic health records contained within the KPNC database include outpatient prescription records processed at a KPNC pharmacy.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Eligibility criteria</title><p>The eligibility criteria have been described previously.<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> The study participants were KPNC health plan members aged &#8805;18 years who were clinically diagnosed with moderate or severe AD between 1 January 2007 and 31 December 2018. Moderate or severe AD was defined as having an outpatient dermatologist-rendered visit coded with an International Classification of Diseases (ICD-9) code of 691.8 or an ICD-10 code of L20 plus treatment criteria as described below. Further inclusion criteria included enrolment in the KPNC healthcare system for at least a year before the study index date, which was defined as the first date at which an eligible patient filled a prescription for a topical or systemic agent. &#8216;Moderate&#8217; AD cases were defined as disease necessitating prescription of topical therapy or phototherapy, and &#8216;severe&#8217; AD cases were defined as disease necessitating prescription of systemic therapies (ie, alitretinoin, apremilast, azathioprine, cyclosporine, dupilumab, interferon-gamma, methotrexate, mycophenolic acid/mycophenolic mofetil, omalizumab, rituximab, ustekinumab, omalizumab or oral corticosteroids).</p><p>The exclusion criteria included any prior documented evidence of HIV infection, hepatitis B or C infection or malignancy (except NMSC or cervical carcinoma in situ); active inflammatory skin disease or tuberculosis and use of any Janus kinase inhibitors within a year before the index date; or systemic infections that required hospitalisation or parenteral antimicrobial therapy within 6 months of the index date. These criteria were applied to reflect clinical trial populations in recent studies of AD treatments. A complete list of the exclusion criteria is provided in the <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table S1</xref>. Therefore, this cohort of patients with AD may be healthier than an average AD population and may be used to contextualise safety events observed in clinical trials of AD treatments.</p><supplementary-material id="SP1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2022-071172.supp1</object-id><label>Supplementary data</label><p>
<inline-supplementary-material xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="SS1" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-071172supp001.pdf" content-type="local-data"/>
</p></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Case adjudication</title><p>The adjudication and confirmation of AD cases including determination of AD severity was based on established criteria, as described previously.<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> A board-certified dermatologist (coauthor MMA) reviewed a total of 100 cases, of which 50 were moderate and 50 were severe. Personal and family history of atopy, including asthma and allergic rhinitis, documented in the electronic medical records was also examined and weighed in assigning case status. Three case assignments were possible: a &#8216;definite&#8217; case of AD, which was defined as having documented diagnostic features in the description of clinical examination findings; a &#8216;possible&#8217; case, defined as a health plan member with some skin features found to be suggestive of AD but insufficient to be assigned as definite; and &#8216;not a case&#8217;, which was defined having no evidence of skin or symptom descriptions indicating AD or, on review of the electronic medical record, was confirmed as a different dermatological diagnosis by biopsy (eg, severe AD that was subsequently diagnosed as cutaneous T cell lymphoma). Cases identified as &#8216;not a moderate-to-severe case&#8217;, including mild AD cases, were excluded from the analytical cohort. For disease severity classification, a threshold of &#8805;80% agreement between the cases identified by study parameters and medical record review was deemed acceptable. The KPNC Institutional Review Board (IRB) approved this study.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Outcomes</title><p>Cancer types relevant to interventional AD clinical trial outcomes, including lung cancer, breast cancer, melanoma, lymphoma, NMSC, basal cell carcinoma (BCC), squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) and lymphoproliferative disorders, were selected for analysis in this study. Cases of malignancies were identified from the KPNC Regional Cancer Registry, which collects, codes and reports all cancer data (except NMSC) to the Surveillance, Epidemiology and End Results (SEER) National Cancer Registry (SEER, 2020).<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> The process of finding cases in the KPNC Regional Cancer Registry includes, but is not limited to, querying the KPNC Electronic Pathology Database, which contains text-based information on all pathology specimens received for examination, including date and type of tissue, tumour location, tumour subtype and gross and microscopic diagnoses. Although the vast majority of newly reportable cancers are discovered via pathology, the registry review process (conducted by certified tumour registrars) also used other resources such as facility inpatient/outpatient ICD-10 disease index listings and radiation therapy treatment logs. Cases of NMSC, which are not reportable to the state of California or to SEER and are not captured by the KPNC Regional Cancer Registry, were identified solely by the KPNC Electronic Pathology Database, with manual adjudication of each potential case.</p><p>Electronic health records obtained from the KPNC database provided information on sex, age, race, ethnicity and body mass index (BMI). Patient-reported behaviour/lifestyle were used to inform and obtain smoking status and BMI data, which were current as of the patient index date.<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The analyses included in this study were descriptive, with no formal power and sample size calculations. The IR of each malignancy was calculated by dividing the number of patients with an incident malignancy event with the total person-years (PY) of observation within the eligible AD cohort. Person-time for each malignancy of interest was determined by adding the number of years between the index date and the censor date. End-of-follow-up dates were determined separately for each safety event and were the earliest of: (1) the first instance of a safety event (after the index date); (2) the first instance of disenrollment or death; or (3) the end of the observation period (31 December 2018).</p><p>Descriptive statistics and IRs per 1000 PY of follow-up and 95% CIs were calculated, and no data were imputed. IRs per 1000 PY were reported overall and according to AD severity (moderate and severe) and were stratified by age group (18&#8211;39, 40&#8211;64 and &#8805;65 years), sex and smoking status. When stratified by sex, severity and smoking status, IRs with non-overlapping CIs were considered statistically significantly different. Additional statistical comparisons were not performed. Statistical analyses were performed using SAS V.9.4 (Cary, North Carolina, USA).</p></sec><sec id="s2-6"><title>Patient and public involvement</title><p>Neither patients nor the public participated in the design, conduct, reporting or dissemination plans of this research. Involvement of patients or the public was not appropriate or feasible for this retrospective study.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>Of 34 405 health plan members in the KPNC database, 18 997 were aged &#8805;12 years and had an AD diagnosis between 2007 and 2018. Of those, 9608 health plan members with moderate to severe AD were identified as per the predefined selection criteria. Of the 50 moderate and the 50 severe cases reviewed for adjudication, 80% and 86% were adjudicated as definite cases, 18% and 4% as possible cases and 2% and 10% as not cases, respectively. The predetermined threshold of &#8805;80% agreement between the cases identified by study parameters and medical record review was met in both the moderate and severe cases and was deemed acceptable for disease severity classification. After excluding mild AD cases, adjudicated non-cases and those who met other exclusion criteria, 7050 adults with moderate to severe AD were included in the final cohort (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>). Details of the demographics and baseline characteristics of this cohort are shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic and baseline characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate to severe AD (N=7050)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate AD<break/>(n=6092)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe AD (n=958)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years), mean (&#177;SD)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.5 (&#177;16.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.6 (&#177;16.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.7 (&#177;16.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years), n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;18&#8211;39</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3183 (45.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2736 (44.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">447 (46.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;40&#8211;64</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3058 (43.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2653 (43.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">405 (42.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8805;65</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">809 (11.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">703 (11.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 (11.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Women</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4542 (64.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4025 (66.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">517 (54.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Men</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2507 (35.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2066 (33.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">441 (46.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Missing</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;White</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2494 (35.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2145 (35.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">349 (36.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Black</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">555 (7.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">501 (8.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (5.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Asian</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2530 (35.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2149 (35.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">381 (39.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Native American</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (0.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (0.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (0.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Islander (Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (1.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (1.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (1.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Multiracial</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">368 (5.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">318 (5.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (5.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Missing/other</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000 (14.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">893 (14.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107 (11.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Hispanic</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">939 (13.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">837 (13.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102 (10.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Non-Hispanic</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3283 (46.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2882 (47.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">401 (41.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Missing</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2828 (40.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2373 (39.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">455 (47.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&lt;25&#8201;kg/m<sup>2</sup>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2599 (36.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2244 (36.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">355 (37.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;25 to &lt;30&#8201;kg/m<sup>2</sup>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2022 (28.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1731 (28.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">291 (30.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8805;30&#8201;kg/m<sup>2</sup>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1580 (22.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1399 (23.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">181 (18.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Missing</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">849 (12.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">718 (11.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131 (13.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes/current</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">450 (6.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">386 (6.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (6.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Quit/former</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1079 (15.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">911 (15.0)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168 (17.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Passive/secondhand</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (0.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (0.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (0.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4106 (58.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3547 (58.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">559 (58.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Missing</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1366 (19.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1206 (19.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160 (16.7)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T1_FN1"><p>AD, atopic dermatitis; BMI, body mass index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Cohort selection. AD, atopic dermatitis; KPNC, Kaiser Permanente Northern California.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-071172f01.jpg"/></fig><p>IRs of malignancies per 1000 PY by AD severity in the overall study population are shown in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2</xref>. Of all malignancies assessed, IRs were highest for NMSC (4.8, 95% CI 4.1 to 5.6) and breast cancer (2.1, 95% CI 1.5 to 2.8). In the moderate and severe AD subpopulations, IRs for NMSC were 4.6 (95% CI 3.9 to 5.5) and 5.9 (95% CI 3.8 to 9.2), and for breast cancer were 2.2 (95% CI 1.6 to 3.0) and 0.5 (95% CI 0.1 to 3.9), respectively. In the moderate and severe AD subpopulations, the IRs for lymphoma were 0.3 (95% CI 0.2 to 0.6) and 0.6 (95% CI 0.1 to 2.3), respectively; and for lymphoproliferative disorders, the IRs were 0.1 (95% CI 0.0 to 0.3) and 0.3 (95% CI 0.0 to 2.1), respectively. The IRs for melanoma in the moderate and severe AD subpopulations were 0.4 (95% CI 0.2 to 0.7) and 0.6 (95% CI 0.1 to 2.3), respectively. The incidence of lung cancer differed between patients with moderate and severe AD (0.5 (95% CI 0.3 to 0.8) vs 0, respectively). However, there were only 13 lung cancer cases in the moderate AD population and no lung cancer cases in the severe AD population. IRs of malignancies were higher with increasing age in both the moderate and severe AD populations; IRs with 95% CIs are reported in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">figure 3</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Incidence rates of malignancies per 1000 person-years by atopic dermatitis (AD) severity. NMSC, non-melanoma skin cancer.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-071172f02.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Incidence rates of malignancies per 1000 person-years by atopic dermatitis (AD) severity and age for (A) lung cancer, breast cancer and melanoma; and (B) lymphoma, non-melanoma skin cancer and lymphoproliferative disorders.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-071172f03.jpg"/></fig><p>For most malignancies, IRs were numerically higher in men versus women in the moderate to severe AD study population; statistically significantly higher rates in men versus women were observed for those with moderate to severe AD for NMSC (7.7 (95% CI 6.1 to 9.5) vs 3.3 (95% CI 2.5 to 4.2)) and BCC (5.6 (95% CI 4.3 to 7.2) vs 1.7 (95% CI 1.2 to 2.4)), respectively (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>). IRs for lung cancer were higher in patients with moderate versus severe AD for both men (0.7 (95% CI 0.3 to 1.5) vs 0) and women (0.4 (95% CI 0.2 to 0.8) vs 0). The IR for lymphoproliferative disorders was higher in men versus women with severe AD (0.6 (95% CI 0.1 to 4.4) vs 0, respectively), but not for those with moderate AD (0.1 (95% CI 0.0 to 0.8) vs 0.1 (95% CI 0.0 to 0.5), respectively). The IR for breast cancer (2.1, 95% CI 1.5 to 2.8) was estimated for women only; men were excluded from the analysis.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>IRs per 1000 person-years of malignancies by AD severity, sex and smoking status</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Malignancy</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="3">IR per 1000 person-years (95% CI)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate to severe AD (N=7050)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate AD (n=6092)</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe AD (n=958)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="3">Basal cell carcinoma</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Overall</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0 (2.5 to 3.7)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1 (2.5 to 3.8)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 (1.4 to 5.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Women</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 (1.2 to 2.4)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8 (1.2 to 2.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.3 to 4.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Men</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6 (4.3 to 7.2)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 (4.4 to 7.6)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4 (2.1 to 9.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.3 to 4.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.3 to 5.1)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0 to 0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 (1.9 to 3.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 (2.0 to 3.7)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 (0.6 to 5.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Former smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 (2.5 to 6.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6 (2.8 to 7.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0 to 0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="4">Breast cancer*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Overall</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (1.5 to 2.8)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (1.6 to 3.0)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.1 to 3.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Women</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (1.5 to 2.8)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (1.6 to 3.0)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.1 to 3.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Men</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (0.6 to 8.9)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (0.6 to 10.0)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0 to 0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 (1.3 to 3.0)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (1.3 to 3.2)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (0.1 to 6.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Former smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (1.1 to 5.6)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8 (1.2 to 6.1)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0 to 0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="4">Lung cancer</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Overall</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.2 to 0.7)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.3 to 0.8)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0 to 0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Women</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.2 to 0.8)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.2 to 0.8)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0 to 0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Men</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.3 to 1.3)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (0.3 to 1.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0 to 0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.3 to 4.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.3 to 5.1)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0 to 0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0.1 to 0.7)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0.1 to 0.8)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0 to 0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Former smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0.4 to 2.6)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.4 to 3.0)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0 to 0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="4">Lymphoma</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Overall</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.2 to 0.7)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0.2 to 0.6)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.1 to 2.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Women</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 (0.0 to 0.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (0.0 to 0.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.1 to 3.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Men</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (0.4 to 1.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (0.4 to 1.6)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.1 to 4.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.3 to 4.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.3 to 5.1)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0 to 0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.2 to 0.9)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.2 to 0.9)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.1 to 4.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Former smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.1 to 2.0)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0.0 to 2.0)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 (0.3 to 14.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="4">Lymphoproliferative disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Overall</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (0.0 to 0.4)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (0.0 to 0.3)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0.0 to 2.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Women</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (0.0 to 0.4)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (0.0 to 0.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0 to 0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Men</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 (0.0 to 0.8)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (0.0 to 0.8)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.1 to 4.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.1 to 4.0)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.1 to 4.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0 to 0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (0.0 to 0.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (0.0 to 0.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0 to 0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Former smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.1 to 2.0)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0.0 to 2.0)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 (0.3 to 14.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="4">Melanoma</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Overall</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.2 to 0.7)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.2 to 0.7)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.1 to 2.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Women</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 (0.1 to 0.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 (0.1 to 0.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.1 to 3.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Men</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (0.4 to 1.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (0.4 to 1.6)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.1 to 4.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.1 to 4.0)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.1 to 4.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0 to 0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0.1 to 0.7)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 (0.1 to 0.8)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0 to 0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Former smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0.4 to 2.6)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (0.3 to 2.6)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 (0.3 to 14.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="4">Non-melanoma skin cancer</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Overall</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8 (4.1 to 5.6)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6 (3.9 to 5.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9 (3.8 to 9.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Women</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3 (2.5 to 4.2)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1 (2.4 to 4.0)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0 (2.6 to 9.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Men</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7 (6.1 to 9.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 (6.1 to 9.8)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 (3.9 to 12.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 (0.5 to 5.3)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 (0.6 to 5.9)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0 to 0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7 (2.8 to 4.7)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5 (2.6 to 4.6)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2 (2.7 to 10.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Former smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3 (5.1 to 10.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 (5.4 to 11.4)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 (1.0 to 15.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="4">Squamous cell carcinoma</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Overall</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 (1.8 to 3.0)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (1.7 to 2.8)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8 (2.2 to 6.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Women</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 (1.4 to 2.6)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 (1.2 to 2.4)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 (1.8 to 8.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Men</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1 (2.2 to 4.4)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0 (2.1 to 4.4)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8 (1.7 to 8.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.3 to 4.5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.3 to 5.1)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 (0.0 to 0.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 (0.9 to 2.1)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.7 to 1.8)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5 (1.6 to 7.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Former smoker</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2 (2.6 to 6.8)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3 (2.6 to 7.1)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 (1.0 to 15.7)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T2_FN1"><p>*The IRs for breast cancer were calculated from the subset of 4542 female patients; males were excluded from the breast cancer analyses.</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN2"><p>AD, atopic dermatitis; IR, incidence rate.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Higher IRs were also observed in former versus never smokers in the moderate to severe AD study population for NMSC (7.3 (95% CI 5.1 to 10.5) vs 3.7 (95% CI 2.8 to 4.7)) and SCC (4.2 (95% CI 2.6 to 6.8) vs 1.4 (95% CI 0.9 to 2.1)) respectively. In patients with moderate AD, IRs were higher in former versus never smokers for NMSC (7.8 (95% CI 5.4 to 11.4) vs 3.5 (95% CI 2.6 to 4.6)) and SCC (4.3 (95% CI 2.6 to 7.1) vs 1.1 (95% CI 0.7 to 1.8)), respectively. In patients with severe AD, IRs were higher in former versus never smokers for lymphoproliferative disorders (2.0 (95% CI 0.3 to 14.0) vs 0) and melanoma (2.0 (95% CI 0.3 to 14.0) vs 0), respectively. No former smokers with severe AD developed BCC or breast cancer; however, IRs of BCC and breast cancer were 1.7 (95% CI 0.6 to 5.3) and 0.9 (95% CI 0.1 to 6.5), respectively, for never smokers (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>This retrospective cohort study estimated IRs of malignancies in patients with moderate and severe AD based on data from a selected group of KPNC health plan members. Generally, IRs for NMSC were numerically higher compared with other malignancies. The incidence of NMSC increased with increasing age, though this only reached statistical significance in the moderate AD subgroup.</p><p>Notably, the IRs for NMSC and breast cancer in the moderate and severe AD populations in this study were markedly higher than those observed in the general US adult population (NMSC: 4.8 (overall in the current study) and 3.3 (women in current study) vs 0.8 (US women) and 7.7 (men in current study) vs 1.2 (US men) per 1000 PY; breast cancer: 2.1 (current study) vs 1.3 (US population) per 1000 PY). Rates of melanoma and lung cancer were comparable to those observed in the general US population (0.4 (current study) vs 0.2 (US population) and 0.4 (current study) vs 0.5 (US population) per 1000 PY, respectively).<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20 21</xref> According to State Cancer Profiles provided by the National Cancer Institute and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, the rate of melanoma in California in 2014&#8211;2018 was also 0.2 per 1000 PY.<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
</p><p>A recent systematic review and meta-analysis found a statistically significant association between AD and NMSC (keratinocyte carcinoma; standardised incidence ratio: 1.46 (95% CI 1.20 to 1.77)).<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Plausible reasons for an increased risk of keratinocyte carcinoma in patients with AD include common treatment with modalities such as ultraviolet (UV) light and topical immunosuppressants; however, the risk appears minimal.<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Other reasons include detection bias due to increased skin surveillance in patients with AD<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> and loss-of-function mutations in the filaggrin gene, given that alterations to filaggrin may predispose keratinocytes to damage induced by UV radiation.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14 25</xref>
</p><p>Several mechanisms for the association between AD and malignancies have been proposed. Heightened immune response,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> upregulation of inflammatory mediators and recruitment of immune cells that may promote tumour growth,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> and defects of the epidermal barrier<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> have been identified as potential mechanisms of tumourigenesis in patients with AD. Chronic inflammation, such as that underlying AD pathogenesis, is associated with higher risk of cancer and promotes all stages of tumourigenesis.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> In the current study, although the rate of NMSC increased numerically with disease severity, CIs overlapped and thus did not reach statistical significance. Light-based therapies may also increase the risk for NMSCs in patients with moderate to severe AD. However, future studies assessing the relationship between AD severity and NMSC are warranted. The standard of care for AD includes the potential need for long-term treatment with immunosuppressive topical and systemic therapies,<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> which may enhance malignancy risk by inhibiting innate antitumour immune responses.<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29&#8211;31</xref> For example, systemic treatments such as immunosuppressants have been associated with increased malignancies in patients with psoriasis.<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32 33</xref> Thus, abnormalities in cell-mediated immunity, whether related to AD pathophysiology or systemic treatment, may alter the immune response to promote the development of malignancies.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> An inverse relationship between AD and malignancies, perhaps due to increased immune surveillance, has also been noted.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14 31</xref>
</p><p>Several limitations of this study should be noted. First, these findings may have limited generalisability to patients from other geographical regions or those without access to healthcare, as the electronic health data only included patients within the KPNC healthcare system. However, the KPNC population is representative of those with access to healthcare, as more than 30% of all insured Californians receive coverage and care from the KPNC healthcare system, and the KPNC population is racially and ethnically diverse.<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> Second, because the cohort was restricted to resemble patients included in recent AD clinical trial programmes, the generalisability of the findings is limited by the exclusion criteria that were applied, and thus the cohort may be healthier than an average AD patient population. Third, no comparison group without AD was included, and thus we could not compare IRs in people with versus without AD. Although confounding variables were not controlled for, results were stratified by age. We did not perform formal statistical comparisons or adjust for multiple testing. Fourth, disease severity was inferred by treatment type since KPNC databases do not provide detailed information on disease severity. Although the use of treatment as a proxy could lead to potential misclassification, a board-certified dermatologist reviewed medical charts to validate the moderate and severe AD classification. Finally, as this study was descriptive in nature, causality cannot be inferred.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Among the malignancies assessed in this study, IRs were numerically highest for NMSC in patients with moderate or severe AD (4.6 and 5.9, respectively), followed by breast cancer (2.2 and 0.5, respectively), melanoma (0.4 and 0.6, respectively) and lymphoma (0.3 and 0.6, respectively). This retrospective cohort study of patients enrolled in the KPNC healthcare system addresses an important gap in the scientific literature by describing IRs of malignancies in patients with moderate and severe AD. Therefore, the data provided by this cohort of patients enrolled in the KPNC healthcare system fill a gap in the scientific literature and provide valuable information for ongoing clinical trials as well as real-world information for clinicians, including general dermatologists, nurses with an interest in dermatology and general practitioners, who care for patients with moderate to severe AD. Future studies should assess the potential relationship between AD and malignancies by including a healthy (non-AD) population for comparison.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="d64e167" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Reviewer comments</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-071172.reviewer_comments.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="d64e168" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Author's
manuscript</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bmjopen-2022-071172.draft_revisions.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>Editorial/medical writing support under the guidance of authors was provided by Gauri Saal, MA Economics, and Natalie Barnes, BASLP, at ApotheCom, San Francisco, California, USA, and was funded by Pfizer Inc., New York, New York, USA, in accordance with Good Publication Practice (GPP 2022) guidelines (<italic toggle="yes">Ann Intern Med</italic> 2022;175(9):1298&#8211;1304. doi: 10.7326/M22-1460).</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Contributors:</bold> MMH, MMA, JG, CPQ and ARL designed the study. MMH, FX, CPQ, ARL and SBS participated in data analysis and interpretation. All authors contributed to the writing of the report and the decision to submit this article for publication.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This study was sponsored by Pfizer Inc.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> MMH, FX, CPQ and SBS are full-time employees of KPNC and received payment from Pfizer Inc. for the study used in this publication. JG is a former employee and a shareholder of Pfizer Inc. ARL is an employee and shareholder of Pfizer Inc. MMA received royalty payments from UptoDate for publications related to skin cancer and also received grant funding to her institution from Pfizer Inc. for the study described in this publication.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient and public involvement:</bold> Patients and/or the public were not involved in the design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Supplemental material:</bold> This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>Individual level data may not be made publicly available due to IRB and privacy concerns. The data used for this study contain protected health information (PHI), and access is protected by the KPNC IRB. Data are available from the Kaiser Permanente Division of Research for researchers who meet the criteria for access to confidential data. For more information about data access and criteria for access to confidential data, please contact Kaiser Permanente Division of Research: DOR.IRB.Submissions@kp.org. All other relevant data are within the paper.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement"><title>Ethics statements</title><sec><title>Patient consent for publication</title><p content-type="ethics-consent-to-publish">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethics approval</title><p content-type="ethics-approval">This study was approved by the KPNC Institutional Review Board (IRB). For this type of study formal consent is not required.</p></sec></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Weidinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bieber</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Dis Primers</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41572-018-0001-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29930242</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Giesey</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The global, regional, and national burden of atopic dermatitis in 195 countries and territories: an ecological study from the global burden of disease study 2017</article-title>. <source>JAAD Int</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdin.2020.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34409347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8362298</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Laughter</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maymone</surname><given-names>MBC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mashayekhi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The global burden of atopic dermatitis: lessons from the global burden of disease study 1990-2017</article-title>. <source>Br J Dermatol</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>184</volume>:<fpage>304</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bjd.19580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33006135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Silverberg</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gelfand</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Margolis</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Patient burden and quality of life in atopic dermatitis in US adults: a population-based cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>Ann Allergy Asthma Immunol</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>121</volume>:<fpage>340</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anai.2018.07.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30025911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nutten</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Atopic dermatitis: global epidemiology and risk factors</article-title>. <source>Ann Nutr Metab</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>66 Suppl 1</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000370220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25925336</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bylund</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kobyletzki</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Svalstedt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and incidence of atopic dermatitis: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Acta Derm Venereol</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<elocation-id>5765</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2340/00015555-3510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32412646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9189744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Johns</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The global burden of skin disease in 2010: an analysis of the prevalence and impact of skin conditions</article-title>. <source>J Invest Dermatol</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>134</volume>:<fpage>1527</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jid.2013.446</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24166134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bieber</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>358</volume>:<fpage>1483</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra074081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18385500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>David Boothe</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tarbox</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tarbox</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Atopic dermatitis: pathophysiology</article-title>. <source>Adv Exp Med Biol</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>1027</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-64804-0_3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29063428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Greten</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Grivennikov</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Inflammation and cancer: triggers, mechanisms, and consequences</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>27</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2019.06.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31315034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6831096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hagstr&#246;mer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nyr&#233;n</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Incidence of cancer among patients with atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source>Arch Dermatol</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>141</volume>:<fpage>1123</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archderm.141.9.1123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16172309</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Olesen</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Engholm</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Storm</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The risk of cancer among patients previously hospitalized for atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source>J Invest Dermatol</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>125</volume>:<fpage>445</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0022-202X.2005.23839.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16117783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Paller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jaworski</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Major comorbidities of atopic dermatitis: beyond allergic disorders</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Dermatol</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>821</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40257-018-0383-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30168085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bierbrier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Drucker</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Noncutaneous and cutaneous cancer risk in patients with atopic dermatitis: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>JAMA Dermatol</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>156</volume>:<fpage>158</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamadermatol.2019.3786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31825457</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6990857</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ruff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Egeberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>YMF</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of cancer in adult patients with atopic dermatitis: a nationwide study</article-title>. <source>Acta Derm Venereol</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>1127</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2340/00015555-2703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28512668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mansfield</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>SAJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Darvalics</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Association between atopic eczema and cancer in England and Denmark</article-title>. <source>JAMA Dermatol</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>156</volume>:<fpage>1086</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>97</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamadermatol.2020.1948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32579178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7315391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hedderson</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Asgari</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Rates of cardiovascular events among patients with moderate-to-severe atopic dermatitis in an integrated health care system: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><year>2022</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<elocation-id>e0277469</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0277469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36395164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9671329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The Kaiser Permanente Northern California adult member health survey</article-title>. <source>Perm J</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>225</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7812/TPP/15-225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5101088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27548806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>Surveillance epidemiology and end results (SEER) program. SEER*stat databases: november 2019 submission</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Bethesda, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Cancer Insitute</publisher-name>; <year>2019</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://seer.cancer.gov/data-software/documentation/seerstat/nov2019/#records">https://seer.cancer.gov/data-software/documentation/seerstat/nov2019/#records</uri> [Accessed <comment>7 Jan 2021</comment>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Global Burden of Disease Cancer Collaboration</collab>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzmaurice</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abate</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Global, regional, and National cancer incidence, mortality, years of life lost, years lived with disability, and disability-adjusted life-years for 29 cancer groups, 1990 to 2017: a systematic analysis for the global burden of disease study</article-title>. <source>JAMA Oncol</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1749</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>68</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaoncol.2019.2996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31560378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6777271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Cancer Insitute</collab></person-group>. <article-title>SEER Cancer Stat Facts</article-title>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://seer.cancer.gov/statfacts/">https://seer.cancer.gov/statfacts/</uri> [Accessed <comment>10 Jan 2022</comment>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Cancer Insitute</collab></person-group>. <article-title>State cancer profiles</article-title>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://statecancerprofiles.cancer.gov/">https://statecancerprofiles.cancer.gov/</uri> [Accessed <comment>10 Jan 2022</comment>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lerche</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wulf</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Photocarcinogenicity of selected topically applied dermatological drugs: calcineurin inhibitors, corticosteroids, and vitamin D analogs</article-title>. <source>Dermatol Reports</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<elocation-id>e13</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4081/dr.2010.e13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25386250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4211469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Drucker</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W-Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Savitz</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Association between health maintenance practices and skin cancer risk as a possible source of detection bias</article-title>. <source>JAMA Dermatol</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>155</volume>:<fpage>353</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamadermatol.2018.4216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30586131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6439894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McAleer</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Irvine</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The multifunctional role of filaggrin in allergic skin disease</article-title>. <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>131</volume>:<fpage>280</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2012.12.668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23374260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Giraldo</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Becht</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Remark</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>The immune contexture of primary and metastatic human tumours</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Immunol</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coi.2014.01.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24487185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cork</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Danby</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vasilopoulos</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Epidermal barrier dysfunction in atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source>J Invest Dermatol</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>129</volume>:<fpage>1892</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>908</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jid.2009.133</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19494826</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boguniewicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fonacier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guttman-Yassky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Atopic dermatitis yardstick: practical recommendations for an evolving therapeutic landscape</article-title>. <source>Ann Allergy Asthma Immunol</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>120</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anai.2017.10.039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29273118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Josephs</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Spicer</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Corrigan</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiological associations of allergy, IgE and cancer</article-title>. <source>Clin Exp Allergy</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>1110</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cea.12178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24074329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Legendre</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barnetche</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mazereeuw-Hautier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of lymphoma in patients with atopic dermatitis and the role of topical treatment: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>992</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1002</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2015.02.1116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25840730</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>YMF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Egeberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Skov</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Comorbidities of atopic dermatitis: beyond rhinitis and asthma</article-title>. <source>Curr Dermatol Rep</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13671-017-0168-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28890845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5556128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Loft</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vaengebjerg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Skov</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer risk in patients with psoriasis: should we be paying more attention?</article-title><source>Expert Rev Clin Immunol</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>479</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1744666X.2020.1754194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32279582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Asgari</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Geier</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Malignancy rates in a large cohort of patients with systemically treated psoriasis in a managed care population</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>632</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2016.10.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28162854</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Similarity of the adult Kaiser Permanente membership in Northern California to the insured and general population in Northern California: statistics from the 2011 California Health Interview Survey</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Oakland, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kaiser Permanente Division of Research</publisher-name>; <year>2015</year>. <comment>Available</comment>: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://divisionofresearch.kaiserpermanente.org/projects/memberhealthsurvey/SiteCollectionDocuments/chis_non_kp_2011.pdf">https://divisionofresearch.kaiserpermanente.org/projects/memberhealthsurvey/SiteCollectionDocuments/chis_non_kp_2011.pdf</uri> [Accessed <comment>11 Apr 2021</comment>].</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>