<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMA Netw Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3211</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jamasd</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JAMA Network Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2574-3805</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>JAMA Network</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10336626</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10336626.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10336626</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10336626</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37432686</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.22743</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zoi230673</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="category" specific-use="electronic"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Investigation</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="online-only"><subject>Online Only</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="subject-area"><subject>Equity, Diversity, and Inclusion</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Association of Language Barriers With Perioperative and Surgical Outcomes</article-title><subtitle>A Systematic Review</subtitle><alt-title alt-title-type="headline">Association of Language Barriers With Perioperative and Surgical Outcomes</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Association of Language Barriers With Perioperative and Surgical Outcomes</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joo</surname><given-names initials="H">Hyundeok</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi230673aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="zoi230673aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#225;ndez</surname><given-names initials="A">Alicia</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi230673aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="zoi230673aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wick</surname><given-names initials="EC">Elizabeth C.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi230673aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno Lepe</surname><given-names initials="G">Gala</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi230673aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref><xref rid="zoi230673aff7" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manuel</surname><given-names initials="SP">Solmaz P.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="zoi230673aff8" ref-type="aff">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="zoi230673aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, University of California, San Francisco, San Francisco</aff><aff id="zoi230673aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Preventive Medicine, Seoul National University College of Medicine, Seoul, Republic of Korea</aff><aff id="zoi230673aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Medicine, University of California San Francisco School of Medicine, San Francisco</aff><aff id="zoi230673aff4"><label>4</label>UCSF Center for Vulnerable Populations, Zuckerberg San Francisco General Hospital, San Francisco, California</aff><aff id="zoi230673aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Surgery, University of California San Francisco School of Medicine, San Francisco</aff><aff id="zoi230673aff6"><label>6</label>University of California San Francisco School of Medicine, San Francisco</aff><aff id="zoi230673aff7"><label>7</label>Now with Department of Internal Medicine, Brigham and Women&#8217;s Hospital, Boston, Massachusetts</aff><aff id="zoi230673aff8"><label>8</label>Department of Anesthesia and Perioperative Care, University of California San Francisco School of Medicine, San Francisco</aff><author-notes><title>Article Information</title><p><bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> May 13, 2023.</p><p content-type="published-online"><bold>Published:</bold> July 11, 2023. doi:<uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.22743</uri></p><p content-type="open-access-note"><bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/pages/cc-by-license-permissions" ext-link-type="uri">CC-BY License</ext-link>. &#169; 2023 Joo H et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic>.</p><corresp id="zoi230673cor1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Solmaz P. Manuel, MD, Department of Anesthesia and Perioperative Care, University of California, San Francisco, 521 Parnassus Ave, Box 0648, San Francisco, CA 94143 (<email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="solmaz.manuel@ucsf.edu">solmaz.manuel@ucsf.edu</email>).</corresp><p content-type="author-contributions"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Dr Manuel had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Concept and design:</italic> Joo, Fern&#225;ndez, Manuel.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> All authors.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Joo, Manuel.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Critical revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</italic> All authors.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Statistical analysis:</italic> Joo, Manuel.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Obtained funding:</italic> Manuel.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Manuel.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Supervision:</italic> Wick, Manuel.</p><p content-type="COI-statement"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> None reported.</p><p content-type="funding-statement"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> This work was supported by grants from the National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (National Institutes of Health, K24DK102057 to Dr Fern&#225;ndez), the Hellman Family Foundation (100020111), and the University of California, San Francisco&#8217;s Patricia Sander Award (100008069 to Dr Manuel).</p><p><bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The funders had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p><p><bold>Disclaimer:</bold> The content of this research is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Institutes of Health.</p><p content-type="data-sharing-statement"><bold>Data Sharing Statement:</bold> See <xref rid="note-ZOI230673-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 2</xref>.</p><p><bold>Additional Contributions:</bold> Josephine Tan, MLIS, University of California, San Francisco, provided expertise in medical databases, literature search, and reference management. She was compensated by University of California, San Francisco for her role as a research librarian consultant.</p></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-07-11T10:00"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>7</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>7</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">440546</issue-id><elocation-id>e2322743</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>11</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>13</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-02-15 00:25:12.480"><day>15</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright 2023 Joo H et al. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic>.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC-BY License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2322743.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf-version" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2322743.pdf">jamanetwopen-e2322743.pdf</self-uri><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="silverchair" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.22743"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary" xml:lang="en" journal-id="JAMA Netw Open" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pubmed" xlink:href="37432694"><article-title>Raising the Bar for Language Equity Health Care Research.</article-title><volume>6</volume><issue>7</issue><date><day>3</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date><fpage>e2324485</fpage><lpage>e2324485</lpage><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.24485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37432694</pub-id></related-article><abstract abstract-type="key-points"><title>Key Points</title><sec id="ab-zoi230673-1"><title>Question</title><p>Is English language proficiency in adult surgical patients associated with differences in perioperative care and surgical outcomes?</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230673-2"><title>Findings</title><p>In this systematic review of 29 studies with 281&#8201;266 patients, surgical patients with limited English proficiency experienced reduced access, delays in care, and longer surgical admissions and were more likely to be discharged to a skilled facility than patients with English proficiency. Clinical outcomes related to mortality, postoperative complications, and unplanned readmissions showed fewer significant associations with English proficiency status.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230673-3"><title>Meaning</title><p>These findings indicate that limited English proficiency is associated with several perioperative process-of-care outcomes; additional studies are needed to understand the impact of language barriers on perioperative health disparities.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" specific-use="electronic"><p>This systematic review examines the association of limited English proficiency with perioperative care and surgical outcomes in adult patients.</p></abstract><abstract><sec id="ab-zoi230673-4"><title>Importance</title><p>English language proficiency has been reported to correlate with disparities in health outcomes. Therefore, it is important to identify and describe the association of language barriers with perioperative care and surgical outcomes to inform efforts aimed at reducing health care disparities.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230673-5"><title>Objective</title><p>To examine whether limited English proficiency compared with English proficiency in adult patients is associated with differences in perioperative care and surgical outcomes.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230673-6"><title>Evidence Review</title><p>A systematic review was conducted in MEDLINE, Embase, Web of Science, Sociological Abstracts, and CINAHL of all English-language publications from database inception to December 7, 2022. Searches included Medical Subject Headings terms related to language barriers, perioperative or surgical care, and perioperative outcomes. Studies that investigated adults in perioperative settings and involved quantitative data comparing cohorts with limited English proficiency and English proficiency were included. The quality of studies was evaluated using the Newcastle-Ottawa Scale. Because of heterogeneity in analysis and reported outcomes, data were not pooled for quantitative analysis. Results are reported in accordance with the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analysis Protocols guideline.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230673-7"><title>Findings</title><p>Of 2230 unique records identified, 29 were eligible for inclusion (281 266 total patients; mean [SD] age, 57.2 [10.0] years; 121 772 [43.3%] male and 159 240 [56.6%] female). Included studies were observational cohort studies, except for a single cross-sectional study. Median cohort size was 1763 (IQR, 266-7402), with a median limited English proficiency cohort size of 179 (IQR, 51-671). Six studies explored access to surgery, 4 assessed delays in surgical care, 14 assessed surgical admission length of stay, 4 assessed discharge disposition, 10 assessed mortality, 5 assessed postoperative complications, 9 assessed unplanned readmissions, 2 assessed pain management, and 3 assessed functional outcomes. Surgical patients with limited English proficiency were more likely to experience reduced access in 4 of 6 studies, delays in obtaining care in 3 of 4 studies, longer surgical admission length of stay in 6 of 14 studies, and more likely discharge to a skilled facility than patients with English proficiency in 3 of 4 studies. Some additional differences in associations were found between patients with limited English proficiency who spoke Spanish vs other languages. Mortality, postoperative complications, and unplanned readmissions had fewer significant associations with English proficiency status.</p></sec><sec id="ab-zoi230673-8"><title>Conclusions and Relevance</title><p>In this systematic review, most of the included studies found associations between English proficiency and multiple perioperative process-of-care outcomes, but fewer associations were seen between English proficiency and clinical outcomes. Because of limitations of the existing research, including study heterogeneity and residual confounding, mediators of the observed associations remain unclear. Standardized reporting and higher-quality studies are needed to understand the impact of language barriers on perioperative health disparities and identify opportunities to reduce related perioperative health care disparities.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="H1-1-ZOI230673"><title>Introduction</title><p>As the proportion of surgically treated conditions continues to increase, health care disparities in the perioperative period (including the preoperative, intraoperative, and postoperative phases of a surgical admission) are of particular concern.<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Although racial and ethnic disparities in surgical access, perioperative quality of care, and surgical outcomes have been persistent and well-documented problems, much less is known about how language barriers contribute to these disparities.</p><p>Currently, 22% of people in the US speak a language other than English at home,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> and limited English proficiency (LEP) has been reported to be correlated with reduced access to health care, increased risk of health care&#8211;related adverse events,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> worse patient care experiences,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> reduced understanding of discharge instructions,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> and worse outcomes for both outpatient and hospitalized patients.<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> There are numerous reasons to postulate that language proficiency may significantly impact perioperative health care and surgical outcomes in particular. Perioperative decisions are complex, involving consent for high-risk procedures and balancing the risk-benefit ratio of competing treatment options. The environment is fast-paced, with time pressure that is at odds with longer interpreter-assisted conversations and examinations. Furthermore, the use of untrained interpreters may compound problems with communication errors and the tendency to omit sensitive material.<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Finally, language barriers may limit access to, or understanding of, important preoperative or postoperative instructions.<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup></p><p>Despite extensive theoretical reasons to surmise that language barriers may impact perioperative care, a clear understanding of the current evidence is needed to inform intervention and policy efforts aimed at improving outcomes for vulnerable surgical patients with LEP. Thus, the objective of this systematic review of the literature was to examine the association of LEP with perioperative care and surgical outcomes.</p></sec><sec id="H1-2-ZOI230673"><title>Methods</title><p>This systematic review was prospectively registered with PROSPERO (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.crd.york.ac.uk/prospero/display_record.php?ID=CRD42022299569" ext-link-type="uri">CRD42022299569</ext-link>)<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> and is reported in accordance with the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analysis Protocols (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.equator-network.org/reporting-guidelines/prisma-protocols/" ext-link-type="uri">PRISMA-P</ext-link>) guideline (eAppendix 1 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230673-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> The search strategy was developed in consultation with a research librarian; was performed in MEDLINE via PubMed, Embase, Web of Science, Sociological Abstracts, and CINAHL with no restriction on publication date; and consisted of Medical Subject Headings terms related to language barriers, perioperative or surgical care, and perioperative outcomes (eAppendix 2 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230673-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). The final search was conducted on December 7, 2022.</p><p>Original observational or experimental studies comparing perioperative care and surgical outcomes between adult patients with and without LEP were included. Outcomes across the perioperative period, including access to surgical procedures, delays in receiving surgical care, perioperative pain management, surgical admission length of stay (LOS), discharge disposition, postoperative complications, functional recovery, mortality, and postoperative readmissions, were examined (<xref rid="zoi230673t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>; eTable 1 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230673-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> The Newcastle-Ottawa Scale for cohort studies was used for risk-of-bias assessment (<xref rid="zoi230673t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup> Because of heterogeneity in analysis and reported outcomes among studies, data were not pooled for quantitative analysis. Included studies were organized by outcome of interest to facilitate data interpretation.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi230673t1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1. </label><caption><title>Study Characteristics and Outcomes of Included Studies</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="7.75%" span="1"/><col width="6.29%" span="1"/><col width="14.01%" span="1"/><col width="5.36%" span="1"/><col width="7.91%" span="1"/><col width="5.18%" span="1"/><col width="12.28%" span="1"/><col width="10.48%" span="1"/><col width="11.18%" span="1"/><col width="9.08%" span="1"/><col width="10.48%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Source</th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Location</th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Study population</th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Sample, No.</th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Data source</th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">LEP, No. (%)</th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">LEP definition</th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Age distribution by LEP, mean (SD) or median (IQR)</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Sex by LEP, No. (%)</th><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Outcome measures</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Female </th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">John-Baptiste et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> 2004</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients admitted to tertiary care hospital for medical and surgical conditions</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 983</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic multicenter</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6124 (13.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clerk assessment of patient&#8217;s inability to communicate in English</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 66.7 (NS); EP, 60.2 (NS)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 3099 (50.6); EP, 15 000 (38.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 3025 (49.4); EP, 23 859 (61.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay, in-hospital mortality</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dowsey et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> 2009</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult patients undergoing total knee arthroplasty</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">278</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic single center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (14.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English spoken language and use of LEP-I </td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 72.0 (7.0); EP, 71.0 (9.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 38 (92.7); EP, 155 (65.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> LEP, 3 (7.3); EP, 82 (34.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Functional outcomes</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MacDonald et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> 2010</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult patients scheduled for elective hip or knee arthroplasty</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community multicenter</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (12.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English spoken language and LEP-I required</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nashed et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> 2012</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult patients diagnosed with supratentorial intra-axial primary brain tumor undergoing neuro-oncologic surgery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic single center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (40.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English spoken language and self-identified as Hispanic (vs White)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 51.8 (21-75); EP, 50.9 (20-87)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 22 (48.7); EP, 34 (50.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> LEP, 23 (51.3); EP, 33 (49.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delay in surgery, long-term survival</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Betjemann et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> 2013</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult patients with medically refractory epilepsy admitted to epilepsy monitoring unit</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic single center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (19.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English language preference</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 37 (NS)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 117 (54.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 96 (45.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Access to surgery</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thompson et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> 2014</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult patients with unilateral mesial temporal sclerosis admitted to epilepsy monitoring unit for potential anterior temporal lobectomy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic single center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (19.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English language preference</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 36.9 (11.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 124 (55.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 99 (44.4) </td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delay in surgery</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tang et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> 2016</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult patients undergoing elective isolated CABG surgery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">691</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic single center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103 (14.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any patient or practitioner-reported LEP status in medical record</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 67.7 (8.4); EP, 65.3 (9.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 28 (27.2); EP, 79 (13.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 75 (72.8); EP, 509 (86.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wilbur et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> 2016</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients admitted to a gynecologic oncology service for surgery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1605</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic single center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (3.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English primary language OR LEP-I required</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 53.2 (NS)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 1605 (100)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 0 (0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Readmission</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inagaki et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> 2017</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients undergoing nonemergency infrainguinal bypass surgery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic single center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (19.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English primary language</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 67.4 (9.8); EP, 63.1 (9.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 24 (47.1); EP, 78 (37.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 27 (52.9); EP, 132 (62.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay, complication, readmission</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyun et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> 2017</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia and New Zealand</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients admitted with ACS event for potential intervention and/or surgery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4387</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community nationwide database</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">294 (6.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English primary language</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 70.9 (12.6); EP, 66.3 (14.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 121 (41.2); EP, 1646 (40.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 173 (58.8); EP, 2447 (59.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay, in-hospital mortality, complications, long-term mortality</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jaiswal et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> 2018</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with nonrecurrent, primary stage 0-III breast cancer receiving medical and/or surgical care</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community single center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (23.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English primary language</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 4 categories of age</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 105 (100)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 0 (0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delay in surgery</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feeney et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> 2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult patients undergoing surgical oncology operations</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37531</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community statewide database</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3398 (9.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English primary language, either Spanish or NENS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP (Spanish), 56.7 (15.8); LEP (NENS), 62.1 (14.8); EP, 59.5 (15.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP (Spanish), 1252 (71.7); LEP (NENS), 1131 (68.5); EP, 25 313 (74.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP (Spanish), 495 (28.3); LEP (NENS), 520 (31.5); EP, 8820 (25.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay, in-hospital mortality, readmission</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sridhar et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> 2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult patients with stage I-IV pancreatic cancer</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">240</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic single center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (22.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">English is not a primary language</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 2 categories of age</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 122 (50.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 118 (49.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Access to surgery, long-term survival</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feeney et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> 2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult patients admitted for emergency surgery occurring within 2 d of admission</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 171</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community statewide database</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 716 (13.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English primary language, either Spanish or NENS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP (Spanish), 42.2 (16.6); LEP (NENS), 50.5 (19.4); EP, 49.1 (19.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP (Spanish), 4961 (56.1); LEP (NENS), 2790 (57.3); EP, 52 907 (57.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP (Spanish), 3888 (43.9); LEP (NENS), 2077 (42.7); EP, 38548 (42.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay, in-hospital mortality, readmission</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feeney et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult patients undergoing surgical oncologic operations</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2467</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic single center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">824 (33.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English primary language, non-English discharge instructions, or LEP-I charges</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 55 (46-64); EP, 55 (45-65)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 709 (86.0); EP, 1279 (77.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 115 (14.0); EP, 364 (22.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay, complications, readmission, long-term mortality</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asokan et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult patients with esophageal cancer undergoing consultation for treatment involving surgery, chemotherapy, or radiation therapy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic single center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (16.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English primary language</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 2 categories of age</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 61 (22.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 205 (77.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Access to surgery, long-term survival</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bernstein et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients undergoing single primary hip or knee arthroplasty</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#8201;885</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic single center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1682 (13.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English primary language, requiring LEP-I or LEP-N</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP-I, 67.1 (11.5); LEP-N, 64.0 (12.1); EP, 62.9 (12.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP-I, 1125 (72.8); LEP-N, 94 (68.6); EP, 6924 (61.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP-I, 420 (27.2); LEP-N, 43 (31.4); EP, 4279 (38.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay, discharge disposition</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Varady et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients undergoing an orthopedic surgical procedure</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#8201;643</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic multicenter</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1205 (6.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English primary language</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 56.9 (16.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 10 170 (57.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 7473 (42.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Access to surgery</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wong et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult patients undergoing colectomy or proctectomy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1763</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic single center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117 (6.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English primary language</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 4 categories of age</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 920 (52.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP 843 (47.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Readmission</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Witt et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult patients undergoing neuro-oncologic surgery for primary brain tumor, meningioma, or brain metastasis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7402</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community statewide database</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">560 (7.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English primary language, either Spanish or NENS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP (Spanish), 55 (44-67); LEP (NENS), 61 (52-69); EP, 60 (50-69)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP (Spanish), 174 (58.0); LEP (NENS), 153 (58.9); EP, 3661 (53.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP (Spanish), 126 (42.0); LEP (NENS), 107 (41.2); EP, 3181 (46.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Access to surgery</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schwartz et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult trauma patients discharged to the community</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1419</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community single center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">237 (16.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English spoken language(s)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 57.3 (20.5); EP 47.2 (19.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 82 (34.6); EP, 380 (32.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 155 (65.4); EP, 884 (74.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain management</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Witt et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult patients undergoing neuro-oncologic surgery for primary brain tumor, meningioma, or brain metastasis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7324</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community statewide database</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">554 (7.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English primary language, either Spanish or NENS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP (Spanish), 55 (44-67); LEP (NENS), 61 (52-69); EP, 60 (50-69)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP (Spanish), 171 (57.6); LEP (NENS), 151 (58.8); EP, 3624 (53.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP (Spanish), 126 (42.4); LEP (NENS), 106 (41.2); EP, 3146 (46.5)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay, discharge disposition, in-hospital mortality, complications</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maurer et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult patients with diverticulitis undergoing a partial colon resection</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9453</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community statewide database</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">592 (6.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English primary language</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 58 (48-70); EP, 59 (50-69)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 305 (51.5); EP, 4707 (53.1)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 287 (48.5); EP, 4154 (46.9)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Access to surgery</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manuel et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> 2022</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult patients undergoing hip or knee arthroplasty</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4721</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic single center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">378 (8.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English preferred language and request for LEP-I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 70.1 (14.2); EP, 63.5 (12.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 264 (69.8); EP, 2408 (55.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 114 (30.2); EP, 1935 (44.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay, discharge disposition, readmission</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aggarwal et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> 2022</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients undergoing elective total hip arthroplasty</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1412</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community multicenter</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">179 (12.8)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English primary spoken language</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 67.0 (11.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 752 (53.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 659 (46.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Functional outcome</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Silverstein et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> 2022</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients referred for minimally invasive gynecologic surgery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1823</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic single center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (3.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English primary language</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 1823 (100)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP and EP, 0 (0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delay in surgery</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manuel et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> 2022</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult patients undergoing craniotomies for brain tumor</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2232</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic single center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150 (6.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English primary language and use of LEP-I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 55.4 (15.4); EP, 52.8 (15.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 82 (54.7); EP, 1027 (49.3)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 68 (45.3); EP, 1055 (50.7)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay, discharge disposition, readmission</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stolarski et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> 2022</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">US</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult patients who underwent laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy or laparoscopic gastric bypass surgery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1662</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic single center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">671 (40.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English preferred language OR use of LEP-I at least once during the study period</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 591 (88.1); EP, 882 (89.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 80 (11.9); EP, 109 (11.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay, complications, long-term outcomes, readmission</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kovoor et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> 2023</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients admitted for general surgery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#8201;846</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic multicenter</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1178 (9.2)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English primary language</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 64.8 (19.1); EP, 53.9 (20.4)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 561 (47.6); EP, 5596 (48.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEP, 617 (52.4); EP, 6072 (52.0)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay, in-hospital mortality, pain management</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviations: ACS, acute coronary syndrome; CABG, coronary artery bypass surgery; EP, English proficiency; LEP, limited English proficiency; LEP-I, limited English proficiency with interpreter required; LEP-N, limited English proficiency with no interpreter required; NENS, non-English/non-Spanish; NS, nonspecified.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="zoi230673t2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2. </label><caption><title>Newcastle-Ottawa Scale Quality Assessment</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="31.74%" span="1"/><col width="13.76%" span="1"/><col width="14.55%" span="1"/><col width="12.98%" span="1"/><col width="11.65%" span="1"/><col width="15.32%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Selection (scale, 1-5)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comparability (scale, 1-2)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome (scale, 1-3)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (scale, 1-9)</th><th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study quality<xref rid="zoi230673t2n1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">John-Baptiste et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> 2004</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dowsey et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> 2009</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MacDonald et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> 2010</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nashed et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> 2012</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Betjemann et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> 2013</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thompson et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> 2014</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tang et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> 2016</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wilbur et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> 2016</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inagaki et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> 2017</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyun et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> 2017</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jaiswal et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> 2018</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feeney et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> 2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sridhar et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> 2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feeney et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> 2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feeney et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asokan et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bernstein et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Varady et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wong et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Witt et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schwartz et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Witt et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maurer et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manuel et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> 2022</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aggarwal et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> 2022</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Silverstein et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> 2022</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manuel et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> 2022</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stolarski et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> 2022</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kovoor et al,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> 2023</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="zoi230673t2n1"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>Based on thresholds for converting the Newcastle-Ottawa scales to Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality standards.<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> Good quality is defined as 3 or 4 in the selection domain AND 1 or 2 in the comparability domain AND 2 or 3 in the outcome or exposure domain. Fair quality is defined as 2 in the selection domain AND 1 or 2 in the comparability domain AND 2 or 3 in the outcome or exposure domain. Poor quality is defined as 0 or 1 in the selection domain OR 0 in the comparability domain OR 0 or 1 in the outcome exposure domain.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="H1-3-ZOI230673"><title>Results</title><sec id="H2-1-ZOI230673"><title>Search Results</title><p>Our database search yielded 2230 unique records (<xref rid="zoi230673f1" ref-type="fig">Figure</xref>). After title and abstract review, 70 manuscripts were identified for full-text review. After full-text review, 29 studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> met the inclusion criteria (eTable 2 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230673-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="zoi230673f1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure. </label><caption><title>Flow Diagram</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2322743-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="H2-2-ZOI230673"><title>Study Characteristics</title><p>All included studies took place in English-speaking countries, including the US, Australia, New Zealand, and Canada (<xref rid="zoi230673t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Although our search had no date restriction, studies in our sample were published between 2004 and 2023, with most published from 2019 to 2022 (eFigure 1 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230673-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>).</p><p>All included studies were observational, and 26 of 29 studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> were retrospective. All were cohort studies except for 1 cross-sectional study. Studies reported findings from academic hospital settings and community hospitals. Eighteen of 29 studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> were performed at a single center, whereas 5 studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> were multicenter and 6 studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> used a statewide or nationwide database (<xref rid="zoi230673t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>Eighteen studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> evaluated a patient cohort that underwent surgical admission, whereas 11 studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> contained patient cohorts that underwent evaluation for surgical intervention from an outpatient, general hospital admission, or emergency department (ED) setting. Median study cohort size was 1763 (IQR, 266-7402), with a median LEP cohort size of 179 (IQR, 51-671).</p><p>The 29 included studies had a total of 281 266 patients (mean [SD] age, 57.2 [10.0] years; 121 772 [43.3%] male and 159 240 [55.6%] female). Cohort summary statistics are presented in <xref rid="zoi230673t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Most studies reported race and/or ethnicity, and 11 studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> controlled for race and/or ethnicity in multivariable analysis. Surgical specialties included general, oncologic, orthopedic, neurologic, thoracic, gynecologic, urologic, head and neck, trauma, and vascular surgery.</p></sec><sec id="H2-3-ZOI230673"><title>Defining LEP</title><p>This review found substantial variation in the methods used to define language proficiency and LEP. Most included studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> defined LEP using self-report measures that were documented in electronic medical records. Many studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> used a non-English preferred language as a proxy for LEP. Nine studies confirmed LEP using multiple methods, such as both self-report of non-English preferred language and documentation of interpreter requirements,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> both self-report of non-English preferred language and self-identification of Hispanic ethnicity,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> cross-checking self-reported preferred language by both electronic records and discharge instructions combined with accrual of interpreter service charges,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> or some other method.<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> Some studies evaluated LEP via structural interview by research clerks<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> or a patient-initiated screening tool.<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> Five studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> subcategorized the preferred language of patients with LEP into Spanish vs others. Studies that solely used ethnicity or country of birth as a proxy for language proficiency were excluded from this systematic review.</p></sec><sec id="H2-4-ZOI230673"><title>Risk-of-Bias Assessment</title><p>The risk-of-bias assessment using the Newcastle-Ottawa Scale and Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality thresholds for study quality found 21 studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> to be of good quality and 8 studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> to be poor quality (<xref rid="zoi230673t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> Poor scores were most commonly due to concerns with comparability (eg, analyses did not adequately control for confounders, such as race and ethnicity).</p></sec><sec id="H2-5-ZOI230673"><title>Access to Surgical Care</title><p>Six included studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> assessed access to surgical care (eTable 1 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230673-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). Of these, 3 studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> directly assessed receipt of surgery. One study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> investigated emergency vs elective admission, and another study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> assessed admission to a low-volume vs high-volume hospital, which indirectly represented reduced access. One study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> used a proxy variable (utilization of the electronic patient portal) to demonstrate differential access to surgical care. Four<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> of these 6 studies found LEP to be significantly associated with reduced access to care in adjusted analysis. However, 1 of these studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> revealed a significant association only in patients with non&#8211;Spanish-speaking LEP. Two studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> performed only unadjusted analyses and identified no association between LEP and limited access to care.</p></sec><sec id="H2-6-ZOI230673"><title>Delays in Surgical Care</title><p>Four studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> evaluated the association between LEP and delays in receiving surgical care (eTable 1 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230673-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). Studies defined surgical delay uniquely: time from the date of diagnosis to date of surgery,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> time from hospital admission to the date of surgery,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> time from the date of diagnosis to the date of treatment,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> and time from the date of referral to the date of surgical department initial encounter.<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> Two studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> reported significant delays in care among patients with LEP, whereas 1 study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> reported no difference. The remaining study was equivocal, reporting significant delays in care for patients with LEP in the more recent subcohort analysis, but such association was not significant in the historical subcohort.<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="H2-7-ZOI230673"><title>Surgical Admission LOS</title><p>Fourteen studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> evaluated the association between LEP and LOS (eTable 1 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230673-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). There was a high degree of heterogeneity in processing and analyzing the LOS variable. Two studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> dichotomized LOS into either long or short LOS using a cutoff at 5 or 7 days each. Although most studies assessed total LOS defined as time from surgical hospital admission to discharge, 2 of 14 studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> assessed postoperative LOS defined as time from end of surgical procedure to discharge.</p><p>Five studies found significantly prolonged total LOS in patients with LEP admitted for surgical procedures, including for coronary artery bypass graft,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> craniotomy,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> intestinal and rectal surgery,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> hip arthroplasty,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> and knee arthroplasty. Of these 5 studies, 1 study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> demonstrated mixed results depending on surgical cohorts. One study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> of neuro-oncology patients showed significantly longer postoperative LOS in patients with non&#8211;Spanish-speaking LEP but no association with total LOS. Eight studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> found no association between LEP and total or postoperative LOS. A single study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> found that patients with Spanish-speaking LEP had shorter total LOS for appendectomy and patients with either Spanish-speaking or non&#8211;Spanish-speaking LEP had shorter total LOS for adhesiolysis compared with English-proficient patients. However, when looking at a subcohort of high-risk procedures in this same study, Spanish-speaking and non&#8211;Spanish-speaking patients with LEP had increased LOS compared with English-proficient patients.</p></sec><sec id="H2-8-ZOI230673"><title>Discharge Disposition</title><p>Four studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> evaluated the association between LEP and postoperative discharge disposition (eTable 1 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230673-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). Patients with LEP were more likely to be discharged to skilled facilities vs home after total joint arthroplasty<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> and craniotomy.<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> In another study,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> patients with LEP who needed an interpreter had a significantly higher chance of discharge to skilled facilities after total joint arthroplasty than those with English proficiency, whereas patients with LEP who did not require an interpreter had no such association. In a study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> of neuro-oncologic surgery patients, Spanish-speaking LEP was associated with lower odds of discharge to skilled facilities, although no association was observed between non&#8211;Spanish-speaking LEP and discharge disposition.</p></sec><sec id="H2-9-ZOI230673"><title>Mortality</title><p>Six studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> evaluated the association between LEP and perioperative in-hospital mortality (eTable 1 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230673-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). Five of these studies found no significant association between LEP and in-hospital mortality; only 1 study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> found a subcohort of patients with LEP undergoing aortic aneurysm repair who had significantly higher in-hospital mortality than those with English proficiency in adjusted analysis.</p><p>Five studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> evaluated the association between LEP and postoperative all-cause mortality (or overall survival). Two studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> assessed the binary outcome of all-cause mortality, and 3 studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> looked at overall survival time to capture mortality data. Four studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> identified no association between LEP and all-cause mortality; however, 1 study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> detected significantly longer median overall survival in a subcohort of patients with stage III to IV pancreatic cancer with LEP in unadjusted analysis. Overall, few studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> found a significant association between LEP and mortality in adjusted analyses.</p></sec><sec id="H2-10-ZOI230673"><title>Complications</title><p>Five studies assessed postoperative complications, including wound infection,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> adverse graft event,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> major adverse cardiac events,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> major morbidities based on the National Surgical Quality Improvement Program risk calculator criteria,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> and general short-term postoperative complications.<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> Only 1 included study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> observed a significant association between LEP and complications. This study found higher odds of developing complications after neuro-oncologic surgery in patients with non&#8211;Spanish-speaking LEP compared with English-proficient patients.</p></sec><sec id="H2-11-ZOI230673"><title>Readmissions</title><p>Nine studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> evaluated the association between LEP and unplanned hospital readmissions after surgical hospitalization. Seven studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> assessed hospital readmissions within 7 days, 30 days, or 1 year after discharge (eTable 1 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230673-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). Four studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> investigated ED visits within 30 days or 1 year after discharge.</p><p>Most studies found no association between LEP and readmissions. A single study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> identified significantly more 30-day readmissions in patients with LEP than English proficiency who underwent gynecologic oncology surgery. Of the 4 studies that addressed ED visits, 2 studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> found no association between LEP and ED visits after infrainguinal bypass or oncologic surgery, 1 study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> reported a significantly higher rate of ED visits among patients with LEP after proctocolectomy, and 1 study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> demonstrated fewer ED visits among patients with LEP after gastric surgery.</p></sec><sec id="H2-12-ZOI230673"><title>Perioperative Pain Management</title><p>A single study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> in our review evaluated the association between LEP and receipt of a discharge opioid prescription after surgical care, finding that patients with LEP were less likely to receive a discharge opioid prescription, and even if they did, the oral morphine equivalent amount was lower for patients with LEP than English proficiency. One other study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> found general surgical patients with LEP had significantly lower median pain scores recorded during their admission than patients with English proficiency.</p></sec><sec id="H2-13-ZOI230673"><title>Functional Outcomes</title><p>Two studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> evaluated the association between LEP and postoperative function after arthroplasty procedures. One study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> found significantly lower 12-month postoperative functional status using International Knee Society scores among patients with LEP vs English-proficient patients. Another study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> found that patients with LEP had significantly lower Oxford hip scores after total hip arthroplasty, indicating worse function and pain. However, the association between LEP and patient-rated improvement scores failed to reach statistical significance in the same study. A single study<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> reported no difference in mean excess weight loss 1 year after laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy or gastric bypass between individuals with and without LEP.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-4-ZOI230673"><title>Discussion</title><p>This systematic review included 29 studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> examining the association between LEP and a broad range of perioperative care and surgical outcomes (eFigure 2 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230673-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). Outcomes corresponding to efficiency in the perioperative process of care, such as accessibility, timely delivery of care, LOS, and discharge disposition, demonstrated the most consistent association with LEP status. On the other hand, clinical outcomes, such as postoperative complications, unplanned readmissions and ED visits, and mortality, were less frequently associated with LEP. Only a small number of studies examined differences in perioperative pain management or postoperative functional outcomes.</p><p>The substantial variation in methods used to define LEP in included studies was notable. Inconsistent ascertainment of our primary exposure of interest led to heterogeneity that limited our ability to accurately estimate the true association of language barriers or draw strong conclusions from the findings. Concerns about potential misclassification of patients by English proficiency status are also valid and can result in underestimation or overestimation of the association. Validated methods for determining the LEP status of patients should be used by future investigators, including asking patients their preferred language combined with the question, &#8220;How well do you speak English?&#8221;<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup> or combining non&#8211;English-preferred language with a request for interpreter services.<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> In addition, data on health care team language proficiency and family member or professional interpreter use were not collected by most included studies but would be useful.</p><p>The heterogeneity of study settings, surgical subspecialties, and outcome measurements also prevented pooling of data for meta-analysis. We are, nonetheless, able to provide important data about the quality and quantity of existing literature and to report the directionality of evidence.</p><p>Most studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> included in this review reported the experience of a single hospital or health care system from 1 of 7 states in the US, limiting generalizability. However, a few studies<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> examined a large statewide (New Jersey) database of community hospital discharges. Although the extent to which this source of hospitalization data provides consistent and standardized measures of LEP status is still unknown, investigators were able to account for hospital- or physician-level effects, enabling more complex analyses to unveil intrahospital or intraphysician correlations.<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup></p><p>Furthermore, with only observational evidence available and likely residual confounding, we cannot infer causation; we can only note the frequently observed associations between LEP and perioperative process outcomes. We recognize that LEP status coexists with, and is extremely difficult to disentangle from, many other social determinants of health, including racism, immigration status, social segregation, occupational hierarchy, economic security, insurance coverage, health literacy, and cultural differences. Although most included studies conducted adjusted analyses to reduce confounding between LEP and observed outcomes, sets of adjustment variables were highly variable and driven by setting, surgical procedure, or population. Although some studies adjusted for race and ethnicity, which are known to be correlated with health outcomes in English-speaking countries, many studies did not include these covariates or did not adjust for them for various statistical reasons: multicollinearity,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> model fitting,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> stepwise selection,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> decision a priori,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> unadjusted analysis only,<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> or other reasons.<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> Simultaneously, however, although risk of unmeasured confounding and inconsistent adjustment in the included observational studies limit our ability to draw conclusions about exposure-outcome relationships, an experimental study design (such as randomized clinical trials) may be considered unethical because there is significant evidence that lack of interpretation services in health care settings is linked to worse outcomes and safety issues.<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="zoi230673r47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> The current lack of inclusion of preferred language and interpreter use data in national databases diminish investigators&#8217; abilities to include language barriers in large multivariable models examining predictors of perioperative outcomes, generate more generalizable findings, more completely control for confounding factors, and detect smaller effect sizes. Unsurprisingly, in unadjusted analyses (eTable 3 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230673-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>), which did not attempt to isolate the impact of language barriers from common confounders, such as insurance status and comorbidities, patients with LEP were more likely to experience more unfavorable perioperative and surgical outcomes than English-proficient patients.</p><p>Despite our inability to comment on mediators of the observed associations, this systematic review corroborates findings from other reviews examining the association of English proficiency with various health care outcomes. Woods et al<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup> reviewed 26 studies and reported that LEP was associated with inpatient LOS in 8 of 17 studies and not associated with LOS in 9 of 17 studies, with directionality toward prolonged LOS for patients with LEP. No association was found between LEP and mortality or clinical complications in hospitalized patients of both medical and surgical services in this review. Hsueh et al<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup> and Diamond et al<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup> reviewed the association of physician-patient language concordance with health outcomes in primary care and hospital settings and found that language discordance was associated with lower-quality medical communication, reduced understanding, reduced health care access and utilization, suboptimal patient-physician interactions, and worse clinical outcomes, including glycemic control and adverse medications events.</p><p>Most recently, Luan-Erfe et al<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup> attempted to review the association of LEP with perioperative and perianesthetic outcomes. They included 10 studies, most of which examined pediatric populations or nonsurgical cohorts and none of which met the inclusion criteria of this systematic review (eTable 2 in <xref rid="note-ZOI230673-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). The results of the review by Luan-Erfe et al<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup> were mixed, with limited ability to draw conclusions because of the small number of studies per outcome examined. Overall, the authors determined that language barriers were negatively associated with patient-centered perioperative outcomes, such as less patient participation in the informed consent process, insufficient understanding of discharge instructions, delayed or infrequent pain assessments, and higher likelihood of ED visits after discharge; however, LEP was not associated with access to appointments, adequacy of procedure preparation, pain management, or postdischarge follow-up encounters.<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup> Our findings complement the findings of Luan-Erfe et al<sup><xref rid="zoi230673r51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup> and more fully characterize the association of language barriers with the care and outcomes of surgical patients with LEP. These reviews all agree that LEP may be independently correlated with efficiency outcomes and patient-centered aspects of care regardless of health care settings; however, evidence of a strong influence of LEP on clinical outcomes is not observed.</p><p>There is a clear need for additional research on the impact of LEP and perioperative and surgical care. An important finding of the current systematic review is that many individual centers observe disparities in outcomes by LEP status, which warrants inclusion of language variables in larger surgical outcome studies. However, to perform higher-quality studies, greater consistency and rigor are needed in the collection of language and interpreter use data and in the ascertainment of perioperative measures of interest. Large nationwide databases should include routine collection of preferred language and English proficiency to facilitate this research as well as investigate concerns of specific language minority groups and assess less common outcomes. Finally, many clinically important underexplored outcomes, such as long-term functional recovery and perioperative pain management, should be examined. Importantly, additional investigations are needed to establish an understanding of the pathways by which language barriers may impact perioperative health outcomes so that interventions to reduce observed disparities can be created.</p><sec id="H2-14-ZOI230673"><title>Strengths and Limitations</title><p> A strength of this systematic review is its use of rigorous methods. However, the results should be interpreted in the context of its limitations. Only peer-reviewed published original research is included, so the findings reported could be subject to publication bias. Because of the heterogeneity of included studies with regard to study setting, surgical subspecialty, outcome measurement, statistical methods, and measure of association, we were unable to pool data to perform a meta-analysis (eMethods in <xref rid="note-ZOI230673-1-s" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplement 1</xref>). We are, nonetheless, able to report directionality of evidence. There was variation in definition and ascertainment of LEP status, and a standardized method of collecting language and interpreter data is needed. The way that outcomes of interest were measured in the included studies may allow for variations in residual confounding effects, which impede our ability to assess differences for patients with LEP. Where numerous outcomes and comparisons were evaluated, there is a risk that some findings might be statistically significant by chance. Additionally, the quality of evidence ratings provided by the Newcastle-Ottawa Scale are largely subjective, and some might disagree with our assessments.</p></sec></sec><sec id="H1-5-ZOI230673"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In this systematic review, many of the included studies found associations between LEP and multiple perioperative process-of-care outcomes, but fewer associations were seen between English proficiency and clinical outcomes. Limited data found lower perioperative opioid use and worse functional recovery among patients with LEP. Because of study limitations, including heterogeneity and residual confounding, mediators of the observed associations remain unclear. Standardized reporting and larger, higher-quality studies are needed to understand the effect of language barriers on perioperative health disparities and provide the basis for interventions to reduce perioperative health care disparities in the increasing LEP population.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="REF-ZOI230673"><title>References</title><ref id="zoi230673r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Torain</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maragh-Bass</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dankwa-Mullen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Surgical disparities: a comprehensive review and new conceptual framework</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Surg</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>223</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>408</fpage>-<lpage>418</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2016.04.047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27296524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>de Jager</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Udyavar</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Disparities in surgical access: a systematic literature review, conceptual model, and evidence map</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Surg</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>228</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>276</fpage>-<lpage>298</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2018.12.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30803548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6391739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab>US Census Bureau</collab></person-group>. QuickFacts. Quick Facts. Accessed April 20, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.census.gov/quickfacts/fact/table/US/PST045219" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.census.gov/quickfacts/fact/table/US/PST045219</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Divi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Koss</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schmaltz</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Loeb</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Language proficiency and adverse events in US hospitals: a pilot study</article-title>. <source>Int J Qual Health Care</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>60</fpage>-<lpage>67</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/intqhc/mzl069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17277013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karliner</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Agger-Gupta</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mutha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The need for more research on language barriers in health care: a proposed research agenda</article-title>. <source>Milbank Q</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>111</fpage>-<lpage>133</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1468-0009.2006.00440.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16529570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2690153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tuot</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karliner</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of an easy-access telephonic interpreter program in the acute care setting: an evaluation of a quality improvement intervention</article-title>. <source>Jt Comm J Qual Patient Saf</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>81</fpage>-<lpage>88</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1553-7250(12)38011-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22372255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karliner</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Association of primary language and hospitalization for ambulatory care sensitive conditions</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>45</fpage>-<lpage>51</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MLR.0000000000001245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31821245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7135941</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>P&#233;rez-Stable</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>El-Toukhy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Communicating with diverse patients: how patient and clinician factors affect disparities</article-title>. <source>Patient Educ Couns</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>101</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2186</fpage>-<lpage>2194</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pec.2018.08.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30146407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6417094</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Quigley</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hambarsoomian</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Inpatient care experiences differ by preferred language within racial/ethnic groups</article-title>. <source>Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>263</fpage>-<lpage>274</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1475-6773.13105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30613960</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6341216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wasserman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Renfrew</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Identifying and preventing medical errors in patients with limited English proficiency: key findings and tools for the field</article-title>. <source>J Healthc Qual</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jhq.12065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24629098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5111827</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karliner</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mutha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Do professional interpreters improve clinical care for patients with limited English proficiency? a systematic review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>727</fpage>-<lpage>754</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1475-6773.2006.00629.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17362215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1955368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karliner</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Auerbach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>N&#225;poles</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schillinger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nickleach</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>P&#233;rez-Stable</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Language barriers and understanding of hospital discharge instructions</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>283</fpage>-<lpage>289</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MLR.0b013e318249c949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22411441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3311126</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Manuel</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#225;ndez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bucklin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno Lepe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wick</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. The impact of language barriers on perioperative care and surgical outcomes: a systematic review proposal. Accessed February 1, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.crd.york.ac.uk/prospero/display_record.php?ID=CRD42022299569" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.crd.york.ac.uk/prospero/display_record.php?ID=CRD42022299569</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2023.22743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10336626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37432686</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bossuyt</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>PRISMA 2020 explanation and elaboration: updated guidance and exemplars for reporting systematic reviews</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>372</volume>(<issue>160</issue>):<fpage>n160</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.n160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33781993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8005925</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>John-Baptiste</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Naglie</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tomlinson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of English language proficiency on length of stay and in-hospital mortality</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>221</fpage>-<lpage>228</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1525-1497.2004.21205.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15009776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1492154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dowsey</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Broadhead</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stoney</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Choong</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Outcomes of total knee arthroplasty in English- versus non-English-speaking patients</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Surg (Hong Kong)</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>305</fpage>-<lpage>309</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/230949900901700312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20065369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ottem</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wasdell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Spiwak</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Predictors of prolonged hospital stays following hip and knee arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>Int J Orthop Trauma Nurs</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>198</fpage>-<lpage>205</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijotn.2010.06.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nashed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Glantz</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Linskey</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bota</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Access to specialized treatment by adult Hispanic brain tumor patients: findings from a single-institution retrospective study</article-title>. <source>Community Oncol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>283</fpage>-<lpage>288</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmonc.2012.06.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Betjemann</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Santos-S&#225;nchez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ivey</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Distinguishing language and race disparities in epilepsy surgery</article-title>. <source>Epilepsy Behav</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>444</fpage>-<lpage>449</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2013.06.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23891765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ivey</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lahiff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Betjemann</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Delays in time to surgery for minorities with temporal lobe epilepsy</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1339</fpage>-<lpage>1346</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/epi.12700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25040697</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Go</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kwok</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The relationship between language proficiency and surgical length of stay following cardiac bypass surgery</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cardiovasc Nurs</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>438</fpage>-<lpage>446</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1474515115596645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26198643</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wilbur</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mannschreck</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Angarita</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Unplanned 30-day hospital readmission as a quality measure in gynecologic oncology</article-title>. <source>Gynecol Oncol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>143</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>604</fpage>-<lpage>610</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygyno.2016.09.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27665313</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Inagaki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Farber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kalish</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Role of language discordance in complication and readmission rate after infrainguinal bypass</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Surg</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1473</fpage>-<lpage>1478</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvs.2017.03.453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28625669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hyun</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Redfern</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Is there inequity in hospital care among patients with acute coronary syndrome who are proficient and not proficient in English language? analysis of the SNAPSHOT ACS Study</article-title>. <source>J Cardiovasc Nurs</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>288</fpage>-<lpage>295</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JCN.0000000000000342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27617562</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jaiswal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hull</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Furniss</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gayou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bayliss</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Delays in diagnosis and treatment of breast cancer: a safety-net population profile</article-title>. <source>J Natl Compr Canc Netw</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1451</fpage>-<lpage>1457</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6004/jnccn.2018.7067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30545992</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feeney</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cassidy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tripodis</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of primary language with outcomes after operations typically performed to treat cancer: analysis of a statewide database</article-title>. <source>Ann Surg Oncol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2684</fpage>-<lpage>2693</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1245/s10434-019-07484-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31187361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sridhar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Misir</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of race, insurance status, and primary language on presentation, treatment, and outcomes of patients with pancreatic adenocarcinoma at a safety-net hospital</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Surg</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>229</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>389</fpage>-<lpage>396</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2019.05.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31212101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feeney</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tripodis</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The association of primary language with emergency general surgery outcomes using a statewide database</article-title>. <source>J Surg Res</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>244</volume>:<fpage>484</fpage>-<lpage>491</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jss.2019.06.082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31330292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feeney</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Godley</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Provider-patient language discordance and cancer operations: outcomes from a single center linked to a state vital statistics registry</article-title>. <source>World J Surg</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>3324</fpage>-<lpage>3332</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00268-020-05614-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32474627</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Asokan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sridhar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Qureshi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Presentation, treatment, and outcomes of vulnerable populations with esophageal cancer treated at a safety-net hospital</article-title>. <source>Semin Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>347</fpage>-<lpage>354</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.semtcvs.2019.12.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31866573</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sharan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lygrisse</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lajam</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The need for an interpreter increases length of stay and influences postoperative disposition following primary total joint arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2405</fpage>-<lpage>2409</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2020.04.083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32446624</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Varady</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>d&#8217;Amonville</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Electronic patient portal use in orthopaedic surgery is associated with disparities, improved satisfaction, and lower no-show rates</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>102</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1336</fpage>-<lpage>1343</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.19.01080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32769600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sokas</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Preventable emergency department visits after colorectal surgery</article-title>. <source>Dis Colon Rectum</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1417</fpage>-<lpage>1425</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/DCR.0000000000002127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34192709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8519030</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Witt</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eruchalu</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of patient primary language in access to brain tumor resection: evaluating emergent admission and hospital volume</article-title>. <source>J Cancer Policy</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<elocation-id>100306</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcpo.2021.100306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35559808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>HEM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Matthay</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Menza</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Inequity in discharge pain management for trauma patients with limited English proficiency</article-title>. <source>J Trauma Acute Care Surg</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>91</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>898</fpage>-<lpage>902</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/TA.0000000000003294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34039923</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Witt</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eruchalu</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Non-English primary language is associated with short-term outcomes after supratentorial tumor resection</article-title>. <source>World Neurosurg</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>155</volume>:<fpage>e484</fpage>-<lpage>e502</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2021.08.087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34461280</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maurer</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Allar</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Non-English primary language is associated with emergency surgery for diverticulitis</article-title>. <source>J Surg Res</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>268</volume>:<fpage>643</fpage>-<lpage>649</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jss.2021.07.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34474213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Manuel</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karliner</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Association of English language proficiency with hospitalization cost, length of stay, disposition location, and readmission following total joint arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<lpage>e221842</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.1842</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35267037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8914571</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Naylor</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Preoperative factors and patient-reported outcomes after total hip arthroplasty: multivariable prediction modeling</article-title>. <source>J Arthroplasty</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>714</fpage>-<lpage>720.e4</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2021.12.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34990754</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McClurg</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fliss</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Louie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Patient characteristics associated with access to minimally invasive gynecologic surgery: changes during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source>J Minim Invasive Gynecol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1110</fpage>-<lpage>1118</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmig.2022.06.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35750193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9216549</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Manuel</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chia</surname><given-names>ZK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Raygor</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#225;ndez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Association of language barriers with process outcomes after craniotomy for brain tumor</article-title>. <source>Neurosurgery</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>91</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>590</fpage>-<lpage>595</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1227/neu.0000000000002080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35857019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10552977</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stolarski</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of English proficiency on outcomes after bariatric surgery</article-title>. <source>Surg Endosc</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>7385</fpage>-<lpage>7391</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00464-022-09148-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35229210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kovoor</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bacchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stretton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Language and gender barriers to pain control after general surgery</article-title>. <source>ANZ J Surg</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>93</volume>(<issue>1-2</issue>):<fpage>104</fpage>-<lpage>107</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ans.18164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36412097</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hartling</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hamm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <italic toggle="yes">Decision Rules for Application of the Newcastle-Ottawa Scale</italic>. Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality; <year>2012</year>. Accessed April 21, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK92291/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK92291/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shea</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Connell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. The Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (NOS) for assessing the quality of nonrandomised studies in meta-analyses. Accessed February 1, 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ohri.ca/programs/clinical_epidemiology/oxford.asp" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ohri.ca/programs/clinical_epidemiology/oxford.asp</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karliner</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Napoles-Springer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schillinger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bibbins-Domingo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>P&#233;rez-Stable</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of limited English proficient patients in clinical care</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1555</fpage>-<lpage>1560</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-008-0693-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18618200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2533382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of medical interpreter services on the quality of health care: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Med Care Res Rev</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>255</fpage>-<lpage>299</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1077558705275416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15894705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Duraiswamy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Limited English proficiency and clinical outcomes after hospital-based care in English-speaking countries: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2050</fpage>-<lpage>2061</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-021-07348-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35112283</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9198156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hsueh</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hirsh</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maupom&#233;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Patient-provider language concordance and health outcomes: a systematic review, evidence map, and research agenda</article-title>. <source>Med Care Res Rev</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1077558719860708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31291823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Diamond</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Izquierdo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Canfield</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Matsoukas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gany</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A systematic review of the impact of patient-physician non-English language concordance on quality of care and outcomes</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1591</fpage>-<lpage>1606</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-019-04847-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31147980</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6667611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zoi230673r51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Luan-Erfe</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Erfe</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>DeCaria</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Okocha</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Limited English proficiency and perioperative patient-centered outcomes: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Anesth Analg</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>136</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1096</fpage>-<lpage>1106</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1213/ANE.0000000000006159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36066429</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><notes notes-type="supplementary-material" id="note-ZOI230673-1"><supplementary-material id="note-ZOI230673-1-s" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplement 1.</label><caption><p><bold>eAppendix 1.</bold> Methodological Details</p><p><bold>eAppendix 2.</bold> Detailed Search Strategy</p><p>
eReferences
</p><p><bold>eTable 1.</bold> Study Outcomes, Methods, and Results by Category</p><p><bold>eTable 2.</bold> Decision for Inclusion and Exclusion</p><p><bold>eTable 3.</bold> Unadjusted Results</p><p><bold>eFigure 1.</bold> Articles per Year that Met Inclusion Criteria</p><p><bold>eFigure 2.</bold> Perioperative Outcomes Represented</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2322743-s001.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplement 2.</label><caption><p>
Data Sharing Statement
</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jamanetwopen-e2322743-s002.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></notes></back></article></pmc-articleset>