<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Hand (N Y)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Hand (N Y)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">664</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">hand</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HAN</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Hand (New York, N.Y.)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1558-9447</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1558-9455</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11571476</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11571476.2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11571476</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12184748</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38491777</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/15589447241235339</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_15589447241235339</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">2</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Intramedullary Screw Fixation of Proximal Phalangeal Fractures: Short- to Medium-Term Outcomes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0009-0004-3714-518X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbot</surname><given-names initials="H">Hagen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1-15589447241235339" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="corresp1-15589447241235339" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6496-8596</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names initials="AR">Adam R.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1-15589447241235339" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCarron</surname><given-names initials="L">Luke</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2-15589447241235339" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3421-822X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names initials="DJ">David J.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2-15589447241235339" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff3-15589447241235339" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff4-15589447241235339" ref-type="aff">4</xref><xref rid="aff5-15589447241235339" ref-type="aff">5</xref><xref rid="aff6-15589447241235339" ref-type="aff">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0890-2132</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Sivakumar</surname><given-names initials="B">Brahman</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1-15589447241235339" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff3-15589447241235339" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff7-15589447241235339" ref-type="aff">7</xref><xref rid="aff8-15589447241235339" ref-type="aff">8</xref><xref rid="aff9-15589447241235339" ref-type="aff">9</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-15589447241235339"><label>1</label>Sydney Medical School, Faculty of Medicine and Health, The University of Sydney, Camperdown, NSW, Australia</aff><aff id="aff2-15589447241235339"><label>2</label>Department of Musculoskeletal Services, Gold Coast University Hospital, Southport, QLD, Australia</aff><aff id="aff3-15589447241235339"><label>3</label>Australian Research Collaboration on Hands (ARCH), Mudgeeraba, QLD, Australia</aff><aff id="aff4-15589447241235339"><label>4</label>School of Medicine and Dentistry, Griffith University, Southport, QLD, Australia</aff><aff id="aff5-15589447241235339"><label>5</label>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Queensland Children&#8217;s Hospital, Brisbane, Australia</aff><aff id="aff6-15589447241235339"><label>6</label>School of Medicine, University of Queensland, Herston, Australia</aff><aff id="aff7-15589447241235339"><label>7</label>Department of Hand and Peripheral Nerve Surgery, Royal North Shore Hospital, St Leonards, NSW, Australia</aff><aff id="aff8-15589447241235339"><label>8</label>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Hornsby Ku-Ring-Gai Hospital, Hornsby, NSW, Australia</aff><aff id="aff9-15589447241235339"><label>9</label>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Nepean Hospital, Kingswood, NSW, Australia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-15589447241235339">Hagen Abbot, Sydney Medical School, Faculty of Medicine and Health, The University of Sydney, Camperdown, NSW 2050, Australia. Email: <email>habb6045@uni.sydney.edu.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>7</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">491242</issue-id><fpage>684</fpage><lpage>690</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>15</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-06-24 10:25:14.643"><day>24</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-version" specific-use="live"><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11571476</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/15589447241235339</article-id><article-version>1</article-version><pub-date><day>15</day><month>03</month><year>2024</year></pub-date></event><event event-type="pmc-version" specific-use="live"><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12184748</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/15589447241235339</article-id><article-version>2</article-version><pub-date><day>15</day><month>03</month><year>2024</year></pub-date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2024</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">American Association for Hand Surgery</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access page (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10.1177_15589447241235339.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="section1-15589447241235339"><title>Background:</title><p>Intramedullary screw fixation of phalangeal and metacarpal fractures has gained popularity as a method of providing rigid internal fixation with minimum tendon disturbance, allowing early mobilization and rehabilitation. Despite this, the literature on outcomes using this technique is limited. Thus, the aim of this study was to assess the short-term to medium-term outcomes of intramedullary screw fixation for proximal phalangeal fracture fixation in an Australian setting.</p></sec><sec id="section2-15589447241235339"><title>Methods:</title><p>A retrospective analysis of consecutive patients with a fracture(s) of the proximal phalanx fixated using intramedullary screws between January 2020 and March 2023 was conducted via telehealth.</p></sec><sec id="section3-15589447241235339"><title>Results:</title><p>Forty-six phalangeal fractures from 37 patients were included in this study. Mean Quick Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder, and Hand score of 6.2 (range: 0-61.4, median: 0), mean pain visual analogue scale score of 1.8 (range: 1-7, median: 1), and mean total active motion of 231&#176; (range: 132-282) were noted. A total of 4.4% of fractures sustained a major complication, and 94.6% of patients reported willingness to undergo intramedullary screw fixation again.</p></sec><sec id="section4-15589447241235339"><title>Conclusion:</title><p>This study concurs with the prior literature that intramedullary screw fixation is a safe and effective method of stabilizing extra-articular proximal phalangeal fractures in the short to medium term. Superior clinical outcomes, as well as cost-effectiveness and time-effectiveness, render it a viable alternative to plate fixation in this setting.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>fracture</kwd><kwd>intramedullary</kwd><kwd>phalanx</kwd><kwd>proximal</kwd><kwd>screw</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>typesetter</meta-name><meta-value>ts1</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="section5-15589447241235339"><title>Introduction</title><p>Hand fractures are common and account for up to a third of all fractures presenting to emergency departments, with phalangeal fractures occurring more commonly than those involving the metacarpals.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<xref rid="bibr2-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr3-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Injury to the proximal phalanx comprises 39% of all phalangeal fractures and poses a significant financial and health burden to both the individual and the community.<sup><xref rid="bibr4-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
<xref rid="bibr5-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr6-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Thus, optimal management is key.</p><p>The treatment objective once the proximal phalanx is fractured is to ensure sufficient stability in a satisfactorily reduced position to allow early mobilization, thus preventing the formation of adhesions that may limit range of motion and function.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr4-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
</sup> Many of these fractures are stable and can be treated nonoperatively.<sup><xref rid="bibr7-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="bibr8-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> However, fracture pattern and mechanism, as well as patient characteristics and functional requirements, may necessitate surgical intervention.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr7-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Rigid fixation constructs are generally preferred to nonrigid fixation, as they facilitate precise alignment and earlier mobilization. However, stable fixation is only one determinant of outcome, with invasiveness, degree of soft tissue dissection, and cost also important considerations.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr9-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
</sup></p><p>Intramedullary screw fixation of phalangeal and metacarpal fractures has gained popularity as a method of providing rigid internal fixation with minimum tendon disturbance, allowing early mobilization and rehabilitation, with novel methods of instrumentation broadening the indications.<sup><xref rid="bibr10-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="bibr11-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Screws may be inserted via retrograde intra-articular, antegrade intra-articular, and antegrade transarticular routes, with choice determined via fracture pattern, patient characteristics, and surgical preference.</p><p>Despite the increasing popularity and adoption of the use of intramedullary screw fixation, the literature on outcomes using this technique is limited. Thus, the aim of this study was to assess the short-term to medium-term outcomes of intramedullary screw fixation for proximal phalangeal fracture fixation in an Australian setting.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="section6-15589447241235339"><title>Methods</title><p>This study was performed as a retrospective review of a series of consecutive patients with proximal phalangeal fractures stabilized by intramedullary screws by 2 fellowship-trained orthopedic hand surgeons in Sydney and the Gold Coast, Australia. The intramedullary screws were inserted via either antegrade or retrograde routes. Following provisional fracture reduction, a guidewire was inserted through the proximal interphalangeal joint (for retrograde insertion), or through the metacarpal head or the metacarpophalangeal joint (for antegrade intra-articular and antegrade transarticular insertion, respectively). For extremely basal fractures, the technique of reverse instrumentation and stabilization of the fracture followed by antegrade intra-articular insertion, as described by Sivakumar and Graham, was used.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr11-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
</sup> A small skin incision was then performed, and screw length measured. The diameter of the screw was determined by the phalangeal anatomy, aiming for an isthmic fit&#8212;in the vast majority of patients, a 2.2-mm cannulated compression screw (Medartis AG, Basel, Switzerland) was used. The screw was inserted with care taken to hold the digits in relaxed flexion, to maintain a normal cascade and prevent any malrotation. Patients commenced active range of motion within 1 week of the operation, with buddy strapping to the adjacent digits to control rotation, within a hand-based thermoplastic splint. Radiographs were taken at a standardized timepoint of 6 weeks after the operation, with a return to normal activities in a graded fashion if union or progression to union was noted.</p><p>For this study, following procurement of institutional ethics approval, records of all patients who had received intramedullary screw fixation of proximal phalangeal fractures under the care of the 2 surgeons in the 38-month period between January 2020 and March 2023 were obtained from a prospectively maintained database. Patient details were identified via the computerized medical records systems of both public and private institutions.</p><p>Patients were eligible for inclusion if they received intramedullary fixation of at least 1 proximal phalanx fracture; were at least 6 months after the operation at follow-up; and consented to receiving telehealth surveys and providing clinical photographs for measurement.</p><p>Demographic information, fracture characteristics, and fixation approach were collated from the medical records. Union was determined by the treating surgeon based on crossing trabeculations at the fracture site on radiographs, and a lack of pain or crepitus on clinical examination. A telehealth interview was conducted to assess patient satisfaction, the presence of complications, return to normal function and work, and outcome measures in the form of a Quick Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder, and Hand (QuickDASH) and a pain visual analogue scale (VAS). Patients also provided clinical photos of the sagittal profile of the affected digit in full flexion and extension, from which total active motion (TAM) of that digit was calculated (Angles in Photo, Kubilay Erdogan, Munich, Germany). Total active motion is used as defined by the American Society for Surgery of the Hand as the sum of active motion of the metacarpophalangeal and interphalangeal joints of a digit and can be compared with a norm of 260&#176;.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr12-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
</sup> Simple statistical analysis was performed where appropriate.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr13-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">T</italic> tests (2 variables) and analysis of variance (3 variables) were used to determine <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="section7-15589447241235339"><title>Results</title><p>Sixty-six patients were identified from the database, with 37 eligible for inclusion (refer <xref rid="table1-15589447241235339" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Thirty-one patients sustained a single fracture; the remainder had involvements of multiple digits, resulting in a cohort of 46 digits (refer <xref rid="table2-15589447241235339" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table1-15589447241235339" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Patient Inclusion and Exclusion Characteristics.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_15589447241235339-table1.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with proximal phalangeal fracture</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All patients</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Eligible for inclusion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Ineligible for inclusion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Unable to contact</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Follow-up &lt;2 mo</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Did not consent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="table2-15589447241235339" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Patient and Fracture Demographics.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_15589447241235339-table2.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fractures</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Single fractures</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Multiple proximal phalangeal fractures</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age&#8212;mean (range), y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (16-80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Hand</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Left</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Right</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Phalanx</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Thumb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Middle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Ring</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Little</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.6</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Fracture location</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Base</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.9</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">&#8195;Shaft</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Proximal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Mid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Distal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Neck</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comminution fracture</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.7</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Hand dominance</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Dominant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Nondominant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Fracture state</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Open</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Closed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Work cover status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Mechanism of injury</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Fall</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Work injuries</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Sport injuries</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.9</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>Most patients were men, with a mean age of 42 years (16-80) at the time of injury. Sixteen fractures occurred following a fall from standing height; 6 fractures were sustained during work and were covered by workers&#8217; compensation insurance. The most frequently involved digit was the little (57%), followed by the index (17%) (refer <xref rid="table2-15589447241235339" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Roughly three-quarters of the cohort were closed injuries, and although most fractures were isolated in nature, some patients had tendon or neurovascular damage, or concomitant fractures (refer <xref rid="table3-15589447241235339" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Thirty-two fractures were stabilized through intramedullary screws inserted retrograde; the remainder were inserted antegrade transarticular (3) or intra-articular (11) (refer <xref rid="fig1-15589447241235339" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table3-15589447241235339" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Comorbidities and Other Injuries.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_15589447241235339-table3.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbidities and other injuries</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Relevant comorbidities</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Nil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Osteoarthritis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Neuropathy of affected hand</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Other injuries</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Nil reported</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Fracture</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Hand</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&#8195;Rib</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Dislocation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Tendon damage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Head injury</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig1-15589447241235339" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Approaches: retrograde intra-articular (32/46; 69.6%), antegrade intra-articular (11/46; 23.9%), and antegrade transarticular (3/46; 6.5%).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_15589447241235339-fig1.jpg"/></fig><p>Mean follow-up was 79 weeks (28-183). All patients were noted to have united or progressing toward union (as evidenced by crossing trabeculation at the fracture site) on the 6-week postoperative radiograph. Patients returned to work at an average of 7 weeks (0-26), and full function at 14 weeks (2-46). At follow-up, mean QuickDASH was 6.2 (0-61.4; median: 0), while mean pain VAS score was 1.8 (1-7; median: 1) (refer <xref rid="table4-15589447241235339" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). One patient developed an infection requiring debridement, whilst another required hardware removal, yielding a complication rate of 4.4% (refer <xref rid="table5-15589447241235339" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). Thirty-five patients reported willingness to undergo intramedullary screw fixation again, resulting in a 94.6% patient satisfaction rate (refer <xref rid="table6-15589447241235339" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table4-15589447241235339" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Outcomes.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_15589447241235339-table4.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up in wk, mean (range)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Return to work in wk, mean (range)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Return to full function in wk, mean (range)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">QuickDASH, mean (range)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain VAS, mean (range)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (11-183)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (0-26)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (2-46)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.30 (0-61.36)<break/>Median: 0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85 (1-7)<break/>Median: 1</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1-15589447241235339"><p><italic toggle="yes">Note.</italic> QuickDASH = Quick Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder, and Hand; VAS = visual analogue scale.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="table5-15589447241235339" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><p>Major Complication.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_15589447241235339-table5.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major complication</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nil reported</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hardware removal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infection and allergic reaction to antibiotics</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="table6-15589447241235339" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6.</label><caption><p>Patient Satisfaction.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_15589447241235339-table6.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient satisfaction</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Subjective malrotation or deformity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Subjective restriction in motion</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Patient would undergo intramedullary fixation again</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>Twenty-nine patients provided clinical photographs of 33 phalanges for TAM assessment. Mean TAM in the lesser digits was 233&#176; (132-282), while TAM for the thumb was 105&#176; (81-129) (refer <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/suppl/10.1177/15589447241235339" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental Table 1</ext-link>).</p><p>One patient had a particularly poor outcome&#8212;after sustaining 2 open proximal phalangeal fractures with tendon damage in a workplace injury, he developed an infection requiring debridement and endured an allergic reaction to his antibiotic therapy. This patient reported a QuickDASH of 61.4, with calculated TAM of 145&#176; and 166&#176; for each digit&#8212;when excluded, the mean QuickDASH for the remainder of the cohort was 3.8 (0-29.6), mean pain VAS was 1.69 (1-7), and the mean TAM was 236&#176; (132-282).</p><p>Subanalysis revealed that closed fractures had significantly improved outcomes when compared with open fractures in mean return to work (6 cf 11 weeks, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .009), return to full function (12 cf 22 weeks, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .006), QuickDASH (3.49 cf 13.44, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .023), and TAM (241&#176; cf 206&#176;, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .017). Similarly, patients sustaining single fractures reported superior outcomes than those suffering from multiple proximal phalangeal injuries, for return to work (5 cf 12 weeks, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .001), QuickDASH (3.5 cf 12.1, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .043), pain VAS (1.35 cf 2.87, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .006), and TAM (238&#176; cf 211&#176;, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .070). Mean QuickDASH was significantly poorer in patients whose injuries were covered by workers&#8217; compensation insurance than those that were not (15.91 cf 4.28, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .026). No difference was noted between alternate insertion routes for the intramedullary screws (refer <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/suppl/10.1177/15589447241235339" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental Table 2</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section8-15589447241235339"><title>Discussion</title><p>Proximal phalangeal fractures are common, posing significant health and financial burdens to individuals and the community.<sup><xref rid="bibr2-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
<xref rid="bibr3-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr4-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr5-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr6-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Thus, optimal management is key. Recently, operative intervention for hand fractures has increased, with Kirschner wire (K-wire) and plate fixation traditionally being the main operative modalities.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup></p><p>Kirschner wire fixation is rapid and cost-effective, requiring minimal soft tissue dissection. However, it often yields decreased construct rigidity and rotational control, and lacks compression at the fracture site. Protruding wires may cause pin site infections; those buried require another operation for removal. These limitations necessitate immobilization prior to rehabilitation, which when combined with potential extensor apparatus tethering on insertion, can cause significant stiffness.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr14-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
</sup></p><p>Biomechanical studies and operative trends indicate that rigid fixation constructs such as plates are favorable to nonrigid alternatives.<sup><xref rid="bibr15-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
<xref rid="bibr16-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr17-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> However, technique invasiveness and soft tissue damage also influence outcomes.<sup><xref rid="bibr18-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="bibr19-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> Although newer generation plating systems are of lower profile, limited cross-sectional area available for implant placement (due to the intimate relationship between soft tissue and bone in the proximal phalanx), and degree of soft tissue dissection required in the traditional dorsal tendon splitting approach, often causes increased scarring and diminished TAM.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr9-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
</sup> Various approaches and plate positions have been suggested to minimize invasiveness and extensor tendon impediment, with a meta-analysis by Sivakumar finding that tendon-sparing approaches resulted in significantly greater TAM (8.5&#176;; 95% confidence interval, 0.8-16.4, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .03) than a tendon-splitting approach.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr9-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
</sup></p><p>Recently, intramedullary screw fixation has been advocated to address concerns of tendon disturbance minimization while providing sufficient stability to facilitate early mobilization.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr20-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
</sup> Intramedullary screws can be inserted via retrograde (through a flexed proximal interphalangeal joint into the head of the proximal phalanx); intra-articular antegrade (where the proximal phalanx base is subluxated at the metacarpophalangeal joint to facilitate direct entry); and transarticular (where the screw is inserted through the metacarpal head into the base of the proximal phalanx) routes.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr21-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
</sup></p><p>Various biomechanical and cadaveric studies have alleviated concerns surrounding this technique. Ibanez found that intramedullary screw fixation provides greater construct stability and load to failure than lateral plating.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr22-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
</sup> Vegas found that insertion of 2.8-mm screws via retrograde insertion damaged 6.2% of the articular surface of the head of cadaveric proximal phalanges, while a 4.1-mm screw affected 13.4%.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr23-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
</sup> Retrograde insertion also preserved the central slip, with the tendon lesion an average of 2.7 mm wide and 4.9 mm proximal to its insertion unto the middle phalanx.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr23-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
</sup></p><p>del Pi&#241;al assessed articular surface involvement following retrograde insertion, finding that the smallest joints had less than 18% and 25% damage with 2.5- and 3.0-mm screws, respectively.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr24-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
</sup> Proximal articular surface lesions of the proximal phalanx (via antegrade techniques) are markedly smaller, with Borbas reporting 4.5% and 8.5% disruption when using a 2.2- or 3.0-mm screw, respectively.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr25-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
</sup> Notably, the screws used in these studies are of relatively large diameter, while this study routinely used 2.2-mm cannulated screws.</p><p>Stern warned that the &#8220;push-up&#8221; technique for antegrade intra-articular screw insertion is technically challenging, as dorsal translation usually occurs at the fracture site and not through the joint.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr26-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
</sup> Sivakumar recommended retrograde K-wire insertion and fracture stabilization through the proximal interphalangeal joint, prior to dorsal translation, followed by antegrade intramedullary screw insertion.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr11-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
</sup> This facilitates screw stabilization of fairly proximal fractures without the need for transarticular insertion, broadening the indications for use of intramedullary screws.</p><p>Despite increasing popularity and adoption of this technique, outcome data are limited, particularly when considering proximal phalangeal fractures alone. del Pinal noted that intramedullary screw fixation was an effective and technically uncomplicated procedure with few drawbacks and excellent postoperative range of motion in a cohort of 19 unstable transverse proximal phalangeal fractures, as did Giesen in a larger group of 24 proximal phalanges.<sup><xref rid="bibr21-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="bibr24-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> Aita reported a DASH score of 3.6 and VAS of 1.5 at 1 year after operation in a cohort of 41 patients with 48 fractures.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr27-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
</sup> A systematic review by Sivakumar in 2020 found a pooled average TAM of 248&#176; in a cohort of 77 fractures, with a 6% complication rate, mean QuickDASH of 3.6, and return to work of 9.3 weeks after an average 70.5-week follow-up.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr10-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
</sup> More recently, Triwidodo described excellent functional and patient-reported outcomes in a small cohort of 3 fractures, while Silins reported significantly shorter durations for return to work and greatly improved postoperative range of motion in a larger cohort (29 patients with 31 fractures).<sup><xref rid="bibr28-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="bibr29-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> Silins also observed that antegrade screw insertion from the radial or ulnar corner allowed treatment of complex juxta-articular basal fractures without violation of the articular surface.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr29-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
</sup></p><p>This study contributes to the limited literature on intramedullary screw fixation in proximal phalangeal fractures. It finds a mean TAM of 231&#176;, QuickDASH of 6.2, and pain VAS of 1.8 at a mean follow-up time of 79 weeks. One patient&#8217;s results were significant outliers (QuickDASH of 61.4, VAS of 6, TAM of 145&#176; and 166&#176;), and removing these drastically improves results of the remaining cohort. Despite this, the cohort results align with previous publications following intramedullary screw fixation in proximal phalangeal fractures and outperform most results following plate fixation, particularly via tendon splitting approaches.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="bibr29-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="bibr30-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> As expected, patients with multiple fractures, open injuries, and injuries covered by workers&#8217; compensation insurance demonstrated poorer outcomes.</p><p>Although clinical outcome is the main determinant, various factors influence optimal surgical modality, such as cost-effectiveness and time-effectiveness. Sivakumar reported greater surgical durations, hardware costs, follow-up requirements, and subsequent hardware removal with plate fixation compared with intramedullary screw insertion in the Australian health care system, resulting in increased expenditure of AUD $1519.41 and AUD $1698.59 in the public and private sectors, respectively.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr6-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
</sup> Wage losses were approximately AUD $1973.35 more when fractures were fixated by a plate, as opposed to an intramedullary screw.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr6-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
</sup> Brewer found that despite lower hardware-associated costs, K-wire stabilization carried significantly increased outpatient follow-up costs (AUD $1826 &#177; $285 vs AUD $1490 &#177; $274) and a trend toward higher health care&#8211;related costs when compared with uncomplicated intramedullary screw fixation.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr31-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
</sup></p><p>Sivakumar further assessed practice variation in proximal phalangeal fracture management by surveying members of the Australian Hand Surgery Society, finding that clinician experience, base specialty training, practice location, and practice volume affected decision-making. Orthopedic surgeons and less experienced surgeons were more likely to feel comfortable with, and attempt, intramedullary screw fixation.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr32-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>
</sup></p><p>This study has several limitations, including its retrospective nature, small sample size, and reliance on the initial documentation accuracy to assess demographic, injury, and surgical data. Operations from multiple surgeons, across the surgical learning curve, with varying methods of screw insertion, lead to potential confounding. Total active motion was not compared with the normal contralateral side, nor was grip strength measured. Quick Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder, and Hand, although allowing comparison with other studies, may be affected by hand dominance.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr33-15589447241235339" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>
</sup> Postoperative rehabilitation protocols were not detailed and may have varied between patients.</p><p>However, this study concurs with the prior literature that intramedullary screw fixation is a safe and effective method of stabilizing extra-articular proximal phalangeal fractures in the short to medium term, due to excellent clinical outcomes, and cost-effectiveness and time-effectiveness. Further long-term studies, and randomized controlled trials, are required.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="section9-15589447241235339" specific-use="figshare"><title>Supplemental Material</title><supplementary-material id="suppl1-15589447241235339" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>sj-docx-1-han-10.1177_15589447241235339 &#8211; Supplemental material for Intramedullary Screw Fixation of Proximal Phalangeal Fractures: Short- to Medium-term Outcomes</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sj-docx-1-han-10.1177_15589447241235339.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><p>Supplemental material, sj-docx-1-han-10.1177_15589447241235339 for Intramedullary Screw Fixation of Proximal Phalangeal Fractures: Short- to Medium-term Outcomes by Hagen Abbot, Adam R. George, Luke McCarron, David J. Graham and Brahman Sivakumar in HAND</p></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="suppl2-15589447241235339" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>sj-docx-2-han-10.1177_15589447241235339 &#8211; Supplemental material for Intramedullary Screw Fixation of Proximal Phalangeal Fractures: Short- to Medium-term Outcomes</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sj-docx-2-han-10.1177_15589447241235339.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><p>Supplemental material, sj-docx-2-han-10.1177_15589447241235339 for Intramedullary Screw Fixation of Proximal Phalangeal Fractures: Short- to Medium-term Outcomes by Hagen Abbot, Adam R. George, Luke McCarron, David J. Graham and Brahman Sivakumar in HAND</p></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="supplementary-material"><p>Supplemental material is available in the online version of the article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethical Approval:</bold> This study was approved by our institutional review board.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Statement of Human and Animal Rights:</bold> All procedures followed were in accordance with the ethical standards of the responsible committee on human experimentation (institutional and national) and with the Helsinki Declaration of 1975, as revised in 2008 (5).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Statement of Informed Consent:</bold> Informed consent was obtained from all patients for being included in the study.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>ORCID iDs:</bold> Hagen Abbot <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="10.1177_15589447241235339-img1.jpg"/>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0009-0004-3714-518X" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0009-0004-3714-518X</ext-link></p><p>Adam R. George <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="10.1177_15589447241235339-img1.jpg"/>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6496-8596" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6496-8596</ext-link></p><p>David J. Graham <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="10.1177_15589447241235339-img1.jpg"/>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3421-822X" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3421-822X</ext-link></p><p>Brahman Sivakumar <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="10.1177_15589447241235339-img1.jpg"/>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0890-2132" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0890-2132</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-15589447241235339"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sivakumar</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>VVG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Symes</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Temporal trends in the management of metacarpal and phalangeal fractures in the 21st century: an analysis of Australian population-based data</article-title>. <source>ANZ J Surg</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2655</fpage>-<lpage>2660</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ans.17818.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35785509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-15589447241235339"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McDaniel</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehman</surname><given-names>UH.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Phalanx Fractures of the Hand</source>. <publisher-loc>Treasure Island, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>StatPearls Publishing</publisher-name>; <year>2023</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32491557</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-15589447241235339"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feehan</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheps</surname><given-names>SB.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidence and demographics of hand fractures in British Columbia, Canada: a population-based study</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. 2006;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1068</fpage>-<lpage>1074</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhsa.2006.06.006.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16945705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-15589447241235339"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamath</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harshvardhan Naik</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Current concepts in managing fractures of metacarpal and phalanges</article-title>. <source>Indian J Plast Surg</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>203</fpage>-<lpage>211</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0970-0358.85341.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22022030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3193632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-15589447241235339"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meulendijks</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Veeramani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Epidemiology and fracture patterns of traumatic phalangeal fractures</article-title>. <source>Plast Reconstr Surg Glob Open</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):e4455. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/gox.0000000000004455.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9351885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35936823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-15589447241235339"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sivakumar</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaotuua</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCarron</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Cost analysis of intramedullary screw versus plate osteosynthesis for phalangeal and metacarpal fractures: an observational study</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Asian Pac Vol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>369</fpage>-<lpage>376</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1142/s242483552350039x.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37173145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-15589447241235339"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaston</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chadderdon</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phalangeal fractures: displaced/nondisplaced</article-title>. <source>Hand Clin</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>395</fpage>-<lpage>401</lpage>, x. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.hcl.2012.05.032.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22883890</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-15589447241235339"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lustenberger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Epidemiology and treatment of phalangeal fractures: conservative treatment is the predominant therapeutic concept</article-title>. <source>Eur J Trauma Emerg Surg</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>567</fpage>-<lpage>571</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00068-020-01397-y.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32451567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8825641</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-15589447241235339"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sivakumar</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Range of motion following extensor tendon splitting vs. tendon sparing approaches for plate osteosynthesis of proximal phalangeal fractures&#8211;a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Asian Pac Vol</source>. <volume>2020</volume>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>462</fpage>-<lpage>468</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1142/s2424835520500514.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33115365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-15589447241235339"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sivakumar</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>VVG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Intramedullary compression screw fixation of proximal phalangeal fractures: a systematic literature review</article-title>. <source>Hand</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>595</fpage>-<lpage>601</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1558944720928503.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32988227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9274898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-15589447241235339"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sivakumar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>DJ.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reverse instrumentation for headless compression screw fixation of basal proximal phalangeal fractures</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):627.e1-627.e5. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhsa.2022.12.012.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36828763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-15589447241235339"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Topoozian</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <part-title>Range of motion</part-title>. In: <source>Clinical Assessment Recommendations</source>. <edition>2nd ed.</edition><publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Society of Hand Therapists</publisher-name>; <volume>1992</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-15589447241235339"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>VVG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sivakumar</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Basic statistics for surgeons</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Asian Pac Vol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>421</fpage>-<lpage>429</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1142/s2424835522300043.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35808879</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-15589447241235339"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ada</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crosbie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Time to commencement of active exercise predicts total active range of motion 6 weeks after proximal phalanx fracture fixation: a retrospective review</article-title>. <source>Hand Therapy</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>73</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1758998316679386.</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-15589447241235339"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ip</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>SP.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A prospective study of 924 digital fractures of the hand</article-title>. <source>Injury</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>279</fpage>-<lpage>285</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0020-1383(95)00222-7.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8762790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-15589447241235339"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fyfe</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mechanical stability of internal fixation of fractured phalanges</article-title>. <source>Hand</source>. <year>1979</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>50</fpage>-<lpage>54</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0072-968x(79)80009-1.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">488778</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-15589447241235339"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reformat</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nores</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Outcome analysis of metacarpal and phalangeal fixation techniques at Bellevue Hospital</article-title>. <source>Ann Plast Surg</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>407</fpage>-<lpage>410</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/sap.0000000000001581.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30067527</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-15589447241235339"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeland</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jabaley</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Open hand fractures: an analysis of the recovery of active motion and of complications</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>387</fpage>-<lpage>394</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0363-5023(93)90080-m.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8515004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-15589447241235339"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pun</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>So</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Unstable phalangeal fractures: treatment by A.O. screw and plate fixation</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>113</fpage>-<lpage>117</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0363-5023(10)80023-1.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1995665</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-15589447241235339"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheah</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hand fractures: indications, the tried and true and new innovations</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>712</fpage>-<lpage>722</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhsa.2016.03.007.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27113910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-15589447241235339"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giesen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gazzola</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poggetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Intramedullary headless screw fixation for fractures of the proximal and middle phalanges in the digits of the hand: a review of 31 consecutive fractures</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Eur Vol</source>. <volume>2016</volume>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>688</fpage>-<lpage>694</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1753193416641330.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27056277</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-15589447241235339"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibanez</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salviani</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Experimental trial on surgical treatment for transverse fractures of the proximal phalanx: technique using intramedullary conical compression screw versus lateral compression plate</article-title>. <source>Rev Bras Ortop</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>509</fpage>-<lpage>514</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rboe.2014.12.009.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26535195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4610986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-15589447241235339"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera Vegas</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Estefan&#237;a D&#237;ez</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez N&#250;nez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Use of intramedullary cannulated headless screws in the treatment of hand fractures&#8211;an anatomical study on long fingers</article-title>. <source>Rev Iberoam Cir Mano</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>094</fpage>-<lpage>103</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0037-1608789.</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-15589447241235339"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>del Pi&#241;al</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moraleda</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>R&#250;as</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Minimally invasive fixation of fractures of the phalanges and metacarpals with intramedullary cannulated headless compression screws</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>692</fpage>-<lpage>700</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhsa.2014.11.023.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25661294</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-15589447241235339"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borbas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poggetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Treatment of proximal phalangeal fractures with an antegrade intramedullary screw: a cadaver study</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Eur Vol</source>. <volume>2016</volume>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>683</fpage>-<lpage>687</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1753193416641319.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27056278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-15589447241235339"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Commentary on &#8220;Intramedullary headless screw fixation for fractures of the proximal and middle phalanges in the digits of the hand: a review of 31 consecutive fractures&#8221; and &#8220;Treatment of proximal phalangeal fractures with an antegrade intramedullary screw: a cadaver study.&#8221;</article-title><source>J Hand Surg Eur Vol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>695</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1753193416654074.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27539831</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-15589447241235339"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aita</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mos</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Paula Cardoso Marques Leite</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Minimally invasive surgical treatment for unstable fractures of the proximal phalanx: intramedullary screw</article-title>. <source>Rev Bras Ortop</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>16</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rboe.2015.12.005.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26962488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4767824</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-15589447241235339"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Triwidodo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Priambodo</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gani</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Closed-reduction intramedullary screw in fractures of the proximal phalanges of the digits of the hand: a series of three cases</article-title> [published online ahead of print December 13, 2021]. <source>Rev Bras Ortop</source>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0041-1739405.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11254437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39027185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-15589447241235339"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silins</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turkmen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>V&#246;gelin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Comparing treatment of proximal phalangeal fractures with intramedullary screws versus plating</article-title>. <source>Arch Orthop Trauma Surg</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>143</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1699</fpage>-<lpage>1706</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00402-022-04516-z.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35994095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9957854</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-15589447241235339"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>von Kieseritzky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordstr&#246;m</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Reoperations and postoperative complications after osteosynthesis of phalangeal fractures: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>J Plast Surg Hand Surg</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>458</fpage>-<lpage>462</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/2000656x.2017.1313261.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28460605</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-15589447241235339"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Young-Sing</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sierakowski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cost comparison of Kirschner wire versus intramedullary screw fixation of metacarpal and phalangeal fractures</article-title>. <source>Hand (N Y)</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>456</fpage>-<lpage>462</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/15589447211030690.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34308715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10152536</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-15589447241235339"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sivakumar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Practice variation in proximal phalangeal fracture management</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Asian Pac Vol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>192</fpage>-<lpage>196</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1142/s2424835523500200.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37120301</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-15589447241235339"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kachooei</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moradi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The influence of dominant limb involvement on DASH and QuickDASH</article-title>. <source>Hand (N Y)</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>512</fpage>-<lpage>515</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11552-014-9734-7.</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26330787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4551649</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>