<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Equity Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Equity Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">113</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">eqhealthj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal for Equity in Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1475-9276</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10696685</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10696685.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10696685</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10696685</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38049838</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12939-023-02050-x</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2050</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Emergency department care experiences among people who use substances: a qualitative study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajab</surname><given-names initials="D">Dana</given-names></name><address><email>d.rajab99@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujioka</surname><given-names initials="JK">Jamie K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names initials="M">Melanie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names initials="SA">Susan A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>MacKenzie</surname><given-names initials="M">Meredith</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Purkey</surname><given-names initials="E">Eva</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02y72wh86</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410356.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8331</institution-id><institution>Department of Medicine, </institution><institution>Queen&#8217;s University, </institution></institution-wrap>Kingston, ON Canada </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02y72wh86</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410356.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8331</institution-id><institution>Department of Emergency Medicine, </institution><institution>Queen&#8217;s University, </institution></institution-wrap>Kingston, ON Canada </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02y72wh86</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410356.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8331</institution-id><institution>Department of Family Medicine, </institution><institution>Queen&#8217;s University, </institution></institution-wrap>Kingston, ON Canada </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02y72wh86</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410356.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8331</institution-id><institution>Department of Public Health Sciences, </institution><institution>Queen&#8217;s University, </institution></institution-wrap>Kingston, ON Canada </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Street Health Centre, Kingston Community Health Centres, Kingston, ON Canada </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>22</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">425145</issue-id><elocation-id>248</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>04</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>06</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-01-28 17:25:10.717"><day>28</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12939_2023_Article_2050.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">People who use substances (PWUS) encounter significant barriers to accessing care for their complex health needs. As a result, emergency departments (EDs) often become the first point of healthcare access for many PWUS and are a crucial setting for the study of health inequities. This study aimed to understand the ED healthcare experiences of PWUS with the intent of informing ways of improving the delivery of equitable care.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">This qualitative study was part of a larger cross-sectional, mixed-methods study that examined ED experiences among diverse underserved and equity-deserving groups (EDGs) within Kingston, Ontario, Canada. Participants shared and self-interpreted a story about a memorable ED or UCC visit within the preceding 24 months. Data from participants who self-identified as having substance use experiences was analyzed through inductive thematic analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Of the 1973 unique participants who completed the survey, 246 participants self-identified as PWUS and were included in the analysis. Most participants were &lt;&#8201;45 years of age (61%), male (53%), and white/European (57%). 45% identified as a person with a disability and 39% frequently struggled to make ends meet. Themes were determined at the patient, provider, and system levels. Patient: <italic toggle="yes">history of substance use</italic> and experience of <italic toggle="yes">intersectionality</italic> negatively influenced participants&#8217; anticipation and perception of care. Provider: negative experiences were linked to <italic toggle="yes">assumption making</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">feelings of stigma and discrimination</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">negative perceptions of provider care</italic>. Whereas positive experiences were linked to <italic toggle="yes">positive perceptions of provider care</italic>. System: <italic toggle="yes">timeliness of care</italic> and the perception of <italic toggle="yes">inadequate mental health resources</italic> negatively impacted participants&#8217; care experience. Overall, these themes shaped participants&#8217; trust of ED staff, their desire to seek care, and their perception of the care quality received.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">PWUS face significant challenges when seeking care in the ED. Given that EDs are a main site of healthcare utilization, there is an urgent need to better support staff in the ED to improve care experiences among PWUS. Based on the findings, three recommendations are proposed: (1) Integration of an equity-oriented approach into the ED, (2) Widespread training on substance use, and (3) Investment in expert resources and services to support PWUS.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>People who use substances (PWUS)</kwd><kwd>Substance use</kwd><kwd>Addictions</kwd><kwd>Emergency department (ED)</kwd><kwd>Equity-deserving group (EDG)</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Queen&#8217;s Catalyst Fund</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Queen&#8217;s CTAQ Endowment Fund</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Queen&#8217;s University Fund for Scholarly Research and Creative Work and Professional Development</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2023</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par6">People who use substances (PWUS) are an equity-deserving group (EDG) that represent a significant proportion of emergency department (ED) visits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. In North America, PWUS account for approximately 1 in 11 ED encounters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The COVID-19 pandemic has further exacerbated this prevalence with over 80,000 hospitalizations attributed to substance use in 2020, an increase of 4000 from 2019 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. PWUS are also at a higher risk of experiencing other complex social challenges including vulnerable housing and mental health challenges [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">The ED is a critical point of contact in the healthcare system for PWUS. PWUS often access the ED for health reasons other than substance use including acute and chronic illness and injuries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Unfortunately, there is evidence that when seeking care in the ED, PWUS still view the hospital as a &#8220;risk environment&#8221; or &#8220;last resort&#8221;, reserved for emergencies or acute situations due to their desire to avoid negative encounters with the healthcare system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">Qualitative studies have explored the healthcare experiences of PWUS from both a health care provider (HCP) and patient perspective, although the latter is limited. From a HCP perspective, studies noted overlapping positive and negative experiences when giving care. On one hand, some providers felt they employed empathetic care and understood the nuances involved in treating PWUS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. On the other hand, many felt ill-equipped and uncertain about how to best serve PWUS, which were noted to contribute to patient experiences of stigma and inaccessibility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. These findings highlight the importance of better understanding how care is provided to PWUS and the meaning of &#8220;appropriate and equitable care&#8221; for this patient population. From a patient perspective, care experiences of PWUS have been explored in various healthcare settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] however, very little is known about the ED context [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. In non-ED healthcare settings, PWUS attributed their negative care experiences to accessibility barriers, discrimination and stigmatization, interpersonal violence and aggression, poor communication, inadequate pain management, and lack of patient centered supports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. The limited research describing ED care of PWUS noted negative experiences including breaches of trust, addictions related stigma, unsympathetic care, and hesitancy to seek future ED care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Although the care experience of PWUS seems to be influenced by both the healthcare system and HCPs, their perception of the patient-provider relationship appeared to be a very prominent aspect of how PWUS interpreted their care experience.</p><p id="Par9">The ED is a critical setting for the study of health inequities faced by PWUS because of the role it plays as the first point of healthcare access for many PWUS. Several studies established useful frameworks that offer guidance for EDs in addressing health inequities directly in the ED environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Such examples are the Equity Oriented Healthcare (EOHC) and Trauma and Violence Informed Care (TVIC) frameworks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. To best apply these frameworks however, it is first and foremost important to learn about the inequities experienced by this population. This study aimed to understand the care experiences of PWUS, described in their own voices, with the goal of moving towards improving their care experiences in the ED.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design</title><p id="Par10">This qualitative study is part of a larger participatory, mixed-methods, cross-sectional study that examined ED care experiences among diverse EDGs in Kingston, Ontario, Canada. This study used a &#8216;sensemaking&#8217; methodology with Spryng.io software. Spryng.io is a digital narrative capture tool that collects typed or audio-recorded micronarratives via handheld tablets. Sensemaking is a process by which a large number of participants self-interpret their micronarratives to help generate meaning from their own and their community&#8217;s experience [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study setting and participants</title><p id="Par11">Participants were recruited via convenience sampling at a single urban ED and a single urban Urgent Care Centre (UCC) in the Kingston Health Sciences Centre (KHSC), as well as through community organizations. KHSC is a large acute and specialty care referral centre that serves a catchment of 500,000 people from surrounding urban and rural communities within southeastern Ontario, Canada. The ED and UCC at KHSC have annual patient volumes of 57,648 and 37,708, respectively.</p><p id="Par12">Between June to August 2021, trained research assistants (RAs) invited patients or individuals accompanying patients presenting to the ED or UCC to participate in the study. Study inclusion criteria included any medically stable patient, aged 16 and older, with adequate English fluency registering in the ED or UCC during study hours, from 9am to 9pm Monday to Friday. Patients who were under the age of 16, were not medically stable, were aggressive towards staff or who did not have the capacity to provide informed consent were not approached to participate. To capture the experiences of those who were not actively seeking care in the ED or UCC during the study period, RAs also recruited eligible participants at community partner organizations such as the Kingston Street Health Centre (a community health centre with a focus on providing substance use and addiction services), Home Based Housing (local shelter services), St. Vincent de Paul (an organization providing food and material support for low-income people), the Kingston Youth Shelter, and the Integrated Care Hub (a location providing low barrier shelter and substance use services for people actively using substances).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Data collection</title><p id="Par13">Participants were prompted to share and self-interpret a micronarrative about their most memorable previous ED or UCC visit within the preceding 24 months. Participants responded to one of the following open-ended prompting questions: (1) <italic toggle="yes">Share an example of how visiting the emergency room helped or harmed you or someone you were at the hospital with?</italic> (2) <italic toggle="yes">Tell a story about the best or worst experience you or someone you were with had in the emergency room?</italic> or (3) <italic toggle="yes">Give an example of an experience that went very well or very badly for you or someone you were with at the emergency room</italic>. Multiple-choice questions at the end of the survey collected demographic information, allowing patients to self-identify as a member of up to three EDGs, and asked questions that contextualized the shared story (e.g., how often do the events in the story happen, who was the story about, was the story related to substance use, etc.). Each participant was assigned a unique identifier to prevent them from participating more than once.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par14">For the purpose of this analysis, micronarrative data from participants who self-identified as having substance use experiences were reviewed, analyzed, and coded using inductive thematic analysis by two independent researchers (DR and JK) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Inductive thematic analysis is a phenomenological approach wherein emergent themes or patterns are generated from the raw data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. NVIVO 12 software was used to establish thematic nodes summarizing ED care experiences which were then collated into higher order subthemes and themes individually by each researcher. Coding, subthemes and themes were then compared, discussed and reviewed. Any conflicting views were resolved by the lead investigator (EP). Following analysis, identified themes and supporting quotes from participants were presented in a focus group format to service providers from community organizations and PWUS. This form of triangulation enhanced study credibility by eliciting feedback about the themes generated from PWUS and service providers caring for PWUS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Ethical considerations</title><p id="Par15">This study was designed in collaboration with members of EDGs and community-based organizations that serve PWUS. Informed consent was recorded digitally from participants on the tablet prior to data collection. No identifying information was collected to maintain participant anonymity. Participants were offered a $5 coffee gift card as a token of appreciation for their time. The study protocol was approved by the Queen&#8217;s University Health Sciences and Affiliated Teaching Hospitals Research Ethics Board (#6,029,400).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Study participants</title><p id="Par16">Of the 1973 unique participants who completed the survey, a total of 246 participants self-identified as PWUS and were included in the study. Their micronarratives were largely collected from local sites including the ED (33%), UCC (17%), and community sites (57%). Most participants were &lt;&#8201;45 years of age (61%), male (53%), and white/European (57%). Further, 45% of participants identified as a person with a disability and 39% frequently struggled to make ends meet.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>ED visit characteristics</title><p id="Par17">For a detailed description of the ED visit characteristics of the study participants, refer to Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> .</p><p id="Par18">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Participant characteristics among those who identify as PWUS compared with those who do not identify as part of an equity-deserving group.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Identifies as a Person Who Uses Substances (PWUS)<break/>(% of N&#8201;=&#8201;246)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Does Not Identify as Equity-Deserving<break/>(% of N&#8201;=&#8201;949)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total Participants<break/>(% of N&#8201;=&#8201;1195)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P-value*</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Gender Identity</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0141</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108 (44%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">517 (54%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">625 (52%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">131 (53%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">411 (43%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">542 (45%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Non-binary</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Missing data</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Age</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;&lt; 18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93 (10%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99 (8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;18&#8211;25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (13%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93 (10%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">124 (10%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;26&#8211;45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92 (37%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">167 (18%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">259 (22%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;46&#8211;65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (20%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">166 (17%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">215 (18%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;&gt; 65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">153 (16%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161 (13%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Missing data</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60 (24%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">277 (29%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">337 (28%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">If the patient is a person with a disability, which relates most to the story (type of disability)?</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Hearing loss/deafness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Low vision/blindness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Intellectual Disability</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Physical Disability</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (10%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 (3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Mental Health Disability</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67 (27%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81 (7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Patient is not a person with a disability</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63 (26%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">571 (60%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">634 (53%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Missing data</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73 (30%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">323 (34%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">396 (33%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">What is patient&#8217;s sexual orientation?</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Asexual</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Bisexual</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36 (15%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63 (5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Gay/Lesbian</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Pansexual</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Straight</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">184 (75%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">830 (87%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1014 (85%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Questioning/unsure</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Sexual orientation not on this list</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Missing data</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65 (7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78 (7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Gender diverse</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">223 (91%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">892 (94%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1115 (93%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Missing data</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12 (5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53 (6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65 (5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Frequency With Which Patient Struggles to Make Ends Meet</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Never</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 (16%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">524 (55%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">564 (47%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Rarely</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (10%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">155 (16%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">179 (15%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Sometimes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48 (20%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">131 (14%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">179 (15%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Often</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32 (13%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66 (6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;All the time</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95 (39%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32 (3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">127 (11%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Missing data</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73 (8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80 (7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Where did the shared story take place?</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Emergency Department</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">186 (76%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">545 (57%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">731 (61%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Urgent Care Centre</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60 (24%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">404 (43%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">464 (39%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Was the story a first-hand or second-hand experience?</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;First-hand personal experience</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">222 (90%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">771 (81%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">993 (83%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Second-hand experience</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">171 (18%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">191 (16%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Other/Missing data</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (1%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">How long ago was the shared ED visit?</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8845</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;0&#8211;6 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94 (38%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">316 (33%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">410 (34%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;7&#8211;12 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (11%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104 (11%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">132 (11%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;13&#8211;18 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77 (8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94 (8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;19&#8211;24 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33 (13%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">123 (13%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">156 (13%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;More than 24 months</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53 (4%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Not sure/Missing data</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63 (26%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">287 (30%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">350 (29%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">How often do you think this situation occurs?</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0006</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;It happens all the time</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100 (41%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">236 (25%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">336 (28%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;It is somewhat typical</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63 (26%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">267 (28%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">330 (28%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;It happens from time to time</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 (14%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">159 (17%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">194 (16%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;It is very rare</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (7%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91 (10%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108 (9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Missing Data</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31 (13%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">196 (21%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">227 (19%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">How did your personal situation, identity, and culture impact the care experience?</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;In a very bad way</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56 (23%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60 (5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;In a bad way</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41 (17%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (2%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59 (5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;It did not impact care</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108 (44%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">715 (75%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">823 (69%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;In a good way</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (6%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 (5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64 (5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;In a very good way</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36 (3%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Missing data</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">133 (14%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">153 (13%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Feelings About the ED Experience</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Positive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75 (30%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">550 (58%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">625 (52%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Negative</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">126 (51%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">242 (26%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">368 (31%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Mixed positive / negative</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32 (13%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79 (8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">111 (9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Missing data</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (5%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78 (8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91 (8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Shared Experience About Lack of Respect and/or Judgement</italic>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">123 (50%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">787 (83%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">910 (76%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98 (40%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85(9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">183 (15%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8195;Missing data</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (10%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77 (8%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102 (9%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Number of EDG groups indicated</italic>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">**Substance use, vulnerably housed, Indigenous, 2SLGBTQ+, ethnic minority, experiencing sexual assault/violence, mental health, disabilities</italic>
</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">949 (100%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">949 (49%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38 (15%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">503 (26%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58 (24%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">223 (11%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150 (61%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">268 (14%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Chi-squared tests were used and did not include missing data / &#8220;not sure/prefer not to say&#8221;</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Thematic analysis</title><p id="Par19">Emerging themes were determined at the patient, provider, and health system levels. Patient-level themes consisted of <italic toggle="yes">history of substance use</italic> and the experience of <italic toggle="yes">intersectionality</italic>. Provider-level considerations were prominent with themes including <italic toggle="yes">assumptions</italic>, feelings of <italic toggle="yes">stigma and discrimination</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">perceptions of provider care</italic>. System-level considerations predominantly focused on themes including <italic toggle="yes">timeliness of care</italic> and the perception of <italic toggle="yes">inadequate mental health resources.</italic> Although these themes were presented distinctly, they often overlapped to influence participants&#8217; ED experiences. Each emerging theme was presented to a focus group comprised of PWUS and service providers from community organizations as a method of triangulation based on their experiences. None of our generated themes were modified following these focus groups.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Patient-level considerations</title><sec id="Sec13"><title>History of substance use</title><p id="Par20">Several participants were aware of being labeled as &#8220;substance users&#8221; in their medical files whether they actively used substances at the time of the visit, and noted the impact this had on their care, and their anticipation of care before even entering the ED. They described feelings of frustration, shame, anxiety, and nervousness about how they would be treated based on previous experiences. As one woman shared: <italic toggle="yes">&#8220;They pull up your form and see you&#8217;re an ex-addict so you tend to be treated with judgment&#8221; (Female, 46-65yrs).</italic> This finding extended to participants who no longer used substances but still faced feelings of worry solely for having a documented history of substance use.</p><p id="Par21">
<italic toggle="yes">&#8220;They just assumed that she was there for pain medication as she is marked as an addict when she has had sobriety for many years&#8230; Her experience was horrible. And it seems that every time she needs to go to the hospital, she is treated like that because of her past&#8221; (Male, 26-45yrs).</italic>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Intersectionality</title><p id="Par22">Alongside their experience with substance use, some participants that identified with other EDGs felt the ED did not adequately meet the needs of their intersectional identities. This was articulated prominently when participants concurrently experienced substance use, housing, and/or mental health challenges.</p><p id="Par23">One vulnerably housed man shared the following after being treated for an overdose:</p><p id="Par24">
<italic toggle="yes">&#8220;After I was sick, um, they kind of just kicked me out right away. They didn&#8217;t really give me a chance to recover. So, then I was homeless at the time. So I was forced to be on the street, and I was sick, and I had nowhere to go&#8221; (Male, 18-25yrs).</italic>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Provider-level considerations</title><sec id="Sec16"><title>Assumptions</title><p id="Par25">ED staff were felt to make assumptions about participants&#8217; substance use status, drug seeking intentions, legitimacy of their health presentation, and method of drug use. They felt that this led to staff focusing on concerns that did not align with patient expectations and was perceived as delayed/and or inadequate care. Downstream effects of this were negative impacts on the patient-provider relationship and fostering feelings of stigma and discrimination.</p><p id="Par26">
<italic toggle="yes">&#8220;I have to say from that experience of being with them realizing that I had a legitimate problem, and I was in actual pain that I was drug-seeking for a reason because I was losing my mind, with the pain&#8230; I am on methadone, low dose. Um, but when they see methadone they judge you. It is always you abuse drugs, that you use needles. And that is not always the case. I use methadone now because I have peripheral neuropathy from all of the chemo I took.&#8221; (Male,45-54yrs).</italic>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Stigma and discrimination</title><p id="Par27">Stories of participants facing feelings of stigma and discrimination were prominently expressed. They shared the perception that once staff knew or suspected substance use their attitudes and treatment of participants quickly changed.</p><p id="Par28">
<italic toggle="yes">&#8220;The last time I went to [hospital] it was because I had a drug problem. And I found that the staff treatment was once they found out that I was on drugs they treated me like garbage. And I wish that would change.&#8221; (Female, 26-45yrs).</italic>
</p><p id="Par29">Negative treatment towards participants included experiences of rough care, negative comments, and care that was felt to lack respect and empathy. One woman shared her story of staff mistreatment of her daughter when she visited the ED with an abscess:</p><p id="Par30">
<italic toggle="yes">&#8220;They weren&#8217;t very polite either to her or to me. And I told them that you know, she may be a drug addict to them, but she is my daughter. And she needs to be treated with respect. And the doctor came in and looked at her abscess and said well you know we are going to have to lance it. And my daughter asked if he would freeze it first. And he said well what the hell is the difference. You know a poke or a cut. And as he said that he just took the scalpel and he cut her arm open. And of course, my daughter is crying because it hurt. And, um, he was being very rough with her.&#8221; (Female, 26-45yrs).</italic>
</p><p id="Par31">The feeling of a lack of non-judgmental care led to participants feeling uncomfortable disclosing their use of substances and in some cases, choosing to terminate the care visit prematurely.</p><p id="Par32">
<italic toggle="yes">&#8220;I went to [hospital] because I was having a minor heart attack as I thought. Um, I was sitting in the waiting room and was told that if I was not on methadone I would not be there. That I was just a junkie and that didn&#8217;t deserve to have healthcare. I went into the room, and it was the same thing, but I had a towel thrown at me and I was told that I was not worth the bed that I was in. And I felt like crap, and so I went home, and my doctor told me I was going to have a heart attack.&#8221; (Female, 26-45yrs).</italic>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Perceptions of provider care</title><p id="Par33">Participants shared both positive and negative experiences pertaining to how they felt that ED staff cared for them. Positive perspectives were related to ED staff being welcoming and professional, providing comfort and emotional safety, effectively communicating, being efficient in their care, and providing resources.</p><p id="Par34">
<italic toggle="yes">&#8220;So, my last experience I had at [hospital] I brought somebody in for alcohol withdrawal. And in doing so they triaged her and brought her right into a bed. They gave her fluids immediately. And the attending physician and the nurses were very kind. They spent lots of time with her trying to find out if there was some way to help and get a bed at detox. They kept her there as long as they could until she was able to walk herself. They wanted to keep her there for longer so that she could get more stable. Um, and further away from alcohol their idea was obviously that would be better. The attending physician brought me aside and asked me if it was safe for her to go home. They were kind, they were thorough, um, there was no sense of judgement, no sense of rush.&#8221; (Male, 55-65yrs).</italic>
</p><p id="Par35">Negative perspectives were related to the perception of rude staff, perceived patient neglect, feelings of inadequate supportive care, and lack of patient-centered care. Lack of patient-centered care was characterized by feelings of not being listened to, not receiving referrals personalized to their needs, and a lack of continuity of care. Patient neglect was often identified in stories of overdose, however, not always.</p><p id="Par36"><italic toggle="yes">&#8220;My mother had stage 4 lung cancer. I had to bring her to emerg at [hospital]. She was a drug user and was treated as so. She was skipped, no one wanted to give her pain meds because she was an addict. We also did have some very nice nurses and doctors but certainly mistreated lots.&#8221; (Female, 24-34yrs)</italic>.</p><p id="Par37">
<italic toggle="yes">My friend brought me in after I fainted and he didn&#8217;t know why. Everyone immediately rushed to me to get looked at, and after learning it was an overdose they didn&#8217;t keep it as a priority. They put me in the waiting room while I was overdosing and didn&#8217;t even check on me. I needed serious medical attention and was pushed aside. I couldn&#8217;t keep my eyes open and kept getting sick, couldn&#8217;t breathe and they just left me there. (Female,18-25yrs)</italic>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>System-level considerations</title><sec id="Sec20"><title>Timeliness of Care</title><p id="Par38">Participants discussed experiences of both timely and untimely care. Time-sensitive care was described when the ED urgently addressed health concerns in what participants felt to be a <italic toggle="yes">&#8220;decent amount of time&#8221;</italic> and quickly directed participants to their next steps.</p><p id="Par39">
<italic toggle="yes">&#8220;I accompanied my brother to the [hospital]. He was needing a prescription for Valium as he was going to Detox. While in the waiting area he had a seizure and fell to the floor. I called for help and there was an immediate response from hospital personnel who got him stabilized and onto a gurney. They were very responsive in the care and reassuring to me. once settled, He was given 5&#160;mg of Valium&#8221; (Female, 55-64yrs).</italic>
</p><p id="Par40">On the other hand, a majority of participants articulated untimely care associated with long wait times that they perceived to be linked to their identity as a PWUS. The ED environment was described as understaffed and/or overworked leading to many participants waiting with challenging health circumstances. Long-wait times were most often discussed in the context of triage and described as <italic toggle="yes">&#8220;excessive&#8221;</italic> resulting in participants feeling frustrated and <italic toggle="yes">&#8220;passed over&#8221;</italic> with some making the decision to leave the ED without receiving care.</p><p id="Par41">
<italic toggle="yes">&#8220;It would seem that they need more staff on Mondays&#8230;because patients were trying to leave because they thought they were in the way of the health team. And that shouldn&#8217;t be a thought that they are having if their condition is life-threatening. Um, so yeah, more staff on Mondays. The experience was bad again, not their fault. All of the people who have helped me have been lovely and very, very personable. But the system that they are working in is not there to serve them&#8221; (Female, 16-24yrs).</italic>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Inadequate mental health resources</title><p id="Par42">Participants with both substance use and mental health experiences often spoke about the perception of the lack of available and accessible mental health resources in the ED to meet their specific needs. These experiences covered descriptions of inadequate mental health programs, difficulties connecting with psychiatrists in the ED, and the challenge of choosing whether to discharge patients presenting to the ED with mental health concerns. One man shared:</p><p id="Par43">
<italic toggle="yes">&#8220;I came 2 months ago, over mental health issues. I was seen in reasonable amount of time, although the results were less than satisfying. I was referred to multiple programs, but none of them were actually suited to my needs. Almost as if, they were &#8220;automatic&#8221; referrals and I hadn&#8217;t actually been listened to&#8221; (Male, 25-34yrs).</italic>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec22" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par44">This study sought to elicit the care experiences of PWUS in the ED to better understand their challenges in seeking care, in hopes of informing more inclusive and equitable ways to improve ED experience and access in future. It was found that the care experience of PWUS was influenced by patient, provider, and system level factors. The challenging and unique societal experiences of PWUS were prominent in our study findings, reflecting existing literature. Assumption-making, stigma, and discrimination were prevailing issues found in the ED that contributed to mistrust, perceptions of negative and poor treatment, and ultimately, patients opting to avoid or leave care. These consequences propagated the experience of inequitable and unmet healthcare needs. These findings are in line with other studies which discuss the profound and long-lasting mark left on patients by the enacted and anticipated stigma they face in healthcare settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. A finding that was not prominent in our study but has been described elsewhere is that the type of substance use influences the degree of stigma experienced [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. For instance, people who inject drugs or use methadone face greater levels of stigmatization in comparison to people who use alcohol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. This reinforces the importance of implementing patient-centered care that treats patients based on their unique experiences and destigmatizes all substance use.</p><p id="Par45">PWUS were found to truly remember their interactions with HCPs and staff in the ED. This emphasizes the power healthcare providers hold in bridging the gap between positive and negative ED experiences for the patients they serve. Negative experiences were rooted in the perception that ED staff were not authentically present to care for the patient. This included the absence of patient-centered care, perceived patient neglect, inadequate supportive care, and the perception of rude or stigmatizing staff; all of which have been found by other studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Importantly, however, in our study and elsewhere positive interpersonal experiences arose where PWUS felt welcomed, comforted, and heard, and when they received well communicated, efficient care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. A mixture of positive and negative experiences suggests that healthcare providers may generally hold the intention to maintain and foster positive relationships with their patients but are experiencing obstacles to providing high-quality, patient-centered care to this vulnerable population, leading to negative experiences, and this requires further study.</p><p id="Par46">A potential explanation underlying negative experiences with healthcare staff is the current state of EDs. In many nations including Canada, EDs are operating under considerable pressures and limited capacities. Although the COVID-19 pandemic has undoubtedly exacerbated this issue, this is nevertheless not a new problem [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. In such stressful and time-sensitive environments, healthcare staff are more likely to face personal and emotional stresses, burnout, and exhaustion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. In fact, over 50% of ED physicians reported feelings of distress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. The sequelae of physician distress and a strenuous work environment may lead to patient depersonalization, worsened interpersonal relationships with patients, decreased patient satisfaction, and ultimately reduced quality of care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. PWUS are a group that repeatedly faces great structural challenges in obtaining appropriate care to meet their needs and so rely on EDs for primary care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Consequently, they may present frequently and may be judged as an &#8220;unnecessary ED visit&#8221; in an already overworked and crowded ED environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. This opens the opportunity to intervene at the structural level to support ED staff in providing adequate and compassionate care to equity deserving populations, as well as creating alternate points of access for non-emergent health concerns. Furthermore, the structural stigma experienced in the ED is mirrored by the widespread stigma in society against substance use which reinforces the devaluation and de-prioritization of PWUS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Therefore, interventions are also needed to de-stigmatize perceptions of PWUS. Finally, substance use and mental health services are commonly underfunded and under-resourced which perpetuates the inaccessibility of these health services among PWUS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>].</p><sec id="Sec23"><title>Recommendations</title><p id="Par47">Based on this study&#8217;s findings and feedback from focus group discussions in the community, our proposed recommendations are three-fold:</p><sec id="Sec24"><title>Integration of equity oriented framework approaches</title><p id="Par48">HCPs possess the power to address health inequities directly at the point of care. Established frameworks such as the Equity Oriented Healthcare Framework (EOHC) by Equipping Health Care for Equity (EQUIP) BC offer useful guidance for healthcare providers in the ED and primary care settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. The EOHC framework consists of three key dimensions that must be contextually tailored: (1) Provision of Culturally Safe Care, (2) Trauma and Violence Informed Care (TVIC), and (3) Harm-Reduction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Based upon this framework, the EQUIP intervention was designed with a dual focus on staff education and organizational-level integration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. From the staff level, this includes educational methods, enhancing staff&#8217;s knowledge and capacity to provide EOHC, further training on harm reduction and trauma informed care, and a focus on navigating care for PWUS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. From an organizational level, this includes shifts in funding, structures, practices, and policies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. This intervention has been tested in EDs and primary healthcare settings in Canada and shown improvements in self-reported patient outcomes, and enhanced staff comfort and confidence in providing EOHC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Widespread training specific to substance use</title><p id="Par49">Substance use is a relatively common phenomenon with approximately 21% of Canadians (6&#160;million) experiencing substance misuse or addiction in their lifetime [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Due to this high prevalence, ED health professionals will regularly come into contact with PWUS. Therefore, training specific to understanding and navigating substance use encounters, treatment, management, withdrawal, and specific resources must be implemented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Particular attention must also be placed on decolonizing approaches, intersectionality, and de-stigmatization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. It is vital for training to be delivered widely across all clinical professionals interacting with PWUS, including trainees. Furthermore, it is pertinent to include individuals with lived experiences in developing and delivering training curricula as educators, peer support workers, and training creators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Finally, research suggests that longer consistent training over time is more likely to produce meaningful effects rather than a one-time session [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Investment in expert resources and services to support PWUS</title><p id="Par50">Expert healthcare teams such as addiction consulting services (ACS) are comprised of physicians, nurses, social workers, and peer support workers that can work alongside ED physicians to provide comprehensive substance use related services [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. These include substance use focused history taking, physical examinations, withdrawal management, and initiating pharmacotherapies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. They are also well equipped to ensure the transfer of care to primary and community providers, enhancing the continuity of care within the system for PWUS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Although these services are scarcely available in North America, they have been demonstrated to successfully improve patient care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Strengths and limitations</title><p id="Par51">This study is not without limitations. The main limitation is that our study did not explore the perspective of ED health providers. Additional research should expand on this important perspective and provide comparison to our findings. Moreover, data were collected from a convenience sample of potential participants who sought care during study hours and therefore the sample may not be representative of the Kingston community. Furthermore, it is possible that the patient characteristics and substance use challenges of our study population differ from other locations and may not be generalizable to all EDs. However, our findings are closely aligned with existing literature conducted worldwide. Finally, our study did not stratify experiences based on the type of substance use which makes it more challenging to ascertain the extent of which this may or may not influence their care experiences.</p><p id="Par52">Despite its limitations, this study has many strengths. To begin, this qualitative study incorporated a large sample size of PWUS from a small city with a high prevalence of substance use. Detailed patient characteristics were collected including but not limited to socioeconomic status, mental health status, vulnerable housing status, indigeneity; all of which provided insight into the study population. By using a &#8216;sensemaking&#8217; approach, participants were empowered to share whatever aspect of the ED care was most important to them. By collecting data at community partner organizations, we engaged with those who may no longer be accessing the ED due to prior negative experiences and in doing so, likely reduced selection bias. Key findings were shared with PWUS in a focus group discussion and with service providers who support PWUS to ensure that results were being interpreted appropriately, thus reducing interpretation bias.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec28" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par53">PWUS encounter numerous inequities when seeking ED care at personal, provider, and system-levels. As a result, they receive care that they perceive as inadequate, require frequent ED visits, avoid seeking care, and leave without care. Further studies need to evaluate the clinical, environmental, and structural interventions in the ED and prioritize integrating provider perceptions when tailoring interventions for improvement to advance equity for this patient population.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>List of Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>PWUS</term><def><p id="Par55">People Who Use Substances</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ED</term><def><p id="Par56">Emergency Department</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EDG</term><def><p id="Par57">Equity Deserving Group</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HCP</term><def><p id="Par58">Health Care Provider</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EOHC</term><def><p id="Par59">Equity Oriented Healthcare</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TVIC</term><def><p id="Par60">Trauma and Violence Informed Care</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UCC</term><def><p id="Par61">Urgent Care Centre</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KHSC</term><def><p id="Par62">Kingston Health Sciences Centre</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EQUIP</term><def><p id="Par63">Equipping Health Care for Equity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ACS</term><def><p id="Par64">Addiction Consulting Services</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#8217;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to acknowledge our community partners for their support. We would also like to thank the people with lived experience and the service providers who advised in our focus groups. Lastly, thank you to the participants who agreed to share their deeply personal stories to shape our understanding.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>MW, SAB, and EP conceptualized the study and applied for funding. Analysis and interpretation of the data was completed by DR, JFK, and EP. Drafting the manuscript was completed by DR and JFK. All authors of this manuscript contributed significantly to the work presented and reviewed the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was funded by the Queen&#8217;s Catalyst Fund, Queen&#8217;s CTAQ Endowment Fund and Queen&#8217;s University Fund for Scholarly Research and Creative Work and Professional Development.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar2"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par67">This study, including on-site data collection by RAs, was approved by the Queen&#8217;s University Health Sciences and Affiliated Teaching Hospitals Research Ethics Board (protocol # 6029400). Informed consent was obtained from all participants by asking the participant to tap a box on the tablet. All methods were carried out in accordance with relevant guidelines and regulations.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par68">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par66">The authors declare that they have no competing interests..</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brubacher JR, Mabie A, Ngo M, Abu-Laban RB, Buchanan J, Shenton T, et al. Substance-related problems in patients visiting an urban Canadian emergency department. Cjem. 2008;10(3):198&#8211;204.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/s1481803500010101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19019269</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGregor</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schull</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holroyd</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>People who make frequent emergency department visits based on persistence of frequent use in Ontario and Alberta: a retrospective cohort study</article-title><source>CMAJ Open</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>E220</fpage><lpage>e31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9778/cmajo.20210131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35292480</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8929439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schull</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGregor</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hohl</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterizing people with frequent emergency department visits and substance use: a retrospective cohort study of linked administrative data in Ontario, Alberta, and B.C., Canada</article-title><source>BMC Emerg Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>127</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12873-022-00673-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35836121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9281237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suen</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Makam</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Repplinger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kushel</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>National Prevalence of Alcohol and other Substance Use disorders among Emergency Department visits and hospitalizations: NHAMCS 2014&#8211;2018</article-title><source>J Gen Intern Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>37</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2420</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-021-07069-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34518978</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8436853</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Information CIH. Hospital visits for substance use increased during first months of the pandemic 2021.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grinman</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Redelmeier</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levinson</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolomiczenko</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Drug problems among homeless individuals in Toronto, Canada: prevalence, Drugs of choice, and relation to health status</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>94</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-10-94</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20181248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2841106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dahlberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mental health problems among young people in substance abuse treatment in Sweden</article-title><source>Subst Abuse Treat Prev Policy</source><year>2020</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>43</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13011-020-00282-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32580732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7315521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Substance</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mental Health Services</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><collab>Office of the Surgeon G</collab></person-group><source>Reports of the Surgeon General. Facing addiction in America: the Surgeon General&#8217;s report on Alcohol, Drugs, and Health</source><year>2016</year><publisher-loc>Washington (DC)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>US Department of Health and Human Services</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28252892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drumm</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McBride</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metsch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickerson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The rock always comes first: drug users&#8217; accounts about using formal health care</article-title><source>J Psychoact Drugs</source><year>2003</year><volume>35</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02791072.2003.10400493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14986875</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McNeil</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Small</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hospitals as a &#8216;risk environment&#8217;: an ethno-epidemiological study of voluntary and involuntary discharge from hospital against medical advice among people who inject Drugs</article-title><source>Soc Sci Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2014.01.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24508718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3951660</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bov&#233;</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lisby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norlyk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do the carers care? A phenomenological study of providing care for patients suffering from Alcohol Use Disorders</article-title><source>Nurs Inq</source><year>2020</year><volume>27</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e12322</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nin.12322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31596036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ezell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolinski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Stigmatize the use, not the user? Attitudes on opioid use, drug injection, treatment, and Overdose prevention in rural communities</article-title><source>Soc Sci Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>113470</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2020.113470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33253992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7755701</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stacey</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dohan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Social stigma and the dilemmas of providing care to substance users in a safety-net emergency department</article-title><source>J Health Care Poor Underserved</source><year>2008</year><volume>19</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1336</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1353/hpu.0.0088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19029756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McWilliam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dingwell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dykeman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gahagan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Key challenges in providing services to people who use Drugs: the perspectives of people working in emergency departments and shelters in Atlantic Canada</article-title><source>Drugs (Abingdon Engl)</source><year>2014</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>244</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24954982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3109/09687637.2013.870534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4046876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelleher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cotter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A descriptive study on emergency department doctors&#8217; and nurses&#8217; knowledge and attitudes concerning substance use and substance users</article-title><source>Int Emerg Nurs</source><year>2009</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ienj.2008.08.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19135010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendiola</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galetto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fingerhood</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An exploration of Emergency Physicians&#8217; attitudes toward patients with Substance Use Disorder</article-title><source>J Addict Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ADM.0000000000000377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29351141</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muncan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amabile</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weimer</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguemeni Tiako</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vallabhajosyula</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardiac surgeons&#8217; perspectives and practices regarding people who use Drugs: a scoping review</article-title><source>J Card Surg</source><year>2022</year><volume>37</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>630</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jocs.16201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34989450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Boekel</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brouwers</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Weeghel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garretsen</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stigma among health professionals towards patients with substance use disorders and its consequences for healthcare delivery: systematic review</article-title><source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source><year>2013</year><volume>131</volume><issue>1&#8211;2</issue><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2013.02.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23490450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bov&#233;</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lisby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norlyk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scheduled care-As a way of caring: a phenomenological study of being cared for when suffering from Alcohol Use Disorders</article-title><source>J Clin Nurs</source><year>2019</year><volume>28</volume><issue>7&#8211;8</issue><fpage>1174</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jocn.14715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30428140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neil</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dell</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berenbaum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Aneed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Qualitative investigation of barriers to accessing care by people who inject Drugs in Saskatoon, Canada: perspectives of service providers</article-title><source>Subst Abuse Treat Prev Policy</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>35</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1747-597X-8-35</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24079946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3850796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Markwick</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McNeil</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Small</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring the Public Health Impacts of Private Security Guards on people who use Drugs: a qualitative study</article-title><source>J Urban Health</source><year>2015</year><volume>92</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1117</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11524-015-9992-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26453195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4675737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McNeil</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Small</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advancing patient-centered care for structurally vulnerable drug-using populations: a qualitative study of the perspectives of people who use Drugs regarding the potential integration of harm reduction interventions into hospitals</article-title><source>Addiction</source><year>2016</year><volume>111</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>685</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/add.13214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26498577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4801725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strike</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Leary</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Illicit drug use while admitted to hospital: patient and health care provider perspectives</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2020</year><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e0229713</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0229713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32134973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7058273</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan Carusone</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Leary</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Maybe if I stop the Drugs, then maybe they&#8217;d care?-hospital care experiences of people who use Drugs</article-title><source>Harm Reduct J</source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>16</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12954-019-0285-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30760261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6373073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ouellet</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ezell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosentel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Breaching Trust: a qualitative study of Healthcare experiences of people who use Drugs in a rural setting</article-title><source>Front Sociol</source><year>2020</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>593925</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fsoc.2020.593925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33869521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8022503</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawk</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edelman</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coupet</surname><given-names>E</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toledo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Perspectives about Emergency Department Care encounters among adults with opioid Use Disorder</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2022</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e2144955</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.44955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35076700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8790663</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wise-Harris</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan de Bibiana</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stergiopoulos</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hospital was the only option: experiences of Frequent Emergency Department Users in Mental Health</article-title><source>Adm Policy Ment Health</source><year>2017</year><volume>44</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10488-016-0728-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26961781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varcoe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford-Gilboe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wathen</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>EQUIP Healthcare: an overview of a multi-component intervention to enhance equity-oriented care in primary health care settings</article-title><source>Int J Equity Health</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>152</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12939-015-0271-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26694168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4688920</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Varcoe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bungay</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Byres</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>EQUIP emergency: can interventions to reduce racism, discrimination and stigma in EDs improve outcomes?</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1113</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12913-022-08475-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36050677</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9436447</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Varcoe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bungay</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wathen</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>EQUIP emergency: study protocol for an organizational intervention to promote equity in health care</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>687</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12913-019-4494-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31601199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6785893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three approaches to qualitative content analysis</article-title><source>Qual Health Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>15</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1277</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1049732305276687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16204405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Member checking: can benefits be gained similar to Group Therapy?</article-title><source>Qualitative Rep</source><year>2012</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>510</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The stigmatization of problem drug users: a narrative literature review</article-title><source>Drugs: Educ Prev Policy</source><year>2013</year><volume>20</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>95</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muncan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ezell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ompad</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>They look at us like junkies: influences of drug use stigma on the healthcare engagement of people who inject Drugs in New York City</article-title><source>Harm Reduct J</source><year>2020</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>53</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12954-020-00399-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32736624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7393740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheppard</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anaf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The patient experience in the emergency department: a systematic synthesis of qualitative research</article-title><source>Int Emerg Nurs</source><year>2010</year><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ienj.2009.05.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20382369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mautner</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shea</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frasso</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Generating hypotheses about care needs of high utilizers: lessons from patient interviews</article-title><source>Popul Health Manag</source><year>2013</year><volume>16</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/pop.2013.0033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24070247</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Twenty years of patient satisfaction research applied to the emergency department: a qualitative review</article-title><source>Am J Med Qual</source><year>2010</year><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1062860609352536</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19966114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Wit</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#233;rin-Lajoie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mercuri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Humans not heroes: Canadian emergency physician experiences during the early COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Emerg Med J</source><year>2023</year><volume>40</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/emermed-2022-212466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36253075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Patel RS, Bachu R, Adikey A, Malik M, Shah M. Factors related to Physician Burnout and its consequences: a review. Behav Sci (Basel). 2018;8(11).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/bs8110098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6262585</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30366419</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marco</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feeser</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monti</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vearrier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-traumatic stress and stress disorders during the COVID-19 pandemic: survey of emergency physicians</article-title><source>J Am Coll Emerg Physicians Open</source><year>2020</year><volume>1</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1594</fpage><lpage>601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/emp2.12305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33392568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7771764</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Varcoe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bungay</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wathen</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Through an Equity Lens: Illuminating the relationships among Social inequities, Stigma and discrimination, and patient experiences of Emergency Health Care</article-title><source>Int J Health Serv</source><year>2022</year><volume>52</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/00207314221075515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35098791</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8894974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vigod</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wishart</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waese</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Barriers and facilitators to primary care for people with mental health and/or substance use issues: a qualitative study</article-title><source>BMC Fam Pract</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>135</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12875-015-0353-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26463083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4604001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Hert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bobes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cetkovich-Bakmas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leucht</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ndetei</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Physical Illness in patients with severe mental disorders. II. Barriers to care, monitoring and treatment guidelines, plus recommendations at the system and individual level</article-title><source>World Psychiatry</source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/j.2051-5545.2011.tb00036.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21633691</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3104888</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Livingston J. Structural Stigma in Health-Care Contexts for People with Mental Health and Substance Use Issues: A Literature Review2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford-Gilboe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wathen</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varcoe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herbert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavoie</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>How equity-oriented Health Care affects Health: Key mechanisms and implications for Primary Health Care Practice and Policy</article-title><source>Milbank Q</source><year>2018</year><volume>96</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1468-0009.12349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30350420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6287068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varcoe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford-Gilboe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadine Wathen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smye</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Disruption as opportunity: impacts of an organizational health equity intervention in primary care clinics</article-title><source>Int J Equity Health</source><year>2018</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>154</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12939-018-0820-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30261924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6161402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pearson C, Teresa Janz and Jennifer Ali. Mental and substance use disorders in Canada Health at a Glance Statistics Canada September 2013;82&#8211;624.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawk</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edelman</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coupet</surname><given-names>E</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toledo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Perspectives about Emergency Department Care encounters among adults with opioid Use Disorder</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2022</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e2144955</fpage><lpage>e</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.44955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35076700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8790663</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heim</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohrt</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koschorke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milenova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thornicroft</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reducing mental health-related stigma in primary health care settings in low- and middle-income countries: a systematic review</article-title><source>Epidemiol Psychiatr Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>e3</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S2045796018000458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30176952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6399081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wakeman</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanter</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donelan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Institutional substance use disorder intervention improves General Internist preparedness, attitudes, and clinical practice</article-title><source>J Addict Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>308</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ADM.0000000000000314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28375881</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wakeman</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nolan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inpatient Addiction Consult Service: expertise for hospitalized patients with complex addiction problems</article-title><source>Med Clin North Am</source><year>2018</year><volume>102</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcna.2018.03.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29933817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6750950</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>