<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2786</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">medicine</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MD</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12237303</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12237303.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12237303</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12237303</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40629632</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000043200</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MD-D-25-06630</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>3400</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Research Article</subject><subject>Observational Study</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The association between red blood cell distribution width-to-albumin ratio and chest pain prevalence in US adults: A cross-sectional analysis of NHANES 2005&#8211;2018</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names initials="M">Minmin</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>mmzhummzhu@163.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names initials="D">Dongxiao</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>hdxss88@163.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0000-1260-7289</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname><given-names initials="H">Hao</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="c1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Anesthesiology, Wuxi No. 2 People&#8217;s Hospital, Wuxi, Jiangsu Province, China.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>*</label>Correspondence: Hao Xi, Department of Anesthesiology, Wuxi No. 2 People&#8217;s Hospital, Liangxi District, Wuxi City 214002, Jiangsu Province, China (e-mail: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="18601482516@163.com">18601482516@163.com</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>04</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>04</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>104</volume><issue>27</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">492505</issue-id><elocation-id>e43200</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>04</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>09</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-07-10 09:25:58.490"><day>10</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2025 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CCBY)</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="medi-104-e43200.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="medi-104-e43200.pdf"/><abstract><p>The red blood cell distribution width-to-albumin ratio (RAR), a novel marker reflecting both inflammation and nutritional status, has emerged as a potential clinical biomarker. However, its link to chest pain in general populations remains underexplored. This study is the first to assess the association between RAR and chest pain prevalence using data from the nationally representative National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey cohort. Data from 21,174 adults in the 2005&#8211;2018 National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey were analyzed. Chest pain was assessed via the Rose Angina Questionnaire. RAR was calculated by dividing red cell distribution width by serum albumin. Multivariable logistic regression models incorporating survey weights, restricted cubic spline analyses, and subgroup analyses were used to evaluate the association, adjusting for demographic, socioeconomic, lifestyle, and clinical factors. A nonlinear relationship was found between RAR and chest pain, with an inflection point at RAR&#8197;=&#8197;3.59. Below this point, each unit increase in RAR was associated with a 32% higher likelihood of chest pain (odds ratio&#8197;=&#8197;1.32, 95% confidence interval: 1.17&#8211;1.49, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.0001). Above 3.59, the association weakened. Compared to the lowest quartile (Q1), individuals in the highest RAR quartile (Q4) had a 26% increased prevalence of chest pain (odds ratio&#8197;=&#8197;1.26, 95% confidence interval 1.15&#8211;1.39, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.0001). Subgroup analysis showed stronger associations in smokers (interaction <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;.016), with consistent results across age and racial/ethnic groups. Higher RAR is independently associated with increased chest pain prevalence, especially below 3.59, suggesting its value in risk stratification, particularly among smokers.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>chest pain</kwd><kwd>cross-sectional study</kwd><kwd>NHANES</kwd><kwd>RAR</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="ID0E1TAE145462"><funding-source>Top Talent Support Program for Young and Middle-aged People of Wuxi Health Committee</funding-source><award-id>HB2023025</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Dongxiao Huang</principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Chest pain is a common clinical symptom with a broad differential diagnosis, encompassing cardiovascular, respiratory, gastrointestinal, and musculoskeletal causes.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> Among these, acute coronary syndromes (ACS) are of particular concern due to their high mortality risk.<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> In the United States, chest pain is the second most frequent reason for emergency department visits, leading to millions of hospital admissions each year for diagnostic evaluation.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> Its lifetime prevalence is estimated at 20% to 40%, reflecting a significant burden on both clinical practice and public health systems.<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> Although many cases are attributed to nonserious conditions, a substantial proportion are linked to cardiovascular diseases, particularly coronary artery disease, which pose serious health threats. cardiovascular diseases remains the leading cause of death in the US, affecting more than 18.2 million adults.<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup> Despite improvements in diagnostic tools, risk assessment, and therapeutic approaches, early recognition and prevention of high-risk cases continue to present major clinical challenges.</p><p>Emerging evidence indicates that inflammation plays a pivotal role in the pathogenesis of chest pain, particularly of cardiovascular origin.<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> Systemic inflammatory processes contribute to endothelial dysfunction and destabilization of atherosclerotic plaques, thereby increasing the likelihood of ischemic events.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup> Elevated levels of inflammatory biomarkers such as C-reactive protein and interleukin-6 (IL-6) have been linked to heightened risk of ACS, supporting the association between inflammation and the severity of chest pain.<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup> In parallel, malnutrition &#8211; characterized by low serum albumin or micronutrient deficiencies &#8211; may exacerbate inflammation and oxidative stress, compounding cardiovascular risk.<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> These findings underscore a complex interplay between immune dysregulation, metabolic imbalance, and the clinical manifestation of chest pain, suggesting that targeting inflammatory pathways could enhance diagnostic precision and therapeutic strategies.</p><p>Red blood cell distribution width-to-albumin ratio (RAR) has recently emerged as a promising composite biomarker reflecting systemic inflammation, oxidative stress, and nutritional status.<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup> Red cell distribution width (RDW) is a standard hematological parameter that reflects erythrocyte size variability and has gained recognition not only in diagnosing anemia but also as a prognostic indicator in cardiovascular, cerebrovascular, and metabolic disorders.<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup> Serum albumin is the most abundant circulating protein and serves as an indicator of nutritional and physiological resilience due to its anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, and vascular-protective properties.<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</sup> Combined as RAR, these 2 measures may better capture the cumulative burden of chronic inflammation and metabolic dysfunction than either marker alone.<sup>[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup> Prior studies have shown RAR&#8217;s predictive superiority in various clinical settings, including ACS, heart failure, stroke, and chronic kidney disease, suggesting it reflects systemic vulnerability and biological aging.<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup> However, its association with more prevalent yet clinically significant symptoms such as chest pain has not been thoroughly investigated.</p><p>This study is the first to utilize nationally representative data from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES) to investigate the association between RAR and chest pain prevalence in the general adult population. By examining this novel biomarker within a broad epidemiological context, we aim to address a key knowledge gap and explore the potential of RAR in enhancing symptom-based risk stratification in clinical practice.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>2. Materials and methods</title><sec><title>2.1. Study population</title><p>This cross-sectional analysis was based on data from NHANES, a continuous program conducted by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention to assess the health and nutritional status of the US civilian, noninstitutionalized population. NHANES utilizes a stratified, multistage probability sampling strategy to ensure nationally representative estimates. Data are collected via in-home interviews, standardized physical examinations at mobile examination center, and laboratory assessments.<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup> All NHANES protocols were approved by the National Center for Health Statistics Research Ethics Review Board, and written informed consent was obtained from all participants. Detailed survey procedures are publicly available on the NHANES website (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhanes/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhanes/</ext-link>).</p><p>For this study, we combined data from 7 NHANES cycles (2005&#8211;2018), initially including 65,535 participants. After excluding individuals under 18 years of age (n&#8197;=&#8197;26,340), those lacking chest pain data (n&#8197;=&#8197;14,903), missing RAR values (n&#8197;=&#8197;2418), or incomplete covariate information (n&#8197;=&#8197;700), a total of 21,174 adults with complete data were retained for the final analysis (Fig. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Flow diagram of the inclusion criteria and exclusion criteria. RAR = red blood cell distribution width-to-albumin ratio.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medi-104-e43200-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>Participants with missing information on chest pain, RAR values, or key covariates were excluded from the final analysis. Listwise deletion was applied, and no imputation method was used, given the relatively low proportion of missing data and to maintain analytic transparency.</p><sec><title>2.1.1. Ethical approval declarations</title><p>Ethical approval for the NHANES protocol was obtained from the National Center for Health Statistics&#8217; institutional review board. Written informed consent was acquired from all study participants beforehand. The current analysis utilized de-identified, open-access NHANES data, thereby exempting it from requiring further ethical clearance or consent procedures.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>2.2. Chest pain</title><p>Chest pain was assessed using the standardized Rose Angina Questionnaire, administered by trained personnel through computer-assisted personal interviews (CAPI) conducted in participants&#8217; homes. Participants were classified as having chest pain based on an affirmative response to the question: &#8220;Have you ever had any pain or discomfort in your chest?&#8221; This binary classification (yes/no) was applied in all subsequent statistical analyses.<sup>[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</sup></p></sec><sec><title>2.3. Measurements of RAR</title><p>RAR was calculated by dividing RDW (%) by serum albumin concentration (g/dL). RDW was obtained from peripheral blood samples using the Coulter<sup>&#174;</sup> DxH 800 analyzer, following standardized NHANES laboratory procedures conducted at Mobile Examination Centers. Serum albumin was measured using the bromocresol purple method, with the absorbance of the albumin&#8211;bromocresol purple complex recorded at 600&#8201;nm via spectrophotometry.<sup>[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</sup> Participants were categorized into 4 RAR quartiles based on the population distribution: Q1 (&lt;2.91, reference), Q2 (2.91&#8211;3.13), Q3 (3.13&#8211;3.42), and Q4 (&gt;3.42).</p></sec><sec><title>2.4. Covariates</title><p>A broad range of covariates known to influence both RAR and chest pain were included in the analysis. Demographic variables comprised age (continuous), sex (male/female), and race/ethnicity (Non-Hispanic White, Non-Hispanic Black, Mexican American, Other Hispanic, Other/Multiracial). Socioeconomic factors included education level (&lt;high school, high school/GED, &gt;high school), marital status (married/cohabiting, widowed/divorced/separated, never married), and the family poverty-income ratio.<sup>[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</sup> Behavioral factors included smoking status, classified as nonsmokers (&lt;100 lifetime cigarettes) or smokers (&#8805;100 cigarettes). Anthropometric status was assessed via body mass index (BMI), categorized as normal (&lt;25&#8201;kg/m&#178;), overweight (25&#8211;30&#8201;kg/m&#178;), or obese (&#8805;30&#8201;kg/m&#178;). Clinical comorbidities, including hypertension, diabetes, coronary heart disease, heart failure, angina, myocardial infarction, and stroke, were identified through self-reported physician diagnoses.<sup>[<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</sup></p></sec><sec><title>2.5. Statistical analyses</title><p>All statistical analyses were conducted using R software (version 4.3.0), Zstats v1.0 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.zstats.net" ext-link-type="uri">www.zstats.net</ext-link>), and EmpowerStats (version 5.0). NHANES sampling weights were applied throughout to account for the complex multistage survey design and to ensure nationally representative estimates. Continuous variables were summarized as weighted means with standard errors, while categorical variables were presented as weighted proportions. The association between RAR and chest pain was examined using weighted multivariable logistic regression, with results reported as adjusted odds ratio (OR) and 95% confidence interval (CI). Two progressively adjusted models were constructed: Model 1 controlled for demographic variables (age, sex, and race/ethnicity), while Model 2 additionally adjusted for socioeconomic factors (education level, marital status, poverty-income ratio), behavioral factors (smoking status), and clinical conditions (BMI, hypertension, diabetes, and stroke). Potential nonlinear relationships between RAR and chest pain were explored using generalized additive models with smoothing splines; when significant nonlinearity was detected (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.05), piecewise linear regression was applied to identify inflection points using maximum likelihood estimation. Subgroup analyses were conducted across categories of age (&lt;60 vs &#8805;60 years), sex, race/ethnicity, marital status, BMI, RAR quartile, smoking status, hypertension, diabetes, and stroke history. Interaction effects were assessed using likelihood ratio tests, with statistical significance defined as a 2-sided <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.05.</p><p>No adjustment for multiple comparisons was performed in the subgroup analyses. Given their exploratory nature, these analyses were conducted to identify potential effect modifiers and generate hypotheses. Accordingly, findings from subgroup comparisons should be interpreted with caution.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>3. Results</title><sec><title>3.1. Characteristics of the participants</title><p>A total of 21,174 adults were included in the final analysis, among whom 5513 (26.04%) reported experiencing chest pain. Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> presents baseline characteristics stratified by chest pain status. The overall mean age was 59.52&#8197;&#177;&#8197;12.28 years, with individuals reporting chest pain being slightly older than those without (59.81&#8197;&#177;&#8197;12.08 vs 59.41&#8197;&#177;&#8197;12.35; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;.022). There were no significant differences in sex distribution between the 2 groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;.097). Significant racial disparities were observed: Non-Hispanic White individuals comprised a larger proportion of the chest pain group compared to those without chest pain (48.99% vs 43.97%), while Mexican Americans were underrepresented (12.21% vs 15.32%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.001). Socioeconomic differences were also evident, with the chest pain group exhibiting a lower mean poverty-income ratio (2.43&#8197;&#177;&#8197;1.54 vs 2.71&#8197;&#177;&#8197;1.56; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.001). However, no significant difference was found in educational attainment between groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;.206). Marital status differed significantly, as a smaller proportion of chest pain participants were married or cohabiting (58.53% vs 64.01%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.001). Clinically, participants reporting chest pain exhibited a significantly higher cardiometabolic burden. Their mean BMI was greater compared to those without chest pain (30.32&#8197;&#177;&#8197;7.14 vs 29.15&#8197;&#177;&#8197;6.48&#8201;kg/m&#178;; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.001). The chest pain group also showed notably higher prevalence rates of diabetes (25.50% vs 18.79%), heart failure (10.07% vs 2.48%), coronary heart disease (13.95% vs 2.94%), angina (10.83% vs 1.08%), and myocardial infarction (15.24% vs 2.55%; all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.001). Additionally, smoking was more common among individuals with chest pain (55.03% vs 45.64%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.001). The chest pain group exhibited a significantly higher mean RAR compared to those without chest pain (3.28&#8197;&#177;&#8197;0.53 vs 3.20&#8197;&#177;&#8197;0.47; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.001). A clear dose-response trend was observed across RAR quartiles, with chest pain prevalence increasing from 21.57% in Q1 to 29.64% in Q4 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.001). This graded pattern supports the potential utility of RAR as a biomarker for chest pain risk.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of participants with or without chest pain.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall<break/>(n&#8197;=&#8197;21,174)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No pain<break/>(n&#8197;=&#8197;15,661)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain<break/>(n&#8197;=&#8197;5513)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.52&#8197;&#177;&#8197;12.28</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.41&#8197;&#177;&#8197;12.35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.81&#8197;&#177;&#8197;12.08</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.022</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PIR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64&#8197;&#177;&#8197;1.56</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.71&#8197;&#177;&#8197;1.56</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.43&#8197;&#177;&#8197;1.54</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.45&#8197;&#177;&#8197;6.68</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.15&#8197;&#177;&#8197;6.48</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.32&#8197;&#177;&#8197;7.14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.097</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,297 (48.63%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7669 (48.97%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2628 (47.67%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,877 (51.37%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7992 (51.03%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2885 (52.33%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Mexican American</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3073 (14.51%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2400 (15.32%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">673 (12.21%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Other Hispanic</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2051 (9.69%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1555 (9.93%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">496 (9.00%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Non-Hispanic White</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9587 (45.28%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6886 (43.97%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2701 (48.99%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Non-Hispanic Black</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4418 (20.87%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3180 (20.31%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1238 (22.46%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Other Race</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2045 (9.66%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1640 (10.47%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">405 (7.35%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education level</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.206</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Less than high school</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5828 (27.52%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4291 (27.40%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1537 (27.88%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;High school</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4850 (22.91%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3552 (22.68%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1298 (23.54%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Above high school</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,496 (49.57%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7818 (49.92%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2678 (48.58%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Married/living with partner</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,252 (62.59%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,025 (64.01%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3227 (58.53%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Widowed/divorced/separated</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6221 (29.38%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4442 (28.36%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1779 (32.27%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never married</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1701 (8.03%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1194 (7.62%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">507 (9.20%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4348 (20.53%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2942 (18.79%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1406 (25.50%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,826 (79.47%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,719 (81.21%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4107 (74.50%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart failure</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">943 (4.45%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">388 (2.48%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">555 (10.07%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,231 (95.55%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,273 (97.52%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4958 (89.93%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coronary heart disease</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1229 (5.80%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">460 (2.94%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">769 (13.95%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,945 (94.20%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,201 (97.06%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4744 (86.05%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Angina</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">766 (3.62%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169 (1.08%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">597 (10.83%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,408 (96.38%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,492 (98.92%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4916 (89.17%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart attack</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1239 (5.85%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">399 (2.55%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">840 (15.24%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,935 (94.15%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,262 (97.45%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4673 (84.76%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stroke</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1100 (5.20%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">623 (3.98%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">477 (8.65%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,074 (94.80%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,038 (96.02%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5036 (91.35%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,181 (48.08%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7147 (45.64%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3034 (55.03%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,993 (51.92%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8514 (54.36%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2479 (44.97%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RAR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.22&#8197;&#177;&#8197;0.49</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20&#8197;&#177;&#8197;0.47</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.28&#8197;&#177;&#8197;0.53</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RAR group</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Q1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5283 (24.95%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4094 (26.14%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1189 (21.57%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Q2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5303 (25.04%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4040 (25.80%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1263 (22.91%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Q3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5291 (24.99%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3864 (24.67%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1427 (25.88%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Q4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5297 (25.02%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3663 (23.39%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1634 (29.64%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>BMI = body mass index, PIR = poverty income ratio.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>3.2. Association of RAR with chest pain</title><p>Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref> illustrates a robust, graded association between RAR and chest pain across all models. In the unadjusted analysis, each 1-unit increase in RAR was associated with a 38% higher odds of chest pain (OR&#8197;=&#8197;1.38, 95% CI: 1.30&#8211;1.46; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.0001). Individuals in the highest RAR quartile (Q4: 3.42&#8211;10.22) had 54% higher odds compared to those in the lowest quartile (Q1), with a significant trend across quartiles (OR&#8197;=&#8197;1.54, 95% CI: 1.41&#8211;1.68; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for trend&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.0001). This association remained largely unchanged after adjusting for demographic variables in Model I (age, sex, race/ethnicity), where the per-unit OR was 1.38 (95% CI: 1.30&#8211;1.47) and Q4 vs Q1 OR was 1.55 (95% CI: 1.41&#8211;1.69; both <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.0001). In the fully adjusted Model II, which additionally accounted for socioeconomic status (education, marital status, and poverty-income ratio), behavioral factors (smoking), and clinical comorbidities (BMI, hypertension, diabetes, and stroke), the association remained significant though attenuated. Each unit increase in RAR was linked to 19% higher odds of chest pain (OR&#8197;=&#8197;1.19, 95% CI: 1.12&#8211;1.27; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.0001), and participants in Q4 continued to show elevated risk compared to Q1 (OR&#8197;=&#8197;1.26, 95% CI: 1.15&#8211;1.39; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.0001). The third quartile (Q3: 3.13&#8211;3.42) also showed a significantly increased risk (OR&#8197;=&#8197;1.16, 95% CI: 1.06&#8211;1.27; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;.0019), while the second quartile (Q2: 2.91&#8211;3.13) did not reach statistical significance (OR&#8197;=&#8197;1.04, 95% CI: 0.94&#8211;1.14; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;.4522). A significant linear trend across quartiles persisted in the fully adjusted model (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for trend&#8197;=&#8197;.0001).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Association between RAR and chest pain.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exposure</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-adjusted model</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model I</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model II</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RAR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38 (1.30, 1.46)&#8197;&lt;&#8197;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38 (1.30, 1.47)&#8197;&lt;&#8197;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 (1.12, 1.27)&#8197;&lt;&#8197;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q1 (2.19&#8211;2.91)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q2 (2.91&#8211;3.13)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.98, 1.18) 0.1101</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.99, 1.19) 0.0789</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.94, 1.14) 0.4522</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q3 (3.13&#8211;3.42)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 (1.16, 1.39)&#8197;&lt;&#8197;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 (1.17, 1.40)&#8197;&lt;&#8197;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 (1.06, 1.27) 0.0019</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q4 (3.42&#8211;10.22)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54 (1.41, 1.68)&#8197;&lt;&#8197;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55 (1.41, 1.69)&#8197;&lt;&#8197;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26 (1.15, 1.39)&#8197;&lt;&#8197;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for trend</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Model 1 adjust for: sex, age, race; Model 2 adjust for: sex, age, race, education level, marital status, PIR, BMI, hypertension, diabetes, stroke, and smoking.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>BMI = body mass index, PIR = poverty income ratio, RAR = red blood cell distribution width-to-albumin ratio.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec><title>3.2.1. Restricted cubic spline regression analysis between RAR and chest pain</title><p>Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> illustrates a significant nonlinear relationship between RAR and chest pain risk (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for overall&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.001; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for nonlinearity&#8197;=&#8197;.072). The restricted cubic spline curve shows a sharp increase in chest pain risk at lower RAR levels (approximately 2.0&#8211;3.5), followed by a plateau beyond a defined threshold. Table <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref> supports this threshold effect, with 2-piecewise logistic regression identifying an inflection point at RAR&#8197;=&#8197;3.59 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for log-likelihood ratio test&#8197;=&#8197;.045). Below this threshold (RAR&#8197;&lt;&#8197;3.59), each unit increase in RAR was associated with a 32% higher odds of chest pain (OR&#8197;=&#8197;1.32, 95% CI: 1.17&#8211;1.49; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.0001). In contrast, above the threshold (RAR&#8197;&#8805;&#8197;3.59), the association was no longer statistically significant (OR&#8197;=&#8197;1.09, 95% CI: 0.97&#8211;1.22; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;.1417). This nonlinear pattern remained robust after adjustment for demographic, socioeconomic, and clinical covariates.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Nonlinearity addressing of RAR and chest pain.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chest pain</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">RAR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitting model by standard logistic regression</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 (1.12, 1.27), &lt;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Fitting model by 2-piecewise logistic regression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inflection point</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.59</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&lt;3.59</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32 (1.17, 1.49), &lt;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;&gt;3.59</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.97, 1.22), .1417</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for log likely ratio test</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.045</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Adjusted for all covariates presented in Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>CI = confidence interval, OR = odds ratio, RAR = red blood cell distribution width-to-albumin ratio.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>The smoothed curve-fit plot of the dose-response relationship between RAR and chest pain. CI = confidence interval, RAR = red blood cell distribution width-to-albumin ratio.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medi-104-e43200-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>3.3. Subgroup analyses</title><p>Figure <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> presents subgroup analyses, revealing notable variation in the association between RAR and chest pain across population strata. A significant interaction was observed with smoking status (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction&#8197;=&#8197;.016), where current smokers showed a stronger association (OR&#8197;=&#8197;1.31, 95% CI: 1.20&#8211;1.44; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;&lt;&#8197;.001) compared to nonsmokers (OR&#8197;=&#8197;1.07, 95% CI: 0.97&#8211;1.19; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;.173), suggesting that smoking may amplify RAR-related inflammatory and oxidative mechanisms. The association remained consistent across sex and age groups. Similar effect sizes were observed in males and females, with no significant interaction (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;.378). Associations were also evident in both younger and older adults (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction&#8197;=&#8197;.423). By race/ethnicity, the association was strongest in Non-Hispanic Whites and Mexican Americans, though no significant interaction was found (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;.872). Some subgroups, including Other Hispanic and Other Race, did not show statistically significant associations. The relationship between RAR and chest pain was not modified by hypertension (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;.420) or diabetes (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8197;=&#8197;.443), with comparable effect sizes across groups. In BMI-stratified analyses (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction&#8197;=&#8197;.535), the strongest association was observed in normal-weight individuals (OR&#8197;=&#8197;1.77, 95% CI: 1.11&#8211;1.46). Overall, these findings underscore the robustness of the RAR &#8211; chest pain association across most subgroups, particularly among smokers, while also highlighting variability in specific populations that merits further investigation.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Subgroup analysis for the association between RAR and chest pain. BMI = body mass index, CI = confidence interval, OR = odds ratio, RAR = red blood cell distribution width-to-albumin ratio.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medi-104-e43200-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>4. Discussion</title><p>In this nationally representative cross-sectional study using NHANES 2005&#8211;2018 data, we found a significant positive association between higher RAR levels and chest pain prevalence. A nonlinear relationship was observed, with a threshold effect at RAR&#8197;=&#8197;3.59. Below this point, each unit increase in RAR was associated with 32% higher odds of chest pain (OR&#8197;=&#8197;1.32, 95% CI: 1.17&#8211;1.49), whereas the association diminished beyond the threshold. Subgroup analyses revealed a particularly strong effect among current smokers (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction&#8197;=&#8197;.016), with consistent associations across age and racial/ethnic groups, although effect sizes varied. These findings support the utility of RAR as a composite biomarker reflecting both inflammatory and nutritional status in assessing chest pain risk. The observed threshold may have clinical relevance in identifying individuals, especially smokers, who may benefit from interventions targeting systemic inflammation and nutritional deficiencies.</p><p>To our knowledge, this is the first large-scale epidemiological study to investigate the association between RAR and chest pain in a nationally representative population. Several clinical studies have highlighted the potential role of RAR and its components in cardiovascular conditions including chest pain and arrhythmia.<sup>[<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</sup> For example, Li and Song<sup>[<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</sup> found that higher RAR values were independently associated with an increased risk of atrial fibrillation among patients undergoing coronary angiography. A retrospective cohort study of elderly patients in China showed that elevated RAR was significantly correlated with 28-day cardiovascular mortality among patients with atrial fibrillation.<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup> Additionally, Eyiol and Ertekin<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup> reported that a lower hemoglobin-to-RDW ratio was predictive of greater stroke severity and in-hospital mortality, suggesting RDW&#8217;s strong prognostic value in acute vascular presentations. Our findings are broadly consistent with these studies, showing that elevated RAR is positively associated with chest pain prevalence in US adults, based on NHANES data. Together, these findings reinforce the inflammatory-nutritional basis of RAR as a biomarker of cardiovascular stress and subclinical ischemia.</p><p>In this comprehensive analysis, we utilized multivariable logistic regression, restricted cubic spline modeling, and detailed subgroup analyses to explore the relationship between RAR and chest pain. Our findings indicate that elevated RAR levels &#8211; particularly those exceeding 3.59 &#8211; are significantly associated with increased chest pain prevalence, with the strongest effects observed among smokers and older adults. The nonlinear pattern and threshold at RAR&#8197;=&#8197;3.59 suggest a potential saturation effect, where inflammatory and nutritional dysregulation may reach a plateau in their impact on chest pain risk.<sup>[<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</sup> Although the association was attenuated after adjusting for demographic, behavioral, and clinical factors, it remained statistically significant (OR&#8197;=&#8197;1.26 for Q4 vs Q1), supporting RAR&#8217;s potential as an independent risk indicator.</p><p>Emerging evidence increasingly supports the view that chest pain, particularly of cardiovascular origin, is intricately linked to systemic inflammation and metabolic dysregulation.<sup>[<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</sup> Elevated RDW, a key component of RAR, reflects anisocytosis driven by oxidative stress, chronic inflammation, and impaired erythropoiesis, all of which can promote endothelial dysfunction and contribute to atherosclerotic plaque instability &#8211; core mechanisms in ischemic chest pain development.<sup>[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</sup> Simultaneously, hypoalbuminemia, the other component of RAR, is not merely a marker of malnutrition but also a negative acute-phase reactant, often suppressed in inflammatory states.<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</sup> Low albumin levels have been associated with reduced antioxidant capacity, impaired vascular integrity, and increased inflammatory cytokine activity, such as interleukin-6 and tumor necrosis factor-alpha.<sup>[<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</sup> Our findings support the hypothesis that RAR reflects cumulative physiological stress arising from both inflammatory activation and nutritional deficits, which may exacerbate chest pain via multiple biological pathways.<sup>[<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</sup> These include impaired oxygen delivery, microvascular dysfunction, and heightened vascular reactivity.<sup>[<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</sup> The observed threshold effect at RAR&#8197;=&#8197;3.59 may indicate a saturation point beyond which the inflammatory-nutritional burden exerts maximal clinical impact. Additionally, smoking &#8211; a significant modifier in our subgroup analysis &#8211; may potentiate these mechanisms by intensifying oxidative stress and impairing endothelial repair capacity.<sup>[<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</sup> It is also possible that nutritional inadequacies associated with low serum albumin contribute to suboptimal myocardial energy metabolism, thereby amplifying pain perception during ischemic episodes.<sup>[<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</sup> The relationship between RAR and chest pain may also be bidirectional. Repeated ischemic injury can elevate systemic inflammation, further suppressing albumin synthesis and driving RDW elevation, thereby creating a feedback loop that sustains or aggravates chest pain symptoms.<sup>[<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</sup> Beyond cardiovascular causes, inflammation and oxidative stress &#8211; reflected by high RAR &#8211; are increasingly recognized in musculoskeletal and visceral pain pathways, suggesting that RAR may be relevant to a broader spectrum of chest pain etiologies.<sup>[<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</sup> However, the precise biological pathways mediating these associations remain to be fully elucidated and warrant further experimental and longitudinal investigation.</p><p>These findings hold particular relevance for high-risk populations, including smokers and individuals with cardiometabolic conditions, in whom elevated RAR may indicate increased inflammatory burden. Future longitudinal and interventional studies are warranted to establish causality and assess the clinical utility of RAR in guiding personalized strategies for chest pain management.</p><sec><title>4.1. Limitations</title><p>This study has several limitations. First, although we adjusted for a wide range of demographic, socioeconomic, behavioral, and clinical covariates, the possibility of residual confounding due to unmeasured or unknown variables cannot be excluded. Sencond, given the cross-sectional nature of NHANES, causality cannot be inferred. The observed associations between RAR and chest pain reflect correlations at a single time point and do not establish temporal directionality. Prospective studies are needed to confirm these findings. Third, chest pain was assessed using the Rose Angina Questionnaire, a self-reported tool. While this questionnaire is widely validated and used in epidemiological research, it is still subject to potential misclassification bias due to recall inaccuracies or subjective interpretation by participants. Such non-differential misclassification may have biased our estimates toward the null, potentially underestimating the true strength of association. Moreover, the findings may not be generalizable to non-US populations, as RDW and albumin distributions may vary across ethnic and regional groups. Finally, although we conducted multiple subgroup analyses to explore potential effect modification, we did not apply statistical corrections for multiple comparisons. As such, the possibility of type I error (false positives) cannot be excluded. These subgroup findings should therefore be viewed as exploratory and interpreted with caution.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>5. Conclusion</title><p>This study identifies RAR as an independent predictor of chest pain, with a significant nonlinear relationship and a threshold effect observed at RAR&#8197;=&#8197;3.59. The association was most pronounced among smokers (OR&#8197;=&#8197;1.31), underscoring its potential utility for risk stratification in pro-inflammatory populations. Given its accessibility and integrative reflection of inflammatory and nutritional status, RAR may serve as a valuable biomarker in clinical evaluation &#8211; particularly in individuals with cardiometabolic risk. Prospective studies are warranted to confirm these findings and explore RAR&#8217;s role in guiding preventive or therapeutic strategies.</p></sec><sec><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We extend our heartfelt appreciation to the staff of the National Center for Health Statistics, under the Centers for Disease Control. Their diligent work in designing, collecting, and collating NHANES data, as well as creating the public database, is highly commendable and has significantly contributed to public health research.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p><bold>Methodology:</bold> Minmin Zhu.</p><p><bold>Funding acquisition:</bold> Dongxiao Huang.</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold> Hao Xi.</p><p><bold>Writing &#8211; original draft:</bold> Minmin Zhu.</p><p><bold>Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing:</bold> Hao Xi.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>
<def-list><title>Abbreviations:</title><def-item><term>ACS</term><def><p>acute coronary syndrome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BMI</term><def><p>body mass index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p>confidence interval</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NHANES</term><def><p>National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OR</term><def><p>odds ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RAR</term><def><p>red blood cell distribution width-to-albumin ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RDW</term><def><p>red blood cell distribution width</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>This work was supported by Top Talent Support Program for Young and Middle-aged People of Wuxi Health Committee (HB2023025).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>The study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and was approved by the Institutional Review Board of the National Centre for Health Statistics.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this published article [and its supplementary information files].</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>How to cite this article: Zhu M, Huang D, Xi H. The association between red blood cell distribution width-to-albumin ratio and chest pain prevalence in US adults: A cross-sectional analysis of NHANES 2005&#8211;2018. Medicine 2025;104:27(e43200).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Geyser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chest pain prevalence, causes, and disposition in the emergency department of a regional hospital in Pretoria.</article-title><source>Afr J Prim Health Care Fam Med</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4102/phcfm.v8i1.1048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4926718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27380782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taruya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishiguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Lesion characteristics and prognosis of acute coronary syndrome without angiographically significant coronary artery stenosis.</article-title><source>Eur Heart J Cardiovasc Imaging</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>202</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31056642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ehjci/jez079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wassie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Single vs serial measurements of cardiac troponin level in the evaluation of patients in the emergency department with suspected acute myocardial infarction.</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e2037930</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33620444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.37930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7903256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wertli</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dangma</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#252;ller</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Non-cardiac chest pain patients in the emergency department: do physicians have a plan how to diagnose and treat them? A retrospective study.</article-title><source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>e0211615</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30707725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0211615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6358153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group>, <collab>Writing Committee of the Report on Cardiovascular Health and Diseases in China</collab>. <article-title>Epidemiology and current management of cardiovascular disease in China.</article-title><source>J Geriatr Cardiol</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>387</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>406</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38800543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.26599/1671-5411.2024.04.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11112149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kosmas</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silverio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sourlas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montan</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anti-inflammatory therapy for cardiovascular disease.</article-title><source>Ann Transl Med</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>147</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31157268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.21037/atm.2019.02.34</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6511577</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sulicka-Grodzicka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szczepaniak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jozefczuk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Systemic and local vascular inflammation and arterial reactive oxygen species generation in patients with advanced cardiovascular diseases.</article-title><source>Front Cardiovasc Med</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1230051</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37745103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fcvm.2023.1230051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10513373</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ridker</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rane</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Interleukin-6 signaling and anti-interleukin-6 therapeutics in cardiovascular disease.</article-title><source>Circ Res</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>128</volume>:<fpage>1728</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33998272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.121.319077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dohi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyauchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Independent and combined effects of serum albumin and C-reactive protein on long-term outcomes of patients undergoing percutaneous coronary intervention.</article-title><source>Circ J</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>1293</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>300</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28428450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1253/circj.CJ-17-0124</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Relationship between the ratio of red cell distribution width to albumin and 28-day mortality among Chinese patients over 80 years with atrial fibrillation.</article-title><source>Gerontology</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>1471</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37793355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000534259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Red cell distribution width as a significant indicator of medication and prognosis in type 2 diabetic patients.</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>2709</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28578411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-017-02904-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5457426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shangguan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Red blood cell distribution width to albumin ratio is associated with increased depression: the mediating role of atherogenic index of plasma.</article-title><source>Front Psychiatry</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1504123</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39950171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpsyt.2025.1504123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11821614</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Namazi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heidar Beygi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vahidi</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Relationship between red cell distribution width and oxidative stress indexes in patients with coronary artery disease.</article-title><source>Rep Biochem Mol Biol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38317815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.61186/rbmb.12.2.241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10838587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eyiol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ertekin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The relationship between hemoglobin-to-red cell distribution width (RDW) ratio (HRR) and mortality in stroke patients.</article-title><source>Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>1504</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38436184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.26355/eurrev_202402_35480</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Potential of seven insulin resistance indicators as biomarkers to predict infertility risk in U.S. women of reproductive age: a cross-sectional study.</article-title><source>Reprod Biol Endocrinol</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>77</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40413481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12958-025-01416-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12102792</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Associations of triglyceride-glucose (TyG) index with chest pain incidence and mortality among the U.S. population.</article-title><source>Cardiovasc Diabetol</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38555461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12933-024-02209-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10981836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Red blood cell distribution width to albumin ratio and urinary incontinence subtypes in NHANES 2007-2018.</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>18132</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40413229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-025-02574-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12103605</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Association between mortality and the ratio of red blood cell distribution width to albumin concentration in pre-hypertension and hypertension: a population-based cohort study.</article-title><source>Maturitas</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>198</volume>:<fpage>108604</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40412146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.maturitas.2025.108604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Association between dietary sugar intake and depression in US adults: a cross-sectional study using data from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey 2011-2018.</article-title><source>BMC Psychiatry</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>110</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38326834</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12888-024-05531-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10851576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between serum potassium and Parkinson&#8217;s disease in the US (NHANES 2005-2020).</article-title><source>Front Neurosci</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1387266</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38784091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fnins.2024.1387266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11111918</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of red blood cell distribution width-albumin ratio on prognosis of patients with CKD.</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>15774</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37737253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-023-42986-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10516924</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Red cell distribution width to albumin ratio is a risk factor for atrial fibrillation in subjects hospitalized with coronary angiography.</article-title><source>BMC Cardiovasc Disord</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38331757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12872-024-03772-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10854169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between red blood cell distribution width-to-albumin ratio and prognosis of patients with aortic aneurysms.</article-title><source>Int J Gen Med</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>6287</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34621131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/IJGM.S328035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8491781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Che</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Association of inflammation/nutrition-based indicators with Parkinson&#8217;s disease and mortality.</article-title><source>Front Nutr</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1439803</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39355557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fnut.2024.1439803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11442420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Association between polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons exposure with red cell width distribution and ischemic heart disease: insights from a population-based study.</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>196</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38168482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-023-50794-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10762247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ananthaseshan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bojakowski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sacharczuk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Red blood cell distribution width is associated with increased interactions of blood cells with vascular wall.</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>13676</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35953533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-022-17847-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9366818</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almasaudi</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hypoalbuminemia reflects nutritional risk, body composition and systemic inflammation and is independently associated with survival in patients with colorectal cancer.</article-title><source>Cancers (Basel)</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1986</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32708140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/cancers12071986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7409314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>[28]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakanishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Relationships among red cell distribution width, anemia, and interleukin-6 in adult congenital heart disease.</article-title><source>Circ J</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>1100</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25740502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1253/circj.CJ-14-1296</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>[29]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dabbaghi Varnousfaderani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Musazadeh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghalichi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Alleviating effects of coenzyme Q10 supplements on biomarkers of inflammation and oxidative stress: results from an umbrella meta-analysis.</article-title><source>Front Pharmacol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1191290</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37614320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fphar.2023.1191290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10442645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>[30]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Association between environmental chemicals co-exposure and peripheral blood immune-inflammatory indicators.</article-title><source>Front Public Health</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>980987</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36483254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpubh.2022.980987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9725172</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>[31]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hahad</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuntic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuntic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daiber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#252;nzel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Tobacco smoking and vascular biology and function: evidence from human studies.</article-title><source>Pflugers Arch</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>475</volume>:<fpage>797</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>805</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36961561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00424-023-02805-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10264470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>[32]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Schenk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beard</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Integrated functions of cardiac energetics, mechanics, and purine nucleotide metabolism.</article-title><source>Compr Physiol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>5345</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>69</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38158366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cphy.c230011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10956446</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>[33]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kostadinova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Damjanovska</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Red cell distribution width and absolute lymphocyte count associate with biomarkers of inflammation and subsequent mortality in rheumatoid arthritis.</article-title><source>J Rheumatol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>166</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36319020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3899/jrheum.211411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9898085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>[34]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cirillo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Argento</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becatti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiorillo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coccia</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fatini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mediterranean diet and oxidative stress: a relationship with pain perception in endometriosis.</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>14601</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37834048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms241914601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10572576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>[35]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shieh</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mitochondrial mechanisms in the pathogenesis of chronic inflammatory musculoskeletal disorders.</article-title><source>Cell Biosci</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38849951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13578-024-01259-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11162051</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>