<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAMIA Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAMIA Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3775</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jamiaopen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jamiaoa</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JAMIA Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2574-2531</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11126158</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11126158.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11126158</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11126158</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38798774</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jamiaopen/ooae044</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ooae044</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01530</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00010</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01060</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Natural language processing systems for extracting information from electronic health records about activities of daily living. A systematic review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0524-8182</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Wieland-Jorna</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yvonne</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><aff>
<institution>Netherlands Institute for Health Services Research (Nivel)</institution>, Utrecht, Postbus 1568, 3500 BN, <country country="NL">The Netherlands</country></aff><aff>
<institution>Tranzo, School of Social Sciences and Behavioural Research, Tilburg University</institution>, Tilburg, Postbus 90153, 5000 LE, <country country="NL">The Netherlands</country></aff><xref rid="ooae044-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Kooten</surname><given-names initials="D">Daan</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><aff>
<institution>Netherlands Institute for Health Services Research (Nivel)</institution>, Utrecht, Postbus 1568, 3500 BN, <country country="NL">The Netherlands</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verheij</surname><given-names initials="RA">Robert A</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Netherlands Institute for Health Services Research (Nivel)</institution>, Utrecht, Postbus 1568, 3500 BN, <country country="NL">The Netherlands</country></aff><aff>
<institution>Tranzo, School of Social Sciences and Behavioural Research, Tilburg University</institution>, Tilburg, Postbus 90153, 5000 LE, <country country="NL">The Netherlands</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Man</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yvonne</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><aff>
<institution>Netherlands Institute for Health Services Research (Nivel)</institution>, Utrecht, Postbus 1568, 3500 BN, <country country="NL">The Netherlands</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Francke</surname><given-names initials="AL">Anneke L</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Netherlands Institute for Health Services Research (Nivel)</institution>, Utrecht, Postbus 1568, 3500 BN, <country country="NL">The Netherlands</country></aff><aff>
<institution>Department of Public and Occupational Health, Location Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam, Amsterdam UMC</institution>, Amsterdam, Postbus 7057, 1007 MB, <country country="NL">The Netherlands</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oosterveld-Vlug</surname><given-names initials="MG">Mariska G</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><aff>
<institution>Netherlands Institute for Health Services Research (Nivel)</institution>, Utrecht, Postbus 1568, 3500 BN, <country country="NL">The Netherlands</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="ooae044-cor1">Corresponding author: Yvonne Wieland-Jorna, MSc, Netherlands Institute of Health Services Research (Nivel), Postbus 1568, Utrecht 3500 BN, The Netherlands (<email>y.jorna@nivel.nl</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2024-05-24"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">459613</issue-id><elocation-id>ooae044</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>21</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="editorial-decision"><day>03</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>24</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>24</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-27 17:25:15.670"><day>27</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2024. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the American Medical Informatics Association.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="ooae044.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ooae044.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="s1"><title>Objective</title><p>Natural language processing (NLP) can enhance research on activities of daily living (ADL) by extracting structured information from unstructured electronic health records (EHRs) notes. This review aims to give insight into the state-of-the-art, usability, and performance of NLP systems to extract information on ADL from EHRs.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>A systematic review was conducted based on searches in Pubmed, Embase, Cinahl, Web of Science, and Scopus. Studies published between 2017 and 2022 were selected based on predefined eligibility criteria.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>The review identified 22 studies. Most studies (65%) used NLP for classifying unstructured EHR data on 1 or 2 ADL. Deep learning, combined with a ruled-based method or machine learning, was the approach most commonly used. NLP systems varied widely in terms of the pre-processing and algorithms. Common performance evaluation methods were cross-validation and train/test datasets, with F1, precision, and sensitivity as the most frequently reported evaluation metrics. Most studies reported relativity high overall scores on the evaluation metrics.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>NLP systems are valuable for the extraction of unstructured EHR data on ADL. However, comparing the performance of NLP systems is difficult due to the diversity of the studies and challenges related to the dataset, including restricted access to EHR data, inadequate documentation, lack of granularity, and small datasets.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>This systematic review indicates that NLP is promising for deriving information on ADL from unstructured EHR notes. However, what the best-performing NLP system is, depends on characteristics of the dataset, research question, and type of ADL.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>natural language processing</kwd><kwd>activities of daily living</kwd><kwd>unstructured data</kwd><kwd>electronic health records</kwd><kwd>free-text notes</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Ministry of Health, Welfare, and Sports</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The ever-increasing amount of data recorded by physicians or nursing staff in patients&#8217; electronic health records (EHRs) offers opportunities for clinical practice and research. Although EHR systems are primarily designed for documentation about individual patient care, EHR data are increasingly used for scientific research. The data used for this purpose are predominantly structured data, which are recordings following a fixed format or category.</p><p>However, solely using structured EHR data for research could lead to biased results, for example, because this may lead to an underestimation of the incidence and prevalence,<xref rid="ooae044-B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> and low performance of prediction models<xref rid="ooae044-B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> of health problems.</p><p>Using unstructured health data, such as clinical notes and discharge letters, can enhance the quality of research results by capturing valuable information not found in structured data. It is estimated that more than half of all health records in the EHR systems are unstructured data.<xref rid="ooae044-B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Even if health information could be recorded as structured data, healthcare professionals sometimes prefer to use unstructured free-text notes, for example, because they think it allows a more accurate representation of the patient&#8217;s situation.<xref rid="ooae044-B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref></p><p>An example of health information often documented in both structured and unstructured manners, is the ability to perform a range of essential daily activities.<xref rid="ooae044-B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8&#8211;10</sup></xref> The activities of ambulating, feeding, dressing, personal hygiene, continence, and toileting are referred to as activities of daily living (ADL).<xref rid="ooae044-B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> For care provision, adequate information on ADL is important for ensuring individuals receive the necessary daily support. Also, the research using health data on ADL requires adequate information to provide insight into the need for support with ADL and, for instance, the effect of a treatment on the ability to perform ADL.</p><p>ADL could be recorded in a structured way, using assessment tools such as the Barthel Index and Katz Activities of Daily Living Index.<xref rid="ooae044-B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> The International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health (ICF) also categorizes different daily activities as part of a larger framework on functional status.<xref rid="ooae044-B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> Furthermore, there are ADL measures developed for a specific target population, for example, the Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS) (for Multiple Sclerosis)<xref rid="ooae044-B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> and the Karnofsky Performance Status Scale (for cancer).<xref rid="ooae044-B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> Despite the availability of assessment tools, ADL are also recorded in unstructured free-text notes in EHR systems.<xref rid="ooae044-B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8&#8211;10</sup></xref></p><p>To extract information from unstructured EHR data, Natural Language Processing (NLP) is currently the most widely used &#8220;big data&#8221; analytical technique.<xref rid="ooae044-B16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> NLP, a subfield of artificial intelligence, focuses on computers and human-language interaction. NLP can be used for various applications, such as information retrieval, text classification, topic identification, word frequency calculation, and sentiment analysis.<xref rid="ooae044-B17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref></p><p>Advancements in computing power, greater availability of large datasets, and recent breakthroughs in the field of NLP have increased the potential for generating valuable insights from unstructured EHR data.<xref rid="ooae044-B18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> While the oldest NLP approach, the rule-based approach, relies on manual rule construction by experts, machine-learning approaches, including Support Vector Regression and Conditional Random Fields, are able to train algorithms with less manual coding.<xref rid="ooae044-B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> Rule-based and machine-learning models generally involve a pre-processing phase to standardize text by cleaning and preparing textual data as tokens, and a modeling phase in which unstructured textual data is fed into a model. In these models, pre-processing is crucial because the performance of the models depends on the quality of the data fed into the model.<xref rid="ooae044-B20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20&#8211;22</sup></xref> The latest breakthrough in machine learning is the deep-learning approach. Examples of deep-learning models are Word2vec<xref rid="ooae044-B23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> and transformers, such as Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers (BERT).<xref rid="ooae044-B24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> In NLP, deep-learning models take a holistic approach considering the entire context and relationships within the sentence rather than individual tokens. This enables deep-learning models to analyze complex patterns in texts.<xref rid="ooae044-B25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> In addition, the holistic approach avoids extensive pre-processing of texts.<xref rid="ooae044-B27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref></p><p>Although the opportunities for NLP in the healthcare sector are recognized, the usability for clinical practice and research depends on how well a NLP system performs.<xref rid="ooae044-B28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> For example, overfitting is a common concern with machine-learning models. Overfitting means that an algorithm aligns too closely with a specific dataset, limiting its application to future data. Various evaluation methods, including train/test datasets and cross-validation, can be used to explore the performance of the NLP system and identify issues such as overfitting.<xref rid="ooae044-B28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28&#8211;30</sup></xref></p><p>While previous systematic reviews have explored the processing of unstructured clinical notes (eg,<xref rid="ooae044-B19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31&#8211;35</sup></xref>) none have specifically focused on ADL. This gap makes it hard to draw conclusions and recommendations for using NLP to derive information on ADL from unstructured EHR notes. It is of significance to understand recent developments specific to NLP in the ADL research field as this will help researchers to gain a broader understanding, and provide insight into methods and techniques supporting and promoting new developments in the field of ADL research.</p><sec><title>Objective and research questions</title><p>This systematic review aims to give insight into the state of the art and usability of NLP systems to extract information on ADL from EHRs. The specific review questions addressed are as follows:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Which NLP systems are used to extract information on ADL from routinely recorded unstructured free-text data in EHRs?</p></list-item><list-item><p>Which methods are used to evaluate the performance of these NLP systems in research?</p></list-item><list-item><p>How do the NLP systems perform with regard to extracting information on ADL from EHRs?</p></list-item></list></sec></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Design</title><p>The reporting of this systematic review was guided by the PRISMA (Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses) statement.<xref rid="ooae044-B36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref></p></sec><sec><title>Search strategy and information sources</title><p>In November 2022, a librarian, in consultation with the authors of this paper, conducted searches in the Pubmed, Embase, Cinahl, Web of Science, and Scopus databases, using predetermined search strategies (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Appendix 1</xref>). The searches initially included studies on ADL and NLP published between January 1, 2012 and November 4, 2022. However, due to the large number of references generated by this search and given the review&#8217;s focus on recent developments, it was decided to exclude studies published before 2017; therefore only studies published in 2017 or later were included. After removal of 1339 duplicates and removal of 403 references published before 2017, 1277 references were retrieved. Additionally, 4 potential references were identified by checking the reference lists of relevant literature reviews.</p></sec><sec><title>Article selection</title><p>Studies were selected in 2 steps, based on the eligibility criteria (see below). First, 2 reviewers independently reviewed the titles and abstracts of the 1277 studies (D.v.K. and Y.W.J.), resulting in a selection of 130 potentially relevant studies. Second, the full texts of these 130 studies were reviewed, in varying compositions, by 2 out of 4 reviewers (Y.W.J., D.v.K., Y.d.M., or M.O.V.). Discrepancies in selection were resolved through discussions between the reviewers (Y.W.J., D.v.K., Y.d.M., and M.O.V.). The steps and results of the selection process are described in the PRISMA flow diagram in <xref rid="ooae044-F1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#160;1</xref>. After the final selection step, 22 studies were included for further analysis.</p><fig position="float" id="ooae044-F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>PRISMA (preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses) flow diagram.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ooae044f1.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Eligibility criteria</title><p>The following criteria were used by the reviewers during the selection of relevant studies.</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>
<italic toggle="yes">The study is an empirical study</italic>
</p><p>All types of empirical studies were eligible for inclusion, including gray literature. Editorials, essays, literature reviews, or other non-empirical studies were excluded.</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<italic toggle="yes">The full text of the study had to be available</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<italic toggle="yes">The study concerns at least 1 activity of daily living</italic>
</p><p>Studies had to use information on at least 1 activity (ambulating, feeding, dressing, personal hygiene, continence, or toileting).<xref rid="ooae044-B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> There were no restrictions regarding care setting and age, health status, and type of disease of the study population.</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Study uses information on ADL that is routinely recorded as unstructured free text in an EHR system</italic>
</p><p>To be included, studies had to use information on ADL that was recorded as unstructured free text in an EHR system by a healthcare professional. Studies were excluded if information on ADL was not routinely recorded, for example, if patients recorded them in a one-time questionnaire as part of scientific research.</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<italic toggle="yes">NLP system is used in the study to extract information on ADL</italic>
</p><p>Studies were excluded if they only used manual processing of the unstructured free texts.</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<italic toggle="yes">The performance of the NLP system is evaluated and reported in the study</italic>
</p></list-item></list><sec><title>Data extraction and synthesis</title><p>For each of the 22 included studies, 1 author (D.v.K. or Y.W.J.) manually extracted information, which was then verified by another author (Y.W.J., D.v.K., R.V., A.F., or M.O.V.). The extracted data were inserted in a prestructured format, developed in consultation with all the authors. The extracted information concerned background information on the study, including the aim of the study, country, whether the unstructured records were retrieved directly from an EHR system or other database, the study population, and type of ADL. Moreover, data were extracted on the NLP system, including the type (rule-based, machine learning, or deep learning), aim (eg, classification or data extraction), pre-processing steps, and tools. Lastly, data were extracted on the evaluation of the NLP system, including the metrics used to evaluate the NLP system, NLP system&#8217;s performance, and limitations of the method according to the authors of the specific study.</p><p>To address the research question regarding which NLP systems were used, we identified the most common aim (ie, data classification or extraction) and type of NLP system (rule-based, machine learning, deep learning, or a combination of these). To analyze trends in the NLP system used, we looked at whether the type of NLP system varied over the years. Furthermore, we determined frequently used pre-processing techniques and identified studies with no or few pre-processing steps. Lastly, we described the software used for the NLP. To answer the research question about which evaluation methods were used, we looked at the most commonly used methods and compared their prevalence across different types of NLP systems. To address the research question regarding the performance, we outlined the primary performance metrics used to evaluate the NLP system.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Study characteristics</title><p>Twenty-two studies were included in the review (<xref rid="ooae044-T1" ref-type="table">Table&#160;1</xref>). The aim of the studies included is described in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>. The year with the most publications was 2019 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;6). Eleven studies were published in 2020 or later.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="ooae044-T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the study and EHR data.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study (year); country</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source(s) of routinely recorded EHRs on ADL</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study population</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of ADL included</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anzaldi et al (2017)<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical notes from a nonprofit medical group (hospital, emergency department, and nursing home)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients aged over 65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Ambulating (walking difficulty)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Continence (absence of fecal control and severe urinary control issues)</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kharrazi et al (2018)<xref rid="ooae044-B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>a</sup>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Same as<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Same as<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Same as<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kan et al (2018)<xref rid="ooae044-B38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref><sup>a</sup>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Same as<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Same as<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Same as<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hernandez-Boussard et al (2017)<xref rid="ooae044-B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical notes from a single, large, academic medical center</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prostate cancer patients</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Continence (UI<xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>)</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Humbert-Droz et al (2022)<xref rid="ooae044-B40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rheumatology notes from the RISE<xref rid="tblfn2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref> registry</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rheumatology patients</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Ambulating</p></list-item><list-item><p>Feeding</p></list-item><list-item><p>Dressing</p></list-item><list-item><p>Personal hygiene</p></list-item><list-item><p>Toileting</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alves et al (2022)<xref rid="ooae044-B41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical notes from neurology practices included in the OM1 MS Registry</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with MS<xref rid="tblfn3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Ambulating (mobility impairments)</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chen et al (2019)<xref rid="ooae044-B42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical notes from a large group practice</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients aged over 65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Ambulating (walking difficulty)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Continence (absence of fecal control and severe urinary control issues)</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Banerjee et al (2019)<xref rid="ooae044-B43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical notes from a tertiary care academic Medical center included in a research database</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prostate cancer patients</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Continence (UI<xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref> and fecal incontinence)</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meskers et al (2022)<xref rid="ooae044-B44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref>; The Netherlands</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical notes from a large teaching hospital</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitalized COVID-19 patients</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Ambulating (mobility activities)</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rivera et al (2022)<xref rid="ooae044-B45" ref-type="bibr"><sup>45</sup></xref>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Provider documentation, discharge notes, and PT and occupational therapy documentation from a large stroke referral center</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischemic stroke patients</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Ambulating (Modified Raking Scale)</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chen et al (2019)<xref rid="ooae044-B46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unstructured free-text from a large multispecialty medical group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients aged over 65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Ambulating (walking difficulty)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Continence (absence of fecal control and severe urinary control issues)</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gori et al (2019)<xref rid="ooae044-B47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47</sup></xref>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical notes from a tertiary academic medical center included in a research data warehouse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prostate cancer patients</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Continence (UI<xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>)</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Newman-Griffis et al (2018)<xref rid="ooae044-B48" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PT<xref rid="tblfn4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref> notes from a Clinical Center</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with PT<xref rid="tblfn4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref> notes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Ambulating (mobility)</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bozkurt et al (2020)<xref rid="ooae044-B49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical notes from an Academic Medical Centre included in a prostate cancer clinical data warehouse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients diagnosed with prostate cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Continence (UI<xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>)</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Doing-Harris et al (2019)<xref rid="ooae044-B50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical notes from a Veteran Health Administration Repository (VINCI)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Veterans diagnosed with cardiac disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Ambulating (able to mobilize, bed-ridden, wheelchair-bound)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Dressing</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Goudar-zvand et al (2019)<xref rid="ooae044-B51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical notes and current visit information from the Mayo Clinic Biobank</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physician-diagnosed CI<xref rid="tblfn5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>e</sup></xref> and CU<xref rid="tblfn6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>f</sup></xref> patients aged 65 years and older</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Ambulating (transferring)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Feeding</p></list-item><list-item><p>Dressing</p></list-item><list-item><p>Personal hygiene (bathing)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Toileting</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greve et al (2022)<xref rid="ooae044-B52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52</sup></xref>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical notes from a single tertiary medical center</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with cerebral palsy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Ambulating</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thieu et al (2021)<xref rid="ooae044-B53" ref-type="bibr"><sup>53</sup></xref>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PT<xref rid="tblfn4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref> notes from a Clinical Center</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with PTi notes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Ambulating (mobility domain of the ICF<xref rid="tblfn7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>g</sup></xref>)</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Newman-Griffis et al (2021)<xref rid="ooae044-B54" ref-type="bibr"><sup>54</sup></xref>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Notes from the Rehabilitation and Medicine Department at the NIH Clinical Center using databases of the NIH Biomedical Translational Research Information System</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients receiving PT<xref rid="tblfn4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Ambulating (mobility activities)</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Newman-Griffis et al (2021)<xref rid="ooae044-B55" ref-type="bibr"><sup>55</sup></xref>; United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Claims database</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients receiving disability benefits primarily related to musculo-skeletal, neurological, or mental impairments</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Ambulating (mobility)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Personal hygiene (self-care)</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sung et al (2021)<xref rid="ooae044-B56" ref-type="bibr"><sup>56</sup></xref>; Taiwan (English written records)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical notes from 2 hospital stroke registries</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients hospitalized for acute ischemic stroke</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Ambulating (Modified Raking Scale)</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yang et al (2022)<xref rid="ooae044-B57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref>; Canada</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical notes from a clinical database from a large MS<xref rid="tblfn3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref> clinic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with MS<xref rid="tblfn3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Ambulating (mobility)</p></list-item></list>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><label>a</label><p>UI: urinary incontinence.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn2"><label>b</label><p>RISE: American College of Rheumatology&#8217;s Rheumatology Informatics System for Effectiveness.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn3"><label>c</label><p>MS: Multiple Sclerosis.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn4"><label>d</label><p>PT: Physical Therapy.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn5"><label>e</label><p>CI: cognitive impaired.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn6"><label>f</label><p>CU: Cognitive Unimpaired.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn7"><label>g</label><p>ICF: International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Three studies were found to use the same dataset and NLP system.<xref rid="ooae044-B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> As 2 of them<xref rid="ooae044-B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> used the NLP system developed in the study by Anzaldi et al,<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> we only refer to the study of Anzaldi et al<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> in the remainder of this review. Thus, the total number of NLP systems we report on is 20.</p></sec><sec><title>Data source</title><p>Of the 20 studies, 1 study used clinical notes written in Dutch,<xref rid="ooae044-B44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref> while the remaining 19 studies used English clinical notes<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39&#8211;43</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B45" ref-type="bibr"><sup>45&#8211;57</sup></xref> (<xref rid="ooae044-T1" ref-type="table">Table&#160;1</xref>). Most clinical notes used were retrieved directly from an EHR system (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;11).<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42&#8211;46</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B48" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B53" ref-type="bibr"><sup>53</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref> In the other studies, clinical notes were first transferred from an EHR system to a research database, registry, or claims database (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;9).<xref rid="ooae044-B40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49&#8211;51</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B54" ref-type="bibr"><sup>54&#8211;56</sup></xref> In such a database or registry, EHR data may be cleaned or combined with data from other sources before the data are transferred to the researchers.<xref rid="ooae044-B58" ref-type="bibr"><sup>58</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B59" ref-type="bibr"><sup>59</sup></xref></p></sec><sec><title>Study population</title><p>The studies included in this review focused on a variety of diagnoses or patient groups (<xref rid="ooae044-T1" ref-type="table">Table&#160;1</xref>). The most frequently studied patient groups were patients aged over 65 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;4),<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref> patients with prostate cancer (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;4),<xref rid="ooae044-B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref> patients suffering from a chronic disease (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;4),<xref rid="ooae044-B40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref> and patients receiving physical therapy (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;3).<xref rid="ooae044-B48" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B53" ref-type="bibr"><sup>53</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B54" ref-type="bibr"><sup>54</sup></xref></p></sec><sec><title>Activities of daily living</title><p>Each of the 6 ADL is covered in at least 1 study (<xref rid="ooae044-T1" ref-type="table">Table&#160;1</xref>). However, none of the studies covered all 6 ADL. The majority of studies focused on 1 activity (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;13),<xref rid="ooae044-B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43&#8211;45</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47&#8211;49</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52&#8211;54</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B56" ref-type="bibr"><sup>56</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref> while others covered 2 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;5)<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B55" ref-type="bibr"><sup>55</sup></xref> or 5 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;2)<xref rid="ooae044-B40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref> activities. The most frequently studied activities were ambulating (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;16)<xref rid="ooae044-B40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40&#8211;42</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44&#8211;46</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B48" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50&#8211;57</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B60" ref-type="bibr"><sup>60</sup></xref> and continence (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;7).<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref></p></sec><sec><title>Purpose of using NLP</title><p>In 70% of the studies, NLP was used for classification purposes (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;14/20),<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42&#8211;46</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B54" ref-type="bibr"><sup>54&#8211;57</sup></xref> for example, classifying patients as frail or not,<xref rid="ooae044-B46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref> determining the presence and severity of urine incontinence,<xref rid="ooae044-B43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref> and assigning ICF categories.<xref rid="ooae044-B54" ref-type="bibr"><sup>54</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B55" ref-type="bibr"><sup>55</sup></xref> The remaining studies used NLP for information extraction (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;3),<xref rid="ooae044-B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39&#8211;41</sup></xref> for Named Entity Recognition (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;2),<xref rid="ooae044-B48" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B53" ref-type="bibr"><sup>53</sup></xref> or topic modeling (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1),<xref rid="ooae044-B51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref> as is shown in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S2</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Type of NLP</title><p>The rule-based approach, the oldest and simplest NLP approach, was used as the sole method in 3 studies,<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref> while another study combined rule-based with deep learning (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S2</xref>).<xref rid="ooae044-B49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref></p><p>More than half of the NLP systems relied on machine learning (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12); all of these studies were published in 2019 or later.<xref rid="ooae044-B41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41&#8211;45</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50&#8211;56</sup></xref> Eight of these studies applied a combination of machine learning and deep learning.<xref rid="ooae044-B44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50&#8211;56</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B60" ref-type="bibr"><sup>60</sup></xref> Various machine-learning algorithms were used, with Support Vector Machines (SVMs) being the most prevalent (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;5).<xref rid="ooae044-B44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B54" ref-type="bibr"><sup>54</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B55" ref-type="bibr"><sup>55</sup></xref></p><p>Thirteen studies applied deep learning; all of them were published in 2018 or later.<xref rid="ooae044-B44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46&#8211;57</sup></xref> Word2Vec was used in 7 studies.<xref rid="ooae044-B46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46&#8211;49</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B54" ref-type="bibr"><sup>54</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref> Among the 13 deep-learning NLP systems, 2 studies were based on ClinicalBERT<xref rid="ooae044-B55" ref-type="bibr"><sup>55</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B56" ref-type="bibr"><sup>56</sup></xref> and 1 study used BERTje.<xref rid="ooae044-B44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref> These 3 studies were published in 2021 or later.</p></sec><sec><title>Pre-processing</title><p>
<xref rid="ooae044-T2" ref-type="table">Table&#160;2</xref> shows a variety of pre-processing steps applied to prepare unstructured notes, with tokenization the most frequently used pre-processing technique (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;10).<xref rid="ooae044-B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39&#8211;42</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52&#8211;55</sup></xref></p><table-wrap position="float" id="ooae044-T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Pre-processing steps used in the included studies.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-processing step</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of studies</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tokenization</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ooae044-B39" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>39&#8211;42</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B46" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>46</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B49" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>49</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B52" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>52&#8211;55</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stop-word removal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ooae044-B41" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>41</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B43" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>43</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B49" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>49</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B51" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>51</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B56" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>56</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B57" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>57</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>37</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B44" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>44</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B45" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>45</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B48" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>48</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normalization</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ooae044-B43" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>43</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B55" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>55</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B56" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>56</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Removal of redundant information</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ooae044-B40" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>40</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B49" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>49</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B57" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>57</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sentence splitting</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ooae044-B39" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>39</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B49" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>49</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lemmatization</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ooae044-B41" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>41</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B52" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>52</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stemming</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ooae044-B43" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>43</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B51" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>51</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sentence segmentation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ooae044-B42" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>42</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B54" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>54</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lowercase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ooae044-B55" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>55</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B56" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>56</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Removal of identifying information</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ooae044-B40" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>40</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="ooae044-B57" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>57</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard tool for text-cleaning methodologies, not further defined</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ooae044-B47" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>47</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manual</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ooae044-B50" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>50</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Removal of formatting</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ooae044-B40" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>40</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>In general, deep learning requires less pre-processing compared to rule-based and machine-learning models. In the 3 studies that employed deep learning only, little to no pre-processing was performed. One of the 3 studies<xref rid="ooae044-B46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref> only used sentence segmentation, the second study reported no pre-processing steps,<xref rid="ooae044-B48" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref> and the third study used a standard tool for text-cleaning methodologies.<xref rid="ooae044-B47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47</sup></xref> However, as the precise methodologies applied to the dataset were not specified in this last study, the extent of data pre-processing remains unclear.</p><p>Pre-processing details were not reported in 3 other studies. Anzaldi et al used a rule-based approach for identifying geriatrics syndromes in EHR free-text notes as well as the explicit mention of &#8220;frailty&#8221; in the notes.<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> In such an approach, pre-processing is not always a necessity. In the study of Rivera et al, although pre-processing was not reported, we cannot conclude that data pre-processing was therefore not applied as a machine learning usually involves pre-processing.<xref rid="ooae044-B45" ref-type="bibr"><sup>45</sup></xref> Lastly, Meskers et al used BERTje to create vectors instead of pre-processing methods.<xref rid="ooae044-B44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref></p></sec><sec><title>Software</title><p>The studies used different software (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S2</xref>). Most studies used Python (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;11).<xref rid="ooae044-B40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B53" ref-type="bibr"><sup>53&#8211;57</sup></xref> For 4 studies it is unclear which software was used.<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B48" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52</sup></xref> In addition, Javascript or a tool developed for NLP applications, including cTakes, GATE, MedTagger, and CRFSuite were used.<xref rid="ooae044-B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B45" ref-type="bibr"><sup>45</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref></p></sec><sec><title>Methods used to evaluate NLP system performance</title><p>Almost all studies used cross-validation or train-/test datasets to evaluate the NLP system&#8217;s performance (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S2</xref>). Six studies evaluated their NLP system using both cross-validation and train-/test datasets.<xref rid="ooae044-B43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B55" ref-type="bibr"><sup>55</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref> In 4 studies, an expert manually evaluated the performance of the NLP system. Five other studies used solely train-/test datasets (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;5) and 4 other studies only cross-validation (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;4).<xref rid="ooae044-B50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B53" ref-type="bibr"><sup>53</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B54" ref-type="bibr"><sup>54</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B56" ref-type="bibr"><sup>56</sup></xref></p><p>The study by Goudarzvand et al used recent publications to evaluate their NLP system,<xref rid="ooae044-B51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref> which was used for topic modeling&#8212;the only study in our review with this purpose. As topic modeling lacks a gold standard for comparing the outcome of the model with, they validated the results against recent publications to verify whether meaningful outcomes were generated.</p><p>The 3 most frequently reported evaluation metrics for the NLP performance for ADL were the F1 score (or harmonic mean of precision and sensitivity), (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12), precision (or positive predictive value) (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8), and sensitivity (or recall) (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;7). Other primary evaluation metrics reported were accuracy (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;4), area under the curve (AUC) (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;4), Inter-Annotator Agreement (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;3), specificity (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1), negative predictive value (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1), false positive rate (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1), and root-mean-square error (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1).</p></sec><sec><title>Outcomes of the performance evaluation</title><p>More than half of the studies reported relatively high scores for the evaluation metrics (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12),<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47&#8211;50</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52&#8211;54</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B56" ref-type="bibr"><sup>56</sup></xref> indicating good performance by the NLP systems for that dataset and the purpose of the study (<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S2</xref>). This was particularly the case for systems extracting information on ambulating.</p><p>Other studies reported mixed performance outcomes (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;7).<xref rid="ooae044-B40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B45" ref-type="bibr"><sup>45</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B55" ref-type="bibr"><sup>55</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref> Some of the studies showed different outcomes when the results were stratified based on the type of ADL. For instance, Chen et al used a machine-learning model for classifying geriatric syndrome constructs. High scores were obtained for fecal control (F1&#8201;=&#8201;0.857) and walking difficulty (F1&#8201;=&#8201;0.758), but for severe urinary control issues low scores were obtained (F1&#8201;=&#8201;0.532).<xref rid="ooae044-B42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref> Another study by Chen et al applied a deep-learning model for the same constructs and obtained comparably mixed scores.<xref rid="ooae044-B46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref> Humbert-Droz et al found that scores varied depending on the method used to evaluate the NLP system. They evaluated NLP performance by comparing the outcome of the NLP tool with (1) a manual review, (2) structured EHR data, and (3) an external database. The highest scores for sensitivity, positive predictive value, and F1 scores were observed for the manual review, while the lowest scores were found in the comparison with structured EHR data. Humbert-Droz et al pointed out that this does not necessarily reflect the NLP system&#8217;s performance. They encountered several issues with structured EHR data limiting their use as the gold standard in an evaluation.<xref rid="ooae044-B40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref> Furthermore, mixed results were found when different approaches were compared. For example, Yang et al showed higher scores for a combined ruled-based and deep-learning model, compared to the scores for each approach individually. They noted that this hybrid approach was better at leveraging the strengths of each approach and tackling challenges with regard to the dataset, including imbalanced data.<xref rid="ooae044-B57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref></p><p>Authors of the studies in this systematic review identified several limitations concerning the NLP systems they developed. Generalizability to other healthcare sectors, practices, languages, patient groups, or data sources emerged as a significant challenge,<xref rid="ooae044-B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39&#8211;41</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52&#8211;57</sup></xref> as the NLP systems were trained on datasets with specific characteristics. Another major challenge relates to the dataset on which the NLP system is trained and tested. Authors reported issues with small datasets due to factors such as restricted access to relevant EHR data, few amount of notes per patient due to a short hospital stay, or few patients in the study sample.<xref rid="ooae044-B37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B54" ref-type="bibr"><sup>54</sup></xref> In addition, inadequate documentation and lack of granularity were mentioned.<xref rid="ooae044-B41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43&#8211;45</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B54" ref-type="bibr"><sup>54</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Principal findings</title><p>This systematic review provides a comprehensive overview of current research employing NLP to extract information on ADL from unstructured free-text notes in EHRs. Adequate information on ADL is important for care provision and research to ensure that individuals receive the necessary daily support. As information on ADL is often recorded in unstructured free-text EHR notes, NLP could be valuable for deriving this information. We explored 20 NLP systems described in 22 studies. Most studies (65%) utilized NLP for classifying unstructured EHR data on 1 or 2 ADL. Our findings show that a variety of NLP methods, algorithms, and pre-processing steps were used. There was a notable prevalence of deep-learning approaches. The majority of studies using deep learning also applied ruled-based methods or machine learning. Evaluation of the NLP system&#8217;s performance predominantly involved train-/test datasets and cross-validation. The studies included in this review used a wide range of evaluation metrics, including F1, precision, and sensitivity. Despite the variety of NLP approaches and evaluation metrics, most studies reported relativity high overall scores on the evaluation metrics, indicating that the characteristics of the best-performing NLP system depend on study-specific factors.</p><p>The variability in models, approaches, and reporting complicates the direct comparison between the NLP systems and the quest for the best possible method. However, overall, the results of this review indicate that NLP systems are promising for research using unstructured EHR data on ADL for the following reasons.</p><p>First, the field of NLP is developing rapidly. It has evolved from ruled-based methods to machine learning and deep learning. Compared to previous systematic reviews on the use of NLP for unstructured EHR notes, we included relatively more deep-learning approaches.<xref rid="ooae044-B32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> This shows that relatively new deep-learning algorithms, including transformers such as BERT, are being studied for NLP systems to extract information from unstructured clinical notes on ADL.</p><p>To improve the performance of the NLP system, often multiple approaches are compared or combined. Most studies adopted a hybrid approach by combining deep learning with ruled-based or machine-learning algorithms in their final model. The possible benefits of hybrid approaches are also recognized by systematic reviews that focused on the application of NLP in other healthcare domains, including radiology,<xref rid="ooae044-B61" ref-type="bibr"><sup>61</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B62" ref-type="bibr"><sup>62</sup></xref> clinical information in general,<xref rid="ooae044-B31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> and chronic diseases.<xref rid="ooae044-B35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> Hybrid approaches may be better able to address challenges related to the dataset, such as small or imbalanced datasets. Some of the studies included in this review encountered challenges with the datasets arising from how the information was recorded during healthcare provision, such as inadequate recordings or a low level of granularity, or because they did not have access to all relevant EHR data. These challenges are not unique to unstructured data but are also mentioned in the broader literature discussing data quality challenges in the use of EHR data for research (eg,<xref rid="ooae044-B59" ref-type="bibr"><sup>59</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B63" ref-type="bibr"><sup>63</sup></xref>)</p><p>Second, the characteristics of the best-performing NLP system depend on the context in which the dataset is generated, such as different EHR systems and different healthcare organizations. The studies included in this review that retrieved the data directly from an EHR system, rather than from a research database or registry, had access to data from a single organization or from organizations belonging to one medical group. It is expected that the NLP system will perform differently on datasets with other characteristics. NLP systems trained on datasets from multiple sources with different characteristics will have a higher external validity.</p><p>Third, a variety of metrics were used to evaluate the performance of the NLP systems. However, most studies evaluated the performance with train-/test datasets and cross-validation and reported F1 scores. Although the most appropriate evaluation metrics depend on the research aim, F1 scores are commonly valuable in many cases, especially for classification purposes, which was the most prevalent purpose of the NLP systems in this review. Almost all F1 scores exceeded 0.7. This indicates that the methodologies used in developing the NLP systems, considering the characteristics of the specific dataset and research question of the study, are promising for generating information on ADL from unstructured EHR data.</p><sec><title>Strengths, limitations, and recommendations for further research</title><p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first systematic review exploring NLP systems for extracting information on ADL from unstructured EHR data. A strength is that we used a broad search strategy in 5 different literature databases. However, the following limitations should be kept in mind. First, while ambulating and continence were covered by most studies, some ADL were only included in a few NLP systems. More research on NLP systems covering all 6 ADL is recommended. Second, some studies provided limited information on the algorithms, for example with few details on the pre-processing. Future NLP studies should prioritize adequate reporting, as is emphasized in other systematic reviews as well.<xref rid="ooae044-B61" ref-type="bibr"><sup>61</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="ooae044-B64" ref-type="bibr"><sup>64&#8211;66</sup></xref> Third, the field of NLP is developing rapidly. To keep up with the developments, it is recommended to conduct the search again in the near future.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The results of this systematic review indicate that NLP is a promising method for deriving information on ADL from unstructured EHR notes. Various NLP systems are already used in research and show overall good evaluation outcomes. Choosing which NLP system will perform best, depends on the characteristics of the dataset, research question, and type of ADL studied. Since there is no one-size-fits-all method, our findings suggest that research on ADL could benefit from an iterative process in which different NLP approaches are compared or combined based on the performance evaluation outcomes. Future developments in NLP for ADL extraction should focus on addressing generalizability issues and refining evaluation methodologies.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>ooae044_Supplementary_Data</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ooae044_supplementary_data.zip" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p>Mariska G. Oosterveld-Vlug, Robert A. Verheij, Anneke L. Francke, and Yvonne Wieland-Jorna conceptualized and designed this review. Yvonne Wieland-Jorna, Daan van Kooten, Yvonne de Man, and Mariska G. Oosterveld-Vlug screened the literature. Data extraction was performed by Yvonne Wieland-Jorna and Daan van Kooten and checked by Yvonne Wieland-Jorna, Daan van Kooten, Robert A. Verheij, Anneke L. Francke, or Mariska G. Oosterveld-Vlug. Yvonne Wieland-Jorna and Daan van Kooten analyzed the data. Anneke L. Francke and Mariska G. Oosterveld-Vlug supervised and guided the project throughout the process. Yvonne Wieland-Jorna wrote the initial draft of the manuscript. Daan van Kooten contributed to and advised on the NLP aspects of the manuscript. Daan van Kooten, Robert A. Verheij, Anneke L. Francke, and Mariska G. Oosterveld-Vlug reviewed and edited the manuscript. All authors have approved the final version of the manuscript for publication.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary material</title><p>
<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref> is available at <italic toggle="yes">JAMIA Open</italic> online.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>The research described in this paper is part of the &#8220;Learning from Data&#8221; program, funded by the Ministry of Health, Welfare, and Sports in the Netherlands.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>None declared.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Data are available on request.</p></sec><ref-list id="ref1"><title>References</title><ref id="ooae044-B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Arslan</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Damen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>de Wilde</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Incidence and prevalence of knee osteoarthritis using codified and narrative data from electronic health records: a population-based study</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken)</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>937</fpage>-<lpage>944</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/acr.24861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35040591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9325508</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kharrazi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Anzaldi</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>The value of unstructured electronic health record data in geriatric syndrome case identification</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1499</fpage>-<lpage>1507</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgs.15411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29972595</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Scheurwegs</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Luyckx</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Luyten</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Daelemans</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Van den Bulcke</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Data integration of structured and unstructured sources for assigning clinical codes to patient stays</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Inform Assoc</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>e1</issue>):<fpage>e11</fpage>-<lpage>e19</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jamia/ocv115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26316458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4954635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seinen</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kors</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>van Mulligen</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fridgeirsson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rijnbeek</surname><given-names>PR.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The added value of text from Dutch general practitioner notes in predictive modeling</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Inform Assoc</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1973</fpage>-<lpage>1984</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jamia/ocad160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37587084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10654855</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Murdoch</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Detsky</surname><given-names>AS.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The inevitable application of big data to health care</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>309</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>1351</fpage>-<lpage>1352</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2013.393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23549579</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Afrizal</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hidayanto</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Handayani</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Budiharsana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eryando</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Narrative review for exploring barriers to readiness of electronic health record implementation in primary health care</article-title>. <source>Healthc Inform Res</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>141</fpage>-<lpage>152</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31406606</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4258/hir.2019.25.3.141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6689507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rahal</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kuziemsky</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yaya</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Factors affecting the mature use of electronic medical records by primary care physicians: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Inform Decis Mak</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>67</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33607986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12911-021-01434-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7893965</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Skube</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lindemann</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Arsoniadis</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Akre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wick</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Melton</surname><given-names>GB.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Characterizing functional health status of surgical patients in clinical notes</article-title>. <source>AMIA Jt Summits Transl Sci Proc. </source><year>2018</year>;<volume>2017</volume>:<fpage>379</fpage>-<lpage>388</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29888096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5961772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schiltz</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Foradori</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reimer</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Plow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dolansky</surname><given-names>MA.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Availability of information on functional limitations in structured electronic health records data</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2161</fpage>-<lpage>2163</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgs.17776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35383877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9283251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Iezzoni</surname><given-names>LI.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Multiple chronic conditions and disabilities: implications for health services research and data demands</article-title>. <source>Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>5 Pt 2</issue>):<fpage>1523</fpage>-<lpage>1540</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1475-6773.2010.01145.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21054370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2965890</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Edemekong</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bomgaars</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sukumaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schoo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></string-name></person-group><italic toggle="yes">Activities of Daily Living</italic>. StatPearls; <year>2023</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29261878</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hartigan</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>A comparative review of the katz ADL and the barthel index in assessing the activities of daily living of older people</article-title>. <source>Int J Older People Nurs</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>204</fpage>-<lpage>212</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-3743.2007.00074.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20925877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <italic toggle="yes">Towards a Common Language for Functioning, Disability and Health ICF</italic>. Geneva: World Health Organization; <year>2002</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kurtzke</surname><given-names>JF.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Rating neurologic impairment in multiple sclerosis: an expanded disability status scale (EDSS)</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1444</fpage>-<lpage>1452</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/wnl.33.11.1444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6685237</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schag</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ganz</surname><given-names>PA.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Karnofsky performance status revisited: reliability, validity, and guidelines</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>187</fpage>-<lpage>193</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/jco.1984.2.3.187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6699671</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pandit</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Concurrence of big data analytics and healthcare: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Inform</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>114</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2018.03.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29673604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Savova</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pestian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dexheimer</surname><given-names>JW.</given-names></string-name></person-group> Natural language processing: applications in pediatric research. In: Pediatric Biomedical Informatics: Computer Applications in Pediatric Research. Translational Bioinformatics, Vol. 10. Singapore: Springer; <year>2016</year>:<fpage>231</fpage>-<lpage>250</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-981-10-1104-7_12</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bohr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Memarzadeh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group> The rise of artificial intelligence in healthcare applications. In: Artificial Intelligence in Healthcare. <year>2020</year>:<fpage>25</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-818438-7.00002-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Data processing and text mining technologies on electronic medical records: a review</article-title>. <source>J Healthc Eng</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>2018</volume>:<fpage>4302425</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2018/4302425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29849998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5911323</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kannan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gurusamy</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vijayarani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Preprocessing techniques for text mining</article-title>. <source>Int J Comput Sci Commun Netw</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haddi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The role of text pre-processing in sentiment analysis</article-title>. <source>Procedia Comput Sci</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>26</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.procs.2013.05.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Symeonidis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Effrosynidis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Arampatzis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>A comparative evaluation of pre-processing techniques and their interactions for twitter sentiment analysis</article-title>. <source>Expert Syst Appl</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>298</fpage>-<lpage>310</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eswa.2018.06.022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Murty</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Navakanth</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>A detailed review on word embedding techniques with emphasis on word2vec</article-title>. <source>Multimed Tools Appl</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>37979</fpage>-<lpage>38007</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Clinical concept extraction using transformers</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Inform Assoc</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1935</fpage>-<lpage>1942</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33120431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jamia/ocaa189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7727351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shum</surname><given-names>H-Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Progress in neural NLP: modeling, learning, and reasoning</article-title>. <source>Engineering</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>275</fpage>-<lpage>290</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eng.2019.12.014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Altosaar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ranganath</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2019</year>. Clinicalbert: modeling clinical notes and predicting hospital readmission. arXiv, arXiv:1904.05342, preprint: not peer reviewed.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Deep learning in clinical natural language processing: a methodical review</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Inform Assoc</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>457</fpage>-<lpage>470</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31794016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jamia/ocz200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7025365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Velupillai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Suominen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liakata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Using clinical natural language processing for health outcomes research: overview and actionable suggestions for future advances</article-title>. <source>J Biomed Inform</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>19</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbi.2018.10.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30368002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6986921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ghojogh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2019</year>. The theory behind overfitting, cross validation, regularization, bagging, and boosting: tutorial. arXiv, arXiv:1905.12787, preprint: not peer reviewed.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Salman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></string-name></person-group><year>2019</year>. Overfitting mechanism and avoidance in deep neural networks. arXiv, arXiv:1901.06566, preprint: not peer reviewed.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goldwasser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Neural natural language processing for unstructured data in electronic health records: a review</article-title>. <source>Comput Sci Rev</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>100511</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cosrev.2022.100511</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Koleck</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dreisbach</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bourne</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bakken</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Natural language processing of symptoms documented in free-text narratives of electronic health records: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Inform Assoc</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>364</fpage>-<lpage>379</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jamia/ocy173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30726935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6657282</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bernstam</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>A frame semantic overview of NLP-based information extraction for cancer-related EHR notes</article-title>. <source>J Biomed Inform</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>103301</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbi.2019.103301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31589927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11771512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kreimeyer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Natural language processing systems for capturing and standardizing unstructured clinical information: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Biomed Inform</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>14</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbi.2017.07.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28729030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6864736</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sheikhalishahi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miotto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lavelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rinaldi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Osmani</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Natural language processing of clinical notes on chronic diseases: systematic review</article-title>. <source>JMIR Med Inform</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e12239</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/12239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31066697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6528438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liberati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tetzlaff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Group</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>; <collab>PRISMA Group</collab>. <article-title>Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement</article-title>. <source>Ann Int Med</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>151</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>264</fpage>-<lpage>269, W64</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19622511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7326/0003-4819-151-4-200908180-00135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Anzaldi</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leff</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kharrazi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Comparing clinician descriptions of frailty and geriatric syndromes using electronic health records: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>BMC Geriatr</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>248</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12877-017-0645-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29070036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5657074</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kharrazi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leff</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Defining and assessing geriatric risk factors and associated health care utilization among older adults using claims and electronic health records</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>233</fpage>-<lpage>239</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MLR.0000000000000865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29438193</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez-Boussard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kourdis</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Mining electronic health records to extract patient-centered outcomes following prostate cancer treatment</article-title>. <source>AMIA Annu Symp Proc</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>2017</volume>:<fpage>876</fpage>-<lpage>882</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29854154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5977629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Humbert-Droz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Izadi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schmajuk</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Development of a natural language processing system for extracting rheumatoid arthritis outcomes from clinical notes using the national rheumatology informatics system for effectiveness registry</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken)</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>608</fpage>-<lpage>615</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/acr.24869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35157365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leavy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Validation of a machine learning approach to estimate expanded disability status scale scores for multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Mult Scler J Exp Transl Clin</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>20552173221108635</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/20552173221108635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35755008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9228644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dredze</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kharrazi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Extraction of geriatric syndromes from electronic health record clinical notes: assessment of statistical natural language processing methods</article-title>. <source>JMIR Med Inform</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e13039</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/13039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30862607</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6454337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Seneviratne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Weakly supervised natural language processing for assessing patient-centered outcome following prostate cancer treatment</article-title>. <source>JAMIA Open</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>150</fpage>-<lpage>159</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jamiaopen/ooy057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31032481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6482003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Meskers</surname><given-names>CGM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>van der Veen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Automated recognition of functioning, activity and participation in COVID-19 from electronic patient records by natural language processing: a proof- of- concept</article-title>. <source>Ann Med</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>235</fpage>-<lpage>243</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07853890.2021.2025418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35040376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8774059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hayson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Neurologic outcomes of carotid and other emergent interventions for ischemic stroke over 6 years with dataset enhanced by machine learning</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Surg</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>76</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1280</fpage>-<lpage>1288.e2</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvs.2022.06.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35760242</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dredze</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kharrazi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Identifying vulnerable older adult populations by contextualizing geriatric syndrome information in clinical notes of electronic health records</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Inform Assoc</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>8-9</issue>):<fpage>787</fpage>-<lpage>795</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jamia/ocz093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31265063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7647225</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gori</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Extracting patient-centered outcomes from clinical notes in electronic health records: assessment of urinary incontinence after radical prostatectomy</article-title>. <source>EGEMS (Wash DC)</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>43</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5334/egems.297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31497615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6706996</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Newman-Griffis D, Zirikly A. <italic toggle="yes">Embedding Transfer for Low-Resource Medical Named Entity Recognition: A Case Study on Patient Mobility</italic>. Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL); <year>2018</year>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18653/v1/w18-2301</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bozkurt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Coquet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Phenotyping severity of patient-centered outcomes using clinical notes: a prostate cancer use case</article-title>. <source>Learn Health Syst</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e10237</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lrh2.10237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33083539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7556418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Doing-Harris</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thackeray</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Development of a cardiac-centered frailty ontology</article-title>. <source>J Biomed Semantics</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>3</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13326-019-0195-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30658684</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6339414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goudarzvand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>St Sauver</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mielke</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sohn</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Early temporal characteristics of elderly patient cognitive impairment in electronic health records</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Inform Decis Mak</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>Suppl 4</issue>):<fpage>149</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12911-019-0858-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31391041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6686236</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Greve</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bailes</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Gross motor function prediction using natural language processing in cerebral palsy</article-title>. <source>Dev Med Child Neurol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>100</fpage>-<lpage>106</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/dmcn.15301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35665923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9720038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thieu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maldonado</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A comprehensive study of mobility functioning information in clinical notes: entity hierarchy, corpus annotation, and sequence labeling</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Inform</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>147</volume>:<fpage>104351</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2020.104351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33401169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8104034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Newman-Griffis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fosler-Lussier</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Automated coding of under-studied medical concept domains: linking physical activity reports to the international classification of functioning, disability, and health</article-title>. <source>Front Digit Health</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>3</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fdgth.2021.620828</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8009547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33791684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Newman-Griffis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maldonado</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Linking free text documentation of functioning and disability to the ICF with natural language processing</article-title>. <source>Front Rehabil Sci</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>2</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fresc.2021.742702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9180751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35694445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jeng</surname><given-names>JS.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Natural language processing enhances prediction of functional outcome after acute ischemic stroke</article-title>. <source>J Am Heart Assoc</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>e023486</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/jaha.121.023486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34796719</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9075227</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B57"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pou-Prom</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Assessment of natural language processing methods for ascertaining the expanded disability status scale score from the electronic health records of patients With multiple sclerosis: algorithm development and validation study</article-title>. <source>JMIR Med Inform</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e25157</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/25157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35019849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8792771</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B58"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kuchinke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ohmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Verheij</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A standardised graphic method for describing data privacy frameworks in primary care research using a flexible zone model</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Inform</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>941</fpage>-<lpage>957</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25241154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2014.08.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B59"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Verheij</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Curcin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Delaney</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McGilchrist</surname><given-names>MM.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Possible sources of bias in primary care electronic health record data use and reuse</article-title>. <source>J Med Internet Res</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e185</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29844010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2196/jmir.9134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5997930</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B60"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Agaronnik</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lindvall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>El-Jawahri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Iezzoni</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Use of natural language processing to assess frequency of functional status documentation for patients newly diagnosed with colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>JAMA Oncol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1628</fpage>-<lpage>1630</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaoncol.2020.2708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32880603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7489406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B61"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Poon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>A systematic review of natural language processing applied to radiology reports</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Inform Decis Mak</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34082729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12911-021-01533-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8176715</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B62"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Diab</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yesha</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Collado-Mesa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Natural language processing for breast imaging: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Diagnostics</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1420</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37189521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/diagnostics13081420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10137579</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B63"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liaw</surname><given-names>S-T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>JGN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Quality assessment of real-world data repositories across the data life cycle: a literature review</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Inform Assoc</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1591</fpage>-<lpage>1599</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33496785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jamia/ocaa340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8475229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B64"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Deimazar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sheikhtaheri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Machine learning models to detect and predict patient safety events using electronic health records: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Inform</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>180</volume>:<fpage>105246</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2023.105246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37837710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B65"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>C-H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ferdowsi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></string-name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal><article-title>Assessing the efficacy of machine learning algorithms for syncope classification: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>MethodsX</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>102508</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mex.2023.102508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38162148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10755776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ooae044-B66"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sharan</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rahimi-Ardabili</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Detecting acute respiratory diseases in the pediatric population using cough sound features and machine learning: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Inform</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>176</volume>:<fpage>105093</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2023.105093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37224643</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>