<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Hepatol Commun</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Hepatol Commun</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3345</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">hep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HC9</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Hepatology Communications</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2471-254X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10043587</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10043587.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10043587</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10043587</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36972386</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/HC9.0000000000000093</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Medications for alcohol use disorder improve survival in patients with hazardous drinking and alcohol-associated cirrhosis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabiee</surname><given-names initials="A">Anahita</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><email>anahita.rabiee@yale.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmud</surname><given-names initials="N">Nadim</given-names></name><email>nmahmud@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Falker</surname><given-names initials="C">Caroline</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref><email>caroline.falker@yale.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Tsao</surname><given-names initials="G">Guadalupe</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref><email>guadalupe.garcia-tsao@yale.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taddei</surname><given-names initials="T">Tamar</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref><email>tamar.taddei@yale.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names initials="DE">David E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><email>dakaplan@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>Section of Digestive Diseases, Yale School of Medicine, New Haven, Connecticut, USA</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Perelman School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>Gastroenterology Section, Corporal Michael J. Crescenz VA Medical Center, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>VA Connecticut Healthcare System, New Haven, Connecticut, USA</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>Department of Internal Medicine &amp; Program in Addiction Medicine, Yale School of Medicine, New Haven, Connecticut, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp><bold>Correspondence</bold> Anahita Rabiee, 20 York St, New Haven, CT, 06511. Email: <email>anahita.rabiee@yale.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">431680</issue-id><elocation-id>e0093</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>24</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>29</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-03-29 00:10:17.753"><day>29</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. on behalf of the American Association for the Study of Liver Diseases.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0</ext-link> (CCBY-NC-ND), where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially without permission from the journal. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="hc9-7-e0093.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="hc9-7-e0093.pdf"/><abstract><title>Background:</title><p>Medications for alcohol use disorder (MAUD) are highly effective in achieving and maintaining abstinence in patients with alcohol use disorder (AUD). Our aim was to evaluate the effect of MAUD on all-cause mortality in patients with alcohol-associated cirrhosis and active alcohol use.</p><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>This was a retrospective cohort study of patients with alcohol-associated cirrhosis and high-risk alcohol use disorder in the Veterans Outcomes and Costs Associated with Liver Disease (VOCAL) database. Propensity score matching for exposure to MAUD (acamprosate or naltrexone) within a year after cirrhosis diagnosis was performed to account for potential confounders, and the association between MAUD and all-cause mortality was subsequently evaluated using Cox regression analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>A total of 9131 patients were included, of whom 886 (9.7%) were exposed to MAUD (naltrexone: 520, acamprosate: 307, both medications: 59). The duration of MAUD exposure was &gt;3 months in 345 patients (39%). The strongest positive predictor of MAUD prescription was an inpatient diagnosis code for AUD, followed by a concurrent diagnosis of depression; the strongest negative predictor was a history of cirrhosis decompensation. After propensity score matching (866 patients in each group) with excellent covariate balance (absolute standardized mean differences &lt;0.1), MAUD exposure was associated with improved survival, with an HR of 0.80 relative to no MAUD exposure (95% CI: 0.67&#8211;0.97, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.024).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>MAUD are underutilized in patients with alcohol-associated cirrhosis with high-risk alcohol use behavior but are associated with improved survival after adjustment for confounders such as the severity of liver disease, age, and engagement in the healthcare system.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical"><p>
<fig position="float" id="GA1" orientation="portrait"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="hc9-7-e0093-g001.jpg"/></fig>
</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Alcohol use disorder (AUD) is a major contributor to liver disease. Complete abstinence from alcohol is associated with improved survival and is currently the mainstay of treatment for alcohol-associated liver disease and alcohol-associated cirrhosis (ArC). Continued alcohol consumption among patients with ArC increases the risk of decompensation, acute alcohol-associated hepatitis, HCC, and death.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> The death rate from ArC has been rising in the US and spiked during the COVID-19 pandemic.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Not surprisingly, ArC remains among the leading indications for liver transplantation.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
</p><p>Medication for alcohol use disorder (MAUD) are highly effective in achieving and maintaining abstinence in patients with AUD.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Food and Drug Administration (FDA)-approved MAUD options include disulfiram, acamprosate, and naltrexone. In addition, non&#8211;FDA-approved medications such as gabapentin, baclofen, and topiramate have been used off-label with varying degrees of success.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> However, none of these medications are currently approved for use in patients with ArC. Patients with liver disease have largely been excluded from randomized trials of MAUD due to concerns regarding altered drug metabolism and/or potential hepatotoxicity. Among FDA-approved MAUD, disulfiram is highly hepatotoxic and contraindicated in patients with cirrhosis. In contrast, acamprosate and naltrexone have been used in patients with ArC.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Baclofen has specifically been studied in ArC,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> however, a recent meta-analysis of 14 randomized trials found no benefit versus placebo.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Furthermore, there are safety concerns related to baclofen use (eg, sedation and drowsiness)<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> which has limited its utility in clinical practice.</p><p>MAUD are vastly underutilized in patients with AUD in the US. A study of Veterans showed that among &#8764;250,000 patients with AUD, only about 3% received MAUD.<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> MAUD are even more underutilized in the alcohol-associated liver disease population with only 1.4% receiving pharmacotherapy<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> despite evidence that behavioral therapy, pharmacotherapy, or a combination thereof effectively decreases the risk of hepatic decompensation and liver-related mortality.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> Not only are FDA-approved MAUD potentially effective in ArC, recent data suggest these therapies are cost-effective and potentially cost-saving by preventing hepatic decompensation.<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
</p><p>Current literature evaluating the role of FDA-approved MAUD in patients with cirrhosis is extremely limited. In the 2 large prior studies assessing treatments in patients with ArC, 88% and 99% of the treatment groups received behavioral therapy alone.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Although behavioral therapy is an important and effective treatment, it is more resource-intensive and not accessible to many patients for various reasons (limited availability, insurance coverage, patient engagement, etc.). In contrast, MAUD can be prescribed easily in a clinical setting by primary care providers, hepatologists, or gastroenterologists; are more likely to be covered by insurance; and are more accessible to patients in resource-limited areas. In the above-mentioned cost analysis, counseling was costlier relative to acamprosate and naltrexone and provided fewer quality-adjusted life years<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>; however, a specific and focused demonstration of the role of FDA-approved MAUD remains lacking. Existing literature is further limited by healthy user bias and confounded by selective prescribing<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> in which healthier patients are more likely to receive MAUD than those with more advanced comorbidities or manifestations of cirrhosis.<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
</p><p>We aimed to retrospectively study the use of FDA-approved MAUD in a large nationwide cohort of Veterans with ArC and AUD. We first evaluated the pattern, incidence, and factors associated with receipt of these medications in the first year after diagnosis of cirrhosis. Second, we evaluated the effect of MAUD prescription in the first year after diagnosis of cirrhosis on all-cause mortality controlling for healthy user biases.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>METHODS</title><sec><title>Data sources</title><p>The Veterans Outcomes and Costs Associated with Liver Disease (VOCAL) cohort is an established time-updating dataset derived from the Veterans Affairs (VA) Corporate Data Warehouse (CDW). Approval for this study was obtained from the institutional review boards at all participating VA sites. Veterans enrolled in VA care with a diagnosis of cirrhosis who exhibited hazardous/high-risk drinking were studied from 2008 to 2021. The diagnosis of cirrhosis was based on a previously validated methodology using the International Classification of Diseases (ICD), versions 9 or 10 diagnosis codes,<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> and required 1 inpatient ICD code or 2 outpatient ICD codes.</p><p>Patients were included if they had (1) hazardous/high-risk drinking based on an Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test-Concise (AUDIT-C) score &#8805;8 in the year before the diagnosis of cirrhosis, (2) diagnosis of AUD in the year before the diagnosis of cirrhosis (defined as 1 inpatient or 2 outpatient ICD 9&#8211;10 codes), and (3) diagnosis of ArC (with or without concomitant chronic HCV infection). Patients were excluded for the following reasons: (1) death or loss to follow-up within the first year after diagnosis of cirrhosis, (2) use of MAUD in the year before the diagnosis of cirrhosis, (3) age below 18 years or above 90 years at the time of diagnosis of cirrhosis, or (4) history of a prior liver transplant.</p><p>AUDIT-C score cutoff of 8 was chosen to maximize specificity (&gt;95% specificity for AUD).<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> In addition, as per VA guidelines, AUDIT-C &#8805;8 requires a more formal treatment plan such as referral to specialty care or pharmacotherapy, while a brief advice/intervention is acceptable in case of a positive screening test (AUDIT-C &#8805;4 for men and &#8805;3 for women).<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Our goal was to focus on the group with the highest risk, who would potentially benefit from pharmacotherapy.</p></sec><sec><title>Exposure</title><p>The primary exposure was new initiation of acamprosate or oral naltrexone, 2 FDA-approved MAUD for AUD. Outpatient pharmacy fills were queried in 30-day windows since diagnosis of cirrhosis. If patients received these medications for at least 7 days in each 30-day window, they were considered as exposed in that window. Other MAUD that are not FDA approved such as baclofen, gabapentin, and topiramate were not studied due to lack of specificity of treatment indication and disulfiram was not included due to known hepatotoxicity.</p></sec><sec><title>Covariates</title><p>Demographics including age, sex, race, and key comorbidities were obtained for each patient. Baseline laboratory values were extracted closest to the index date of cirrhosis diagnosis, obtained between 180 days before or 30 days after the diagnosis code(s). Throughout the follow-up period, median laboratory values in each quarter were used to generate time-updating measures of liver disease severity such as the Model of End-Stage Liver Disease-Sodium (MELD-Na).<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Liver disease etiology was assigned per the schema of Beste et al.<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
</p><p>Depression and substance use disorder (other than alcohol or tobacco) were identified from 1 year before the diagnosis of cirrhosis. Depression and substance use disorder each were defined as 1 inpatient or 2 outpatient ICD codes consistent with published validated algorithms.<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> These diagnoses were also evaluated as time-updating variables, and once established, were carried forward in subsequent time periods.</p><p>AUDIT-C scores performed at the VA in the year before diagnosis of cirrhosis were collected. If a patient had 2 AUDIT-C scores in the year before the diagnosis of cirrhosis, the higher score was used.</p></sec><sec><title>Outcome</title><p>All-cause mortality was ascertained using the Vital Status Master File.<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Patients were right censored at the time of transplant or at the maximum follow-up date.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>To evaluate trends in MAUD use over time, we plotted the absolute number and proportion of MAUD versus non-MAUD users by calendar year. Next, to account for possible confounding related to the decision to initiate MAUD, we used a propensity score&#8211;matching approach. We computed the standardized mean difference (SMD) between MAUD and non-MAUD users for all baseline covariates; variables with an SMD &gt;0.1 were entered into a logistic regression model with MAUD exposure as the outcome. This model was used to generate propensity scores for the probability of receiving the exposure. Propensity score matching was then performed to match cases and controls 1:1 using the nearest neighbor method and a caliper of 0.05 without replacement. SMDs in the matched cohort were computed to ensure that all SMDs were &lt;0.1, representing excellent covariate balance.</p><p>To evaluate the association between MAUD use and all-cause mortality while avoiding immortal time bias, we used an intention-to-treat landmark survival analysis approach. Exposure was considered from diagnosis of cirrhosis to 1-year follow-up. The start time was considered 1 year after diagnosis of cirrhosis for all patients (time zero). Follow-up occurred until death (primary outcome), or date of last follow-up (censored) or transplant (censored). The association between MAUD exposure in the year after diagnosis of cirrhosis and all-cause mortality was estimated using Cox proportional hazards regression in the propensity-matched cohort. A secondary analysis was also performed by moving the landmark to 6 months rather than 1 year. For this analysis, exposure was re-defined as MAUD in the first 6 months after diagnosis of cirrhosis, follow-up started at 6 months after diagnosis of cirrhosis, and only patients who died in the first 6 months (before landmark) were excluded. We also performed an as-treated analysis, evaluating the association of time-updating MAUD exposure using marginal structural models<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> and time-updating Cox proportional hazards models in the propensity-matched cohort, adjusting for time-updating diagnosis of depression, time-updating age, and time-updating decompensation status. The Kaplan-Meier analysis was used to evaluate the association between MAUD exposure and survival. To evaluate for dose-response, we evaluated the effects of categorical durations of MAUD exposure in the first year on mortality. Although there is no optimal duration for MAUD, a minimum of 3 months has been recommended for treatment with naltrexone and acamprosate; however, many recommend continuing these medications for a full year as the risk of recurrence is highest during this time.<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Therefore, we used 3 months as the cutoff to determine the categorical duration (&lt;3&#160;mo vs. 3&#8211;12&#160;mo). We also explored differential survival in patients receiving naltrexone versus acamprosate. Multivariable Cox proportional hazard and Kaplan-Meier analyses were performed using the <italic toggle="yes">survival</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">survminer</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">ggplot2</italic> packages in R.<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Patient characteristics</title><p>After the application of selection criteria (Figure <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), 9131 patients were included in the analytic cohort, of whom 886 (9.7%) received at least 7 days of MAUD in the year after diagnosis of cirrhosis. Patients were predominantly male (98%) and White (65%), with a mean age of 58.5 years.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Identification and selection of cases and controls. Abbreviations: AUD, alcohol use disorder; AUDIT-C, Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test-Concise; MAUD, medications for alcohol use disorder (including acamprosate and/or naltrexone).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="hc9-7-e0093-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Temporal use of MAUD</title><p>Overall, MAUD utilization increased between 2008 and 2020 (Figure <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>); the lowest rate was 4% in 2009 and 2010 and the highest rates were after 2017 (ranging between 16% and 23%). Of the 886 patients receiving MAUD, 520 (59%) were started on naltrexone, 307 (35%) on acamprosate, and 59 (7%) had exposure to both medications. Patients receiving acamprosate and naltrexone were similar except that acamprosate was used more frequently among patients with more advanced liver disease (Supplementary Table 1, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/HC9/A191" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/HC9/A191</ext-link>). The duration of MAUD exposure was &#8804;3 months in 541 (61%), and &gt;3 months in 345 (39%). Among patients on naltrexone, 37% received it for &gt;3 months, and among those on acamprosate, 32% had &gt;3 months of exposure (although not all exposures were continuous).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Temporal changes in MAUD prescription patterns. (A) Among the total number of patients diagnosed with alcohol-associated cirrhosis with hazardous drinking (defined as AUDIT-C score &#8805;8 and diagnosis of alcohol use disorder) in the years 2008&#8211;2019, the number of MAUD exposed (including acamprosate and/or naltrexone) (dark gray) are shown. (B) A fraction of patients who received MAUD among patients diagnosed with alcohol-associated cirrhosis with hazardous drinking (defined as AUDIT-C score &#8805;8 and diagnosis of alcohol use disorder) in the years 2008&#8211;2019 are shown. Abbreviations: AUDIT-C, Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test-Concise; MAUD, medications for alcohol use disorder</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="hc9-7-e0093-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Factors associated with receipt of MAUD</title><p>At baseline, patients who received MAUD tended to be younger (53.7 vs. 58.6&#160;y, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), more often White (72% vs. 65%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), less likely to have cirrhosis decompensation at baseline (18% vs. 30%; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and less likely to have concurrent hepatitis C (25% vs. 32%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). Hospitalization for AUD (80% vs. 62%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) was associated with MAUD prescription, as were higher baseline AUDIT-C scores (11 vs. 10.5, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). Patients prescribed MAUD also tended to have a higher prevalence of depression and substance use disorder in the year before the diagnosis of cirrhosis (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, left panel).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Baseline patient characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="3" axis="1">Actual cohort</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="3" axis="1">Propensity score&#8211;matched cohort</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No MAUD [n (%)]</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAUD [n (%)]</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMD</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No MAUD [n (%)]</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAUD [n (%)]</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8245</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">886</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">866</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">866</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="7">Demographics</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Age [mean (SD)]</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>59 (9)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>54 (10)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.517</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (11)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (10)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.059</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Sex (male)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8061 (98)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">851 (96)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.099</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">831 (96)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">832 (96)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="7">Race</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Black</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1501 (18)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>111 (13)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.165</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 (13)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111 (13)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Other</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1396 (17)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>144 (16)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135 (16)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142 (16)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;White</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5348 (65)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>631 (72)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">621 (72)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">613 (71)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="7">Tobacco</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Current smoker</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3842 (47)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">396 (45)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">418 (49)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">385 (45)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Former smoker</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2316 (28)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">240 (27)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229 (27)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">235 (27)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Never smoker</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2000 (24)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241 (27)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210 (25)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">237 (28)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="7">Etiology</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Alcohol and hepatitis C</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2672 (32)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>225 (25)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.155</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220 (25)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222 (26)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Alcohol</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5573 (68)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>661 (75)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">646 (75)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">644 (74)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI [mean (SD)]</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3 (5.6)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.8 (5.6)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.095</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (6)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (6)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year of cirrhosis diagnosis [mean (SD)]</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2013.7 (3.4)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2015.6 (3.1)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.584</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015.8 (3.2)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015.6 (3.1)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic center</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4776 (58)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">532 (60)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">504 (58)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">526 (61)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="7">Severity of AUD</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;AUDIT-C score [mean (SD)]</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10.5 (1.4)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>11 (1.3)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.421</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (1.3)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (1.3)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Inpatient AUD ICD code</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5133 (62)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>707 (80)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.394</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">673 (78)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">688 (79)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="7">Severity of liver disease</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;MELD-Na [mean (SD)]</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>11.86 (5.95)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10.92 (5.58)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.162</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (6)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (5.6)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Decompensated</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2456 (30)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>163 (18)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.269</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154 (18)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162 (19)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Total bilirubin [mean (SD)]</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94 (2.89)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93 (2.81)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 (3)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 (2.8)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Platelet count [mean (SD)]</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">171 (93)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">171 (86)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180 (95)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">171 (86)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Jaundice</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1192 (15)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135 (15)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 (14)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">132(15)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="7">Psychiatric comorbidities</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;History of depression in the year before diagnosis of cirrhosis</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3212 (39)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>536 (60)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.441</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">516 (60)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">518 (60)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;History of substance use disorder in the year before diagnosis of cirrhosis</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2709 (33)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>394 (44)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.24</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">395 (46)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">381 (44)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="7">Medical comorbidities</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Hypertension</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7918 (96)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">855 (97)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">830 (96)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">836 (97)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Heart failure</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2006 (24)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>135 (15)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.23</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 (14)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135 (16)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Chronic kidney disease</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1619 (20)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>110 (12)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.198</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 (13)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 (13)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3480 (42)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">333 (38)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.095</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">346 (40)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">330 (38)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Diabetes</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3334 (40)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">351 (40)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">292 (34)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">344 (40)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="7">Other medications at baseline/involvement in care</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Gabapentin</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1153 (14)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>215 (24)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.264</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222 (26)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208 (24)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Topiramate</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (0.8)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (1.6)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (1)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (2)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Baclofen</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104 (1.3)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (2)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (2)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (2)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. outpatient visits in the year before diagnosis of cirrhosis [mean (SD)]</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9 (16)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>14 (24)</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.2543</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (22)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (24)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Values with SMD &gt;0.1 are shown in bold.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Abbreviations: AUD, alcohol use disorder; AUDIT-C, Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test-Concise; BMI, body mass index; ICD, International Classification of Diseases; MAUD, medications for alcohol use disorder MELD-Na, Model for End-Stage Liver Disease-Sodium; SMD, standardized mean difference.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In multivariable regression modeling the variables most strongly associated with receipt of MAUD included inpatient diagnosis code for AUD (OR: 1.82, 95% CI: 1.52&#8211;2.18, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), depression (OR: 1.68, 95% CI: 1.44&#8211;1.97, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and White versus Black race (OR: 1.5, 95% CI: 1.2&#8211;1.87, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). The presence of cirrhosis decompensation was inversely associated with MAUD prescription (OR: 0.68, 95% CI: 0.56&#8211;0.82, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) (Figure <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Baseline factors associated with receiving MAUD; OR and 95% CI for receiving MAUD (including acamprosate and/or naltrexone) in the first year after diagnosis of alcohol-associated cirrhosis in patients with hazardous drinking (defined as AUDIT-C score &#8805;8 and diagnosis of AUD). Abbreviations: AUD, alcohol use disorder; AUDIT-C, Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test-Concise; MAUD, medications for alcohol use disorder MELD-Na, Model for End-Stage Liver Disease-Sodium.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="hc9-7-e0093-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Association between MAUD and all-cause mortality</title><p>After the application of propensity score matching, excellent covariate balance was achieved between MAUD and non-MAUD groups, as evidenced by covariate SMDs &lt;0.1 (Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, right panel).</p><p>A total of 866 patients remained in the 1:1 matched cohort. Over a median (interquartile range) follow-up time of 2.2 years (1&#8211;4.3) in the matched control, and 2.5 years (1.2&#8211;4.5) in the MAUD group (starting at 1&#160;y after diagnosis of cirrhosis per inclusion criteria), 435 patients died (233 in control, and 202 in treatment). In Kaplan-Meier analysis using an intention-to-treat approach, MAUD exposure was associated with reduced all-cause mortality (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.024) (Figure <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>(A) Kaplan-Meier analysis comparing the survival curve among patients who received MAUD in the first year after diagnosis of cirrhosis versus the propensity score&#8211;matched controls. (B) Kaplan-Meier analysis comparing the survival curve among patients who did not receive MAUD received 3 months or less, or &gt;3 months, in the first year after diagnosis of cirrhosis in the propensity score&#8211;matched cohort. Abbreviation: MAUD, medications for alcohol use disorder.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="hc9-7-e0093-g005.jpg"/></fig><p>In intention-to-treat Cox regression analysis in the propensity-matched cohorts, MAUD use in the first year after cirrhosis diagnosis was associated with a 20% reduced hazard of all-cause mortality (HR: 0.80, 95% CI: 0.67&#8211;0.97, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.024). In an as-treated analysis in the propensity-matched cohort incorporating time-updating MAUD exposure and adjusting for time-updating depression diagnosis, age, and decompensation status, MAUD use was associated with a 68% reduced hazard of all-cause mortality (HR: 0.32, 95% CI: 0.18&#8211;0.59, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001; Figure <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F5" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p>(A) Forest plot showing HR and 95% CI of time-updating variable in cox regression analysis for prediction of all-cause mortality. (B) Forest plot showing HR and 95% CI of baseline factors and different medication types (acamprosate vs. naltrexone) in cox regression analysis for prediction of all-cause mortality. Abbreviations: ACAMP, acamprosate; AIC, Akaike Information Criterion; EtOH, alcohol; MAUD, medication for alcohol use disorder; MELD-Na, Model for End-Stage Liver Disease-Sodium; NAL, naltrexone ***: &lt;0.001; **: &lt;0.01; *: &lt;0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="hc9-7-e0093-g006.jpg"/></fig><p>In the secondary analysis, after moving the landmark to 6 months, the number of patients meeting the eligibility criteria who received MAUD decreased by 25%, and there was no statistically significant difference in the mortality among groups (data not shown).</p></sec><sec><title>Association between duration of MAUD exposure and all-cause mortality</title><p>After dividing the patients with MAUD exposure into &#8804;3 months (529 patients) and 3&#8211;12 months categories (337 patients), longer duration of exposure was associated with improved survival in the propensity-matched cohort: HR: 0.85 for &#8804;3 months versus no MAUD (95% CI: 0.69&#8211;1.05, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.135) and HR: 0.73 for 3&#8211;12 months versus no MAUD (95% CI: 0.56&#8211;0.96, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.022) (Figure <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Comparison of naltrexone and acamprosate</title><p>The baseline characteristics of patients receiving naltrexone versus acamprosate are shown in Supplemental Table 1 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/HC9/A191" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/HC9/A191</ext-link>). In general, patients on acamprosate had more severe liver disease (higher MELD, decompensation, jaundice) as compared with patients on naltrexone. In Cox models comparing naltrexone and acamprosate, adjusting for baseline MELD, decompensation status, and etiology, there were no differences in terms of mortality (Figure <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The primary finding of our study was that MAUD exposure was associated with improved all-cause mortality. Our rationale for looking at all-cause mortality rather than liver-related mortality alone was 2-fold. First, patients with ArC are also affected by nonhepatic morbidities related to alcohol use, including cancer risk, falls, and motor vehicle accidents, which are important potential contributors to death that could plausibly be impacted by MAUD. Second, the adjudication of liver-related mortality in large databases is inherently challenging, whereas all-cause mortality is a well-validated outcome in the VA.<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Although prospective studies are warranted to validate our findings, the results in our study argue for a potentially causal association between MAUD use and improved survival. The observed protective effect was maintained in both intention-to-treat and time-updating analyses after careful propensity score matching to comprehensively balance potential confounders. Moreover, we identified a dose-response effect where longer durations of MAUD exposure were associated with further improved survival. The chronicity of AUD and high relapse rates mandates long-term interventions.<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> The magnitude of the effect size with MAUD use was highest in time-updating analysis, showing that in the 30-day window patients were actively receiving MAUD, they were less likely to die compared with matched patients not on MAUD during that 30-day window (HR: 0.3). A potential mechanism of this finding is that MAUD assists patients with high-risk drinking to remain abstinent from alcohol, reduce episodes of binge drinking, and/or minimize alcohol intake overall. This may not only prevent the progression of liver disease and decompensation but may also decrease mortality from nonhepatic causes through improved engagement in healthcare and other treatments, medications, and surveillance recommendations.</p><p>In our secondary analysis, once the landmark was moved to 6 months rather than 1 year after diagnosis of cirrhosis, the mortality among groups was not statistically different. This could be related to a 25% decrease in sample size, potentially losing power to demonstrate a difference. Alternatively, this phenomenon could be attributed to the greater inclusion of patients with very poor prognosis who might not benefit from MAUD. Future prospective studies are needed to better understand that subpopulations of patients that would benefit most from these medications.</p><p>There were no differences between acamprosate and naltrexone in terms of survival after adjusting for the severity of the liver disease. Acamprosate is dosed 3 times daily which may decrease compliance, as shown in previous studies.<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> We saw a similar trend with 37% of patients on naltrexone and 32% of patients on acamprosate remaining on these medications for &gt;3 months which was not a statistically significant difference.</p><p>Naltrexone and acamprosate have been shown in randomized trials as well as systematic reviews to improve alcohol-associated outcomes including time to relapse, drinking days, and number of drinks per drinking day. This effect is preserved even when delivered alone without behavioral therapy.<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Previous studies looking at barriers to MAUD prescription cite the main reasons as lack of provider and patient confidence in the effectiveness of AUD medications along with inadequate training.<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>
</p><p>Our work provides evidence regarding the utility of MAUD in patients with liver disease. These treatments not only have the benefit of improving patient outcomes but would also be expected to yield cost savings to healthcare systems from both liver and non&#8211;liver-related comorbidities associated with alcohol use and accidental injuries from heavy drinking. If providers have improved training to prescribe MAUD, these medications also represent a readily scalable treatment for AUD in contrast to more resource-intensive cognitive behavioral interventions. This is especially important given the shortage of mental health and addiction care providers in the US.<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> Our study along with previous work done in this area can help provide the foundation to educate providers, both primary care and hepatologists, regarding the efficacy and overall safety of these medications.</p><p>Despite increased prescription since 2008, MAUD remains vastly underutilized in patients with ArC. Factors associated with a higher likelihood of prescription included an inpatient diagnosis of AUD, concurrent depression, or concomitant substance use diagnosis. Similar associations were observed in Rieckmann et al<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> in which patients with AUD with a dual diagnosis of depression and/or anxiety were more likely to receive MAUD. This strong association could stem from greater engagement with healthcare in general, but more likely reflects greater exposure specifically to behavioral health and addiction care services.</p><p>Interestingly, patients with concurrent AUD and hepatitis C were less likely to receive these medications compared with patients with alcohol alone as the etiology of liver disease. Lower utilization in chronic hepatitis C patients may suggest hesitancy on behalf of providers to offer these medications due to concerns of added hepatotoxicity or under-treatment of AUDs while focusing on HCV antiviral therapy. Concerns related to the hepatotoxicity of MAUD are further corroborated by the lower likelihood of MAUD prescription in patients with more advanced liver disease (higher MELD-Na and/or prior hepatic decompensations).</p><p>It is also important to note that in our study, Black patients were less likely to receive MAUD compared with White patients or patients of other races. Similar disparities between racial/ethnic groups have been reported in the prescription of MAUD for AUD, especially when comparing Blacks with Whites<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> While outside the scope of the current study, these disparities are of paramount concern and warrant further investigation to identify and address potential barriers.</p><p>Inpatient admission with AUD at the time of diagnosis of cirrhosis was the variable most strongly associated with MAUD prescription. An inpatient admission provides an opportunity for intervention, as these patients are very likely to undergo detoxification during admission and be started on these medications on discharge. Prior studies have shown that the best abstinence outcomes can be achieved with acamprosate after detoxification,<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> and compliance with naltrexone is also likely higher once patients have already stopped active drinking.</p><p>Our observational study has some limitations. First, despite our best efforts to match the patients who received MAUD to those who did not, there is the possibility of imperfect matching and residual confounding. It is possible that patients who are receiving MAUD are more compliant with follow-up, medication adherence, completing age-appropriate cancer screening, etc. However, it could be argued that MAUD may mediate improved healthcare engagement through the minimization of hazardous alcohol use. For this reason, we included a number of outpatient visits in the year before the diagnosis of cirrhosis in our matching process to account for differences in engagement with care at baseline. However we did not account for inpatient or outpatient substance and alcohol use treatments and behavioral therapy during follow-up, and it is plausible that patients receiving MAUD were more likely to also receive concurrent behavioral treatments. Second, our population might not be generalizable to the general US population, as it consisted of mostly male US Veterans. Third, we were not able to assess MAUD compliance, as patients might have been prescribed MAUD but did not take them. However, this would be expected to bias results towards the null hypothesis, and thus the estimates provided in this study may in fact be conservative. Fourth, we did not specifically look at MAUD-related side effects, but it appears that the net benefit still resulted in improved survival, and the potential side effects associated with these medications are likely negligible in contrast to the risk of drinking in patients with liver disease. Last, choosing landmark analysis to address immortal time biases inevitably resulted in the exclusion of patients who died within the first year, shifting the population towards healthier patients.</p><p>Despite these limitations, our study has major strengths. This is one of the largest studies to demonstrate, in a large cohort of US Veterans with ArC, a survival benefit of MAUD after careful matching for potential confounders. The findings should encourage the use of MAUD in patients with ArC.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>MAUD are underutilized in patients with ArC with high-risk alcohol use behavior. There are multiple factors that affect the likelihood of being prescribed MAUD, such as an inpatient diagnosis code for AUD and a history of depression. When utilized, MAUD are associated with improved survival after comprehensive adjustment for confounders such as the severity of liver disease, age, and engagement in the healthcare system, with longer duration of use associated with increased survival benefit.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><fig id="s001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="hc9-7-e0093-s001.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></fig></sec></body><back><ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>CONFLICT OF INTEREST</title><p>The authors have no conflicts to report.</p></sec></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>
<bold>Abbreviations:</bold> ArC, Alcohol-associated Cirrhosis; AUD, Alcohol Use Disorder; AUDIT-C, Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test-Concise; CDW, Corporate Data Warehouse; FDA, Food and Drug Administration; ICD, International Classification of Diseases; MAUD, Medications for alcohol use disorder; MELD-Na, Model of End-Stage Liver Disease-Sodium; SMD, standardized mean difference; VA, Veterans Affairs; VOCAL, Veterans Outcomes and Costs Associated with Liver Disease.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lackner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spindelboeck</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haybaeck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Douschan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rainer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Terracciano</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Histological parameters and alcohol abstinence determine long-term prognosis in patients with alcoholic liver disease</article-title>. <source>J Hepatol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>610</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>618</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27894795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jhep.2016.11.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altamirano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#243;pez-Pelayo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michelena</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gin&#232;s</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Alcohol abstinence in patients surviving an episode of alcoholic hepatitis: Prediction and impact on long-term survival</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>1842</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1853</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28646515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hep.29338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mandayam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jamal</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Alcohol and hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>127</volume>:<fpage>S87</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>S96</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15508108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.gastro.2004.09.020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tapper</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mortality due to cirrhosis and liver cancer in the United States, 1999-2016: observational study</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>362</volume>:<fpage>k2817</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30021785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmj.k2817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6050518</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bittermann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmud</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Trends in liver transplantation for acute alcohol-associated hepatitis during the COVID-19 pandemic in the US</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e2118713</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34323988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.18713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8322991</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vittinghoff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dodge</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cullaro</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Terrault</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>National trends and long-term outcomes of liver transplant for alcohol-associated liver disease in the United States</article-title>. <source>JAMA Intern Med</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>179</volume>:<fpage>340</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30667468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamainternmed.2018.6536</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6439700</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amick</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feltner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bobashev</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wines</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacotherapy for adults with alcohol use disorders in outpatient settings: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>311</volume>:<fpage>1889</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24825644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2014.3628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reus</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fochtmann</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bukstein</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eyler</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilty</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horvitz-Lennon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The American Psychiatric Association Practice Guideline for the pharmacological treatment of patients with alcohol use disorder</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>175</volume>:<fpage>86</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29301420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1176/appi.ajp.2017.1750101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Addolorato</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirijello</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leggio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrulli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Landolfi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Management of alcohol dependence in patients with liver disease</article-title>. <source>CNS Drugs</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>287</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>299</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23456576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40263-013-0043-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4979989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Addolorato</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leggio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrulli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cardone</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vonghia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirijello</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness and safety of baclofen for maintenance of alcohol abstinence in alcohol-dependent patients with liver cirrhosis: randomised, double-blind controlled study</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>370</volume>:<fpage>1915</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1922</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18068515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(07)61814-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bschor</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henssler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#252;ller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baethge</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Baclofen for alcohol use disorder-a systematic meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Acta Psychiatr Scand</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>138</volume>:<fpage>232</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>242</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29888478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/acps.12905</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaignot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zureik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dray-Spira</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coste</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weill</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of hospitalisation and death related to baclofen for alcohol use disorders: Comparison with nalmefene, acamprosate, and naltrexone in a cohort study of 165 334 patients between 2009 and 2015 in France</article-title>. <source>Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1239</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1248</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30251424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pds.4635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6282718</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>AHS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kivlahan</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacotherapy of alcohol use disorders in the Veterans Health Administration</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Serv</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>392</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>398</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20360279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1176/ps.2010.61.4.392</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Youk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gellad</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fine</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Good</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of alcohol use disorder treatment on clinical outcomes among patients with cirrhosis</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>2080</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2092</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31758811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hep.31042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8032461</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vannier</surname><given-names>AGL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shay</surname><given-names>JES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fomin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Incidence and progression of alcohol-associated liver disease after medical therapy for alcohol use disorder</article-title>. <source>JAMA Netw Open</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e2213014</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35594048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.13014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9123494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Avance&#241;a</surname><given-names>ALV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uttal</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mellinger</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cost-effectiveness of alcohol use treatments in patients with alcohol-associated cirrhosis</article-title>. <source>J Hepatol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>1286</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1294</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33326815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jhep.2020.12.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8177741</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mellinger</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shedden</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winder</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fontana</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Volk</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Gender disparities in alcohol use disorder treatment among privately insured patients with alcohol-associated cirrhosis</article-title>. <source>Alcohol Clin Exp Res</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>334</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>341</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30667521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/acer.13944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6379081</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serper</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aytaman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of hypercholesterolemia and statin exposure on survival in a large national cohort of patients with cirrhosis</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>156</volume>:<fpage>1693</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1706.e12</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30660733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.gastro.2019.01.026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davila</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Serag</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The validity of viral hepatitis and chronic liver disease diagnoses in Veterans Affairs administrative databases: Liver Disease Codes Validation Study</article-title>. <source>Aliment Pharmacol Ther</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>274</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>282</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17996017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2036.2007.03572.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubinsky</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative performance of the AUDIT-C in screening for DSM-IV and DSM-5 alcohol use disorders</article-title>. <source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>384</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>388</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22728044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2012.05.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3469743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>US Departmnet of Veterans Affairs</collab>. <comment>VA/DoD clinical practice guideline for the management of substance use disorders; 2015</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aytaman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baytarian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Development and performance of an algorithm to estimate the Child-Turcotte-Pugh Score from a National Electronic Healthcare Database</article-title>. <source>Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>2333</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2341.e6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26188137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cgh.2015.07.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4655141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamath</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A model to predict survival in patients with end-stage liver disease</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>464</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>470</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11172350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/jhep.2001.22172</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beste</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leipertz</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dominitz</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ioannou</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Trends in burden of cirrhosis and hepatocellular carcinoma by underlying liver disease in US Veterans, 2001&#8211;2013</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>149</volume>:<fpage>1471</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1482.e5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26255044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.gastro.2015.07.056</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trivedi</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Post</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pomerantz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saxon</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piette</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence, comorbidity, and prognosis of mental health among US Veterans</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>2564</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2569</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26474009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2105/AJPH.2015.302836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4638236</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sohn</surname><given-names>M-W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maynard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hynes</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Accuracy and completeness of mortality data in the Department of Veterans Affairs</article-title>. <source>Popul Health Metr</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16606453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1478-7954-4-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1458356</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism</collab>. <comment>Helping patients who drink too much: a clinician&#8217;s guide; 2007</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anton</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Naltrexone for the management of alcohol dependence</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>359</volume>:<fpage>715</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>721</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18703474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMct0801733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2565602</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Therneau</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group>. <comment>A package for survival analysis in S. R package version 2.37-7; 2014</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moos</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moos</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rates and predictors of relapse after natural and treated remission from alcohol use disorders</article-title>. <source>Addiction</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>212</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>222</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16445550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1360-0443.2006.01310.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1976118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morley</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Logge</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>S-A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baillie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>National trends in alcohol pharmacotherapy: findings from an Australian claims database</article-title>. <source>Drug Alcohol Depend</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>166</volume>:<fpage>254</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>257</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27394934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2016.06.027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anton</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Malley</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciraulo</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cisler</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Couper</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Combined pharmacotherapies and behavioral interventions for alcohol dependence: the COMBINE study: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>295</volume>:<fpage>2003</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2017</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16670409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.295.17.2003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>AHS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellerbe</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reeder</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagedorn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacotherapy for alcohol dependence: perceived treatment barriers and action strategies among Veterans Health Administration service providers</article-title>. <source>Psychol Serv</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>410</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>419</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23356858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1037/a0030949</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliva</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maisel</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Barriers to use of pharmacotherapy for addiction disorders and how to overcome them</article-title>. <source>Curr Psychiatry Rep</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>374</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>381</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21773951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11920-011-0222-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4403628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrilla</surname><given-names>CHA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garberson</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coulthard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Geographic variation in the supply of selected behavioral health providers</article-title>. <source>Am J Prev Med</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>S199</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>S207</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29779543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amepre.2018.01.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abuse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>mental health services administration an action plan for behavioral health workforce development (HHS Publication No SMA 11-4629)</source>. <publisher-name>Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Czeisler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrosky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiley</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Njai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mental health, substance use, and suicidal ideation during the COVID-19 pandemic&#8212;United States, June 24-30, 2020</article-title>. <source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>1049</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1057</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32790653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.15585/mmwr.mm6932a1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7440121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rieckmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muench</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McBurnie</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leo</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Medication-assisted treatment for substance use disorders within a national community health center research network</article-title>. <source>Subst Abus</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>625</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>634</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27218678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/08897077.2016.1189477</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maisel</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blodgett</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilbourne</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finney</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Meta-analysis of naltrexone and acamprosate for treating alcohol use disorders: when are these medications most helpful?</article-title><source>Addiction</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>108</volume>:<fpage>275</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>293</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23075288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1360-0443.2012.04054.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3970823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>