<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2035</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">lwwopen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JS9</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Surgery (London, England)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1743-9191</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1743-9159</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Lippincott Open Access</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10389611</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10389611.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10389611</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10389611</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37057905</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JS9.0000000000000356</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effect of regional versus general anesthesia on thirty-day outcomes following carotid endarterectomy: a cohort study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kline</surname><given-names initials="LA">Leigh A.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><email>LAK8ZB@uvahealth.org</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kothandaraman</surname><given-names initials="V">Venkatraman</given-names></name><degrees>BS</degrees><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><email>vk9dj@uvahealth.org</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5696-873X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Knio</surname><given-names initials="ZO">Ziyad O.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><email>zok3dg@hscmail.mcc.virginia.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3542-5047</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhiyi</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><email>zz3c@virginia.edu</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>a</label>Department of Anesthesiology, University of Virginia Health</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>b</label>School of Medicine, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Virginia, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Address: Department of Anesthesiology, University of Virginia Health, PO Box 800710, Charlottesville, VA 22908-0710, USA. Tel: +434 924 2283, fax: +434 982 0019. E-mail: <email>zok3dg@virginia.edu</email> (Z. O. Knio); E-mail: <email>zz3c@virginia.edu</email> (Z. Zuo).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>109</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">436662</issue-id><fpage>1291</fpage><lpage>1298</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>31</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-08-01 10:25:10.673"><day>01</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0</ext-link> (CCBY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>
</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="js9-109-1291.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="js9-109-1291.pdf"/><abstract><title>Background:</title><p>The effect of regional versus general anesthesia on carotid endarterectomy outcomes is debated. This study assesses the effect of anesthetic technique on major morbidity and mortality and additional secondary endpoints following carotid endarterectomy.</p><sec><title>Materials and methods:</title><p>This was a retrospective propensity-matched-cohort analysis investigating elective carotid endarterectomy patients in the 2015&#8211;2019 American College of Surgeons National Surgical Quality Improvement Program (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=37&#160;204). The primary endpoint was 30-day mortality and major morbidity, defined as stroke, myocardial infarction, or death. Secondary endpoints included minor morbidity, bleeding events, healthcare resource utilization, and length of hospital stay. Univariate, multivariable, and survival analyses were applied.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>The 1&#160;:&#160;1 propensity-matched-cohort included 8304 patients (4152 in each group). Regional anesthesia was associated with similar incidences of major morbidity and mortality [odds ratio (OR), 0.81 (95% CI, 0.61&#8211;1.09); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.162] and unplanned resource utilization [OR, 0.93 (95% CI, 0.78&#8211;1.11); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.443], but lower incidences of minor morbidity [OR, 0.60 (95% CI, 0.44&#8211;0.81); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001] and bleeding events [OR, 0.49 (95% CI, 0.30&#8211;0.78); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.002], and a shorter length of hospital stay [1.4 vs. 1.6 days; mean difference, -0.16 days (95% CI, -0.25 to -0.07); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001]. On multivariable analysis, regional anesthesia remained independently predictive of minor morbidity [adjusted odds ratio (AOR), 0.58 (95% CI, 0.42&#8211;0.79); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.001] and bleeding events [AOR, 0.49 (95% CI, 0.30&#8211;0.77); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.003]. Significance was maintained on survival analysis for these two endpoints. A mortality benefit was observed on univariate [OR, 0.50 (95% CI, 0.25&#8211;1.00); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.045], multivariable [AOR, 0.49 (95% CI, 0.24&#8211;0.96); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.043], and survival analysis (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.045).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions:</title><p>Carotid endarterectomy patients receiving regional anesthesia experience favorable outcomes compared to propensity-matched general anesthesia controls.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical"><p>
<fig position="float" id="GA1" orientation="portrait"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="js9-109-1291-g001.jpg"/></fig>
</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords:</title><kwd>carotid endarterectomy</kwd><kwd>general anesthesia</kwd><kwd>major morbidity</kwd><kwd>mortality</kwd><kwd>perioperative outcomes</kwd><kwd>regional anesthesia</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>SDC</meta-name><meta-value>T</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><boxed-text content-type="shaded" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Highlights</p></caption><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The effect of regional versus general anesthesia on carotid endarterectomy complications remains unclear.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A matched-cohort study design may reduce the effect of confounding by anesthetic technique.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Regional anesthesia is associated with similar incidences of 30-day major morbidity and mortality and unplanned resource utilization.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Regional anesthesia is associated with fewer minor morbidity and bleeding events.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Robust fragility indices support the above findings.</p></list-item></list></boxed-text><p>The optimal anesthetic technique for carotid endarterectomy remains highly debated<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>. One advantage of regional anesthesia is that it allows for the &#8216;gold standard&#8217; awake neurologic assessment for perioperative ischemia and hypoxia<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>. Other proposed benefits include better hemodynamic stability, decreased vasopressor use, and preserved cerebrovascular reflexes that maintain cerebral perfusion and reduce the need for a shunt (which may damage the arterial wall and lead to embolism)<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>. Conversely, disadvantages of regional anesthesia include the need for a patient who is comfortable and compliant with akinesia. Additionally, regional anesthesia offers limited airway protection and may require a technically difficult intraoperative emergent tracheal intubation<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>. The advantages of general anesthesia include a secure airway and a more comfortable operating environment for both the surgeon and the patient<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>. On the other hand, disadvantages of general anesthesia include hemodynamic instability and increased usage of shunts during cross-clamping due to less effective neuromonitoring<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>.</p><p>The GALA Trial Collaborative Group (2008) demonstrated no difference in primary outcome (a composite of 30-day stroke, myocardial infarction (MI), or death) between the two anesthetic techniques in a landmark randomized controlled trial<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>. While these results have been replicated by some studies<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, others have demonstrated a clinical benefit with regional anesthesia<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>. Several studies found an increased risk for postoperative MI with general anesthesia<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>. Furthermore, a few studies found that patients undergoing general anesthesia had higher rates of strokes and transient ischemic attacks<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>.</p><p>Given the discordant conclusions of various studies, further investigation into the impact of anesthetic technique is warranted. Furthermore, robust methodology must be employed in order to balance cohorts, as selection bias often results in regional anesthesia cohorts comprising individuals of better functional status<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>.</p><p>This retrospective study was designed to investigate whether anesthetic technique was associated with major morbidity and mortality (stroke, MI, or death within 30 days) following elective carotid endarterectomy in a propensity-matched-cohort sample. The goal of this methodology was to reduce confounding by indication for primary anesthetic technique. Secondary endpoints that were investigated included minor morbidity, bleeding events, unplanned healthcare resource utilization, and length of hospital stay. The authors hypothesized that the use of regional anesthesia during carotid endarterectomy would be associated with lower incidences of major morbidity and mortality, minor morbidity, bleeding events, unplanned resource utilization, and a shorter length of hospital stay.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Material and methods</title><sec><title>Study design and data sources</title><p>This research was retrospectively registered with clinicaltrials.gov (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT05706688" ext-link-type="uri">https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT05706688</ext-link>). The study was exempt from Institutional Review Board approval given that it was a retrospective cohort analysis of a national de-identified database. The American College of Surgeons National Surgeons Quality Improvement Program (ACS-NSQIP) database from 2015 to 2019 was queried, with carotid endarterectomy defined by the Current Procedural Terminology code 35301. The work has been reported in line with the Strengthening the Reporting of Cohort Studies in Surgery (STROCSS) Criteria<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, Supplemental Digital Content 1, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/A330" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/A330</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Patient inclusion and exclusion criteria</title><p>After the initial query, the following criteria were applied in order to produce a more homogenous investigation sample. Only elective, nonemergent cases were included. Patients with concurrent procedures were excluded. Patients with preoperative documentation of acute kidney injury, end-stage renal disease, metastatic disease, wound infection, and sepsis were excluded. Patients with American Society of Anesthesiologist Physical Status (ASA) classification 5 were excluded. These criteria were agreed upon by the study authors <italic toggle="yes">a priori</italic>. General anesthesia cases were identified by &#8216;General&#8217; documentation in primary anesthesia type, without any further specifications in secondary anesthesia type. Regional anesthesia cases were identified by any combination of &#8216;Local,&#8217; &#8216;MAC/IV Sedation,&#8217; and &#8216;Regional&#8217; documentation in the primary anesthesia type, without the appearance of &#8216;General&#8217; in the secondary anesthesia type.</p></sec><sec><title>Measurements and data handling</title><p>The primary independent variable was anesthetic technique (regional vs. general). Independent variables also included age, sex, BMI, hypertension, insulin-dependent diabetes, current smoker, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), congestive heart failure (CHF), chronic steroid use, functional status, and the American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical status classification (ASA 4 versus ASA 1-3).</p><p>The primary endpoint was major morbidity and mortality, defined as stroke, MI, or death within 30 days.</p><p>Secondary endpoints included minor morbidity, bleeding events requiring transfusion, unplanned resource utilization, and length of hospital stay. Minor morbidity included reintubation, prolonged (&gt;48&#160;h) ventilator dependence, pneumonia, deep venous thrombosis, pulmonary embolism, superficial surgical site infection (SSI), deep incisional SSI, organ space SSI, wound dehiscence, sepsis, septic shock, acute kidney injury, and progressive renal insufficiency. Unplanned resource utilization included unplanned readmission and unplanned reoperation.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Statistical analysis was performed with R version 4.2.0 (R Core Team)<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>. Regional anesthesia cases were identified, and general anesthesia cases were matched using propensity scores computed by patient demographics and medical comorbidities. Specifically, cases were matched by the following variables: age, sex, BMI, hypertension, insulin-dependent diabetes, current smoker, COPD, CHF, chronic steroid use, functional status, and ASA physical status classification (ASA 4 versus ASA 1-3). A 1:1 nearest neighbor propensity score matching algorithm using probit regression covariate estimates without replacement was applied. Balance among matched pairs was assessed by standardized mean differences<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>. Propensity score matching has been applied in prior studies; the proposed advantage of this methodology is adjusting for baseline differences between those receiving general and regional anesthesia<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>. Not infrequently, patients receiving regional anesthesia have fewer comorbidities<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>. Despite this, there remains the possibility for residual confounding between cohorts<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>.</p><p>The associations between anesthetic technique and composite endpoints or anesthetic technique and component outcomes were first assessed with univariate analyses. Pearson&#8217;s <italic toggle="yes">&#967;</italic>
<sup>2</sup>-test without continuity correction was applied to categorical variables while Student&#8217;s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test was applied to the length of hospital stay. Additionally, odds ratios (OR), 95% CI, and fragility indices were calculated following <italic toggle="yes">&#967;</italic>
<sup>2</sup> methodology<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>. The fragility index is a quantitative measure of how many subject-dependent classifications influence the statistical significance of a hypothesis test, with greater numbers suggesting a more robust difference between groups<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>.</p><p>Multivariable analyses were then performed on primary and secondary endpoints demonstrating statistical significance and a robust fragility index on univariate testing. Multiple logistic regression modeling was applied, with adjustments made for age, sex, BMI, hypertension, diabetes, smoking, COPD, CHF, chronic steroid use, functional status, ASA physical status classification, and anesthetic technique when significance was demonstrated on univariate testing at &#945; less than or equal to 0.05. Only complete cases were considered, and missing data were not imputed. Subsequent variable selection was accomplished by backward stepwise model adjustment by Akaike information criterion. Backward stepwise adjustment, in contrast to forward stepwise adjustment, was applied such that all predictors would be considered in the null model, essentially favoring more rather than fewer predictors in the final regression. Regardless, the Akaike information criterion assesses the overall model fit and favors parsimony, a balance between over- and under-fitting. Independent predictors were not added/eliminated stepwise by statistical significance but rather by their contribution to a more optimized adjusted model (as demonstrated by a lower Akaike information criterion)<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>. Adjusted odds ratios (AOR) and 95% CI are reported for independent predictors, and model discrimination was assessed with the c-statistic<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>.</p><p>Survival analyses were then performed on the same endpoints. Kaplan&#8211;Meier curves modeling days of event-free survival against anesthetic technique were constructed. The risk attributable to anesthetic technique was quantified with the log-rank <italic toggle="yes">P-</italic>value<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>
</p><p>Continuous variables were summarized by mean (SD), while categorical variables were summarized by frequency (%). All hypothesis tests were two-sided, with significance defined by &#945; less than or equal to 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>Of 37&#160;204 carotid endarterectomy patients meeting inclusion criteria, 4252 (11.4%) received regional anesthesia. After 1:1 propensity score matching by patient demographics and medical comorbidities, a total of 8304 patients were matched (4152 in each study group) (Fig. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Balance between cohorts was achieved as evidenced by standardized mean differences &lt; 0.1 (Fig. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The distribution of patient demographics and medical comorbidities in the regional and general anesthesia cohorts both before and after matching are presented in Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials diagram detailing selection of patients within each cohort, including numbers of patients in each cohort before and after matching. ACS-NSQIP, American College of Surgeons National Surgical Quality Improvement Program.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="js9-109-1291-g002.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Absolute standardized mean differences before (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=37&#160;204) and after (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=8304) matching the regional and general anesthesia cohorts 1:1 by propensity score. ASA, American Society of Anesthesiologists physical status; CHF, congestive heart failure; COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="js9-109-1291-g003.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographics and medical comorbidities by anesthetic technique, before and after propensity score matching.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="3" axis="1">Before propensity score matching</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="3" axis="1">After propensity score matching</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="2" axis="1">No./total (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1" axis="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="2" axis="1">No./total (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1" axis="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Characteristic</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">General (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=32&#160;952)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Regional (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=4252)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">General (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=4152)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Regional (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=4152)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, mean (SD), years</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.7 (8.7)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.5 (8.7)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.5 (8.7)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.5 (8.7)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.710</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female sex</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13113/32952 (39.8%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1624/4252 (38.2%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1577/4152 (38.0%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1577/4152 (38.0%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 0.999</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, mean (SD), kg/m<sup>2</sup>
</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.9 (5.8)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.7 (5.6)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.6 (5.4)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.7 (5.6)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.585</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27620/32952 (83.8%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3574/4252 (84.1%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.694</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3533/4152 (85.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3493/4152 (84.1%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.224</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insulin-dependent diabetes</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3889/32952 (11.8%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">481/4252 (11.3%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.351</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">446/4152 (10.7%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">477/4152 (11.5%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.279</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current smoker</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9243/32952 (28.0%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">983/4252 (23.1%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">963/4152 (23.2%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">966/4152 (23.3%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.938</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COPD history</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3777/32952 (11.5%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">413/4252 (9.7%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">402/4152 (9.7%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">405/4152 (9.8%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.912</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHF history</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">412/32952 (1.3%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53/4252 (1.2%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.983</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44/4152 (1.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50/4152 (1.2%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.534</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic steroid use</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">994/32952 (3.0%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131/4252 (3.1%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.817</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128/4152 (3.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126/4152 (3.0%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.899</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dependent functional status</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">731/32802 (2.2%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80/4244 (1.9%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.150</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85/4152 (2.0%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78/4152 (1.9%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.580</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASA 4</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6304/32893 (19.2%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">662/4237 (15.6%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">652/4152 (15.7%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">649/4152 (15.6%)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.928</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>ASA, American Society of Anesthesiologists; CHF, congestive heart failure; COPD, chronic obstructive lung disease.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>On univariate analysis, regional anesthesia was not associated with rates of major morbidity and mortality [2.0% (85/4152) vs. 2.5% (104/4152); OR, 0.81 (95% CI, 0.61&#8211;1.09); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.162] or resource utilization events [6.1% (254/4152) vs. 6.5% (271/4152); OR, 0.93 (95% CI, 0.78&#8211;1.11); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.443]. However, regional anesthesia was associated with a lower incidence of minor morbidity [1.6% (65/4152) vs. 2.6% (108/4152); OR, 0.60 (95% CI, 0.44&#8211;0.81); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001] and bleeding events [0.6% (26/4152) vs. 1.3% (53/4152); OR, 0.49 (95% CI, 0.30&#8211;0.78); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.002]. The fragility indices for these endpoints were robust. The length of hospital stay was shorter in the regional anesthesia cohort [1.4 vs. 1.6 days; mean difference, -0.16 days (95% CI, -0.25 to -0.07); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001]. Of the component outcomes demonstrating a significant association with anesthesia type, thirty-day mortality was considered for subsequent analyses given that it is a clinically meaningful outcome demonstrating a lower incidence in the regional anesthesia cohort [0.3% (12/4152) vs. 0.6% (24/4152); OR, 0.50 (95% CI, 0.25&#8211;1.00); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.045] (Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Univariate analyses by anesthetic technique (regional vs. general).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="2" axis="1">No./total (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Outcome</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">General (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4152)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Regional (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4152)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Odds ratio (95% CI)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1" axis="1">Fragility index</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major morbidity and mortality (composite)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104/4152 (2.5%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85/4152 (2.0%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.61&#8211;1.09)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.162</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Stroke</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59/4152 (1.4%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57/4152 (1.4%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.67&#8211;1.39)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.852</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Myocardial infarction</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39/4152 (0.9%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26/4152 (0.6%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 (0.40&#8211;1.09)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.105</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Mortality</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24/4152 (0.6%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/4152 (0.3%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 (0.25&#8211;1.00)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minor morbidity (composite)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108/4152 (2.6%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65/4152 (1.6%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 (0.44&#8211;0.81)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Unplanned reintubation</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44/4152 (1.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20/4152 (0.5%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 (0.27&#8211;0.77)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Ventilator dependence &gt;48h</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20/4152 (0.5%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/4152 (0.3%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 (0.29&#8211;1.23)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.156</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Pneumonia</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37/4152 (0.9%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20/4152 (0.5%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 (0.31&#8211;0.93)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Deep venous thrombosis</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/4152 (0.0%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/4152 (0.0%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 (0.18&#8211;22.07)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.564</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Pulmonary embolism</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/4152 (0.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/4152 (0.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.20&#8211;4.96)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 0.999</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Superficial SSI</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/4152 (0.3%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/4152 (0.4%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 (0.58&#8211;2.68)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.563</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Deep incisional SSI</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/4152 (0.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/4152 (0.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 (0.19&#8211;2.36)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.527</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Organ space SSI</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/4152 (0.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/4152 (0.0%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 (0.09&#8211;2.73)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.414</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Wound dehiscence</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/4152 (0.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/4152 (0.0%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 (0.03&#8211;3.20)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.317</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Sepsis</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/4152 (0.3%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/4152 (0.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 (0.20&#8211;1.47)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.225</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Septic shock</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/4152 (0.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/4152 (0.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 (0.17&#8211;3.35)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.705</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Acute kidney injury</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/4152 (0.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/4152 (0.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.20&#8211;4.96)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 0.999</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Progressive renal insufficiency</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/4152 (0.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/4152 (0.0%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 (0.03&#8211;2.24)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.180</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bleeding event</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53/4152 (1.3%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26/4152 (0.6%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 (0.30&#8211;0.78)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unplanned resource utilization (composite)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">271/4152 (6.5%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">254/4152 (6.1%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 (0.78&#8211;1.11)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.443</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Unplanned readmission</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209/4152 (5.0%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">191/4152 (4.6%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.74&#8211;1.11)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.356</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8195;Unplanned reoperation</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102/4152 (2.5%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108/4152 (2.6%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.81&#8211;1.39)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.675</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of hospital stay, mean (SD), days</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (1.9)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 (2.3)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.16 (&#8722;0.25 to &#8722;0.07)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>SSI, surgical site infection.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Regional anesthesia remained an independent predictor of minor morbidity [AOR, 0.58 (95% CI, 0.42&#8211;0.79); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.001], bleeding events [AOR, 0.49 (95% CI, 0.30&#8211;0.77); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.003], and mortality [AOR, 0.49 (95% CI, 0.24&#8211;0.96); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.043] after adjusting for covariates on multivariable analysis (Appendix A, Supplemental Digital Content 2, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/A331" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/A331</ext-link>).</p><p>Additional predictors of minor morbidity included insulin-dependent diabetes [AOR, 2.23 (95% CI, 1.52&#8211;3.22); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001], current smoker [AOR, 1.71 (95% CI, 1.23&#8211;2.35); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.001], COPD [AOR, 2.13 (95% CI, 1.43&#8211;3.10); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001], CHF [AOR, 2.99 (95% CI, 1.22&#8211;6.28); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.008], and dependent functional status [AOR, 2.14 (95% CI, 0.94&#8211;4.21, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.044] with model c-statistic=0.654. Additional predictors of bleeding events included age [AOR, 1.03 per year (95% CI, 1.01&#8211;1.06); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.014], BMI [AOR, 0.93&#160;per kg/m<sup>2</sup> (95% CI, 0.89&#8211;0.97); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.003], and ASA 4 [AOR, 1.97 (95% CI, 1.16&#8211;3.20); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.009], with model c-statistic=0.684. Additional predictors of mortality included age [AOR, 1.06 per year (95% CI, 1.02&#8211;1.11); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.004], COPD [AOR, 4.36 (95% CI, 2.08&#8211;8.67); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001], and ASA 4 [AOR, 2.48 (95% CI, 1.20&#8211;4.89); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.010], with model c-statistic=0.758 (eTable 1, Supplemental Digital Content 3, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://links.lww.com/JS9/A332" ext-link-type="uri">http://links.lww.com/JS9/A332</ext-link>).</p><p>Survival analysis demonstrated a significantly longer time to minor morbidity (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001), bleeding events (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.002), and death (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.045) in patients receiving regional anesthesia (Fig. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Survival analysis by anesthetic technique for (a) minor morbidity, (b) bleeding events, and (c) mortality.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="js9-109-1291-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study determined that patients receiving regional anesthesia had lower event rates of minor morbidity, bleeding requiring transfusion, and mortality within 30 days of elective carotid endarterectomy. Event rates for the composite primary outcome (stroke, MI, or death), wound complications, and unplanned resource utilization were comparable between the two anesthetic techniques. The length of hospital stay was statistically significantly shorter in the regional anesthesia cohort by 0.16 days, which may be of limited clinical significance. Regardless, there were no composite or component endpoints in which patients receiving regional anesthesia experienced worse outcomes than their propensity-matched general anesthesia counterparts.</p><p>The present study corroborates the conclusion by the GALA Trial Collaborative Group (2018) that major morbidity and mortality are not associated with anesthetic technique<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>. However, other clinically meaningful benefits with regional anesthesia were identified in the present study, and the component analysis demonstrates a lower 30-day mortality rate. It is possible that the nonsignificant difference in stroke and MI rates has skewed the results of the GALA Trial Collaborative Group (2018) to find no difference. Interestingly, Lumas <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> identified a signal in their composite, but not their component, outcomes in a matched-cohort study design.</p><p>There are other matched-cohort studies that found higher rates of MIs in carotid endarterectomy patients receiving general anesthesia<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>. One such study by Leichtle <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> determined that an elevated risk of postoperative MI was observed only in general anesthesia patients with preoperative neurologic symptoms; asymptomatic patients did not share this association. This finding could explain some of the discrepancies found between these studies. None of the matched-cohort studies conducted thus far have found a difference in the incidence of stroke postoperatively. Interestingly, a randomized prospective study by Orlicky <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> also found no difference in stroke incidence but found that patients receiving general anesthesia had more silent brain infarctions when 24&#160;h preoperative and 24&#160;h postoperative MRIs were compared to those of patients who received local anesthesia (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.031).</p><p>Malik <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> found no mortality difference in their 22&#160;845 propensity-matched-cohort sample, but showed that general anesthesia was associated with a significantly higher rate of perioperative transfusions (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.037) and perioperative pneumonia (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.027), a finding shared by the present study. Their finding that patients with low hematocrit and low platelet count were more likely to get regional anesthesia supports the use of propensity-matching.</p><p>There are unmatched cohort studies that have identified a reduction in rates of stroke<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, MI<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, and mortality<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, in carotid endarterectomy patients receiving regional anesthesia. However, these results may be influenced by selection bias, with confounding factors influencing the choice of anesthetic technique. Moreover, these results have not been reliably replicated in other unmatched cohort studies<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>. Another factor that could contribute to the varied results from these studies is the length of follow-up. An unmatched cohort study by G&#252;rer <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> was one of the only studies that examined long-term outcomes and found that at 8&#8211;10 year follow-up, there was no statistically significant difference in terms of restenosis-free survival, ipsilateral stroke-free survival, or overall survival.</p><p>The present study identified additional characteristics that were unequally distributed between the unmatched cohorts; the general anesthesia cohort before propensity score matching had an overrepresentation of patients who were younger, female, of lower BMI, current smokers, COPD patients, and ASA 4. Propensity score matching produced cohorts that were balanced in all of the aforementioned characteristics, with standardized mean differences less than 0.1. While propensity score matching reduces the effect of confounding, it does not eliminate the potential for selection bias<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>.</p><p>This study is significantly strengthened by reporting fragility indices for all outcomes, complementing the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value with an interpretable measure of patient classification on statistical significance<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>. At a minimum, the classification of 16 minor morbidity events and 8 bleeding events would need to be changed to the opposite class to alter the statistical significance of these findings. Importantly, the significance of the mortality association with anesthetic technique is contingent on just one classification.</p><p>There are several limitations that are inherent to the study design. The endpoints and covariates that could be investigated in this retrospective observational study are limited to those captured by the ACS-NSQIP database. Endpoints such as patient-reported outcomes and covariates such as preoperative neurologic deficits are examples of variables not captured by the ACS-NSQIP database. Furthermore, ACS-NSQIP outcomes sampling is limited to 30 days postoperatively, thus stroke and mortality incidences beyond this time point cannot be computed. Also, there is the possibility that with such a large sample size, the study was over-powered to detect differences between the two cohorts. Thus, it is important to consider the reported odds ratios rather than rely solely on statistical significance to quantify the difference in outcomes between anesthetic techniques. While an increased risk of adverse events was observed in the general anesthesia cohort, a causal relationship could not be determined. A randomized clinical trial design would be better suited to test such a hypothesis. Further research is certainly warranted in order to explain the mechanisms by which regional anesthesia confers these clinical benefits.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In summary, the present study demonstrates a favorable postoperative complication profile in carotid endarterectomy patients receiving regional anesthesia. A regional anesthetic technique is independently predictive of a reduction in minor morbidity, bleeding, and mortality events, even after adjusting for preoperative and operative characteristics.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>This research was retrospectively registered with clinicaltrials.gov (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT05706688" ext-link-type="uri">https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT05706688</ext-link>). The study was exempt from Institutional Review Board approval given that it was a retrospective cohort analysis of a national de-identified database. The data is in a publicly accessible database.</p></sec><sec><title>Sources of funding</title><p>This study is supported by Robert M. Epstein Professorship from the University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA. The funder has no role in experimental design, data analysis, manuscript writing, or decision on publication of this study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest disclosure</title><p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contribution</title><p>L.A.K.: investigation, writing &#8211; original draft; V.K.: investigation, writing &#8211; original draft; Z.O.K.: methodology, software, formal analysis, writing &#8211; original draft; Z.Z.: conceptualization, resources, writing &#8211; review, and editing, supervision, project administration.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>American College of Surgeons National Surgical Quality Improvement Program and the hospitals participating in the ACS-NSQIP are the source of the data used herein. The Participant Use Data File (PUF) is a Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA)-compliant data file containing cases submitted to the American College of Surgeons National Surgical Quality Improvement Program&#174;. To request a copy of the PUF, individuals (data recipients) must agree to comply with the terms and conditions set forth in the Data Use Agreement, provide contact information, and complete a short online questionnaire. Once the information provided by the data recipient is received and processed by ACS-NSQIP staff, a website address will be submitted electronically to the data recipient. The data recipient will then have 10 days (240&#160;h) to visit the website and download the data file.</p></sec><sec><title>Guarantor</title><p>The ACS-NSQIP database was accessed by Z.O.K. Z.O.K. and Z.Z. have full access to all the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Provenance and Peer Review</title><p>Not commissioned, externally peer-reviewed.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><fig id="s001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="js9-109-1291-s001.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="s002" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="js9-109-1291-s002.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="s003" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="js9-109-1291-s003.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></fig></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>
<bold>Disclosures</bold>: American College of Surgeons National Surgical Quality Improvement Program and the hospitals participating in the ACS-NSQIP are the source of the data used herein; they have not verified and are not responsible for the statistical validity of the data analysis or the conclusions derived by the authors.</p></fn><fn fn-type="supplementary-material"><p>Supplemental Digital Content is available for this article. Direct URL citations are provided in the HTML and PDF versions of this article on the journal's website, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.journal-surgery.net" ext-link-type="uri">www.journal-surgery.net</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal"><p>Published online 14 April 2023</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rerkasem</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orrapin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Local versus general anaesthesia for carotid endarterectomy</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>CD000126</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34642940</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD000126.pub5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8511439</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hans</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jareunpoon</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prospective evaluation of electroencephalography, carotid artery stump pressure, and neurologic changes during 314 consecutive carotid endarterectomies performed in awake patients</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Surg</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>511</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>515</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17275248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jvs.2006.11.035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>GALA Trial Collaborative Group</collab>, <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warlow</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bodenham</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>General anaesthesia versus local anaesthesia for carotid surgery (GALA): a multicentre, randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>372</volume>:<fpage>2132</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2142</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19041130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(08)61699-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Unic-Stojanovic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Babic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neskovic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>General versus regional anesthesia for carotid endarterectomy</article-title>. <source>J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1379</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1383</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23287445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.jvca.2012.09.021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zdrehu&#351;</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anaesthesia for carotid endarterectomy &#8211; general or loco-regional?</article-title><source>Rom J Anaesth Intensive Care</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28913451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5505327</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Licker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Regional or general anaesthesia for carotid endarterectomy: does it matter?</article-title><source>Eur J Anaesthesiol</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>243</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26928169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/EJA.0000000000000376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCleary</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maritati</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gough</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Carotid endarterectomy; local or general anaesthesia?</article-title><source>Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11461095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/ejvs.2001.1382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bodenham</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>General anaesthesia vs local anaesthesia: an ongoing story</article-title>. <source>Br J Anaesth</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>785</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>789</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19918020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bja/aep310</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paraskevas</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikhailidis</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oikonomou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Local versus general anesthesia for carotid endarterectomy: issues beyond stroke, myocardial infarction, and death rates</article-title>. <source>Angiology</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>405</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>408</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22210736</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0003319711430828</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#252;rer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yapici</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yapici</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison between local and general anesthesia for carotid endarterectomy: early and late results</article-title>. <source>Vasc Endovascular Surg</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>138</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22232328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1538574411431345</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mofidi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nimmo</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moores</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Regional versus general anaesthesia for carotid endarterectomy: impact of change in practice</article-title>. <source>Surgeon</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>158</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>162</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16764201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1479-666x(06)80086-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of anesthetic modality on the outcome of carotid endarterectomy</article-title>. <source>Am J Surg</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>188</volume>:<fpage>741</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>747</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15619493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amjsurg.2004.08.048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sternbach</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Illig</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Hemodynamic benefits of regional anesthesia for carotid endarterectomy</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Surg</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>333</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>339</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11854732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1067/mva.2002.121579</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Markovic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vlajkovic</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sindjelic</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cervical plexus block versus general anesthesia in carotid surgery: single center experience</article-title>. <source>Arch Med Sci</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1035</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1040</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23319978</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5114/aoms.2012.32411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3542493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schechter</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shortell</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scarborough</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Regional versus general anesthesia for carotid endarterectomy: the American College of Surgeons National Surgical Quality Improvement Program perspective</article-title>. <source>Surgery</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>152</volume>:<fpage>309</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>314</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22749369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.surg.2012.05.008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sideso</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Handa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>General or local anesthesia for carotid endarterectomy&#8211;the &#8220;real-world&#8221; experience</article-title>. <source>Angiology</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>609</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>613</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21555313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0003319711405507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Viazzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Carotid endarterectomy: comparison between general and local anesthesia. Revision of our experience with 428 consecutive cases</article-title>. <source>Ann Vasc Surg</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>1034</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1037</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20800430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.avsg.2010.04.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lobo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mour&#227;o</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Afonso</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Carotid endarterectomy: review of 10 years of practice of general and locoregional anesthesia in a tertiary care hospital in Portugal</article-title>. <source>Braz J Anesthesiol</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>249</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>254</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26123143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bjane.2014.03.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leichtle</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mouawad</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Outcomes of carotid endarterectomy under general and regional anesthesia from the American College of Surgeons&#8217; National Surgical Quality Improvement Program</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Surg</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>88.e3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22480761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jvs.2012.01.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez-Wilson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Outcome of carotid endarterectomy after regional anesthesia versus general anesthesia - A retrospective study using two independent databases</article-title>. <source>Transl Perioper Pain Med</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>14</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26023678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4444227</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dakour Aridi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paracha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nejim</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Anesthetic type and hospital outcomes after carotid endarterectomy from the Vascular Quality Initiative database</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Surg</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>1419</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1428</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29242070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jvs.2017.09.028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gahl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Local versus general anaesthesia for carotid endarterectomy&#8211;improving the gold standard&#8239;?</article-title><source>Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>145</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>149</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18485760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ejvs.2008.03.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Papavasiliou</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magnadottir</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical outcomes after carotid endarterectomy: comparison of the use of regional and general anesthetics</article-title>. <source>J Neurosurg</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>291</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>296</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10659017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3171/jns.2000.92.2.0291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lumas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsiang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Regional anesthesia is underutilized for carotid endarterectomy despite improved perioperative outcomes compared with general anesthesia</article-title>. <source>Ann Vasc Surg</source><year>2021</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>336</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>343</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33373769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.avsg.2020.11.035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mullard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oppat</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Increased resource utilization and overall morbidity are associated with general versus regional anesthesia for carotid endarterectomy in data collected by the Michigan Surgical Quality Collaborative</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Surg</source><year>2017</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>802</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>809</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28433337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jvs.2017.01.060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdall-Razak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crossley</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <collab>for the STROCSS Group</collab>. <article-title>The STROCSS 2019 guideline: strengthening the reporting of cohort studies in surgery</article-title>. <source>Int J Surg</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>156</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>165</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31704426</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijsu.2019.11.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>R Core Team</collab><collab>(2022)</collab>. <comment>R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria. URL <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.R-project.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.R-project.org/</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>MatchIt: nonparametric preprocessing for parametric causal inference</article-title>. <source>J Stat Soft</source><year>2011</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brovman</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urman</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The use of regional or local anesthesia for carotid endarterectomies may reduce blood loss and pulmonary complications</article-title>. <source>J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>935</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>942</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30243870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.jvca.2018.08.195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Why propensity scores should not be used for matching</article-title>. <source>Polit Anal</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>435</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>454</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <comment>(2020). fragility: Assessing and Visualizing Fragility of Clinical Results with Binary Outcomes. R package version 1.1. URL <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=fragility" ext-link-type="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=fragility</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0268754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9159630</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35648746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feinstein</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The unit fragility index: an additional appraisal of &#8220;statistical significance&#8221; for a contrast of two proportions</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source><year>1990</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>201</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>209</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2303850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0895-4356(90)90186-s</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Srinathan</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McAuley</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The statistical significance of randomized controlled trial results is frequently fragile: a case for a Fragility Index</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>622</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>628</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24508144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2013.10.019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>MZI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turin</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Variable selection strategies and its importance in clinical prediction modelling</article-title>. <source>Fam Med Community Health</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e000262</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32148735</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/fmch-2019-000262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7032893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Portet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A primer on model selection using the Akaike Information Criterion</article-title>. <source>Infect Dis Model</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>128</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31956740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.idm.2019.12.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6962709</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrell</surname><given-names>FE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>. <comment>(2020). rms: Regression Modeling Strategies. R package version 6.0-0. URL <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=rms" ext-link-type="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=rms</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Therneau T (2020)</collab>. <comment>A Package for Survival Analysis in R. R package version 3.2-7. URL <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=survival" ext-link-type="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=survival</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Therneau</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grambsch</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Modeling Survival Data: Extending the Cox Model</source>. <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>2000</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orlick&#253;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hrb&#225;&#269;</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Same&#353;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Anesthesia type determines risk of cerebral infarction after carotid endarterectomy</article-title>. <source>J Vasc Surg</source>, <volume>70</volume><year>2019</year>:<fpage>138</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>147</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30792052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jvs.2018.10.066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Love</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hollyoak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Carotid endarterectomy and local anaesthesia: reducing the disasters</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>429</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>435</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10996095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0967-2109(00)00057-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>