<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="case-report" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Radiol Case Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Radiol Case Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2848</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">rcr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Radiology Case Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1930-0433</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10331020</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10331020.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10331020</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10331020</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37434619</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.radcr.2023.05.075</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1930-0433(23)00367-9</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A rare complication with superior mesenteric vein thrombosis after laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy: A case report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001"><name name-style="western"><surname>Juniku-Shkololli</surname><given-names initials="A">Argjira</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gjikolli</surname><given-names initials="B">Bujar</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>bujargjikolli@yahoo.com</email><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">&#8270;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0003"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoti</surname><given-names initials="KD">Kreshnike Dedushi</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0004"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyseni</surname><given-names initials="G">Guri</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kadrijaj</surname><given-names initials="F">Fatbardh</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0006"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lahu</surname><given-names initials="F">Flamur</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0007"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gjikolli</surname><given-names initials="D">Dea</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0008"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyseni</surname><given-names initials="F">Fjolla</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0009"><name name-style="western"><surname>Musa</surname><given-names initials="J">Juna</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>a</label>Clinic of Gastroenterology, University of Pristina&#8211;University Clinical Centre of Kosovo, Pristina, Kosovo</aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>b</label>Clinic of Radiology, University of Pristina&#8211;University Clinical Centre of Kosovo, Pristina, Kosovo</aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>c</label>AAB College &#8211; Faculty of Radiology, Prishtina, Kosovo</aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>d</label>Department of Pediatric Surgery, University of Pristina&#8211;University Clinical Centre of Kosovo, Pristina, Kosovo</aff><aff id="aff0005"><label>e</label>NYU Langone Health, New York, NY, USA</aff><aff id="aff0006"><label>f</label>Department of Endocrinology, Diabetes and Nutrition, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, NY, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor0001"><label>&#8270;</label>Corresponding author. <email>bujargjikolli@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>9</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><issue>9</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">438890</issue-id><fpage>3020</fpage><lpage>3025</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>25</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>21</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-07-12 11:25:16.183"><day>12</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2023 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. on behalf of University of Washington.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0001"><p>Laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy (LSG) has become a frequent procedure to reduce weight and morbid obesity. The procedure involves laparoscopic resection of more than 75% of the greater curvature of the stomach, resulting in early satiety and neuro-hormonal changes that collectively promote effective weight loss. We present a rare case of complication of superior mesenteric vein thrombosis (SMVT) and splenic vein after LSG, with consequent bowel ischemia that was treated with open laparotomy and appropriate anticoagulation therapy. A 56-year-old obese woman (BMI of 42.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), smoker for 30 years, presented to the emergency department with symptoms such as abdominal pain, fever, nausea and vomiting, 2 weeks after LSG intervention. Her white blood cell count was 15.5 (normal values: 3.8-10.4&#160;&#215;&#160;10<sup>3</sup> /&#181;L), while C- reactive protein level was 193 (normal values: 0.0-6.0 mg/L) and her D-Dimer level 4.69 (normal values: 0-0.50 mg/L). Abdominal CT with contrast showed a filling defect in the superior mesenteric and splenic vein, free perihepatic and Douglas pouch fluid, as well as small bowel thickening. An open laparotomy was performed and the necrotic segment of bowel of 80 cm was removed. The postoperative period went relatively well, despite the diarrhea that continued for the next 4 months after the intervention. The most common causes leading the development of this complication include: hypercoagulable state, dehydration, increased intra-abdominal pressure during the procedure and other secondary factors. The main symptom is abdominal pain, followed by nausea, vomiting, diarrhea and bleeding from the gastrointestinal tract. SMVT and SVT should be considered as a possible complication in patients with abdominal pain and increased inflammatory parameters after LSG. Early diagnosis through CT imaging and rapid anticoagulation therapy is considered to reduce further complications such as intestinal infarction and portal hypertension.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="keys0001"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy</kwd><kwd>Superior mesenteric vein thrombosis</kwd><kwd>Intestinal ischemia and necrosis</kwd><kwd>Anticoagulation therapy</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec0001"><title>Introduction</title><p id="para0002">Metabolic and bariatric surgery is superior to medical therapy in achieving significant weight loss, diabetes remission and remission or improvement of other comorbidities and cardiovascular risk factors <xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Bariatric surgery should be considered for patients with a BMI &#8805;40 or BMI 35-39.9 with a serious comorbidity who have not achieved weight loss goals with lifestyle modifications and drug therapy <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy (LSG) has become a safe and effective primary bariatric surgical method with increasing frequency of use and high popularity for both surgeons and patients <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. The procedure involves laparoscopic resection of more than 75% of the greater curvature of the stomach, creating a smaller narrow tubular structure with a residual volume of 100 mL. Smaller volume causes early satiety and weight loss. Further mechanisms contributing to weight loss after sleeve gastrectomy include neuro-hormonal changes such as decreased concentrations of the hunger stimulating hormone ghrelin, but a decrease in serum leptin concentrations is also found after the procedure <xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. However, there are some complications of the procedure, such as gastric leakage, bleeding, fluid collection, obstruction, infection, and rarer by frequency, but potentially fatal complication, superior mesenteric vein thrombosis (SMVT) and splenic vein thrombosis (SVT), with a consequence of intestinal ischemia <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. The main symptom is abdominal pain, followed by nausea and vomiting, lack of bowel movement, decreased appetite, diarrhea, and dehydration <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Early diagnosis and appropriate anticoagulant therapy administered immediately after the diagnosis, is essential in preventing further complications such as intestinal infarction and portal hypertension <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">[7</xref>,<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">8]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec0002"><title>Case presentation</title><p id="para0003">We present a case of a 56-year-old obese woman (BMI of 42.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), a 30-year smoker, who underwent a laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy for weight loss. She was discharged 3 days after the procedure, with instructions for a specific diet and adequate hydration. The patient presented 2 weeks after the procedure, to the emergency room with abdominal pain, fever, nausea and vomiting. Her white blood cell count was 15.5 (normal values: 3.8-10.4&#160;&#215;&#160;10<sup>3</sup> /&#181;L), while her C-reactive protein level was 193 (normal values: 0.0-6.0 mg/L) and her D-dimer 4.69 (normal values: 0-0.50 mg/L). The patient was admitted to the clinic for further evaluation and an abdominal CT was ordered. Postcontrast CT images in the portal phase showed a filling defect in the superior mesenteric vein and splenic vein, presence of perihepatic free liquid and in the pouch of Douglas and increased thickness of the small bowel, as shown on images (<xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref rid="fig0003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>, <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, <xref rid="fig0006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, <xref rid="fig0007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>, <xref rid="fig0008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>). The patient was immediately admitted and taken directly to the operation theater. As a result of intestinal ischemia and necrosis, an open laparotomy was performed and the necrotic segment of the intestine of 80 cm was surgically removed. The patient was treated after the operation with antibiotics and anticoagulants, namely dalteparin sodium 60 mg subcutaneous administration, twice a day for 2 weeks. The postoperative period was characterized by prolonged diarrhea during the next 4 months after the intervention.<fig id="fig0001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Abdominal and pelvic CT on postcontrast axial image show the stomach after performing the laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy, resulting in reduction of the stomach lumen in a shape of sleeve. White arrows show the operative hyper-dense suture materials.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0001">Fig 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig0002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>(A, B, C, D): Abdominal and pelvic CT axial and reformatted images, in late phase after the administration of the iodine contrast dye, portal phase abdominal CT shows the filling defect - thrombosis inside the enlarged superior mesenteric vein (white arrows) in A) the upper segment image, in B) the lower segment image, and C) with sagittal reformatting.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0002">Fig 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig0003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>(A and B): Abdominal and pelvic CT coronal (A) and axial (B) images show the edematous and thickened small bowel walls annotated with white arrows in both postcontrast images. In the (B) image, presence of inter intestinal free liquid annotated with yellow arrows, and the dirty fatty tissue nearby the SMV - with the red arrows.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0003">Fig 3</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig0004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Abdominal and pelvic CT axial images show the partial thrombosis of the splenic vein annotated with white arrows.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0004">Fig 4:</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig0005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>(A and B): Abdominal CT, axial postcontrast images show the presence of the free fluid: perihepatic (A) and (B) subhepatic.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0005">Fig 5</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr5.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig0006" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>(A and B): Abdominal and pelvic CT, axial postcontrast images show the presence of the free fluid: (A) interintestinal and (B) in the Douglas pouch.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0006">Fig 6</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr6.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig0007" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Abdominal and pelvic CT, coronal reconstruction, shows restored functionality of SMV (white arrows) with slight postintraluminal irregularity (red arrow) and fully re-canalized SV (yellow arrow).</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0007">Fig 7</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr7.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig0008" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>(A and B) Gastro duodenography image and small bowel enema show reduced volume and cylinder shape of the stomach, as well as appropriate propagation of barium, respectively.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0008">Fig 8</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr8.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="para0004">Four months later, abdominal and pelvic CT control examination showed restored functionality of the SMV with slight irregularities in its central part and fully re-canalized SV. Barium enema showed appropriate propagation of barium through cylinder-shaped stomach, duodenum and small bowels.</p></sec><sec id="sec0003"><title>Discussion</title><p id="para0005">SMVT is uncommon but potentially fatal complication of LSG, which can lead to intestinal ischemia and infarction. There are many factors that contribute to the development of thrombosis of the superior mesenteric vein as a complication of LSG, including dehydration after the procedure, reduced splanchnic and portal circulation, increased intra-abdominal pressure during laparoscopic surgery due to CO2 insufflation and hypercapnia in itself. There are some secondary factors, appearing in 60% of cases with thrombosis of the mesenteric superior vein, such as congenital hypercoagulable conditions, hematological disorders with thrombophilia, solid neoplasms, hormonal factors (use of contraceptives), autoimmune disorders, pancreatitis, cirrhosis, and bed rest after the procedure <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Another contributing factor is considered the movement of a local thrombus created as a result of damage during the intervention <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Smoking is also considered an important predisposing factor for the development of thrombosis <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. The most common symptom of SMVT is a vague crampy abdominal pain, and sometimes accompanied by nausea, vomiting, diarrhea and/or constipation. Hematochezia, melena and hematemesis are rare <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Enhanced abdominal CT with oral and intravenous contrast, is the method of choice for diagnosing SMVT, with a sensitivity of 90% <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Most patients with mild SMVT can be successfully treated with low molecular weight heparin or intravenous unfractionated heparin, when there are no signs of intestinal ischemia <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Patients with acute SMVT should be treated with anticoagulation therapy as soon as possible, in order to recanalize the portal venous system and reduce further thrombotic complications <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">[11</xref>,<xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">12]</xref>. The optimal duration of treatment with systemic anticoagulation has not been definitively determined. Some authors recommended 3-6 months of anticoagulation, while others suggest a longer duration of anticoagulation therapy, ranging from 6-12 months <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">[13</xref>,<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">14]</xref>. In some cases, when anticoagulation therapy does not seem effective and there is no evidence of intestinal ischemia, percutaneous or trans-hepatic thrombolytic therapy is suggested <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[5</xref>,<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">15]</xref>. Bowel rest, fluid resuscitation and nasogastric suction are recommended as supportive measures to supplement anticoagulation therapy <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. In our case, the most likely causes that led to the development of SMVT and SVT were dehydration after the procedure, combined with a predisposition for thrombosis as a result of long-term smoking and the metabolic syndrome itself.</p></sec><sec id="sec0004"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="para0006">SMVT and SVT should be considered as a possible complication in patients with abdominal pain and increased inflammatory parameters after LSG. Early diagnosis through CT imaging and prompt anticoagulation therapy is considered to reduce further complications such as bowel ischemia, peritonitis and portal hypertension. Dehydration after the procedure and predisposition to thrombosis play an important role in the development of this complication.</p></sec><sec id="sec0005"><title>Patient consent</title><p id="para0007">Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and accompanying images.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebibl1"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0001"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0001"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ammori</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skarulis</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soran</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Syed</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eledrisi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medical and surgical management of obesity and diabetes: what's new?</article-title><source>Diab Med</source><volume>37</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/dme.14215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31850536</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0002"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inadomi</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Medical, surgical, and endoscopic treatment of obesity</part-title><source>Yamada's handbook of gastroenterology.</source><edition>4th ed</edition><year>2020</year><publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/9781119515777</pub-id><comment>p</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0003"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0003"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brethauer</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sleeve gastrectomy</article-title><source>Surg Clin N Am</source><volume>91</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>1265</fpage><lpage>1279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.suc.2011.08.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22054153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0004"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0004"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gandhi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boregowda</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahuja</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A review of commonly performed bariatric surgeries: imaging features and its complications</article-title><source>Clin Imaging</source><volume>72</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>122</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinimag.2020.11.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33232899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0005"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goitein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matter</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raziel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keidar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hazzan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rimon</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Portomesenteric thrombosis following laparoscopic bariatric surgery: incidence, patterns of clinical presentation, and etiology in a bariatric patient population</article-title><source>JAMA Surg</source><volume>148</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2013.1053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23715896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0006"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghanem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De La Cruz-Munoz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Domkowski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessing risk factors, presentation, and management of portomesenteric vein thrombosis after sleeve gastrectomy: a multicenter case-control study</article-title><source>Surg Obes Relat Dis</source><volume>14</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>478</fpage><lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.soard.2017.10.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29174885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0007"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0007"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Villagr&#225;n</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cariaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Araya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Portomesenteric vein thrombosis after laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy: incidence, analysis and follow-up in 1236 consecutive cases</article-title><source>Obes Surg</source><volume>26</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>2555</fpage><lpage>2561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11695-016-2183-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27079191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5069330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0008"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0008"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joh</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D-I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mesenteric and portal vein thrombosis: treated with early initiation of anticoagulation</article-title><source>Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg</source><volume>29</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejvs.2004.10.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15649730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0009"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0009"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#350;en</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>T&#252;rk&#231;apar</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Porto-mesenteric vein thrombosis after laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy. A case report</article-title><source>Int J Surg Case Rep</source><volume>79</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>424</fpage><lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijscr.2021.01.086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33524799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7851411</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Speranskaya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olivares</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pascual</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez De Cabo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masmiquel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mesenteric vein thrombosis after laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy</article-title><source>Clin Obes</source><volume>3</volume><issue>1-2</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cob.12012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25586392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0011"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0011"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#199;etink&#252;nar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erdem</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aktimur</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aziret</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#214;zdas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Y&#252;rekli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effect of laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy on morbid obesity and obesity related comorbidities: a cohort study</article-title><source>Ulusal Cerrahi Dergisi</source><volume>31</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>202</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5152/UCD.2015.2993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26668527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4674040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0012"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0012"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muneer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelrahman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Menyar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zarour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Awad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Dhaheri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Portomesenteric vein thrombosis after laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy: 3 case reports and a literature review</article-title><source>Am J Case Rep</source><volume>17</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12659/ajcr.896892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27068354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4831301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0013"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0013"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Condat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pessione</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillaire</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Denninger</surname><given-names>M-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guillin</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poliquin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Current outcome of portal vein thrombosis in adults: risk and benefit of anticoagulant therapy</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><volume>120</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2001</year><fpage>490</fpage><lpage>497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/gast.2001.21209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11159889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0014"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0014"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gandhi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaul</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mesenteric vein thrombosis after laparoscopic gastric sleeve procedure</article-title><source>J Thromb Thrombol</source><volume>30</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11239-009-0434-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20140480</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarr</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamath</surname><given-names>PS.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mesenteric venous thrombosis</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>345</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>1683</fpage><lpage>1688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra010076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11759648</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn id="d35e86"><p id="notep0001">Competing Interests: The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>