<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Iran J Nurs Midwifery Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Iran J Nurs Midwifery Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1516</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">iranjnmres</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJNMR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Iranian Journal of Nursing and Midwifery Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1735-9066</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2228-5504</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer -- Medknow Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10215542</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10215542.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10215542</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10215542</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37250949</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijnmr.ijnmr_381_20</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJNMR-28-110</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effect of Local Hyperthermia on Respiratory Indices of Patients with Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahpasand</surname><given-names initials="M">Masume</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadpour</surname><given-names initials="A">Ali</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Najafi</surname><given-names initials="S">Samane</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sobhani</surname><given-names initials="M">Mansooreh</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>School of Nursing, Gonabad University of Medical Sciences, Gonabad, Iran</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>School of Nursing, Nursing Research Center, Gonabad University of Medical Sciences, Gonabad, Iran</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>School of Nursing, Social Development &amp; Health Promotion Research Center, Gonabad University of Medical Sciences, Gonabad, Iran</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Internal Medicine, School of Edicine, Allameh Bohlool Hospital, Gonabad University of Medical Sciences, Gonabad, Iran</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><italic toggle="yes"><bold>Address for correspondence</bold></italic>: Dr. Ali Mohammadpour, Gonabad University of Medical Sciences, Next to the Asian Road, Gonabad, Khorasan Razavi, Gonabad - 0098, Iran. E-mail: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="amohammadpur@yahoo.com">amohammadpur@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Jan-Feb</season><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>28</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">436730</issue-id><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>27</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>27</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-05-06 14:25:14.593"><day>06</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#169; 2023 Iranian Journal of Nursing and Midwifery Research</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncsalicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access journal, and articles are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as appropriate credit is given and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="IJNMR-28-110.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Background:</title><p>Change in respiratory indices is the most common problem in Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) patients. This problem is managed through pharmaceutical and non-pharmaceutical methods. This study aimed to determine local hyperthermia effect on respiratory parameters of COPD patients.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Materials and Methods:</title><p>This randomized controlled trial study was conducted on 46 patients with COPD referred to Allameh Bohlool Hospital in Gonabad, Iran in 2019. The participants were randomly assigned into two groups using quadrupled blocks. In both groups, a local pack was placed on the anterior chest for 23 min twice daily for 5 days. In the intervention group, the temperature of the hot pack was 50&#176; and in the placebo group was the same as the body temperature. Respiratory indices including force vital capacity (FVC), forced expiratory volume in first second (FEV1), etc., were measured and compared before and after the last intervention in both groups. To gather data, demographic information form and respiratory indices record form were used.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Results:</title><p>Compared to before the intervention, all respiratory indices such as vital capacity (VC) (z = -4.25, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), FEV1 (t<sub>22</sub> = -114.18, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), PEF (t<sub>22</sub> = 5.91, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) in the experimental group were increased significantly. Moreover, the difference in the mean respiratory indicators such as Pick Expiratory Flow rate (PEF) (t<sub>44</sub> = 94.63, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and SPO<sub>2</sub> (z = -3.27, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) was also statistically significant in the two groups before and after the intervention.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Conclusions:</title><p>Local hyperthermia is effective in the improvement of respiratory indices among COPD patients, but it is recommended to conduct further studies before the implementation of this approach.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Chronic obstructive</kwd><kwd>hyperthermia</kwd><kwd>pulmonary disease</kwd><kwd>respiration</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) is a disease accompanied by a continuum of respiratory symptoms and restriction of airflow.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] According to the prediction of the World Health Organization, more than 200 million individuals around the world live with COPD.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] A survey study conducted in Iran reported the prevalence of COPD as 5.7%.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] This disease is a condition that causes high morbidity and mortality globally and is currently considered one of the main public health issues.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] Patients with COPD experience symptoms including short breathing, coughing, and fatigue.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</p><p>To assess the status of the disease and the efficacy of specific pharmaceutical methods for COPD, respiratory symptoms are assessed regularly.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] According to Peter, measuring lung function by spirometry is the most sensitive way to diagnose COPD and determine lung function.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] Symptoms aggregation in patients with COPD leads to serious outcomes and is related to an increase in using health care, a decrease in lung function, an increase in referral to hospital, and even death.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] Therefore, the treatment and control of patients with COPD symptoms are most important. COPD is controlled pharmaceutically and nonpharmaceutically. Airway dilators, corticosteroids, antibiotics, and expectorants are the medications used to treat this disease.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] These medications cause unexpected side effects in addition to useful effects and despite the high costs of treatment for patients with COPD, a thorough recovery could not be achieved.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] Therefore, nonpharmaceutical strategies are developed to manage this disease. Training patients and their families and providing special services for these patients such as breathing exercises, physical therapy, and occupational therapy to save energy during daily activities are among the appropriate nursing interventions.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] One of the recommended nonpharmaceutical methods to relieve symptoms of the patients is hyperthermia, which is expected to improve these patients through various mechanisms.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] During the increase in the temperature of body tissues, numerous changes occur. One of these changes is the dilation of blood vessels which via the increase in blood flow in inflamed and damaged regions removes toxic metabolites such as histamine and bradykinin and improves oxygen flow.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] Besides, according to other studies, hyperthermia increases the synthesis of Nitric Oxide (NO).[<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] NO is used as a bronchodilator and plays a role in the regulation of the diameter of respiratory tracts, preserving mucosa, and repairing it.[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</p><p>For hyperthermia, various methods, including local hyperthermia, sauna, and warm water bathing are used.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] Studies results indicate that sauna therapy is accompanied by a decline in the risk of acute and chronic respiratory disorders, improvement of the obstruction of airways, and improvement of life quality in patients with COPD. In addition, no side effect caused by sauna therapy was observed.</p><p>Although the benefits of systemic heat therapy are proven in previous studies,[<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref><xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] the access to saunas and systemic heat therapy in medical centers is difficult and expensive. Therefore, we do not see its usage in medical centers. Local hyperthermia using a hot pack is one of the techniques used to apply heat to the body surface.[<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] Topical hyperthermia is a cheap, accessible, and easy intervention and is more accepted publicly. Mohammadpour <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] in their study found that localized hyperthermia of the chest is effective in improving the respiration of patients with Acute Coronary Syndrome (ACS). However, Bito <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] in their study, expressed that hyperthermia with a hot pack could not change respiratory functions. In terms of the contradictory results of studies and as the effect of topical hyperthermia with a hot pack on respiratory indices in the patients with COPD is not yet investigated (we could not find the effects), this study aimed to determine the effect of local hyperthermia on respiratory indices in patients with COPD.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>This randomized controlled clinical trial was conducted from December 2018 to March 2019. The research was done in internal wards of the training hospital covered by Gonabad University of Medical Sciences, Gonabad, Iran. The study sample included all patients with COPD who were referred to the study place. The study was registered in the Iranian clinical trial registry center IRCT20161004030141N1.</p><p>Inclusion criteria for this study included the age of 40&#8211;70 years,[<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] stage 2&#8211;4 of the disease according to the Global Initiative for Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) criterion,[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] Body Mass Index (BMI) of 18.5&#8211;25, no history of mental and hyperthyroidism based on the patient's self-report and physician approval, consciousness, speaking and communication ability, stable physiological state to answer the questions, no structural disorder or known deformity and lesions (swelling, sores, scratches, and rash) in the chest area, not having conditions of contraindication of spirometry not controlled Hypertension (HTN), communicable respiratory infection, active hemoptysis, recent surgery of the eye or ear, myringorupture, recent history of Cerebrovascular Accident (CVA) or embolism, history of Myocardial Infarction (MI) or unstable angina in recent 6 weeks. Exclusion criteria included lack of tendency and cooperation to continue participating in each step of the study, the incidence of any clinical conditions, which need specific diagnostic and therapeutic attempts, and if local hyperthermia is contraindicated according to the opinion of the specialist, and in case of loss of consciousness during the treatment. The researcher identified the criteria based on interviews, physical examinations, and spirometry indicators. The sample size was computed at 23 individuals using G-power software version 3, T family tests, and statistical test comparing two independent groups and considering confidence coefficient of 95%, test power of 90%, and effect size of 1.09, which finally by 5% attrition rate for each group, 24 individuals were considered [<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Consort diagram for the patient selection mechanism</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJNMR-28-110-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>The research units were selected based on their availability according to the study's inclusion criteria and were then randomly assigned to the two groups using quadrupled blocks. In this method, the six possible conditions were listed, one number was assigned to each block, and a number was selected by a person other than the researcher by random. The main researcher registered patients and assigned them to the intervention and control groups. Besides, blinding was not performed. The data were collected using the patient's demographic profile and the form of recording respiratory indices. The demographic information form included questions such as age, gender, weight, height, educational level, marital status, hospitalization, smoking history, history of underlying disease, which were completed before the intervention based on the patient's medical record or through interviewing the patient or self-report. Form of recording respiratory indices included Vital Capacity (VC), Force Vital Capacity (FVC), forced expiratory volume in first second (FEV1), FEV/FVC, Pick Expiratory Flow rate (PEF), forced expiratory flow at 25%&#8211;75% (FEF25-75), blood oxygen saturation (SPO<sub>2</sub>), and Respiration Rate (RR). Spirometer system Miri Spir model manufactured by Italy and pulse oximeter system model Nellcor manufactured by America were used to measure respiratory indicators.</p><p>The patients in both groups received routine COPD treatments. At baseline, respiratory indices in both groups were measured and recorded. In the intervention group, hot packs were used for local hyperthermia, which was a special cotton bag with a standard size of 25 &#215; 35 containing hydrophile silicate and was heated to 50&#176;C by a hydrocollator. It was then placed in a special towel and was used for 23 min on the front of the chest in a semi-fowler position.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] The hot pack was used twice a day every 12 h. The hyperthermia continued for 5 days. In the placebo group, a similar hot pack was used at the same time yet with a temperature of 37&#176;C (equal to body temperature) twice a day for 5 days, the respiratory indices were measured and recorded again 24 h after the last intervention in both groups.</p><p>The descriptive statistics were reported as frequency, percentage, and mean (SD). Mann&#8211;Whitney U test, Chi-square test, Wilcoxon signed-rank test, paired t-test, and independent t-test were used to analyze the data. The significance level was considered as 0.05. The statistical software used for data analysis was SPSS software (version 23, IBM Corp. Armonk, NY, USA).</p><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Ethical considerations</title><p>After obtaining the approval of the ethics committee (IR.GMU.REC.1398.079), the study was started. The participants were informed of the objectives of the study, and a written informed consent was signed by them.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title>Results</title><p>The data relating to 46 patients with COPD were analyzed. The mean (SD) age of the participants was 63.05 (8.45) years. Most of the participants in this study were male patients (52.17%). Results of tests of Man&#8211;Whitney U and Chi-square tests showed no significant difference regarding demographic information among study groups, and the groups were homogeny in this regard [<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>].</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of demographic information of the patients with COPD* between the two groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variable</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=23)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=23)</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Test statistic</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">&#160;</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)**</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.69 (9.17)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.30 (7.87)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.35<sup>$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.39 (8.01)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.10 (9.13)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.58<sup>$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158.52 (7.21)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162.17 (9.20)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.43<sup>$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI***</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.99 (2.46)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.67 (2.68)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.61<sup>$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitalization</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.34 (3.60)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.21 (2.10)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.86<sup>$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)****</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Test statistic</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>df</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Gender</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (43.47)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (60.86)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (56.52)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (39.13)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Stage of disease</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;2<sup>nd</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (39.13)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (17.39)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.01<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;3<sup>rd</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (39.13)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (60.86)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;4<sup>th</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (21.73)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (21.73)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Smoking history</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (21.73)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (21.73)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (78.26)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (78.26)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Occupation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Governmental/self-employed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (21.73)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (34.78)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.85<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Household</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (52.17)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (39.13)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Retired</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (26.08)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (26.08)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Income</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Insufficient</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (43.47)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (69.50)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.18<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Sufficient</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (56.52)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (30.43)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Place of residence</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Urban</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (47.82)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (26.08)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.33<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Rural</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (52.17)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (73.91)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">History of underlying disease</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (52.18)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (47.82)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (47.82)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (52.18)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Type of underlying disease</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Diabetes and heart disease</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (11.11)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (27.27)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48<sup>$$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Hypertension</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (88.89)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (72.73)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">History of respiratory disease</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Fewer than 1 year</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (4.34)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (26.08)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.21<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;1-5 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (60.86)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (47.82)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;More than 5 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (34.78)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (26.08)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><p>*Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease. **Standard deviation. ***Body Mass Index. ****Number (Percent). <sup>$</sup>Mann&#8211;Whitney. <sup>$$</sup>Chi square. <sup>$$$</sup>Fisher's exact test</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Results did not show any significant statistical difference in FEV1/FVC (z = -1.49, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.13, Wilcoxon test), FEF25-75 (z = -4.19, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.82, Wilcoxon test), SPO<sub>2</sub> (z = -1.19, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.23, Wilcoxon test), and RR (z = -0.63, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.49, Wilcoxon test) before and after intervention in the placebo group, but according to the results of this test and VC (t<sub>22</sub> = -15.90, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, Paired t-test), FVC (z = -7.70, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.007, Wilcoxon test), FEV1 (t<sub>22</sub> = -114.18, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, Paired t-test), and PEF (t<sub>22</sub> = -52.36, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, Paired t-test) were different in the placebo group, so after the intervention they were decreased. Moreover, there were significant statistical differences in all respiratory indicators such as VC (z = -4.25, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, Wilcoxon test), FEV1 (t<sub>22</sub> = -114.18, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, Paired t-test), PEF (t<sub>22</sub> = 5.91, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, Paired t-test), SPO<sub>2</sub> (z = -4.22, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, Wilcoxon test) and etc., before and after intervention in the experimental group so that these indicators after the intervention in this group were increased.</p><p>After the intervention, there was no significant statistical difference in terms of VC (t<sub>44</sub> = 1.20, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.23, Independent t-test), FVC (t<sub>44</sub> = 1.20, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.30, Independent t-test), FEV1 (t<sub>44</sub> = 0.86, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.39, Independent t-test) between the two placebo and experimental groups. But there were significant statistical difference in respiratory indicators including FEV1/FVC (z = -4.63, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, Mann&#8211;Whitney U test), PEF (t<sub>44</sub> = 2.59, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.01, Independent t-test), FEF25-75 (z = -2.07, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.03, Mann&#8211;Whitney U test), SPO<sub>2</sub> (z = -2.81, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, Mann&#8211;Whitney U test) and RR (t<sub>44</sub> = -6.24, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, Independent t-test) after intervention between the two placebo and experimental groups [<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>].</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The comparison of mean respiratory indices before and the intervention between two groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Respiratory indices</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental group</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo group</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Test statistic</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">df</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">VC* [L]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Before</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56 (0.58)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56 (0.89)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.03<sup>$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;After</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.84 (0.57)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.58 (0.84)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20<sup>$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Test statistic</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-113.88</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-15.90</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;df</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">FVC** [L]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Before</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 (0.67)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 (0.65)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.13<sup>$$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;After</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47 (0.67)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 (0.64)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20<sup>$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Test statistic</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.25<sup>$$$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.70<sup>$$$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;df</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">FEV1*** [L]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Before</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 (0.38)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.41)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.41<sup>$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;After</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.38)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 (0.41)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86<sup>$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Test statistic</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-114.18<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.20<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;df</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">FEV1/FVC [L]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Before</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.26 (18.81)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.78 (11.54)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40<sup>$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;After</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.32 (8.03)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.03 (11.64)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.63<sup>$$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Test statistic</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.83<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.49<sup>$$$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;df</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">PEF**** [L/S]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Before</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 (0.62)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33 (0.68)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.32<sup>$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;After</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.74 (0.63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 (0.67)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.59<sup>$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Test statistic</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 91<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-52.36<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;df</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">FEF25-75***** [L/S]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Before</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (0.38)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 (0.41)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.42<sup>$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;After</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.06 (10.01)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 (0.27)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.07<sup>$$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Test statistic</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.22<sup>$$$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.19<sup>$$$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;df</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">SPO<sub>2</sub>****** [%]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Before</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.82 (2.70)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.04 (2.43)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.10<sup>$$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;After</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.26 (2.28)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.52 (1.78)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.81<sup>$$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Test statistic</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.22<sup>$$$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.19<sup>$$$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;df</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">[beat per minute] RR*******</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Before</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.26 (1.71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.82 (1.64)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.24<sup>$$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;After</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.47 (1.64)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.78 (1.92)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-6.24<sup>$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Test statistic</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.22<sup>$$$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.68<sup>$$$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;df</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF2"><p>*Vital Capacity. **Forced Vital Capacity. ***Forced Expiratory Volume in First Second. ****Pick Expiratory Flow Rate. *****Forced Expiratory Flow at 25%-75%. ******Blood Oxygen Saturation. ******Respiration Rate. <sup>$</sup>Independent <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>- test. <sup>$$</sup>Paired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test. <sup>$$$</sup>Mann&#8211;Whitney. <sup>$$$$</sup>Wilcoxon</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The results showed the difference in the mean of all respiratory indicators such as VC (t<sub>44</sub> = 94.63, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, Independent t-test), FEV1 (t<sub>44</sub> = 61.16, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, Independent t-test), FVC (z = -5.87, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, Mann&#8211;Whitney U test), PEF (t<sub>44</sub> = 94.63, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, Independent t-test), SPO<sub>2</sub> (z = -3.27, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, Mann&#8211;Whitney U test) was statistically significant in the two groups before and after the intervention [<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>].</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The comparison of the changes in the mean respiratory indices before the intervention between the two groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Respiratory indices</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experimental group</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo group</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Test statistic</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">df</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean deviation (SD)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean deviation (SD)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VC*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28 (0.01)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 (0.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.63<sup>$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FVC**</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 (0.28)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.03 (0.04)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-5.87<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FEV1***</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13 (0.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.01 (0.01)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.16<sup>$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FEV1/FVC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.06 (15.57)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.25 (14.09)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.97<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEF****</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 (0.47)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.90 (0.07)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.63<sup>$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FEF25-75*****</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25 (10.11)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.11 (0.27)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.97<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPO<sub>2</sub>******</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.43 (1.19)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 (1.95)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.27<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR*******</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.78 (1.12)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.04 (10.11)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.92<sup>$$</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF3"><p>*Vital Capacity. **Force Vital Capacity. ***Forced Expiratory Volume in First Second. ****Pick Expiratory Flow Rate. *****Forced Expiratory Flow at 25%-75%. ******Blood Oxygen Saturation. *******Respiration Rate. <sup>$</sup>Independent <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test. <sup>$$</sup>Mann&#8211;Whitney</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study aimed to investigate the effect of local hyperthermia on respiratory indices of patients with COPD. The results showed that local thermotherapy of the chest effectively improves respiratory indices. To justify the improvement of respiratory indices, it seems that physiologic changes caused by hyperthermia could be effective. The increase of blood flow of the area, acceleration of excretion of waste and harmful substances produced by metabolism, and facilitating of chemical reactions are examples of these changes Moreover, hyperthermia is effective in increasing oxide nitric synthesis, which plays a role to regulate the diameter of airways, preserving mucosa, and its repair.[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] It can be said that the local hyperthermia causes the decrease in the resistance of pulmonary vessels and their dilation. Following that exchange of oxygen through alveoli on the lung surface and blood improves.[<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] Many diseases related to abnormal function of the respiratory system are caused in terms of insufficient performance of respiratory muscles.[<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] Weakness of respiratory muscles in COPD is effective in changes of respiratory indices.[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] The results of the study by Kim <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] represent that 8 weeks of local hyperthermia improves the strengths of muscles and increases skeletal muscles capillary in muscular fibers. Their study showed that inactive heat could be a tool for the treatment of conditions related to capillary weakness and muscle weakness. Y&#305;ld&#305;r&#305;m <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] showed in one study that local hyperthermia reduces pain and stiffness caused by knee osteoarthritis and improves body function. Therefore, the results of current studies confirmed the positive effect of hyperthermia on respiratory indices.</p><p>Bito <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] conducted a study aimed to investigate the immediate effects of hyperthermia on Chest Wall Mobility (CWM) and respiratory function. In this study, a hot pack increased only the tenth rib excursion which could not change respiratory functions. The hyperthermia with the hot pack was performed only once for 15 min. According to the researchers, the small sample size and short duration of the intervention were limitations of this study. In our study, thermotherapy was used for 23 min, twice a day and every 12 h, and the sample size was 46 people. Therefore, this difference in the results can be in terms of the difference in the duration of intervention and the number of studied people. Nutritional problems are also one of the common problems in patients with COPD, which is related to respiratory indices.[<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] These patients develop gastrointestinal dysfunction due to short breathing, heaviness, problem breathing after eating food, and the inability in sufficient absorption caused by these disorders leads to weight loss, fatigue, weakness, and activity intolerance.[<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] Sadeghian <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] showed in one study that local hyperthermia affects gastrointestinal function in patients undergoing nasogastric tube feeding. According to this scientific finding, although we did not examine the nutritional status of the patients, based on the results of our study on the improvement of respiratory parameters, it can be expected that the improvement of nutrition and the resulting energy levels have also occurred in our study. Therefore, this study supports the results of the current study. Besides, Mohammadian <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] stated that local hyperthermia with a hot pack causes calmness and decline in the anxiety of patients with acute coronary syndrome. They concluded that breathing and oxygen flow are improved following local hyperthermia with a hot pack. Mohammadpour <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] found in their study that local hyperthermia in anterior chest improves breathing and percentage of blood oxygen saturation. The researchers in this study stated a decrease in pulmonary vessels resistance and their dilation, and also an increase in cardiac output following hyperthermia in justifying an increase in percentage of oxygen saturation and improvement of breathing. Due to the direct relationship between pulmonary circulation and respiratory status of patients.[<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] The improvement of pulmonary vessel function following hyperthermia improves oxygen exchange and subsequently increases oxygen saturation percentage.</p><p>Although the study population in these studies is different, its results show positive effects of hyperthermia on vital organs and the possibility of using it even in acute and urgent situations. In addition, in most studies mentioned similar to the current study, hyperthermia of the anterior chest was done, and as the heart and lung are close to each other, and their actions are dependent on each other, these studies can support the results of the current study.</p><p>Study results by Kikuchi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] showed that systemic hyperthermia at a temperature of 60&#176;C is effective in spirometry parameters, exercise enduring, and pulmonary function of the patient with COPD and can improve the obstruction of airways. According to the study, the changes in VC, PEF, and FEF50 were significantly higher in the intervention group than in the control group. They believed a larger improvement of VC, PEF, and FEF50 after repeated Waon therapy in their results was speculated to result from the suppression of airway inflammation and the alleviation of airway obstruction after repeated Waon therapy; the expansibility of lung parenchyma might also be heightened. It can be said that local hyperthermia can dilate the vessels via the increase in vessels' blood flow, removing inflammatory mediators, and stimulating heat receptors in the skin and deeper tissues.[<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] Hence, local hyperthermia in these patients improves vascular endothelial performance, increases the production of nitric oxide and as a result dilates vessels as well as bronchioles and improves lung function in this way.[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</p><p>Kunbootsri <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] concluded in their study that the 6 weeks of repeated sauna treatment could increase FEV1 in patients with allergic rhinitis. They believed that the increase of bronchial smooth muscle endurance and strength from hyperthermia might improve the FEV1. Local hyperthermia can also cause the above mechanism similarly. Results of the study by Kunutsor <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] showed that regular sauna bathing is related to a decrease in the risk of acute and chronic respiratory diseases. Other studies have shown that warming reduces fatigue, improves sleep, and maintains energy.[<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref><xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] These conditions can also improve respiratory indicators.[<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref><xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] Like what happened in the present study.</p><p>One of the limitations of this study is that it was not possible to apply blinding methods to the patients because they could easily detect heat. It is recommended to perform further studies with blinding.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Local hyperthermia improves respiratory indices. These findings are clinically important in nursing care as the improvement of these indicators without using drugs is counted as an important care aim. Therefore, by considering the high prevalence of these patients in all the societies, in case the results of the present study on the effect of local hyperthermia on reducing fatigue among patients with COPD are confirmed in more extensive studies, it can be used as a safe, noninvasive, and cost-effective intervention. This way provides an opportunity for the medical team, especially nurses, to have better care for these patients.</p><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Financial support and sponsorship</title><p>Gonabad University of Medical Sciences</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec2-3"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>Nothing to declare.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This research resulted from the thesis obtaining a master's degree in medical-surgical nursing at Gonabad University of Medical Sciences with the approved code (A-10-1812-1). Their searchers should then thank the university's higher education department, the officials, and the staff of Allameh Bohlool Hospital in Gonabad, especially all the patients participating in this research.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>R-R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Air pollution and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Chronic Dis Transl Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>260</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33336171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cdtm.2020.05.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7729117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yohannes</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Junkes-Cunha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vestbo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of dyspnea and anxiety in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: A critical review</article-title><source>J Am Med Dir Assoc</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1096.e1</fpage><lpage>.7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jamda.2017.09.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29108885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chegeni</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gholami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azargoon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pour</surname><given-names>AHH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Birjandi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norollahi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of progressive muscle relaxation on the management of fatigue and quality of sleep in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: A randomized controlled clinical trial</article-title><source>Complement Ther Clin Pract</source><year>2018</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29705482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ctcp.2018.01.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Montserrat-Capdevila</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsal</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casta&#241;-Abad</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miquel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferran</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinico- epidemiological characteristics of men and women with a new diagnosis of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: A database (SIDIAP) study</article-title><source>BMC Pulm Med 21</source><year>2021</year><volume>44</volume><comment>doi.org/10.1186/s12890-021-01392-y</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12890-021-01392-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7842000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33509131</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spruit</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vercoulen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sprangers</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wouters</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatigue in COPD: An important yet ignored symptom</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>542</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28438501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2213-2600(17)30158-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bajestani</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seyed</surname><given-names>Ali Javad Mousavi</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezaei</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shooshtary</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Araby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relation of serum Vitamin D level and pulmonary punction in COPD patients</article-title><source>Razi J Med Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>40</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosseinzadeh Yonesi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mircheraghi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammdzadeh Moghadam</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mojalli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of thymus vulgaris inhaling on wheezing and respiratory rate in patients with acute exacerbation of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Qtly Horiz Med Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keyhanmanesh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmadi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeddy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagban</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirzaei Bavil</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alipour</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of vitamin C on tracheal responsiveness and pulmonary inflammation in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease model of guinea pig</article-title><source>Physiol Pharmacol</source><year>2013</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>15</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jokar</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khankeh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabiee</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falah Tafti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of home-based pulmonary rehabilitation on daily activity of patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Evid Based Care</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>76</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahpasand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadpour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Najafi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sobhani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of local heat therapy on fatigue among patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: A randomized controlled clinical trial</article-title><source>NPT</source><year>2020</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>31</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadpour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadian</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basiri Moghadam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nematollahi</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of topical heat therapy on chest pain in patients with acute coronary syndrome: A randomised double-blind placebo-controlled clinical trial</article-title><source>J Clin Nurs</source><year>2014</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>3460</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24698126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jocn.12595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sobajima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nozawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Repeated sauna therapy attenuates ventricular remodeling after myocardial infarction in rats by increasing coronary vascularity of noninfarcted myocardium</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>301</volume><fpage>H548</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21622828</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajpheart.00103.2011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirzaei</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khazaei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of nitric oxide in biological systems: A systematic review</article-title><source>J Maz Univ Med Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>222</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiozawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitsunobu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of repeated Waon therapy on exercise tolerance and pulmonary function in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: A pilot controlled clinical trial</article-title><source>Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24363555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/COPD.S50860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3865971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunutsor</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laukkanen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laukkanen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sauna bathing reduces the risk of respiratory diseases: A long-term prospective cohort study</article-title><source>Eur J Epidemiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1107</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28905164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10654-017-0311-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadeghian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadpour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of local heat therapy on gastric residual volume and abdominal distention in patients with nasogastric tube feeding: A randomized controlled clinical trial</article-title><source>J Hayat</source><year>2019</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>55</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadpour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadian</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basiri Moghadam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nematollahi</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of local heat therapy on physiologic parameters of patients with acute coronary syndrome: A randomized controlled clinical trial</article-title><source>J Crit Care Nurs</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jocn.12595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24698126</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kajiwara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeidan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimoura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of deep thermotherapy on chest wall mobility of healthy elderly women</article-title><source>Electromagn Biol Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32131642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/15368378.2020.1737803</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What is the average age for COPD? Medical News Today</article-title><year>2018</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Last accessed on 2020 Feb 23</date-in-citation><comment>Available from: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/323350">https://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/323350</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadian</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadpour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nematollahi</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jamiati</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of local heat therapy in the posterior part of chest on physiologic parameters in the patients with acute coronary syndrome: A randomized double-blind placebo-controlled clinical trial</article-title><source>Sci J Kurd Univ Med Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>81</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eikermann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postoperative respiratory muscle dysfunctionpathophysiology and preventive strategies</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><year>2013</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>961</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23429163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/ALN.0b013e318288834f</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of repeated local heat therapy on skeletal muscle structure and function in humans</article-title><source>J Appl Physiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31971474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/japplphysiol.00701.2019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Y&#305;ld&#305;r&#305;m</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Filiz Ulusoy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bodur</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of heat application on pain, stiffness, physical function and quality of life in patients with knee osteoarthritis</article-title><source>J Clin Nurs</source><year>2010</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1113</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20492056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2702.2009.03070.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mete</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pehlivan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#252;lba&#351;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#252;nen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of malnutrition in COPD and its relationship with the parameters related to disease severity</article-title><source>Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>3307</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30349235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/COPD.S179609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6188194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tajvidi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parsinia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Babaee</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing the effects of nutritional guideline education on spirometric tests in patients with COPD</article-title><source>Iran J Nurs Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunbootsri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janyacharoen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arrayawichanon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chainansamit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanpittaya</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Auvichayapat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effect of six-weeks of sauna on treatment autonomic nervous system, peak nasal inspiratory flow and lung functions of allergic rhinitis Thai patients</article-title><source>Asian Pac J Allergy Immunol</source><year>2013</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>142</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23859414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.12932/AP0262.31.2.2013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Economou</surname><given-names>N-T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ilias</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Velentza</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Papachatzakis</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zarogoulidis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kallianos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sleepiness, fatigue, anxiety and depression in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and obstructive sleep apnea-overlap-syndrome, before and after continuous positive airways pressure therapy</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e0197342</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29889828</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0197342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5995394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sawatari</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishizaka</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyazono</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ando</surname><given-names>S-I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takemoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Three nights leg thermal therapy could improve sleep quality in patients with chronic heart failure</article-title><source>Heart and Vessels</source><year>2018</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28905211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00380-017-1047-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Najafi Mehri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pashandi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmoodi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghanei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of fatigue and spirometery parameters in chemical war victims with respiratory disease</article-title><source>Iran J War Public Health</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>35</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadpour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shakeri</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirzaei</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparing the effect of open and closed ndotracheal suctioning on pain and oxygenation in post CABG patients under mechanical ventilation</article-title><source>Iran J Nurs Midwifery Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25878695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4387642</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>