<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2757</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cureus</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12183529</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12183529.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12183529</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12183529</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40551919</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.84686</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Orthopedics</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Healthcare Technology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Second Look at the Use of VersaWrap&#174; Nerve Protector in Spine Surgery: A Case Report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names initials="A">Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names initials="JR">John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruggeman</surname><given-names initials="A">Adam</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Schouwen</surname><given-names initials="K">Kelly</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keswani</surname><given-names initials="R">Robin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Orthopaedic Surgery, Texas Spine Care, San Antonio, USA </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Orthopaedic Surgery, Research Source, Austin, USA </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Robin Keswani <email>robin@researchtex.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">487761</issue-id><elocation-id>e84686</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>23</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>23</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-06-24 15:25:17.200"><day>24</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2025, Bruggeman et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Bruggeman et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000084686.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/352840-a-second-look-at-the-use-of-versawrap-nerve-protector-in-spine-surgery-a-case-report">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/352840-a-second-look-at-the-use-of-versawrap-nerve-protector-in-spine-surgery-a-case-report</self-uri><abstract><p>The presence of severe epidural fibrosis (EF) during a spinal revision procedure increases the risk of interoperative complications and post-operative success.&#160;We present a retrospective series of one surgeon&#8217;s standard of care application of VersaWrap<sup>&#174;</sup>&#160;Nerve Protector (Alafair Biosciences, Inc., Austin, TX, USA) in 169 lumbar decompressions in conjunction with Depo-Medrol (80 mg) and Marcaine/epinephrine (1 mL) to manage scar tissue tethering of the nerve root to the surrounding tissues.&#160;Of the 169 total lumbar decompression procedures, there were zero (0) complications reported for VersaWrap in conjunction with the medicinal agents in the dosages reported.&#160;A representative case of a patient who later underwent a revision procedure is highlighted to allow a second-look assessment of the initial VersaWrap application.&#160;The surgeon's experience was that VersaWrap bioresorbed completely and that any scar tissue present was easy to remove without significant mechanical disruption. We also discuss standard of care surgical practice with VersaWrap in conjunction with medicinal agents and future directives of VersaWrap application.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>nerve root tethering</kwd><kwd>orthopedic spine surgery</kwd><kwd>post-laminectomy syndrome</kwd><kwd>spine revision surgery</kwd><kwd>versawrap nerve protector</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>Research funding is provided by Alafair Biosciences, Inc.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Epidural fibrosis (EF), the formation of scar tissue in the epidural space of the spine, following a spine surgical procedure is a well-documented contributor of failed back surgery syndrome (FBSS) and other complications including the need for reoperation [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. FBSS is characterized by persistent or recurring pain in the back or legs after a spine procedure and the occurrence of FBSS varies among studies, with estimates from 8% to 20% [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. One study found that EF caused the need for a revision procedure in 4% to 9% of postdisectomy cases [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The presence of postoperative EF significantly increases the technical difficulty and risk of complications during revision spinal procedures [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] and has been reported as the third most common cause of FBSS [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p>The use of perioperative adhesion barriers (or nerve protectors) to reduce the risk of complications in the presence of scar tissue is common. These adhesion barriers (or nerve protectors) have historically included carboxymethylcellulose/polyethylene oxide (CMC/PEO) [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], gelatin USP products [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], bacterial cellulose with mesenchymal stem cells [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], and carbohydrate polymer gels [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>The formation of scar tissue begins with an inflammatory reaction in the first few days after a surgical procedure [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Current literature supports the prophylactic perioperative use of Depo-Medrol for immediate postoperative inflammation control [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and Marcaine/epinephrine for pain management [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Adhesion barriers (or nerve protectors) used in conjunction with medicinal agents may offer promising patient outcomes and there is currently no standard of care for management of nerve root in conjunction with medicinal agents during spine procedures.</p><p>VersaWrap&#174; Nerve Protector (Alafair Biosciences, Inc., Austin, TX, USA), is a thin, gelatinous hydrogel peripheral nerve protector that creates a protective layer between the nerve root and surrounding tissues [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. VersaWrap is comprised of hydrophilic, biocompatible, bioresorbable biopolymers hyaluronic acid (non-animal) and alginate [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. VersaWrap bioresorbs completely, does not remodel into additional tissue, and is designed to bioresorb over a period of three to six months [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The hydrogel is highly conformable and tissue-adherent, precluding the need for suturing or tissue glue [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. VersaWrap&#8217;s conformability and bioresorbable nature may facilitate its integration with other intraoperative agents.</p><p>In this paper, we present a retrospective series of one orthopedic spine surgeon&#8217;s standard of care application method of VersaWrap Nerve Protector in conjunction with Depo-Medrol (80 mg) and Marcaine/epinephrine (1 mL) in 169 lumbar decompressions, from May 2018 to March 2020. A representative case of a patient who later underwent a revision procedure is highlighted to allow a second-look assessment of the initial VersaWrap application.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case presentation</title><p>Initial procedure: left L4-5 laminectomy</p><p>A 42-year-old male presented with chronic low back pain that had been ongoing for many years. He had a surgical history of an L5-S1 fusion and reported reinjury to his back. He had no other relevant medical or personal history. He had undergone multimodal conservative treatment through a series of epidural injections, physical therapy, and daily pain management with anti-inflammatory and narcotic medication use. He was diagnosed with spinal stenosis and elected for a left L4-5 laminectomy.</p><p>Intraoperatively, the laminectomy was performed using the minimally invasive tubular retraction (MITR) technique. The VersaWrap sheet was cut into 1 cm x 1 cm squares, advanced through the tube, and placed onto the peripheral nerve root and the adjacent dura, under the lamina of the spine (Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The VersaWrap wetting solution was added dropwise to the sheet to create a tissue-adherent, conformable, gelatinous hydrogel layer (Figure <xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Depo-Medrol (80 mg) and Marcaine/epinephrine (1 mL) were applied separately on top of the VersaWrap to reduce immediate postoperative pain and inflammation.</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Top view illustration of VersaWrap Nerve Protector 1 cm x 1 cm square sheet application onto the peripheral nerve root and the adjacent dura, under the lamina of the spine in the laminectomy procedure.</title><p>Image reproduced with permission from&#160;Alafair Biosciences, Inc., Austin, TX, USA</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000084686-i01.jpg"/></fig><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Top view illustration of VersaWrap Nerve Protector wetting solution dropwise application on implanted VersaWrap sheet on the peripheral nerve root and the adjacent dura, under the lamina of the spine in the laminectomy procedure to create a tissue-adherent, conformable, gelatinous hydrogel layer.</title><p>Image reproduced with permission from&#160;Alafair Biosciences, Inc., Austin, TX, USA</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000084686-i02.jpg"/></fig><p>Second procedure: left L4-5 revision laminectomy</p><p>At 21 months post-operative, the patient had recurrent disk herniation and significant spinal stenosis along with correlating radicular pain down his left leg. The patient was diagnosed with post-laminectomy syndrome and elected for a left L4-5 laminectomy revision.</p><p>During reoperation, the revision procedure was performed using the MITR technique. The surgeon noted that the previously applied VersaWrap (left L4-5 laminectomy) had completely bioresorbed. When he encountered scar tissue, he was able to easily remove this tissue from the nerve root and adjacent tissues without significant mechanical disruption.</p><p>Surgeon experience was that the scar on tissues where VersaWrap was not previously placed (L5-S1 fusion) was significantly thicker when compared to the scar on tissues where VersaWrap was applied in the initial laminectomy (Video <xref rid="VID1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="video" id="VID1" orientation="portrait"><label>Video 1</label><caption><title>Video of scar on tissues being easily removed where VersaWrap Nerve Protector was applied in the initial left L4-5 laminectomy (left side). Thick scar on tissues where VersaWrap was not previously placed in the L5-S1 fusion (right side).</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000084686-i01.mp4" id="d67e210" position="anchor" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mp4" orientation="portrait"/></fig><p>After the scar tissue was completely removed, the VersaWrap sheet was cut into 1 cm x 1 cm squares, advanced through the tube, and placed on the peripheral nerve root and the adjacent dura, under the lamina of the spine. The VersaWrap wetting solution was added to the sheet dropwise to create a hydrogel layer (Video <xref rid="VID2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Depo-Medrol (80 mg) and Marcaine/epinephrine (1 mL) were applied separately on top of the VersaWrap to reduce immediate postoperative pain and inflammation.</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="video" id="VID2" orientation="portrait"><label>Video 2</label><caption><title>Video of VersaWrap Nerve Protector application during the revision laminectomy. The VersaWrap sheet was applied onto nerve root and then the VersaWrap wetting solution was applied onto the implanted VersaWrap sheet. Conformance to underlying tissues is observed with application of VersaWrap solution.</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="cureus-0017-00000084686-i02.mp4" id="d67e221" position="anchor" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mp4" orientation="portrait"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>VersaWrap Nerve Protector was implanted as standard of care during 169 lumbar decompressions in conjunction with Depo-Medrol (80 mg) and Marcaine/epinephrine (1 mL) to manage scar tissue tethering of the nerve root to the surrounding tissues such as bone, dura, and muscle. Of the 169 total lumbar decompression procedures, there were zero (0) complications reported for VersaWrap application in conjunction with Depo-Medrol and Marcaine/epinephrine in the dosages reported [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p><p>The rate of spine surgical procedures continues to increase worldwide [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. It is known that patient success rates decline with each reoperation [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. VersaWrap is a novel option unique from previous barrier (or nerve protector) technologies. Similar barrier (or nerve protector) technologies suggest easy-to-use applications and promising clinical outcomes but lack reports of conjunction use with medicinal agents [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. When used in conjunction with medicinal agents, other technologies report reduced postoperative pain after spine procedures [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Yet, when used alone, these same technologies also report postoperative complications, such as disturbed muscle healing [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Surgeon experience in our representative case was that VersaWrap use allowed for minimal mechanical disruption and decreased the risk of complications during reoperation in the presence of scar tissue. These findings suggest that VersaWrap, when used with Depo-Medrol and Marcaine/epinephrine, was not associated with intraoperative or postoperative complications in this series.</p><p>The use of VersaWrap in surgical procedures is well-established [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>-<xref rid="REF20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].&#160;Intraoperative local irrigation with medicinal agents during spine procedures is a common practice [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The irrigation activity will vary based on the procedure, patient characteristics, and combination of techniques and treatments. VersaWrap is often used in procedures where surgeons irrigate with anesthetics, antibiotics, or steroids, but the report of VersaWrap in conjunction with medicinal agents is unknown, to our knowledge, until now.</p><p>While the present series reports compatibility of VersaWrap with medicinal agents, there are some limitations that warrant consideration. First, this series provides only one representative case. Second, the synergistic impact that VersaWrap and medicinal agents have on one another still needs to be quantified. This series did not consider clinical evidence that the viscous biopolymers in VersaWrap provide a vehicle for localized delivery of medicinal agents that are currently only administered systemically. An additional study reviewing the impact that the viscous VersaWrap gel may have on sustained local release of medicinal agent is warranted. Despite these limitations, the present series allows for a second-look assessment of the initial VersaWrap application and provides surgeon experience that any scar tissue present was easy to remove without significant mechanical disruption.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The integration of VersaWrap with medicinal agents represents a promising approach to manage scar tissue tethering of the nerve root to the surrounding tissues in spine procedures. The ability to apply medicinal agents alongside VersaWrap introduces a new sequela that optimizes personalized treatment options based on specific patient anatomy or conditions and reduces the need for systemic administration of drugs. We expect continued development of VersaWrap application techniques in innovative spine procedures, giving peer-to-peer insight and advancement of use to allow more patients the option of VersaWrap.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent for treatment and open access publication was obtained or waived by all participants in this study.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> Research funding is provided by Alafair Biosciences, Inc. .</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#160; Robin Keswani, Kelly Van Schouwen, Adam Bruggeman</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#160; Robin Keswani, Kelly Van Schouwen, Adam Bruggeman</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#160; Robin Keswani, Kelly Van Schouwen, Adam Bruggeman</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#160; Robin Keswani, Kelly Van Schouwen, Adam Bruggeman</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The aetiologies of failed back surgery syndrome: a systematic review</article-title><source>J Back Musculoskelet Rehabil</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Clancy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><volume>30</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27689601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3233/BMR-150318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Epidural fibrosis after lumbar disc surgery: prevention and outcome evaluation</article-title><source>Asian Spine J</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohi Eldin</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel Razek</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>370</fpage><lpage>385</lpage><volume>9</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26097652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4184/asj.2015.9.3.370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4472585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Prevalence of failed back surgery syndrome across hospital corporation of America healthcare in the United States, their correlation with mood disorders and other lifestyle-related comorbidities</article-title><source>Am J Lifestyle Med</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez-Ramos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanif</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hurlock</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><volume>18</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39262884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/15598276231196499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11384841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Prevalence, characteristics, and burden of failed back surgery syndrome: the influence of various residual symptoms on patient satisfaction and quality of life as assessed by a nationwide Internet survey in Japan</article-title><source>J Pain Res</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishihara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikemoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ushida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>811</fpage><lpage>823</lpage><volume>10</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28435318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/JPR.S129295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5388346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Clinical assessment of a novel antiadhesion barrier gel: prospective, randomized, multicenter, clinical trial of ADCON-L to inhibit postoperative peridural fibrosis and related symptoms after lumbar discectomy</article-title><source>Am J Orthop</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>de Tribolet</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Porchet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><volume>27</volume><year>1998</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9506196</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Reduction of leg pain by Oxiplex gel after lumbar discectomy in patients with predominant leg pain and elevated levels of lower back pain a prospective, randomized, blinded, multicenter clinical study</article-title><source>J Spinal Disord Tech</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehmsen</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiacchierini</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krelle</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>diZerega</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><volume>28</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23897052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/BSD.0b013e3182a35590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Prospective randomized comparative study to evaluate epidural fibrosis and surgical outcome in patients undergoing lumbar laminectomy with epidural autologous free fat graft or gelfoam: a preliminary study</article-title><source>Int J Appl Basic Med Res</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sobti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grover</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grewal</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><volume>8</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29744317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/ijabmr.IJABMR_349_17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5932927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A novel bacterial cellulose membrane immobilized with human umbilical cord mesenchymal stem cells-derived exosome prevents epidural fibrosis</article-title><source>Int J Nanomedicine</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shangguan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>5257</fpage><lpage>5273</lpage><volume>13</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30237713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/IJN.S167880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6136916</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Delayed detected unexpected complication of ADCON-L&#174; gel in lumbar surgery</article-title><source>J Korean Neurosurg Soc</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><volume>48</volume><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21082057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3340/jkns.2010.48.3.268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2966731</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Efficacy of the morphine-Adcon-L compound in the management of postoperative pain after lumbar microdiscectomy</article-title><source>Neurosurgery</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mastronardi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pappagallo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puzzilli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tatta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>518</fpage><lpage>524</lpage><volume>50</volume><year>2002</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11841719</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00006123-200203000-00017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Regulation of matrix turnover: fibroblasts, forces, factors and fibrosis</article-title><source>Biochem Soc Trans</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Laurent</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McAnulty</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>647</fpage><lpage>651</lpage><volume>35</volume><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17635112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1042/BST0350647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Does epidural corticosteroid application during spinal surgery reduce postoperative pain?: An adjunct to multimodal analgesia</article-title><source>Clin Spine Surg</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards C</surname><given-names>2nd</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruess</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><volume>37</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/BSD.0000000000001586</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11421561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38446588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Intradermal and intramuscular bupivacaine reduces opioid use following noninstrumented spine surgery</article-title><source>World Neurosurg</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cleary</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciacci</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><volume>170</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.wneu.2022.11.099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36442775</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>VersaWrap&#174; hydrogel barrier for reducing adhesions</article-title><date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date-in-citation><year>2024</year><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.alafairbiosciences.com/spine">https://www.alafairbiosciences.com/spine</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Polysaccharide-based films for the prevention of unwanted postoperative adhesions at biological interfaces</article-title><source>Acta Biomater</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayes</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><volume>106</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32097711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.actbio.2020.02.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8552357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Results of a bioresorbable hydrogel sheet utalized as an adhesion barrier in spine surgery</article-title><source>JSM Neurosurg Spine</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruggeman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>VanSchouwen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>1104</fpage><volume>9</volume><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Trends in lumbar spinal fusion-a literature review</article-title><source>J Spine Surg</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Reisener</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pumberger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shue</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Girardi</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>752</fpage><lpage>761</lpage><volume>6</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33447679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.21037/jss-20-492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7797794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Outcomes following use of VersaWrap nerve protector in treatment of patients with recurrent compressive neuropathies</article-title><source>Front Surg</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hones</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hones</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>1123375</fpage><volume>10</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37025263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fsurg.2023.1123375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10071003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Sugical arthoscopy with intramuscular-articular hylauronic acid/alginate adjunct in the treatment of osteoarthritis</article-title><source>Tech Foot Ankle Surg</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bridges</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCahon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parekh</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><volume>10</volume><year>2024</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A novel urological application of hyaluroinic acid/alginate sheet to prevent adhesion formation: a technique guide and case series</article-title><source>Cureus</source><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>16</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.75849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11650429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39691412</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>