<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Arch Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Arch Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1671</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ams</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AMS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Archives of Medical Science : AMS</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1734-1922</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1896-9151</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Termedia Publishing</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10507757</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10507757.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10507757</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10507757</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37732043</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5114/aoms/171473</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">171473</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Letter</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Association between electronic nicotine delivery systems use and risk of stroke: a meta-analysis of 1,024,401 participants</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Awad</surname><given-names initials="K">Kamal</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names initials="M">Maged</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names initials="SS">Seth S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Banach</surname><given-names initials="M">Maciej</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">4</xref><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">5</xref><on-behalf-of>the Lipid and Blood Pressure Meta-analysis Collaboration (LBPMC) Group</on-behalf-of></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>Faculty of Medicine, Zagazig University, Zagazig, El-Sharkia, Egypt</aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label>Primary Health Care Centers, Health Insurance Organization, El-Sharkia, Egypt</aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label>Johns Hopkins Ciccarone Center for the Prevention of Cardiovascular Disease, Baltimore, MD, United States</aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label>Department of Preventive Cardiology and Lipidology, Medical University of Lodz (MUL), Lodz, Poland</aff><aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label>Department of Cardiology and Adult Congenital Heart Diseases, Polish Mother&#8217;s Memorial Hospital Research Institute (PMMHRI), Lodz, Poland</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Prof. Maciej Banach MD, PhD, FNLA, FAHA, FESC, FASA Department of Preventive Cardiology and Lipidology, Medical University of Lodz, Rzgowska 281/289, 93-338 Lodz, Poland. Phone: +48 42 62711124, Fax: +48 42 639 37 71. E-mail: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Maciej.banach@icloud.com">Maciej.banach@icloud.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">445550</issue-id><fpage>1538</fpage><lpage>1540</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>27</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>20</day><month>09</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-09-21 11:25:17.853"><day>21</day><month>09</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#169; 2023 Termedia &amp; Banach</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncsalicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) License, allowing third parties to copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format and to remix, transform, and build upon the material, provided the original work is properly cited and states its license.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="AMS-19-5-171473.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>To evaluate the relationship between electronic nicotine delivery systems (ENDS) use and the risk of stroke when compared to non-smokers.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Methods</title><p>A comprehensive search was conducted until June 15, 2023. We included observational studies that assessed association of current or former usage of ENDS with risk of stroke compared with non-smokers, reported the risk estimate as odds ratio (OR) or hazard ratio (HR) and were adjusted for possible confounders.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>6 studies with 1,024,401 participants were included in our analysis. ENDS use was associated with a significant increased risk of stroke (OR = 1.52; 95% CI: 1.17&#8211;1.97) compared with non-users. A non-significant association was found between former ENDS use and risk of stroke (OR = 1.03; 95% CI: 0.87&#8211;1.21).</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The ENDS usage appears to be associated with a higher risk of stroke compared to non-use, whereas there was no association between former ENDS use and the risk of stroke.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>lifestyle changes</kwd><kwd>risk</kwd><kwd>prevention</kwd><kwd>smoking</kwd><kwd>stroke</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>In recent years, the use of electronic nicotine delivery systems (ENDS) has dramatically increased, particularly as an alternative to traditional tobacco smoking. In the United States, it is estimated that about 8 million adults have used ENDS at some point in their lives [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. While the association of ENDS with myocardial infarction has been suggested by multiple studies, their association with stroke remains unclear and inconsistent across relevant studies [<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Therefore, we conducted this meta-analysis to evaluate the relationship between ENDS use and the risk of stroke when compared to non-smokers.</p><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec1"><title>Methods</title><p>A comprehensive search of PubMed, Scopus, and Web of Science was conducted from inception year of each database until June 15, 2023, using a combination of relevant keywords such as &#8220;e-cigarette&#8221;, &#8220;ENDS&#8221; and &#8220;stroke&#8221;. We included observational studies that assessed association of current or former usage of ENDS with risk of stroke compared with non-smokers, reported the risk estimate as odds ratio (OR) or hazard ratio (HR) with a 95% confidence interval (CI), and adjusted for possible confounders (as per each individual study). We assessed the risk of bias in cohort studies using the Newcastle-Ottawa Scale and in cross-sectional studies using the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality checklist. Under the assumption of rare event prevalence (&lt; 10%), we employed the random-effects model to combine adjusted risk estimates as a pooled OR with corresponding 95% CI. We used the <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> and &#967;<sup>2</sup> tests for heterogeneity assessment. A leave-one-out sensitivity analysis was conducted to assess the impact of each individual study on the overall combined risk estimate. Furthermore, an additional sensitivity analysis was conducted, excluding studies that utilized HR as their risk estimate. Due to the inclusion of &lt; 10 studies in this meta-analysis, it was not possible to reliably assess publication bias using funnel plot asymmetry tests, as recommended by Cochrane. All analyses were conducted using MetaXL version 5.3 (Microsoft Excel add-in; <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.epigear.com" ext-link-type="uri">www.epigear.com</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec2"><title>Results</title><p>Our search yielded 296 unique records, of which 19 articles underwent full-text screening. Only 6 studies (4 cross-sectional and 2 prospective cohort studies) matched our criteria and were included in this meta-analysis [<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. A total of 1,024,401 participants were included in our analysis, consisting of 54,888 current ENDS users, 111,754 former users, and 857,759 non-users. All included studies were conducted in the USA and were published between 2021 and 2023. All studies reported their risk estimates as ORs, except for two studies, which reported HRs [<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Both included cohort studies were of high quality and scored 8 out of 9 on the Newcastle-Ottawa Scale. Moreover, the cross-sectional studies showed acceptable quality; however, these studies relied on self-reported stroke diagnosis, which may be a potential source of bias.</p><p>The analysis revealed that ENDS use was associated with a statistically significant increased risk of stroke (OR = 1.52; 95% CI: 1.17&#8211;1.97; <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1 A</xref>) compared with non-users. However, a non-significant association was found between former ENDS use and risk of stroke (OR = 1.03; 95% CI: 0.87&#8211;1.21; <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1 B</xref>). Significant heterogeneity was observed in both current and former ENDS use analyses (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup>: 80% and 63%, respectively). Leave-one-out sensitivity analysis confirmed the robustness of both presented results. In addition, exclusion of the two studies that employed HR as their risk estimate did not change the result significance in terms of current ENDS use (OR = 1.49; 95% CI: 1.10&#8211;2.01).</p><fig position="float" id="f0001" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Forest plots showing the results of meta-analysis that assessed the association of: current ENDS use (<bold>A</bold>), and former ENDS use (<bold>B</bold>) with the risk of stroke</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="AMS-19-5-171473-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p>The current meta-analysis, which included over one million participants, suggested that the use of ENDS may be associated with approximately a 50% increased risk of stroke compared to non-smokers. However, the analysis found no significant association in the case of former ENDS users, emphasizing the importance of smoking cessation. Multiple meta-analyses have consistently reported a significant increase in the risk of stroke among former traditional tobacco smokers, in contrast to the findings related to former ENDS use. Nevertheless, this discrepancy may be attributed to the limited number of available studies assessing the risk of stroke associated with former ENDS use.</p><p>Long-term exposure to nicotine has been recognized to significantly elevate the risk of developing atherosclerosis, consequently increasing the likelihood of experiencing a stroke. Besides nicotine, ENDS contain other harmful components, such as carbonyls (e.g., acrolein, formaldehyde, and acetaldehyde), benzene, toluene, as well as fine and ultrafine particulate matters [<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Many of these components have been linked to various pathophysiological mechanisms that could potentially explain the observed rise in stroke risk. These mechanisms involve damaging of the blood-brain barrier, blood pressure elevation, impairment of vascular repair, induction of vascular inflammation and injury, endothelial dysfunction, and platelet activation, all of which contribute to an increased susceptibility to thrombosis [<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>In a recent meta-analysis, Zhao <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. [<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] aimed to assess the association of ENDS use with the risk of stroke. However, their analysis included a study that did not report stroke as a separate outcome but rather as part of the composite cardiovascular diseases&#8217; outcome. In addition, another completely unrelated study, to the analysis objectives, that assessed the awareness (by sociodemographic variables) of the health effects of ENDS use was included. Therefore, the reliability of that analysis is compromised, and it should not be considered as a credible reference on this issue.</p><p>This meta-analysis has some limitations. Most of the included studies (4 out of 6) had a cross-sectional design, and as a result the temporal association of ENDS and the risk of stroke still needs to be established in future cohort or case-control studies. Additionally, the reliance on surveys and self-reporting methods (e.g., stroke history) for data collection might have been a source for recall and non-response biases. Furthermore, the study by Chelikam <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> [<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] did not adjust for possible history of traditional smoking. Lastly, there is insufficient reported data on the frequency and duration of ENDS use, as well as the different types of strokes in the included studies.</p><p>In conclusion, the usage of ENDS appears to be associated with a higher risk of stroke compared to non-use, whereas there was no association between former ENDS use and the risk of stroke. However, further longitudinal investigations are necessary to validate these findings.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The results of these meta-analysis will be presented during the European Society of Cardiology Congress 2023 in Amsterdam as a Moderated Poster during the Session <italic toggle="yes">Arterial occlusive disease: a chronic pandemic needing attention to detail</italic> (26<sup>th</sup> Aug 2023). The graphical abstract was produced on app.diagrams.net, using SMART materials (Servier Medical Art; smart.servier.com) which are licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Creamer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Babb</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Tobacco product use and cessation indicators among adults &#8211; United States, 2018</article-title>. <source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>1013</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.15585/mmwr.mm6845a2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6855510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31725711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Venkatesh</surname><given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Golamari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Arya</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>E-cigarettes and myocardial infarction: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Int J Cardiol</source><year>2023</year>; <volume>371</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36087629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijcard.2022.09.007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bricknell</surname><given-names>RAT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ducaud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>An association between electronic nicotine delivery systems use and a history of stroke using the 2016 behavioral risk factor surveillance system</article-title>. <source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>e27180</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34516517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MD.0000000000027180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8428735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Falk</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Okut</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vindhyal</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ablah</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Hypertension and cardiovascular diseases among electronic and combustible cigarette users</article-title>. <source>Kans J Med</source><year>2022</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>226</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35899059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.17161/kjm.vol15.16752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9311785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hirschtick</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Longitudinal associations between exclusive and dual use of electronic nicotine delivery systems and cigarettes and self-reported incident diagnosed cardiovascular disease among adults</article-title>. <source>Nicotine Tob Res</source><year>2023</year>; <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>386</fpage>-<lpage>94</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35907264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ntr/ntac182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9910147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The association between electronic cigarettes, sleep duration, and the adverse cardiovascular outcomes: Findings from behavioral risk factor surveillance system, 2020</article-title>. <source>Front Cardiovasc Med</source><year>2022</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>909383</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36277785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fcvm.2022.909383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9582666</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chelikam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammad</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tavrawala</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of cerebrovascular accidents among the US population with substance use disorders: a nationwide study</article-title>. <source>Cureus</source><year>2022</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>e31826</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36579212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.31826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9786611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goldberg Scott</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feigelson</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>. <article-title>Demographic, clinical, and behavioral factors associated with electronic nicotine delivery systems use in a large cohort in the united states</article-title>. <source>Tob Use Insights</source><year>2023</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1179173X221134855</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1179173X221134855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9829996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36636234</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Qasim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karim</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khasawneh</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alshbool</surname><given-names>FZ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of electronic cigarettes on the cardiovascular system</article-title>. <source>J Am Heart Assoc</source><year>2017</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e006353</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28855171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/JAHA.117.006353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5634286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Is electronic cigarette use a risk factor for stroke? A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Tob Induc Dis</source><year>2022</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>101</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36447455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18332/tid/154364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9661377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>