<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="1.4"><!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.--><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Hum Reprod Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Hum Reprod Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3586</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">hropen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">hropen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Human Reproduction Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2399-3529</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10229433</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10229433.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10229433</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10229433</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37265937</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hropen/hoad013</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">hoad013</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Protocol</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00905</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Study protocol for a Developmental Epidemiological Study of Children born through Reproductive Technologies (DESCRT)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2354-680X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Adeleye</surname><given-names initials="AJ">A J</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Section of Reproductive Endocrinology and Infertility, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, University of Chicago</institution>, Chicago, IL, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><xref rid="hoad013-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zablotska</surname><given-names initials="L">L</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, University of California, San Francisco</institution>, San Francisco, CA, <country country="US">USA</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rinaudo</surname><given-names initials="P">P</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Division of Reproductive Endocrinology and Infertility, Department of Obstetrics, Gynecology and Reproductive Sciences, University of California, San Francisco</institution>, San Francisco, CA, <country country="US">USA</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names initials="D">D</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Division of Reproductive Endocrinology and Infertility, Department of Obstetrics, Gynecology and Reproductive Sciences, University of California, San Francisco</institution>, San Francisco, CA, <country country="US">USA</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lustig</surname><given-names initials="RH">R H</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Division of Endocrinology, Department of Pediatrics, University of California, San Francisco</institution>, San Francisco, CA, <country country="US">USA</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cedars</surname><given-names initials="MI">M I</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Division of Reproductive Endocrinology and Infertility, Department of Obstetrics, Gynecology and Reproductive Sciences, University of California, San Francisco</institution>, San Francisco, CA, <country country="US">USA</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="hoad013-cor1">Correspondence address. Section of Reproductive Endocrinology and Infertility, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, The University of Chicago, 5841 South Maryland Avenue, MC 2050, Chicago, IL 60637, USA. E-mail: <email>aadeleye@bsd.uchicago.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-05-05"><day>05</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>2023</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">430689</issue-id><elocation-id>hoad013</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>8</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="editorial-decision"><day>23</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="corrected-typeset"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>05</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-06-02 17:25:20.527"><day>02</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of European Society of Human Reproduction and Embryology 2023. </copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><license-p>This work is written by (a) US Government employee(s) and is in the public domain in the US.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="hoad013.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="hoad013.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="s1"><title>STUDY QUESTIONS</title><p>The primary objective of this study is to determine what parental factors or specific ART may influence the risk for adverse cardiometabolic outcomes among children so conceived and their parents. The secondary objective of this study is to prospectively examine the effects of infertility or ART on the intrauterine environment, obstetric and neonatal outcomes.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>WHAT IS KNOWN ALREADY</title><p>Pregnancies conceived with ART are at an increased risk of being affected by adverse obstetric and neonatal outcomes when compared to spontaneously conceived (SC) pregnancies among fertile women. Small cohort studies have suggested ART-conceived children may have a higher risk of long-term cardiometabolic disturbances as well. Currently, few studies have compared long-term cardiometabolic outcomes among ART-conceived children and non-IVF treated (NIFT) children, to children conceived spontaneously to parents with infertility (subfertile parents).</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>STUDY DESIGN, SIZE, DURATION</title><p>The Developmental Epidemiological Study of Children born through Reproductive Technologies (DESCRT) is a prospective cohort study that aims to: establish a biobank and epidemiological cohort of children born to subfertile or infertile parents who either conceived spontaneously (without assistance) or used reproductive technologies to conceive (all offspring were from couples assessed and/or treated in the same institute); prospectively examine the effects of infertility or ART on the intrauterine environment, obstetric and neonatal outcomes; and determine what parental factors or ART may influence the cardiometabolic risk of children so conceived. Pregnancies and resultant children will be compared by mode of conception, namely offspring that were conceived without medical assistance or SC or following NIFT, IVF with fresh embryo transfer or frozen embryo transfer (FET), and by fertilization method (conventional versus ICSI). DESCRT has a Child group evaluating long-term outcomes of children as well as a Pregnancy group that will compare obstetric and neonatal outcomes of children conceived since the commencement of the study. Recruitment started in May of 2017 and is ongoing. When the study began, we estimated that &#8764;4000 children would be eligible for enrollment.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>PARTICIPANTS/MATERIALS, SETTING, METHODS</title><p>Eligible participants are first-trimester pregnancies (Pregnancy group) or children (Child group) born to parents who were evaluated at an infertility center in the University of California, San Francisco, CA, USA who were SC or conceived after reproductive treatments (NIFT, IVF &#177; ICSI, FET). Children in the Child group were conceived at UCSF and born from 2001 onwards. In the Pregnancy group, enrollment began in November of 2017.</p><p>The primary outcome is the cardiometabolic health of offspring in the Child group, as measured by blood pressure and laboratory data (homeostatic model assessment for insulin resistance (HOMA-IR), oral glucose disposition). There are several secondary outcome measures, including: outcomes from parental survey response (assessing parent/child medical history since delivery&#8212;incidence of cardiometabolic adverse events), anthropomorphic measurements (BMI, waist circumference, skinfold thickness), and laboratory data (liver enzymes, lipid panel, metabolomic profiles). In the Pregnancy group, outcomes include laboratory assessments (bhCG, maternal serum analytes, soluble fms-like tyrosine kinase-1 (sFLT-1), and placental growth factor (PlGF)) and placental assessments (placental volume in the second and third trimester and placental weight at delivery). Importantly, aliquots of blood and urine are stored from parents and offspring as part of a biobank. The DESCRT cohort is unique in two ways. First, there is an extensive amount of clinical and laboratory treatment data: parental medical history and physical examination at the time of treatment, along with ovarian reserve and infertility diagnosis; and treatment specifics: for example, fertilization method, culture O<sub>2</sub> status, embryo quality linked to each participant. These reproductive data will aid in identifying explanatory variables that may influence the primary cardiometabolic outcomes of the offspring&#8212;and their parents. Second, the DESCRT control group includes pregnancies and children SC from parents with subfertility, which may help to assess when infertility, as opposed to reproductive treatments, may be affecting offspring cardiometabolic health.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>STUDY FUNDING/COMPETING INTEREST(S)</title><p>This study is funded by the National Institutes of Health NICHD (1R01HD084380-01A1). A.J.A. is a shareholder in Carrot and consultant for Flo Health. The other authors have no conflicts of interest.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>TRIAL REGISTRATION NUMBER</title><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT03799107">NCT03799107</ext-link></p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>TRIAL REGISTRATION DATE</title><p>10 January 2019</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>DATE OF FIRST PATIENT&#8217;S ENROLLMENT</title><p>10 May 2017</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>infertility</kwd><kwd>IVF</kwd><kwd>health</kwd><kwd>ICSI</kwd><kwd>cardiovascular</kwd><kwd>offspring</kwd><kwd>ART</kwd><kwd>long-term outcomes</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/100000002</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>1R01HD084380-01A1</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front></article></pmc-articleset>